Foreword

Disclaimer: J. K. Rowling owns Harry Potter, and no one owns the methods of rationality.

This fic is widely considered to have really hit its stride starting at around Chapter 5. If you still don't like it after Book 1, give up.

Please visit HPMOR DOT COM for:

Current Author's Notes and progress updates;
Lovely fan-made book-style PDF version;
Ad-free mirror of the text;
Ongoing podcast of the story;
Fan art in vast quantities;
Cameo list (characters named after fan artists);
Fan-fanfiction of this fanfiction;
Fan music, songs, and animations;
Fan translations;
The OKCupid keyword for HPMOR readers;
How to learn everything the main character knows;
Open job positions at a related nonprofit;
And ever so much more.

Reviews make me happy. You can leave reviews on any chapter, no login required, and there's no need to finish reading it all before you start reviewing chapters - but do please leave at most one review per chapter.

This is not a strict single-point-of-departure fic - there exists a primary point of departure, at some point in the past, but also other alterations. The best term I've heard for this fic is ‘parallel universe’.

The text contains many clues: obvious clues, not-so-obvious clues, truly obscure hints which I was shocked to see some readers successfully decode, and massive evidence left out in plain sight. This is a rationalist story; its mysteries are solvable, and meant to be solved.

All science mentioned is real science. But please keep in mind that, beyond the realm of science, the views of the characters may not be those of the author. Not everything the protagonist does is a lesson in wisdom, and advice offered by darker characters may be untrustworthy or dangerously double-edged.

Trigger warnings

By reader request, a list of trigger warnings - parts of the story with potentially traumatic associations for some readers. These will contain some spoilers. Show trigger warnings

Reciprocation

Petunia Evans-Verres’s lips were trembling and her eyes were tearing up as Harry hugged her midsection on Platform Nine of the King’s Cross Station. ‘Are you sure you don’t want me to come with you, Harry?’

Harry glanced over to his father Michael Verres-Evans, who was looking stereotypically stern-but-proud, and then back to his mother, who really did look rather … discomposed. ‘Mum, I know you don’t like the wizarding world very much. You don’t have to come with. I mean it.’

Petunia winced. ‘Harry, you shouldn’t worry about me, I’m your mother and if you need someone with you –’

‘Mum, I’m going to be on my own at Hogwarts for months and months. If I can’t manage a train platform alone, better to find out sooner rather than later so we can abort.’ He lowered his voice to a whisper. ‘Besides, Mum, they all love me over there. If I have any problems, all I need to do is take off my sweatband,’ Harry tapped the exercise band covering his scar, ‘and I’ll have way more help than I can handle.’

‘Oh, Harry,’ Petunia whispered. She knelt down and hugged him hard, face to face, their cheeks resting against each other. Harry could feel her ragged breathing, and then he heard a muffled sob escape. ‘Oh, Harry, I do love you, always remember that.’

It’s like she’s afraid she’ll never see me again, the thought popped into Harry’s head. He knew the thought was true but he didn’t know why Mum was so afraid.

So he made a guess. ‘Mum, you know that I’m not going to turn into your sister just because I’m learning magic, right? I’ll do any magic you ask for – if I can, I mean – or if you want me not to use any magic around the house, I’ll do that too, I promise I’ll never let magic come between us –’

A tight hug cut off his words. ‘You have a good heart,’ his mother whispered into his ear. ‘A very good heart, my son.’

Harry choked up himself a little, then.

His mother released him, and stood up. She took a handkerchief out of her handbag, and with a trembling hand dabbed at the running make-up around her eyes.

There were no questions about his father accompanying him to the magical side of King’s Cross Station. Dad had trouble just looking at Harry’s trunk directly. Magic ran in families, and Michael Verres-Evans couldn’t even walk.

So instead his father just cleared his throat. ‘Good luck at school, Harry,’ he said. ‘Do you think I bought you enough books?’

Harry had explained to his father about how he thought this might be his big chance to do something really revolutionary and important, and Professor Verres-Evans had nodded and dumped his extremely busy schedule for two solid days in order to go on the Greatest Second-hand Bookshop Raid Ever, which had covered four cities and produced thirty boxes of science books now sitting in the cavern level of Harry’s trunk. Most of the books had gone for a pound or two, but some of them definitely hadn’t, like the very latest Handbook of Chemistry and Physics or the complete 1972 set of the Encyclopædia Britannica. His father had tried to block Harry off from seeing the till displays but Harry figured his father must have spent at least a thousand pounds. Harry had said to his father that he would pay him back as soon as he figured out how to convert wizarding gold into Muggle money, and his father had told him to go jump in a lake.

And then his father had asked him: Do you think I bought you enough books? It was quite clear what answer Dad wanted to hear.

Harry’s throat was hoarse, for some reason. ‘You can never have enough books,’ he recited the Verres family motto, and his father knelt down and gave him a quick, firm embrace. ‘But you certainly tried,’ Harry said, and felt himself choking up again. ‘It was a really, really, really good try.’

His Dad straightened. ‘So …’ he said. ‘Do you see a Platform Nine and Three-Quarters?’

King’s Cross Station was huge and busy, with walls and floors paved with ordinary dirt-stained tiles. It was full of ordinary people hurrying about their ordinary business, having ordinary conversations which generated lots and lots of ordinary noise. King’s Cross Station had a Platform Nine (which they were standing on) and a Platform Ten (right next to it) but there was nothing between Platform Nine and Platform Ten except a thin, unpromising barrier wall. A great skylight overhead let in plenty of light to illuminate the total lack whatsoever of any Platform Nine and Three-Quarters.

Harry stared around until his eyes watered, thinking, come on, mage-sight, come on, mage-sight, but absolutely nothing appeared to him. He thought about taking out his wand and waving it, but Professor McGonagall had warned him against using his wand. Plus if there was another shower of multicoloured sparks that might lead to being arrested for setting off fireworks inside a train station. And that was assuming his wand didn’t decide to do something else, like blowing up all of King’s Cross. Harry had only lightly skimmed his schoolbooks (though that skim was quite bizarre enough) in a very quick effort to determine what sort of science books to buy over the next 48 hours.

Well, he had – Harry glanced at his watch – one whole hour to figure it out, since he was supposed to be on the train at eleven. Maybe this was the equivalent of an IQ test and the stupid kids couldn’t become wizards. (And the amount of extra time you gave yourself would determine your Conscientiousness, which was the second most important factor in scholarly success.)

‘I’ll figure it out,’ Harry said to his waiting parents. ‘It’s probably some sort of test thingy.’

His father frowned. ‘Hm … maybe look for a trail of mixed footprints on the ground, leading somewhere that doesn’t seem to make sense –’

‘Dad!’ Harry said. ‘Stop that! I haven’t even tried to figure it out on my own!’ It was a very good suggestion, too, which was worse.

‘Sorry,’ his father apologised.

‘Ah …’ Harry’s mother said. ‘I don’t think they would do that to a student, do you? Are you sure Professor McGonagall didn’t tell you anything?’

‘Maybe she was distracted,’ Harry said without thinking.

‘Harry!’ hissed his father and mother in unison. ‘What did you do?’

‘I, um –’ Harry swallowed. ‘Look, we don’t have time for this now –’

‘Harry!’

‘I mean it! We don’t have time for this now! Because it’s a really long story and I’ve got to figure out how to get to school!’

His mother had a hand over her face. ‘How bad was it?’

‘I, ah,’ I can’t talk about that for reasons of National Security, ‘about half as bad as the Incident with the Science Project?’

‘Harry!’

‘I, er, oh look there are some people with an owl I’ll go ask them how to get in!’ and Harry ran away from his parents towards the family of fiery redheads, his trunk automatically slithering behind him.

The plump woman looked to him as he arrived. ‘Hello, dear. First time at Hogwarts? Ron’s new, too –’ and then she peered closely at him. ‘Harry Potter?’

Four boys and a red-headed girl and an owl all swung around and then froze in place.

‘Oh, come on!’ Harry protested. He’d been planning to go as Harry Verres at least until he got to Hogwarts. ‘I bought a sweatband and everything! How come you know who I am?’

‘Yes,’ Harry’s father said, coming up behind him with long easy strides, ‘how do you know who he is?’ His voice indicated a certain dread.

‘Your picture was in the newspapers,’ said one of two identical-looking twins.

‘Harry!’

‘Dad! It’s not like that! It’s ’cause I defeated the Dark Lord You-Know-Who when I was one year old!’

‘What?’

‘Mum can explain.’

‘What?’

‘Ah … Michael dear, there are certain things I thought it would be best not to bother you with until now –’

‘Excuse me,’ Harry said to the red-headed family who were all staring at him, ‘but it would be quite extremely helpful if you could tell me how to get to Platform Nine and Three Quarters right now.’

‘Ah …’ said the woman. She raised a hand and pointed at the wall between platforms. ‘Just walk straight at the barrier between platforms nine and ten. Don’t stop and don’t be scared you’ll crash into it, that’s very important. Best do it at a bit of a run if you’re nervous.’

‘And whatever you do, don’t think of an elephant.’

‘George! Ignore him, Harry dear, there’s no reason not to think of an elephant.’

‘I’m Fred, Mum, not George –’

‘Thanks!’ Harry said and took off at a run towards the barrier –

Wait a minute, it wouldn’t work unless he believed in it?

It was at times like this that Harry hated his mind for actually working fast enough to realise that this was a case where ‘resonant doubt’ applied, that is, if he’d started out thinking that he would go through the barrier he’d have been fine, only now he was worried about whether he sufficiently believed he’d go through the barrier, which meant that he actually was worried about crashing into it –

‘Harry! Get back here, you have some explaining to do!’ That was his Dad.

Harry shut his eyes and ignored everything he knew about justified credibility and just tried to believe really hard that he’d go through the barrier and –

– the sounds around him changed.

Harry opened his eyes and stumbled to a halt, feeling vaguely dirtied by having made a deliberate effort to believe something.

He was standing in a bright, open-air platform next to a single huge train, fourteen long carriages headed up by a massive scarlet-metal steam engine with a tall chimney that promised death to air quality. The platform was already lightly crowded (even though Harry was a full hour early); dozens of children and their parents swarmed around benches, tables, and various hawkers and stalls.

It went entirely without saying that there was no such place in King’s Cross Station and no room to hide it.

Okay, so either (a) I just teleported somewhere else entirely (b) they can fold space like no one’s business or (c) they are simply ignoring all the rules.

There was a slithering sound behind him, and Harry turned around to observe that his trunk had indeed followed him on its small clawed tentacles. Apparently, for magical purposes, his luggage had also managed to believe with sufficient strength to pass through the barrier. That was actually a little disturbing when Harry started thinking about it.

A moment later, the youngest-looking red-haired boy came through the iron archway (iron archway?) at a run, pulling his trunk behind him on a lead and nearly crashing into Harry. Harry, feeling stupid for having stayed around, quickly began moving away from the landing area, and the red-haired boy followed him, yanking hard on his trunk’s lead in order to keep up. A moment later, a white owl fluttered through the archway and came to rest on the boy’s shoulder.

‘Cor,’ said the red-haired boy, ‘are you really Harry Potter?’

Not this again. ‘I have no logical way of knowing that for certain. My parents raised me to believe that my name was Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres, and many people here have told me that I look like my parents, I mean my other parents, but,’ Harry frowned, realising, ‘for all I know, there could easily be spells to polymorph a child into a specified appearance –’

‘Er, what, mate?’

Not headed for Ravenclaw, I take it. ‘Yes, I’m Harry Potter.’

‘I’m Ron Weasley,’ said the tall skinny freckled long-nosed kid, and stuck out a hand, which Harry politely shook as they walked. The owl gave Harry an oddly measured and courteous hoot (actually more of an eehhhhh sound, which surprised Harry).

At this point Harry realised the potential for imminent catastrophe. ‘Just a second,’ he said to Ron, and opened one of the drawers of his trunk, the one that if he recalled correctly was for Winter Clothes – it was – and then he found the lightest scarf he owned, underneath his winter coat. Harry took off his sweatband, and just as quickly unfolded the scarf and tied it around his face. It was a little hot, especially in the summer, but Harry could live with that.

Then he shut that drawer and pulled out another drawer and drew forth black wizarding robes, which he shrugged over his head, now that he was out of Muggle territory.

‘There,’ Harry said. The sound came out slightly muffled through the scarf over his face. He turned to Ron. ‘How do I look? Stupid, I know, but am I identifiable as Harry Potter?’

‘Er,’ Ron said. He closed his mouth, which had been open. ‘Not really, Harry.’

‘Very good,’ Harry said. ‘However, so as not to obviate the point of the whole exercise, you will henceforth address me as,’ Verres might not work any more, ‘Mr Spoo.’

‘Okay, Harry,’ Ron said uncertainly.

The Force is not particularly strong in this one. ‘Call … me … Mister … Spoo.’

‘Okay, Mister Spoo –’ Ron stopped. ‘I can’t do that, it makes me feel stupid.’

That’s not just a feeling. ‘Okay. You pick a name.’

‘Mr Cannon,’ Ron said at once. ‘For the Chudley Cannons.’

‘Ah …’ Harry knew he was going to terribly regret asking this. ‘Who or what are the Chudley Cannons?’

‘Who’re the Chudley Cannons? Only the most brilliant team in the whole history of Quidditch! Sure, they finished at the bottom of the league last year, but –’

‘What’s Quidditch?’

Asking this was also a mistake.

‘So let me get this straight,’ Harry said as it seemed that Ron’s explanation (with associated hand gestures) was winding down. ‘Catching the Snitch is worth one hundred and fifty points?’

‘Yeah –’

‘How many ten-point goals does one side usually score not counting the Snitch?’

‘Um, maybe fifteen or twenty in professional games –’

‘That’s just wrong. That violates every possible rule of game design. Look, the rest of this game sounds like it might make sense, sort of, for a sport I mean, but you’re basically saying that catching the Snitch overwhelms almost any ordinary point spread. The two Seekers are up there flying around looking for the Snitch and usually not interacting with anyone else, spotting the Snitch first is going to be mostly luck –’

‘It’s not luck!’ protested Ron. ‘You’ve got to keep your eyes moving in the right pattern –’

‘That’s not interactive, there’s no back-and-forth with the other player and how much fun is it to watch someone incredibly good at moving their eyes? And then whichever Seeker gets lucky swoops in and grabs the Snitch and makes everyone else’s work moot. It’s like someone took a real game and grafted on this pointless extra position so that you could be the Most Important Player without needing to really get involved or learn the rest of it. Who was the first Seeker, the King’s idiot son who wanted to play Quidditch but couldn’t understand the rules?’ Actually, now that Harry thought about it, that seemed like a surprisingly good hypothesis. Put him on a broomstick and tell him to catch the shiny thing …

Ron’s face pulled into a scowl. ‘If you don’t like Quidditch, you don’t have to make fun of it!’

‘If you can’t criticise, you can’t optimise. I’m suggesting how to improve the game. And it’s very simple. Get rid of the Snitch.’

‘They won’t change the game just ’cause you say so!’

‘I am the Boy-Who-Lived, you know. People will listen to me. And maybe if I can persuade them to change the game at Hogwarts, the innovation will spread.’

A look of absolute horror was spreading over Ron’s face. ‘But, but if you get rid of the Snitch, how will anyone know when the game ends?’

‘Buy … a … clock. It would be a lot fairer than having the game sometimes end after ten minutes and sometimes not end for hours, and the schedule would be a lot more predictable for the spectators, too.’ Harry sighed. ‘Oh, stop giving me that look of absolute horror, I probably won’t actually take the time to destroy this pathetic excuse for a national sport and remake it stronger and smarter in my own image. I’ve got way, way, way more important stuff to worry about.’ Harry looked thoughtful. ‘Then again, it wouldn’t take much time to write up the Ninety-Five Theses of the Snitchless Reformation and nail it to a church door –’

‘Potter,’ drawled a young boy’s voice, ‘what is that on your face and what is standing next to you?’

Ron’s look of horror was replaced by utter hatred. ‘You!’

Harry turned his head; and indeed it was Draco Malfoy, who might have been forced to wear standard school robes, but was making up for that with a trunk looking at least as magical and far more elegant than Harry’s own, decorated in silver and emeralds and bearing what Harry guessed to be the Malfoy family crest, a beautiful fanged serpent over crossed ivory wands.

‘Draco!’ Harry said. ‘Er, or Malfoy if you prefer, though that kind of sounds like Lucius to me. I’m glad to see you’re doing so well after, um, our last meeting. This is Ron Weasley. And I’m trying to go incognito, so call me, eh,’ Harry looked down at his robes, ‘Mister Black.’

‘Harry!’ hissed Ron. ‘You can’t use that name!’

Harry blinked. ‘Why not?’ It sounded nicely dark, like an international man of mystery –

‘I’d say it’s a fine name,’ said Draco, ‘but it belongs to the Noble and Most Ancient House of Black. I’ll call you Mr Silver.’

‘You get away from … from Mr Gold,’ Ron said coldly, and took a forward step. ‘He doesn’t need to talk to the likes of you!’

Harry raised a placating hand. ‘I’ll go by Mr Bronze, thanks for the naming schema. And, Ron, um,’ Harry struggled to find a way to say this, ‘I’m glad you’re so … enthusiastic about protecting me, but I don’t particularly mind talking to Draco –’

This was apparently the last straw for Ron, who spun on Harry with eyes now aflame with outrage. ‘What? Do you know who this is?’

‘Yes, Ron,’ Harry said, ‘you may remember that I called him Draco without him needing to introduce himself.’

Draco sniggered. Then his eyes lit on the white owl on Ron’s shoulder. ‘Oh, what’s this?’ Draco said in a drawl rich with malice. ‘Where’s the famous Weasley family rat?’

‘Buried in the backyard,’ Ron said coldly.

‘Aw, how sad. Pot … ah, Mr Bronze, I should mention that the Weasley family is widely agreed to have the best pet story ever. Want to tell it, Weasley?’

Ron’s face contorted. ‘You wouldn’t think it was funny if it happened to your family!’

‘Oh,’ Draco purred, ‘but it wouldn’t ever happen to the Malfoys.’

Ron’s hands clenched into fists –

‘That’s enough,’ Harry said, putting as much quiet authority into the voice as he could manage. It was clear that whatever this was about, it was a painful memory for the red-haired kid. ‘If Ron doesn’t want to talk about it, he doesn’t have to talk about it, and I’d ask that you not talk about it either.’

Draco turned a surprised look on Harry, and Ron nodded. ‘That’s right, Harry! I mean Mr Bronze! You see what kind of person he is? Now tell him to go away!’

Harry counted to ten inside his head, which for him was a very quick 12345678910 – an odd habit left over from the age of five when his mother had first instructed him to do it, and Harry had reasoned that his way was faster and ought to be just as effective. ‘I’m not telling him to go away,’ Harry said calmly. ‘He’s welcome to talk to me if he wants.’

‘Well, I don’t intend to hang around with anyone who hangs around with Draco Malfoy,’ Ron announced coldly.

Harry shrugged. ‘That’s up to you. I don’t intend to let anyone say who I can and can’t hang around with.’ Silently chanting, please go away, please go away …

Ron’s face went blank with surprise, like he’d actually expected that line to work. Then Ron spun about, yanked his luggage’s lead and stormed off down the platform.

‘If you didn’t like him,’ Draco said curiously, ‘why didn’t you just walk away?’

‘Um … his mother helped me figure out how to get to this platform from King’s Cross Station, so it was kind of hard to tell him to get lost. And it’s not that I hate this Ron guy,’ Harry said, ‘I just, just …’ Harry searched for words.

‘Don’t see any reason for him to exist?’ offered Draco.

‘Pretty much.’

‘Anyway, Potter … if you really were raised by Muggles –’ Draco paused here, as if waiting for a denial, but Harry didn’t say anything ‘– then you mightn’t know what it’s like to be famous. People want to take up all of our time. You have to learn to say no.’

Harry nodded, putting a thoughtful look on his face. ‘That sounds like good advice.’

‘If you try to be nice, you just end up spending the most time with the pushiest ones. Decide who you want to spend time with and make everyone else leave. You’re just getting here, Potter, so everyone’s going to judge you by who they see you with, and you don’t want to be seen with the likes of Ron Weasley.’

Harry nodded again. ‘If you don’t mind my asking, how did you recognise me?’

‘Mister Bronze,’ Draco drawled, ‘I have met you, remember. I saw someone going around with a scarf wrapped around his head, looking absolutely ridiculous. So I took a guess.’

Harry bowed his head, accepting the compliment. ‘I’m terribly sorry about that,’ Harry said. ‘Our first meeting, I mean. I didn’t mean to embarrass you in front of Lucius.’

Draco waved it off while giving Harry an odd look. ‘I just wish Father could have come in while you were flattering me –’ Draco laughed. ‘But thank you for what you said to Father. If not for that, I might’ve had a harder time explaining.’

Harry swept a deeper bow. ‘And thank you for reciprocating with what you said to Professor McGonagall.’

‘You’re welcome. Though one of the assistants must’ve sworn her closest friend to absolute secrecy, because Father says there’re weird rumours going around, like you and I got in a fight or something.’

‘Ouch,’ Harry said, wincing. ‘I’m really sorry –’

‘No, we’re used to it, Merlin knows there’s lots of rumours about the Malfoy family already.’

Harry nodded. ‘I’m glad to hear you’re not in trouble.’

Draco smirked. ‘Father has, um, a refined sense of humour, but he does understand making friends. He understands it very well. He made me repeat that before I went to bed every night for the last month, “I will make friends at Hogwarts.” When I explained everything to him and he saw that’s what I was doing, he bought me an ice-cream.’

Harry’s jaw dropped. ‘You managed to spin that into an ice-cream?’

Draco nodded, looking every bit as smug as the feat deserved. ‘Well, father knew what I was doing, of course, but he’s the one who taught me how to do it, and if I grin the right way while I’m doing it, that makes it a father-son thing and then he has to buy me an ice-cream or I’ll give him this sort of sad look, like I think I must have disappointed him.’

Harry eyed Draco calculatingly, sensing the presence of another master. ‘You’ve had lessons on how to manipulate people?’

‘Of course,’ Draco said proudly. ‘I’m a Malfoy. Father bought me tutors.’

‘Wow,’ Harry said. Reading Robert Cialdini’s Influence: Science and Practice probably didn’t stack up very high compared to that (though it was still one heck of a book). ‘Your dad is almost as awesome as my dad.’

Draco’s eyebrows rose loftily. ‘Oh? And what does your father do?’

‘He buys me books.’

Draco considered this. ‘That doesn’t sound very impressive.’

‘You had to be there. Anyway, I’m glad to hear all that. The way Lucius was looking at you, I thought he was going to c-crucify you.’

‘My father really loves me,’ Draco said firmly. ‘He wouldn’t ever do that.’

‘Um …’ Harry said. He remembered the black-robed, white-haired figure of elegance that had stormed through Madam Malkin’s, wielding that beautiful, deadly silver-handled cane. It wasn’t easy to visualise him as a doting father. ‘Don’t take this the wrong way, but how do you know that?’

‘Huh?’ It was clear that this was a question Draco did not commonly ask himself.

‘I ask the fundamental question of rationality: why do you believe what you believe? What do you think you know and how do you think you know it? What makes you think Lucius wouldn’t sacrifice you the same way he’d sacrifice anything else for power?’

Draco shot Harry another odd look. ‘Just what do you know about Father?’

‘Um … seat on the Wizengamot, seat on Hogwarts’ Board of Governors, incredibly wealthy, has the ear of Minister Fudge, has the confidence of Minister Fudge, probably has some highly embarrassing photos of Minister Fudge, most prominent blood purist now that the Dark Lord’s gone, former Death Eater who was found to have the Dark Mark but got off by claiming to be under the Imperius Curse, which was ridiculously implausible and pretty much everyone knew it … evil with a capital E and a born killer … I think that’s it.’

Draco’s eyes had narrowed to slits. ‘McGonagall told you that, did she.’

‘No, she wouldn’t say anything to me about Lucius afterwards, except to stay away from him. So during the Incident at the Potions Shop, while Professor McGonagall was busy yelling at the shopkeeper and trying to get everything under control, I grabbed one of the customers and asked them about Lucius.’

Draco’s eyes were wide again. ‘Did you really?’

Harry gave Draco a puzzled look. ‘If I lied the first time, I’m not going to tell you the truth just because you ask twice.’

There was a certain pause as Draco absorbed this.

‘You’re so completely going to be in Slytherin.’

‘I’m so completely going to be in Ravenclaw, thank you very much. I only want power so I can get books.’

Draco giggled. ‘Yeah, right. Anyway … to answer what you asked …’ Draco took a deep breath, and his face turned serious. ‘Father once missed a Wizengamot vote for me. I was on a broom and I fell off and broke a lot of ribs. It really hurt. I’d never hurt that much before and I thought I was going to die. So Father missed this really important vote, because he was there by my bed at St. Mungo’s, holding my hands and promising me that I was going to be okay.’

Harry glanced away uncomfortably, then, with an effort, forced himself to look back at Draco. ‘Why are you telling me that? It seems sort of … private …’

Draco gave Harry a serious look. ‘One of my tutors once said that people form close friendships by knowing private things about each other, and the reason most people don’t make close friends is because they’re too embarrassed to share anything really important about themselves.’ Draco turned his palms out invitingly. ‘Your turn?’

Knowing that Draco’s hopeful face had probably been drilled into him by months of practise did not make it any less effective, Harry observed. Actually it did make it less effective, but unfortunately not ineffective. The same could be said of Draco’s clever use of reciprocation pressure with an unsolicited gift, a technique which Harry had read about in his social psychology books (one experiment had shown that an unconditional gift of $5 was twice as effective as a conditional offer of $50 in getting people to fill out surveys). Draco had made an unsolicited gift of a confidence, and now invited Harry to offer a confidence in return … and the thing was, Harry did feel pressured. Refusal, Harry was certain, would be met with a look of sad disappointment, and maybe a small amount of contempt indicating that Harry had lost points.

‘Draco,’ Harry said, ‘just so you know, I recognise exactly what you’re doing right now. My own books called it reciprocation and they talk about how giving someone a straight gift of two Sickles was found to be twice as effective as offering them twenty Sickles in getting them to do what you want …’ Harry trailed off.

Draco was looking sad and disappointed. ‘It’s not meant as a trick, Harry. It’s a real way of becoming friends.’

Harry held up a hand. ‘I didn’t say I wasn’t going to respond. I just need time to pick something that’s private but just as non-damaging. Let’s say … I wanted you to know that I can’t be rushed into things.’ A pause to reflect could go a long way in defusing the power of a lot of compliance techniques, once you learned to recognise them for what they were.

‘All right,’ Draco said. ‘I’ll wait while you come up with something. Oh, and please take off the scarf while you say it.’

Simple but effective.

And Harry couldn’t help but notice how clumsy, awkward, graceless his attempt at resisting manipulation / saving face / showing off had appeared compared to Draco. I need those tutors.

‘All right,’ Harry said after a time. ‘Here’s mine.’ He glanced around and then rolled the scarf back up over his face, exposing everything but the scar. ‘Um … it sounds like you can really rely on your father. I mean … if you talk to him seriously, he’ll always listen to you and take you seriously.’

Draco nodded.

‘Sometimes,’ Harry said, and swallowed. This was surprisingly hard, but then it was meant to be. ‘Sometimes I wish my own Dad was like yours.’ Harry’s eyes flinched away from Draco’s face, more or less automatically, and then Harry forced himself to look back at Draco.

Then it hit Harry what on Earth he’d just said, and Harry hastily added, ‘Not that I wish my Dad was a flawless instrument of death like Lucius, I only mean taking me seriously –’

‘I understand,’ Draco said with a smile. ‘There … now doesn’t it feel like we’re a little closer to being friends?’

Harry nodded. ‘Yeah. It does, actually. Um … no offence, but I’m going to put on my disguise again, I really don’t want to deal with –’

‘I understand.’

Harry rolled the scarf back down over his face.

‘My father takes all his friends seriously,’ Draco said. ‘That’s why he has lots of friends. You should meet him.’

‘I’ll think about it,’ Harry said in a neutral voice. He shook his head in wonder. ‘So you really are his one weak point. Huh.’

Now Draco was giving Harry a really odd look. ‘You want to go get something to drink and find somewhere to sit down?’

Harry realised he had been standing in one place for too long, and stretched himself, trying to crick his back. ‘Sure.’

At 2:35PM, when most of the seats were taken and no one else seemed to be coming in, Professor Quirrell gave a sudden jerk in his chair and sat up straight, and his face appeared on all the flat, white rectangular objects that were propped up on the students’ desks.

Harry was taken by surprise, both by the sudden appearance of Professor Quirrell’s face and by the resemblance to Muggle television. There was something both nostalgic and sad about that, it seemed so much like a piece of home and yet it wasn’t really …

‘Good afternoon, my young apprentices,’ said Professor Quirrell. His voice seemed to come from the desk screen and to be speaking directly to Harry. ‘Welcome to your first lesson in Battle Magic, as the founders of Hogwarts would have put it; or, as it happens to be called in the late twentieth century, Defence Against the Dark Arts.’

There was a certain amount of frantic scrabbling as students, taken by surprise, reached for their parchment or notebooks.

‘No,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘Don’t bother writing down what this subject was once called. No such pointless question will count toward your marks in any of my lessons. That is a promise.’

Many students sat straight up at that, looking rather shocked.

Professor Quirrell was smiling thinly. ‘Those of you who have wasted time by reading your useless first-year Defence textbooks –’

Someone made a choking sound. Harry wondered if it was Hermione.

‘– may have got the impression that although this subject is called Defence Against the Dark Arts, it is actually about how to defend against Nightmare Butterflies, which cause mildly bad dreams, or Acid Slugs, which can dissolve all the way through a two-inch wooden beam given most of a day.’

Professor Quirrell stood up, shoving his chair back from the desk. The screen on Harry’s desk followed his every move. Professor Quirrell strode towards the front of the classroom, and bellowed:

‘The Hungarian Horntail is taller than a dozen men! It breathes fire so quickly and so accurately that it can melt a Snitch in mid-flight! One Killing Curse will bring it down!’

There were gasps from the students.

‘The Mountain Troll is more dangerous than the Hungarian Horntail! It is strong enough to bite through steel! Its hide is resistant enough to withstand Stunning Hexes and Cutting Charms! Its sense of smell is so acute that it can tell from afar whether its prey is part of a pack, or alone and vulnerable! Most fearsome of all, the troll is unique among magical creatures in continuously maintaining a form of Transfiguration on itself – it is always transforming into its own body. If you somehow succeed in ripping off its arm it will grow another within seconds! Fire and acid will produce scar tissue which can temporarily confuse a troll’s regenerative powers – for an hour or two! They are smart enough to use clubs as tools! The mountain troll is the third most perfect killing machine in all Nature! One Killing Curse will bring it down.’

The students were looking rather shocked.

Professor Quirrell was smiling rather grimly. ‘Your sad excuse for a third-year Defence textbook will suggest to you that you expose the mountain troll to sunlight, which will freeze it in place. This, my young apprentices, is the sort of useless knowledge you will never find in my lessons. You do not encounter mountain trolls in open daylight! The idea that you should use sunlight to stop them is the result of foolish textbook authors trying to show off their mastery of minutiae at the expense of practicality. Just because there is a ridiculously obscure way of dealing with mountain trolls does not mean you should actually try to use it! The Killing Curse is unblockable, unstoppable, and works every single time on anything with a brain. If, as an adult wizard, you find yourself incapable of using the Killing Curse, then you can simply Apparate away! Likewise if you are facing the second most perfect killing machine, a Dementor. You just Apparate away!’

‘Unless, of course,’ Professor Quirrell said, his voice now lower and harder, ‘you are under the influence of an anti-Apparition jinx. No, there is exactly one monster which can threaten you once you are fully grown. The single most dangerous monster in all the world, so dangerous that nothing else comes close. The Dark Wizard. That is the only thing that will still be able to threaten you.’

Professor Quirrell’s lips were set in a thin line. ‘I will reluctantly teach you enough trivia for a passing mark on the Ministry-mandated portions of your first-year exams. Since your exact mark on these sections will make no difference to your future life, anyone who wants more than a passing mark is welcome to waste their own time studying our pathetic excuse for a textbook. The title of this subject is not Defence Against Minor Pests. You are here to learn how to defend yourselves against the Dark Arts. Which means, let us be very clear on this, defending yourselves against Dark Wizards. People with wands who want to hurt you and who will likely succeed in doing so unless you hurt them first! There is no defence without offence! There is no defence without fighting! This reality is deemed too harsh for eleven-year-olds by the fat, overpaid, Auror-guarded politicians who mandated your curriculum. To the abyss with those fools! You are here for the subject that has been taught at Hogwarts for eight hundred years! Welcome to your first year of Battle Magic!’

Harry started applauding. He couldn’t help himself, it was too inspiring.

Once Harry started clapping there was some scattered response from Gryffindor, and more from Slytherin, but most students simply seemed too stunned to react.

Professor Quirrell made a cutting gesture, and the applause died instantly. ‘Thank you very much,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Now to practicalities. I have combined all my first-year Battle classes into one, which allows me to offer you twice as much classroom time as Doubles sessions –’

There were gasps of horror.

‘– an increased load which I will make up to you by not assigning any homework.’

The gasps of horror cut off abruptly.

‘Yes, you heard me correctly. I will teach you to fight, not to write twelve inches on fighting due Monday.’

Harry desperately wished he’d sat next to Hermione so he could see the look on her face now, but on the other hand he was pretty sure he was imagining it accurately.

Also Harry was in love. It would be a three-way wedding: him, the Time-Turner, and Professor Quirrell.

‘For those of you who so choose, I have arranged some after-school activities that I think you will find quite interesting as well as educational. Do you want to show the world your own abilities instead of watching fourteen other people play Quidditch? More than seven people can fight in an army.’

Hot damn.

‘These and other after-school activities will also earn you Quirrell points. What are Quirrell points, you ask? The House point system does not suit my needs, because it makes House points too rare. I prefer to let my students know how they are doing more frequently than that. And on the rare occasions I offer you a written test, it will mark itself as you go along, and if you get too many related questions wrong, your test will show the names of students who got those questions right, and those students will be able to earn Quirrell points by helping you.’

… wow. Why didn’t the other professors use a system like that?

‘What good are Quirrell points, you wonder? For a start, ten Quirrell points will be worth one House point. But they will earn you other favours as well. Would you like to take your exam at an unusual time? Is there a particular session you would very much prefer to skip? You will find that I can be very flexible on behalf of students who have accumulated enough Quirrell points. Quirrell points will control the generalship of the armies. And for Christmas – just before the Christmas break – I will grant someone a wish. Any school-related feat that lies within my power, my influence, or above all, my ingenuity. Yes, I was in Slytherin and I am offering to formulate a cunning plot on your behalf, if that is what it takes to accomplish your desire. This wish will go to whoever has earned the most Quirrell points within all seven years.’

That would be Harry.

‘Now leave your books and loose items at your desks – they will be safe, the screens will watch over them for you – and come down onto this platform. It’s time to play a game called Who’s the Most Dangerous Student in the Classroom.’

Harry twisted his wand in his right hand and said ‘Ma-ha-su!’

There was another high-pitched ‘bing’ from the floating blue sphere that Professor Quirrell had assigned to Harry as his target. That particular sound meant a perfect strike, which Harry had managed on nine out of his last ten attempts.

Somewhere Professor Quirrell had dug up a spell that was incredibly easy to pronounce, and had a ridiculously simple wand motion, and had a tendency to hit wherever you were currently looking at. Professor Quirrell had disdainfully proclaimed that real battle magic was far more difficult than this. That the hex was entirely useless in actual combat. That it was a barely ordered burst of magic whose only real content was the aiming, and that it would produce, when it hit, a pain briefly equivalent to being punched hard in the nose. That the sole purpose of this test was to see who was a fast learner, since Professor Quirrell was certain no one would have previously encountered this hex or anything like it.

Harry didn’t care about any of that.

‘Ma-ha-su!’

A red bolt of energy shot out of his wand and struck the target and the blue sphere once again made the bing which meant the spell had actually worked for him.

Harry was feeling like a real wizard for the first time since he’d come to Hogwarts. He wished the target would dodge like the little spheres that Ben Kenobi had used for training Luke, but for some reason Professor Quirrell had instead lined up all the students and targets in neat orders which made sure they wouldn’t fire on each other.

So Harry lowered his wand, skipped to the right, snapped up his wand and twisted and shouted ‘Ma-ha-su!’

There was a lower-pitched ‘dong’ which meant he’d gotten it almost right.

Harry put his wand into his pocket, skipped back to the left and drew and fired another red bolt of energy.

The high-pitched bing which resulted was easily one of the most satisfying sounds he’d heard in his life. Harry wanted to scream in triumph at the top of his lungs. I can do magic! Fear me, laws of physics, I’m coming to violate you!

‘Ma-ha-su!’ Harry’s voice was loud, but hardly noticeable over the steady chant of similar cries from around the classroom platform.

‘Enough,’ said Professor Quirrell’s amplified voice. (It didn’t sound loud. It sounded like normal volume, coming from just behind your left shoulder, no matter where you were standing relative to Professor Quirrell.) ‘I see that all of you have succeeded at least once now.’ The target-spheres turned red and began to drift up towards the ceiling.

Professor Quirrell was standing on the raised dais in the centre of the platform, leaning slightly on his teacher’s desk with one hand.

‘I told you,’ Professor Quirrell said, ‘that we would play a game called Who’s the Most Dangerous Student in the Classroom. There is one student in this classroom who mastered the Sumerian Simple Strike Hex faster than anyone else –’

Oh blah blah blah.

‘– and went on to help seven other students. For which she has earned the first seven Quirrell points awarded to your year. Come forth, Hermione Granger. It is time for the next stage of the game.’

Hermione Granger began striding forwards, a mixed look of triumph and apprehension on her face. The Ravenclaws looked on proudly, the Slytherins with glares, and Harry with frank annoyance. Harry had done fine this time. He was probably even in the upper half of the class, now that everyone had been faced with an equally unfamiliar spell and Harry had read all the way through Adalbert Waffling’s Magical Theory. And yet Hermione was still doing better.

Somewhere in the back of his mind was the fear that Hermione was simply smarter than him.

But for now Harry was going to pin his hopes on the known facts that (a) Hermione had read a lot more than the standard textbooks and (b) Adalbert Waffling was an uninspired sod who’d written Magical Theory to pander to a school board that didn’t think much of eleven-year-olds.

Hermione reached the central dais and stepped up.

‘Hermione Granger mastered a completely unfamiliar spell in two minutes, almost a full minute faster than the next runner-up.’ Professor Quirrell turned slowly in place to look at all the students watching them. ‘Could Miss Granger’s intelligence make her the most dangerous student in the classroom? Well? What do you think?’

No one seemed to be thinking anything at the moment. Even Harry wasn’t sure what to say.

‘Let’s find out, shall we?’ said Professor Quirrell. He turned back to Hermione, and gestured toward the wider class. ‘Select any student you like and cast the Simple Strike Hex on them.’

Hermione froze where she stood.

‘Come now,’ Professor Quirrell said smoothly. ‘You have cast this spell perfectly over fifty times. It is not permanently harmful or even all that painful. It hurts as much as a hard punch and lasts only a few seconds.’ Professor Quirrell’s voice grew harder. ‘This is a direct order from your professor, Miss Granger. Choose a target and fire a Simple Strike Hex.’

Hermione’s face was screwed up in horror and her wand was trembling in her hand. Harry’s own fingers were clenching his own wand hard in sympathy. Even though he could see what Professor Quirrell was trying to do. Even though he could see the point Professor Quirrell was trying to make.

‘If you do not raise your wand and fire, Miss Granger, you will lose a Quirrell point.’

Harry stared at Hermione, willing her to look in his direction. His right hand was softly tapping his own chest. Pick me, I’m not afraid …

Hermione’s wand twitched in her hand; then her face relaxed, and she lowered her wand to her side.

‘No,’ said Hermione Granger.

Her voice was calm, and even though it wasn’t loud, everyone heard it in the silence.

‘Then I must deduct one point from you,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘This is a test, and you have failed it.’

That reached her. Harry could see it. But she kept her shoulders straight.

Professor Quirrell’s voice was sympathetic and seemed to fill the whole room. ‘Knowing things isn’t always enough, Miss Granger. If you cannot give and receive violence on the order of stubbing your toe, then you cannot defend yourself and you will not pass Defence. Please rejoin your classmates.’

Hermione walked back towards the Ravenclaw cluster. Her face looked peaceful and Harry, for some odd reason, wanted to start clapping. Even though Professor Quirrell had been right.

‘So,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘It becomes clear that Hermione Granger is not the most dangerous student in the classroom. Who do you think might actually be the most dangerous person here? – besides me, of course.’

Without even thinking, Harry turned to look at the Slytherin contingent.

‘Draco, of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘It seems that many of your fellow pupils are looking in your direction. Come forth, if you would.’

Draco did so, walking with a certain pride in his bearing. He stepped onto the dais and looked up at Professor Quirrell with a smile.

‘Mr Malfoy,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘Fire.’

Harry would have tried to stop it if there’d been time but in one smooth motion Draco spun on the Ravenclaw contingent and raised his wand and said ‘Mahasu!’ like it was all one syllable and Hermione was saying ‘Ow!’ and that was that.

‘Well struck,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Two Quirrell points to you. But tell me, why did you target Miss Granger?’

There was a pause.

Finally Draco said, ‘Because she stood out the most.’

Professor Quirrell’s lips turned up in a thin smile. ‘And that is the true reason why Draco Malfoy is dangerous. Had he selected any other, that child would more likely resent being singled out, and Mr Malfoy would more probably make an enemy. And while Mr Malfoy might have given some other justification for selecting her, that would have served him no purpose save to alienate some of you, while others are already cheering him whether he says anything or not. Which is to say that Mr Malfoy is dangerous because he knows who to strike and who not to strike, how to make allies and avoid making enemies. Two more Quirrell points to you, Mr Malfoy. And as you have demonstrated an exemplary virtue of Slytherin, I think that Salazar’s House has earned a point as well. You may rejoin your friends.’

Draco bowed slightly and walked back to the Slytherin contingent. Some clapping started from the green-trimmed robes, but Professor Quirrell made a cutting gesture and silence fell again.

‘It might seem that our game is done,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘And yet there is a single student in this classroom who is more dangerous than the scion of Malfoy.’

And now for some reason there seemed to be an awful lot of people looking at …

‘Harry Potter. Come forth.’

This did not bode well.

Harry reluctantly walked towards where Professor Quirrell stood on his raised dais, still leaning slightly against his teacher’s desk.

The nervousness of being put into the spotlight seemed to be sharpening Harry’s wits as he approached the dais, and his mind was ruffling through possibilities for what Professor Quirrell might think could demonstrate Harry’s dangerousness. Would he be asked to cast a spell? To defeat a Dark Lord?

Demonstrate his supposed immunity to the Killing Curse? Surely Professor Quirrell was too smart for that …

Harry stopped well short of the dais, and Professor Quirrell didn’t ask him to come any closer.

‘The irony is,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘you all looked at the right person for entirely the wrong reasons. You are thinking,’ Professor Quirrell’s lips twisted, ‘that Harry Potter has defeated the Dark Lord, and so must be very dangerous. Bah. He was one year old. Whatever quirk of fate killed the Dark Lord likely had little to do with Mr Potter’s abilities as a fighter. But after I heard rumours of one Ravenclaw facing down five older Slytherins, I interviewed several eyewitnesses and came to the conclusion that Harry Potter would be my most dangerous student.’

A jolt of adrenaline poured into Harry’s system, making him stand up straighter. He didn’t know what conclusion Professor Quirrell had come to, but that couldn’t be good.

‘Ah, Professor Quirrell –’ Harry started to say.

Professor Quirrell looked amused. ‘You’re thinking that I’ve come up with a wrong answer, aren’t you, Mr Potter? You will learn to expect better of me.’ Professor Quirrell straightened from where he had leaned on the desk. ‘Mr Potter, all things have their accustomed uses. Give me ten unaccustomed uses of objects in this room for combat!’

For a moment Harry was rendered speechless by the sheer, raw shock of having been understood.

And then the ideas started to pour out.

‘There are desks which are heavy enough to be fatal if dropped from a great height. There are chairs with metal legs that could impale someone if driven hard enough. The air in this classroom would be deadly by its absence, since people die in vacuum, and it can serve as a carrier for poison gases.’

Harry had to stop briefly for breath, and into that pause Professor Quirrell said:

‘That’s three. You need ten. The rest of the class thinks that you’ve already used up the whole contents of the classroom.’

‘Ha! The floor can be removed to create a spike pit to fall into, the ceiling can be collapsed on someone, the walls can serve as raw material for Transfiguration into any number of deadly things – knives, say.’

‘That’s six. But surely you’re scraping the bottom of the barrel now?’

‘I haven’t even started! Just look at all the people! Having a Gryffindor attack the enemy is an ordinary use, of course –’

‘I will not count that one.’

‘– but their blood can also be used to drown someone. Ravenclaws are known for their brains, but their internal organs could be sold on the black market for enough money to hire an assassin. Slytherins aren’t just useful as assassins, they can also be thrown at sufficient velocity to crush an enemy. And Hufflepuffs, in addition to being hard workers, also contain bones that can be removed, sharpened, and used to stab someone.’

By now the rest of the class was staring at Harry in some horror. Even the Slytherins looked shocked.

‘That’s ten, though I’m being generous in counting the Ravenclaw one. Now, for extra credit, one Quirrell point for each use of objects in this room which you have not yet named.’ Professor Quirrell favoured Harry with a companionable smile. ‘The rest of your class thinks you are in trouble now, since you’ve named everything except the targets and you have no idea what may be done with those.’

‘Bah! I’ve named all the people, but not my robes, which can be used to suffocate an enemy if wrapped around their head enough times, or Hermione Granger’s robes, which can be torn into strips and tied into a rope and used to hang someone, or Draco Malfoy’s robes, which can be used to start a fire –’

‘Three points,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘no more clothing now.’

‘My wand can be pushed into an enemy’s brain through their eye socket’ and someone made a horrified, strangling sound.

‘Four points, no more wands.’

‘My wristwatch could suffocate someone if jammed down their throat –’

‘Five points, and enough.’

‘Hmph,’ Harry said. ‘Ten Quirrell points to one House point, right? You should have let me keep going until I’d won the House Cup, I haven’t even started yet on the unaccustomed uses of everything I’ve got in my pockets’ or the mokeskin pouch itself and he couldn’t talk about the Time-Turner or the invisibility cloak but there had to be something he could say about those red spheres …

‘Enough, Mr Potter. Well, do you all think you understand what makes Mr Potter the most dangerous student in the classroom?’

There was a low murmur of assent.

‘Say it out loud, please. Terry Boot, what makes your dorm-mate dangerous?’

‘Ah … um … he’s creative?’

‘Wrong!’ bellowed Professor Quirrell, and his fist came down sharply on his desk with an amplified sound that made everyone jump. ‘All of Mr Potter’s ideas were worse than useless!’

Harry started in surprise.

‘Remove the floor to create a spike trap? Ridiculous! In combat you do not have that sort of preparation time and if you did there would be a hundred better uses! Transfigure material from the walls? Mr Potter cannot perform Transfiguration! Mr Potter had exactly one idea which he could use immediately, right now, without extensive preparation or a cooperative enemy or magic he does not know. That idea was to jam his wand through his enemy’s eye socket. Which would be more likely to break his wand than kill his opponent! In short, Mr Potter, I’m afraid that your proposals were uniformly awful.’

‘What?’ Harry said indignantly. ‘You asked for unusual ideas, not practical ones! I was thinking outside the box! How would you use something in this classroom to kill someone?’

Professor Quirrell’s expression was disapproving, but there were smile crinkles around his eyes. ‘Mr Potter, I never said you were to kill. There is a time and a place for taking your enemy alive, and inside a Hogwarts classroom is usually one of those places. But to answer your question, hit them on the neck with the edge of a chair.’

There was some laughter from the Slytherins, but they were laughing with Harry, not at him.

Everyone else was looking rather horrified.

‘But Mr Potter has now demonstrated why he is the most dangerous student in the classroom. I asked for unaccustomed uses of items in this room for combat. Mr Potter could have suggested using a desk to block a curse, or using a chair to trip an oncoming enemy, or wrapping cloth around his arm to create an improvised shield. Instead, every single use that Mr Potter named was offensive rather than defensive, and either fatal or potentially fatal.’

What? Wait, that couldn’t be true … Harry had a sudden sense of vertigo as he tried to remember what exactly he’d suggested, surely there had to be a counterexample …

‘And that,’ Professor Quirrell said, ‘is why Mr Potter’s ideas were so strange and useless – because he had to reach far into the impractical in order to meet his standard of killing the enemy. To him, any idea which fell short of that was not worth considering. This reflects a quality that we might call intent to kill. I have it. Harry Potter has it, which is how he could stare down five older Slytherins. Draco Malfoy does not have it, not yet. Mr Malfoy would hardly shrink from talk of ordinary murder, but even he was shocked – yes you were Mr Malfoy, I was watching your face – when Mr Potter described how to use his classmates’ bodies as raw material. There are censors inside your mind which make you flinch away from thoughts like that. Mr Potter thinks purely of killing the enemy, he will grasp at any means to do so, he does not flinch, his censors are off. Even though his youthful genius is so undisciplined and impractical as to be useless, his intent to kill makes Harry Potter the Most Dangerous Student in the Classroom. One final point to him – no, let us make that a point to Ravenclaw – for this indispensable requisite of a true fighting wizard.’

Harry’s mouth gaped open in speechless shock as he searched frantically for something to say to this. That is so completely not what I am about!

But he could see that the other students were starting to believe it. Harry’s mind was flipping through possible denials and not finding anything that could stand up against the authoritative voice of Professor Quirrell. The best Harry had come up with was ‘I’m not a psychopath, I’m just very creative’ and that sounded kind of ominous. He needed to say something unexpected, something that would make people stop and reconsider –

‘And now,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘Mr Potter. Fire.’

Nothing happened, of course.

‘Ah, well,’ said Professor Quirrell. He sighed. ‘I suppose we must all start somewhere. Mr Potter, select any student you please for a Simple Strike Hex. You will do so before I dismiss your class for the day. If you do not, I will begin deducting House points, and I will keep on deducting them until you do.’

Harry carefully raised his wand. He had to do that much, or Professor Quirrell might start deducting House points right away.

Slowly, as though on a roasting platter, Harry turned to face the Slytherins.

And Harry’s eyes met Draco’s.

Draco Malfoy didn’t look the slightest bit afraid. The blonde-haired boy wasn’t giving any visible sign of assent such as Harry had given Hermione, but then he could hardly be expected to do so. The other Slytherins would think that rather odd.

‘Why the hesitation?’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Surely there’s only one obvious choice.’

‘Yes,’ Harry said. ‘Only one obvious choice.’

Harry twisted the wand and said ‘Ma-ha-su!’

There was complete silence in the classroom.

Harry shook his left arm, trying to get rid of the lingering sting.

There was more silence.

Finally Professor Quirrell sighed. ‘Yes, quite ingenious, but there was a lesson to be taught and you dodged it. One point from Ravenclaw for showing off your own cleverness at the expense of the actual goal. Class dismissed.’

And before anyone else could say anything, Harry sang out:

‘Just kidding! Ravenclaw!’

There was silence for a brief moment after that, a sound of people thinking, and then the murmurs started and rapidly rose to a roar of conversation.

Harry turned towards Professor Quirrell, the two of them needed to talk –

Quirrell had slumped over and was trudging back to his chair.

No. Not acceptable. They really needed to talk. Stuff the zombie act, Professor Quirrell would probably wake up if Harry poked him a couple of times. Harry started forward –

Wrong

Don't

Bad idea

Harry swayed and stopped in his tracks, feeling dizzy.

And then a flock of Ravenclaws descended on him and the discussions began.

Dominance Hierarchies

It was breakfast time on Friday morning. Harry took another huge bite out of his toast and then tried to remind his brain that scoffing his breakfast wouldn’t actually get him into the dungeons any faster. Anyway they had a full hour of study time between breakfast and the start of Potions.

But dungeons! In Hogwarts! Harry’s imagination was already sketching the chasms, narrow bridges, torch-lit sconces, and patches of glowing moss. Would there be rats? Would there be dragons?

‘Harry Potter,’ said a quiet voice from behind him.

Harry looked over his shoulder and found himself beholding Ernie Macmillan, smartly dressed in yellow-trimmed robes and looking a little worried.

‘Neville thought I should warn you,’ Ernie said in a low voice. ‘I think he’s right. Be careful of the Potions Master in our session today. The older Hufflepuffs told us that Professor Snape can be really nasty to people he doesn’t like, and he doesn’t like most people who aren’t Slytherins. If you say anything smart to him it … it could be really bad for you, from what I’ve heard. Just keep your head down and don’t give him any reason to notice you.’

There was a pause as Harry processed this, and then he lifted his eyebrows. (Harry wished he could raise just one eyebrow, like Spock, but he’d never been able to manage.) ‘Thanks,’ Harry said. ‘You might’ve just saved me a lot of trouble.’

Ernie nodded, and turned to go back to the Hufflepuff table.

Harry resumed eating his toast.

It was around four bites afterwards that someone said ‘Pardon me,’ and Harry turned around to see an older Ravenclaw, looking a little worried –

Some time later, Harry was finishing up his third plate of rashers. (He’d learned to eat heavily at breakfast. He could always eat lightly at lunch if he didn’t end up using the Time-Turner.) And there was yet another voice from behind him saying ‘Harry?’

‘Yes,’ Harry said wearily, ‘I’ll try not to draw Professor Snape’s attention –’

‘Oh, that’s hopeless,’ said Fred.

‘Completely hopeless,’ said George.

‘So we had the house elves bake you a cake,’ said Fred.

‘We’re going to put one candle on it for every point you lose for Ravenclaw,’ said George.

‘And have a party for you at the Gryffindor table during lunch,’ said Fred.

‘We hope that’ll cheer you up afterwards,’ finished George.

Harry swallowed his last bite of rasher and turned around. ‘All right,’ said Harry. ‘I wasn’t going to ask this after Professor Binns, I really wasn’t, but if Professor Snape is that awful why hasn’t he been fired?’

‘Fired?’ said Fred.

‘You mean, let go?’ said George.

‘Yes,’ Harry said. ‘It’s what you do to bad teachers. You fire them. Then you hire a better teacher instead. You don’t have unions or tenure here, right?’

Fred and George were frowning in much the same way that hunter-gatherer tribal elders might frown if you tried to tell them about calculus.

‘I don’t know,’ said Fred after a while. ‘I never thought about that.’

‘Me neither,’ said George.

‘Yeah,’ said Harry, ‘I get that a lot. See you at lunch, guys, and don’t blame me if there aren’t any candles on that cake.’

Fred and George both laughed, as if Harry had said something funny, and bowed to him and headed back toward Gryffindor.

Harry turned back to the breakfast table and grabbed a cupcake. His stomach already felt full, but he had a feeling this morning might use a lot of calories.

As he ate his cupcake, Harry thought of the worst teacher he’d met so far, Professor Binns of History. Professor Binns was a ghost. From what Hermione had said about ghosts, it didn’t seem likely that they were fully self-aware. There were no famous discoveries made by ghosts, or much of any original work, no matter who they’d been in life. Ghosts tended to have trouble remembering the current century. Hermione had said they were like accidental portraits, impressed into the surrounding matter by a burst of psychic energy accompanying a wizard’s sudden death.

Harry had run into some stupid teachers during his abortive forays into standard Muggle education – his father had been a lot pickier when it came to selecting grad students as tutors, of course – but History class was the first time he’d encountered a teacher who literally wasn’t sentient.

And it showed, too. Harry had given up after five minutes and started reading a textbook. When it became clear that ‘Professor Binns’ wasn’t going to object, Harry had also reached into his pouch and withdrawn earplugs.

Did ghosts not require a salary? Was that it? Or was it literally impossible to fire anyone in Hogwarts even if they died?

Now it seemed that Professor Snape was going about being absolutely awful to everyone who wasn’t a Slytherin and it hadn’t even occurred to anyone to terminate his contract.

And the Headmaster had set fire to a chicken.

‘Excuse me,’ came a worried voice from behind him.

‘I swear,’ Harry said without turning around, ‘this place is almost eight and a half percent as bad as what Dad says about Oxford.’

Harry stamped down the stone corridors, looking affronted, annoyed, and infuriated all at once.

‘Dungeons!’ Harry hissed. ‘Dungeons! These are not dungeons! This is a basement! A basement!’

Some of the Ravenclaw girls gave him odd looks. The boys were all used to him by now.

It seemed that the level in which the Potions classroom was located was called the ‘dungeons’ for no better reason than that it was below ground and slightly colder than the main castle.

In Hogwarts! In Hogwarts! Harry had been waiting his whole life and now he was still waiting and if there was anywhere on the face of the Earth that had decent dungeons it ought to be Hogwarts! Was Harry going to have to build his own castle if he wanted to see one little bottomless abyss?

A short time later they got to the actual Potions classroom and Harry cheered up considerably.

The Potions classroom had strange preserved creatures floating in huge jars on shelves that covered every centimetre of wall space between the closets. Harry was far enough along in his reading now that he could actually identify some of the creatures, like the Zabriskan Fontema. Albeit the fifty-centimetre spider looked like an Acromantula but it was too small to be one. He’d tried asking Hermione, but she hadn’t seemed very interested in looking anywhere near where he was pointing.

Harry was looking at a large dust ball with eyes and feet when the assassin swept into the room.

That was the first thought that crossed Harry’s mind when he saw Professor Severus Snape. There was something quiet and deadly about the way the man stalked between the children’s desks. His robes were unkempt, his hair spotted and greasy. There was something about him that seemed reminiscent of Lucius, although the two of them looked nothing remotely alike, and you got the impression that where Lucius would kill you with flawless elegance, this man would simply kill you.

‘Sit down,’ said Professor Severus Snape. ‘Now.’

Harry and a few other children who had been standing around talking to each other scrambled for desks. Harry had planned on ending up next to Hermione but somehow he found himself sitting down in the nearest empty desk next to Justin Finch-Fletchley (it was a Doubles session, Ravenclaw and Hufflepuff) which put him two desks to the left of Hermione.

Severus seated himself behind the teacher’s desk, and without the slightest transition or introduction, said, ‘Hannah Abbott.’

‘Here,’ said Hannah in a somewhat trembling voice.

‘Susan Bones.’

‘Present.’

And so it went, no one daring to say a word in edgewise, until:

‘Ah, yes. Harry Potter. Our new … celebrity.’

‘The celebrity is present, sir.’

Half the class flinched, and some of the smarter ones suddenly looked like they wanted to run out the door while the classroom was still there.

Severus smiled in an anticipatory sort of way and called the next name on his list.

Harry gave a mental sigh. That had happened way too fast for him to do anything about it. Oh well. Clearly this man already didn’t like him, for whatever reason. And when Harry thought about it, better by far that this Potions professor should pick on him rather than, say, Neville or Hermione. Harry was a lot better able to defend himself. Yep, probably all for the best.

When full attendance had been taken, Severus swept his gaze over the full class. His eyes were as empty as a night sky without stars.

‘You are here,’ Severus said in a quiet voice which the students at back strained to hear, ‘to learn the subtle science and exact art of potion-making. As there is little foolish wand-waving here, many of you will hardly believe this is magic. I don’t expect you will really understand the beauty of the softly simmering cauldron with its shimmering fumes, the delicate power of liquids that creep through human veins,’ this in a rather caressing, gloating tone, ‘bewitching the mind, ensnaring the senses,’ this was just getting creepier and creepier. ‘I can teach you how to bottle fame, brew glory, even stopper death – if you aren’t as great a pack of fools as I usually have to teach.’

Severus somehow seemed to notice the look of skepticism on Harry’s face, or at least his eyes suddenly jumped to where Harry was sitting.

‘Potter!’ snapped the Potions professor. ‘What would I get if I added powdered root of asphodel to an infusion of wormwood?’

Harry blinked. ‘Was that in Magical Drafts and Potions?’ he said. ‘I just finished reading it, and I don’t remember anything which used wormwood –’

Hermione’s hand went up and Harry shot her a glare which caused her to raise her hand even higher.

‘Tut, tut,’ Severus said silkily. ‘Fame clearly isn’t everything.’

‘Really?’ Harry said. ‘But you just told us you’d teach us how to bottle fame. Say, how does that work, exactly? You drink it and turn into a celebrity?’

Three-quarters of the class flinched.

Hermione’s hand was dropping slowly back down. Well, that wasn’t surprising. She might be his rival, but she wasn’t the sort of girl who would play along after it became clear that the professor was deliberately trying to humiliate him.

Harry was trying hard to keep control of his temper. The first rejoinder that had crossed his mind was Abracadabra.

‘Let’s try again,’ said Severus. ‘Potter, where would you look if I told you to find me a bezoar?’

‘That’s not in the textbook either,’ Harry said, ‘but in one Muggle book I read that a trichinobezoar is a mass of solidified hair found in a human stomach, and Muggles used to believe it would cure any poison –’

‘Wrong,’ Severus said. ‘A bezoar is found in the stomach of a goat, it is not made of hair, and it will cure most poisons but not all.’

‘I didn’t say it would, I said that was what I read in one Muggle book –’

‘No one here is interested in your pathetic Muggle books. Final try. What is the difference, Potter, between monksblood and wolfsbane?’

That did it.

‘You know,’ Harry said icily, ‘in one of my quite fascinating Muggle books, they describe a study in which people managed to make themselves look very smart by asking questions about random facts that only they knew. Apparently the onlookers only noticed that the askers knew and the answerers didn’t, and failed to adjust for the unfairness of the underlying game. So, Professor, can you tell me how many electrons are in the outermost orbital of a carbon atom?’

Severus’s smile widened. ‘Four,’ he said. ‘It is a useless fact which no one should bother writing down, however. And for your information, Potter, asphodel and wormwood make a sleeping potion so powerful it is known as the Draught of Living Death. As for monkshood and wolfsbane, they are the same plant, which also goes by the name of aconite, as you would know if you had read One Thousand Magical Herbs and Fungi. Thought you didn’t need to open the book before coming, eh, Potter? All the rest of you should be copying that down so that you will not be as ignorant as him.’ Severus paused, looking quite pleased with himself. ‘And that will be … five points? No, let us make it an even ten points from Ravenclaw for backchat.’

Hermione gasped, along with a number of others.

‘Professor Severus Snape,’ Harry bit out. ‘I know of nothing which I have done to earn your enmity. If there is some problem you have with me which I do not know about, I suggest we –’

‘Shut up, Potter. Ten more points from Ravenclaw. The rest of you, open your books to page 3.’

There was only a slight, only a very faint burning sensation in the back of Harry’s throat, and no moisture at all in his eyes. If crying was not an effective strategy for destroying this Potions professor then there was no point in crying.

Slowly, Harry sat up very straight. All his blood seemed to have been drained away and replaced with liquid nitrogen. He knew he’d been trying to keep his temper but he couldn’t seem to remember why.

‘Harry,’ whispered Hermione frantically from two desks over, ‘stop, please, it’s all right, we won’t count it –’

‘Talking in class, Granger? Three –’

‘So,’ said a voice colder than zero Kelvin, ‘how does one go about filing a formal complaint against an abusive professor? Does one talk to the Deputy Headmistress, write a letter to the Board of Governors … would you care to explain how it works?’

The class was utterly frozen.

‘Detention for one month, Potter,’ Severus said, smiling even more broadly.

‘I decline to recognize your authority as a teacher and I will not serve any detention you give.’

People stopped breathing.

Severus’s smile vanished. ‘Then you will be –’ his voice stopped short.

‘Expelled, were you about to say?’ Harry, on the other hand, was now smiling thinly. ‘But then you seemed to doubt your ability to carry out the threat, or fear the consequences if you did. I, on the other hand, neither doubt nor fear the prospect of finding a school with less abusive professors. Or perhaps I should hire private tutors, as is my accustomed practise, and be taught at my full learning speed. I have enough money in my vault. Something about bounties on a Dark Lord I defeated. But there are teachers at Hogwarts who I rather like, so I think it will be easier if I find some way to get rid of you instead.’

‘Get rid of me?’ Severus said, now also smiling thinly. ‘What an amusing conceit. How do you suppose you will do that, Potter?’

‘I understand there have been a number of complaints about you from students and their parents,’ a guess but a safe one, ‘which leaves only the question of why you’re not already gone. Is Hogwarts too financially strapped to afford a real Potions professor? I could chip in, if so. I’m sure they could find a better class of teacher if they offered double your current salary.’

Two poles of ice radiated freezing winter across the classroom.

‘You will find,’ Severus said softly, ‘that the Board of Governors is not the slightest bit sympathetic to your offer.’

‘Lucius …’ Harry said. ‘That’s why you’re still here. Perhaps I should chat with Lucius about that. I believe he desires to meet with me. I wonder if I have anything he wants?’

Hermione frantically shook her head. Harry noticed out of the corner of his eye, but his attention was all on Severus.

‘You are a very foolish boy,’ Severus said. He wasn’t smiling at all, now. ‘You have nothing that Lucius values more than my friendship. And if you did, I have other allies.’ His voice grew hard. ‘And I find it increasingly unlikely that you were not Sorted into Slytherin. How was it that you managed to stay out of my House? Ah, yes, because the Sorting Hat claimed it was joking. For the first time in recorded history. What were you really chatting about with the Sorting Hat, Potter? Did you have something that it wanted?’

Harry stared into Severus’s cold gaze and remembered that the Sorting Hat had warned him not to meet anyone’s eyes while thinking about – Harry dropped his gaze to Severus’s desk.

‘You seem oddly reluctant to look me in the eyes, Potter!’

A shock of sudden understanding – ‘So it was you the Sorting Hat was warning me about!’

‘What?’ said Severus’s voice, sounding genuinely surprised, though of course Harry didn’t look at his face.

Harry got up out of his desk.

‘Sit down, Potter,’ said an angry voice from somewhere he wasn’t looking.

Harry ignored it, and looked around the classroom. ‘I have no intention of letting one unprofessional teacher ruin my time at Hogwarts,’ Harry said with deadly calm. ‘I think I’ll take my leave of this class, and either hire a tutor to teach me Potions while I’m here, or if the Board is really that locked up, learn over the summer. If any of you decide that you don’t care to be bullied by this man, my sessions will be open to you.’

‘Sit down, Potter!’

Harry strode across the room and grasped the doorknob.

It didn’t turn.

Harry slowly turned around, and caught a glimpse of Severus smiling nastily before he remembered to look away.

‘Open this door.’

‘No,’ said Severus.

‘You are making me feel threatened,’ said a voice so icy it didn’t sound like Harry’s at all, ‘and that is a mistake.’

Severus’s voice laughed. ‘What do you intend to do about it, little boy?’

Harry took six long strides forward away from the door, until he was standing near the back row of desks.

Then Harry drew himself upright and raised his right hand in one terrible motion, fingers poised to snap.

Neville screamed and dived under his desk. Other children shrank back or instinctively raised their arms to shield themselves.

‘Harry don’t!’ shrieked Hermione. ‘Whatever you were going to do to him, don’t do it!’

‘Have you all gone mad?’ barked Severus’s voice.

Slowly, Harry lowered his hand. ‘I wasn’t going to hurt him, Hermione,’ Harry said, his voice a little lower. ‘I was just going to blow up the door.’

Though now that Harry remembered it, you weren’t supposed to Transfigure things that were to be burned, which meant that going back in time afterwards and getting Fred or George to Transfigure some carefully measured amount of explosives might not actually have been such a good idea …

‘Silencio,’ said Severus’s voice.

Harry tried to say ‘What?’ and found that no sound was coming out.

‘This has become ridiculous. I think you’ve been allowed to get yourself in enough trouble for one day, Potter. You are the most disruptive and unruly student I have ever seen, and I don’t recall how many points Ravenclaw has right now, but I’m sure I can manage to wipe them all out. Ten points from Ravenclaw. Ten points from Ravenclaw. Ten points from Ravenclaw! Fifty points from Ravenclaw! Now sit down and watch the rest of the class take their lesson!’

Harry put his hand into his pouch and tried to say marker but of course no words came out. For one brief moment that stopped him; and then it occurred to Harry to spell out M-A-R-K-E-R using finger motions, which worked. P-A-D and he had a pad of paper. Harry strode over to an empty desk, not the one he’d originally sat down in, and scrawled a brief message. He tore off that sheet of paper, put away the marker and pad in a pocket of his robes for quicker access, and held up his message, not to Snape, but to the rest of the class.

I’m leaving
does anyone else
need to get out?

‘You’re insane, Potter,’ Severus said with cold contempt.

Aside from that, no one spoke.

Harry swept an ironic bow to the teacher’s desk, walked over to the wall, and with one smooth motion yanked open a closet door, stepped in, and slammed the door shut behind him.

There was the muffled sound of someone snapping his fingers, and then nothing.

In the classroom, students looked at each other in puzzlement and fear.

The Potions Master’s face was now completely enraged. He crossed the room in terrible strides and yanked open the closet door.

The closet was empty.

One hour earlier, Harry listened from inside the closed closet. There was no sound from outside, and no point in taking risks either.

C-L-O-A-K, his fingers spelled out.

Once he was invisible, he very carefully and slowly cracked open the closet door and peeked out. No one seemed to be in the classroom.

The door wasn’t locked.

It was when Harry was outside the dangerous place and inside the hallway, safely invisible, that some of the anger drained away and he realized what he’d just done.

What he’d just done.

Harry’s invisible face was frozen in absolute horror.

He’d antagonized a teacher three orders of magnitude beyond anything he’d ever managed before. He’d threatened to walk out of Hogwarts and might have to follow through on it. He’d lost all the points Ravenclaw had and then he’d used the Time-Turner …

His imagination showed him his parents yelling at him after he was expelled, Professor McGonagall disappointed in him, and it was just too painful and he couldn’t bear it and he couldn’t think of any way to save himself –

The thought that Harry allowed himself to think was that if getting angry had landed him in all this trouble, then maybe when he was angry he’d think of a way out, things seemed clearer somehow when he was angry.

And the thought that Harry didn’t let himself think was that he just couldn’t face this future if he wasn’t angry.

So he cast his thoughts back and remembered the burning humiliation …

Tut, tut. Fame clearly isn’t everything.

Ten points from Ravenclaw for backchat.

The calming cold washed back through his veins like a wave reflected and returning from some breaker, and Harry let out his breath.

Okay. Back to being sane now.

He was actually feeling a bit disappointed in his non-angry self for collapsing like that and wanting only to get out of trouble. Professor Severus Snape was everyone’s problem. Normal-Harry had forgotten that and wished for a way to protect himself. And let all the other victims go hang? The question wasn’t how to protect himself, the question was how to destroy this Potions professor.

So this is my dark side, is it? Bit of a prejudiced term that, my light side seems more selfish and cowardly, not to mention confused and panicky.

And now that he was thinking clearly, it was equally clear what to do next. He’d already given himself an extra hour to prepare, and could get up to five hours more if required …

Minerva McGonagall waited in the Headmaster’s office.

Dumbledore sat in his padded throne behind his desk, dressed in four layers of formal lavender robes. Minerva sat in a chair before him, opposite Severus in another chair. Facing the three of them was an empty wooden stool.

They were waiting for Harry Potter.

Harry, Minerva thought despairingly, you promised you wouldn’t bite any teachers!

And in her mind she could see very clearly the reply, Harry’s angry face and his outraged response: I said I wouldn’t bite anyone who didn’t bite me first!

There was a knock at the door.

‘Come in!’ Dumbledore called.

The door swept open, and Harry Potter entered. Minerva almost gasped out loud. The boy looked cool, collected, and utterly in control of himself.

‘Good mor–’ Harry’s voice suddenly cut off. His jaw dropped.

Minerva tracked Harry’s gaze, and she saw that Harry was staring at Fawkes where the phoenix sat on its golden perch. Fawkes fluttered his bright red-golden wings like the flickering of a flame, and dipped his head in a measured nod to the boy.

Harry turned to stare at Dumbledore.

Dumbledore winked at him.

Minerva felt she was missing something.

Sudden uncertainty crossed Harry’s face. His coolness wavered. Fear showed in his eyes, then anger, and then the boy was calm again.

A chill went down Minerva’s spine. Something was not right here.

‘Please sit down,’ said Dumbledore. His face was now serious once more.

Harry sat.

‘So, Harry,’ said Dumbledore. ‘I’ve heard one report of this day from Professor Snape. Would you care to tell me what happened in your own words?’

Harry’s gaze flicked dismissively to Severus. ‘It’s not complicated,’ said the boy, smiling thinly. ‘He tried bullying me the way he’s been bullying every non-Slytherin in the school since the day Lucius foisted him off on you. As for the other details, I request a private conversation with you concerning them. A student who is reporting abusive behaviour from a professor can hardly be expected to speak frankly in front of that same professor, after all.’

This time Minerva couldn’t stop herself from gasping out loud.

Severus simply laughed.

And the Headmaster’s face grew grave. ‘Mr Potter,’ the Headmaster said, ‘one does not speak of a Hogwarts professor in such terms. I fear that you labour under a terrible misapprehension. Professor Severus Snape has my fullest confidence, and serves Hogwarts at my own behest, not Lucius Malfoy’s.’

There was silence for a few moments.

When the boy spoke again his voice was icy. ‘Am I missing something here?’

‘Quite a number of things, Mr Potter,’ said the Headmaster. ‘You should understand, to start with, that the purpose of this meeting is to discuss how to discipline you for the events of this morning.’

‘This man has terrorized your school for years. I spoke to students and collected stories to make sure there would be enough for a newspaper campaign to rally the parents against him. Some of the younger students cried while they told me. I almost cried when I heard them! You allowed this abuser to run free? You did this to your students? Why?’

Minerva swallowed a lump in her throat. She’d – thought that, sometimes, but somehow she’d never quite –

‘Mr Potter,’ said the Headmaster, his voice now stern, ‘this meeting is not about Professor Snape. It is about you and your disregard for school discipline. Professor Snape has suggested, and I have agreed, that three full months of detention will be appropriate –’

‘Declined,’ Harry said icily.

Minerva was speechless.

‘This is not a request, Mr Potter,’ the Headmaster said. The full, entire force of the wizard’s gaze was turned on the boy. ‘This is your punishme–’

‘You will explain to me why you allowed this man to hurt the children placed in your care, and if your explanation is not sufficient then I will begin my newspaper campaign with you as the target.’

Minerva’s body swayed with the force of that blow, with the sheer raw lèse majesté.

Even Severus looked shocked.

‘That, Harry, would be most extremely unwise,’ Dumbledore said slowly. ‘I am the primary piece opposing Lucius on the game board. For you to do such a thing would strengthen him greatly, and I did not think that was your chosen side.’

The boy was still for a long moment.

‘This conversation grows private,’ Harry said. His hand flicked in Severus’s direction. ‘Send him away.’

Dumbledore shook his head. ‘Harry, did I not tell you that Severus Snape has my fullest confidence?’

The boy’s face showed the shock of it. ‘This man’s bullying makes you vulnerable! I am not the only one who could start a newspaper campaign against you! This is insane! Why are you doing this?’

Dumbledore sighed. ‘I’m sorry, Harry. It has to do with things that you are not, at this time, ready to hear.’

The boy stared at Dumbledore. Then he turned to look at Severus. Then back to Dumbledore again.

‘It is insanity,’ the boy said slowly. ‘You haven’t reined him in because you think he’s part of the pattern. That Hogwarts needs an evil Potions Master to be a proper magical school, just as it needs a ghost to teach History.’

‘That does sound like the sort of thing I would do, doesn’t it?’ said Dumbledore, smiling.

‘Unacceptable,’ Harry said flatly. His gaze was now cold and dark. ‘I will not tolerate bullying or abuse. I had considered many possible ways of dealing with this problem, but I will make it simple. Either this man goes, or I do.’

Minerva gasped again. Something strange flickered in Severus’s eyes.

Now Dumbledore’s gaze was also growing cold. ‘Expulsion, Mr Potter, is the final threat which may be used against a student. It is not customarily used as a threat by students against the Headmaster. This is the best magical school in the entire world, and an education here is not an opportunity given to everyone. Are you under the impression that Hogwarts cannot get along without you?’

And Harry sat there, smiling thinly.

Sudden horror dawned on Minerva. Surely Harry wouldn’t –

‘You forget,’ Harry said, ‘that you’re not the only one who can see patterns. This grows private. Now send him –’ Harry flicked a hand at Severus again, and then stopped in mid-sentence and mid-gesture.

Minerva could see it on Harry’s face, the moment when he remembered.

She’d told him, after all.

‘Mr Potter,’ said the Headmaster, ‘once again, Severus Snape has my fullest confidence.’

‘You told him,’ whispered the boy. ‘You utter fool.’

Dumbledore didn’t react to the insult. ‘Told him what?’

‘That the Dark Lord is alive.’

‘What in Merlin’s name are you on about, Potter?’ cried Severus in tones of sheer astonishment and outrage.

Harry glanced briefly at him, smiling grimly. ‘Oh, so we are a Slytherin, then,’ Harry said. ‘I was starting to wonder.’

And then there was silence.

Finally Dumbledore spoke. His voice was mild. ‘Harry, what are you talking about?’

‘I’m sorry, Albus,’ Minerva whispered.

Severus and Dumbledore turned to look at her.

‘Professor McGonagall didn’t tell me,’ said Harry’s voice, swiftly and less calm than it had been. ‘I guessed. I told you, I can see the patterns too. I guessed, and she controlled her reaction just as Severus did. But her control fell a shade short of perfection, and I could tell it was control, not genuine.’

‘And I told him,’ said Minerva, her voice trembling a little, ‘that you, and I, and Severus were the only ones who knew.’

‘Which she did as a concession to prevent me from simply going around asking questions, as I threatened to do if she didn’t talk,’ Harry said. The boy chuckled briefly. ‘I really should have got one of you alone and told you that she told me everything, to see if you let anything slip. Probably wouldn’t have worked, but would have been worth a shot.’ The boy smiled again. ‘Threat’s still on the table and I do expect to be briefed fully at some point.’

Severus was giving her a look of utter contempt. Minerva raised her chin and bore it. She knew it was deserved.

Dumbledore leaned back in his padded throne. His eyes were as cold as anything Minerva had seen from him since the day his brother died. ‘And you threaten to abandon us to Voldemort if we do not comply with your wishes.’

Harry’s voice was razor-sharp. ‘I regret to inform you that you are not the centre of the universe. I’m not threatening to walk out on magical Britain. I’m threatening to walk out on you. I am not a meek little Frodo. This is my quest and if you want in you will play by my rules.’

Dumbledore’s face was still cold. ‘I am beginning to doubt your suitability as the hero, Mr Potter.’

Harry’s return gaze was equally icy. ‘I am beginning to doubt your suitability as my Gandalf, Mr Dumbledore. Boromir was at least a plausible mistake. What is this Nazgûl doing in my Fellowship?’

Minerva was completely lost. She looked at Severus, to see if he was following this, and she saw that Severus had turned his face away from Harry’s field of vision and was smiling.

‘I suppose,’ Dumbledore said slowly, ‘that from your perspective it is a reasonable question. So, Mr Potter, if Professor Snape is to leave you alone henceforth, will that be the last time this issue arises, or will I find you here every week with a new demand?’

‘Leave me alone?’ Harry’s voice was outraged. ‘I am not his only victim and certainly not the most vulnerable! Have you forgotten how defenceless children are? How much they hurt? Henceforth Severus will treat every student of Hogwarts with appropriate and professional courtesy, or you will find another Potions Master, or you will find another hero!’

Dumbledore started laughing. Full-throated, warm, humorous laughter, as if Harry had just performed a comic dance in front of him.

Minerva didn’t dare move. Her eyes flickered and she saw that Severus was equally motionless.

Harry’s visage grew even colder. ‘You mistake me, Headmaster, if you think that this is a joke. This is not a request. This is your punishment.’

‘Mr Potter –’ Minerva said. She didn’t even know what she was going to say. She simply couldn’t let that go by.

Harry made a shushing gesture at her and continued to speak to Dumbledore. ‘And if that seems impolite to you,’ Harry said, his voice now a little less hard, ‘it seemed no less impolite when you said it to me. You would not say such a thing to anyone who you considered a real human being instead of a subordinate child, and I will treat you with just the same courtesy as you treat me –’

‘Oh, indeed, in very deed, this is my punishment if ever there was one! Of course you’re in here blackmailing me to save your fellow students, not to save yourself! I can’t imagine why I would have thought otherwise!’ Dumbledore was now laughing even harder. He pounded his fist on the desk three times.

Harry’s gaze grew uncertain. His face turned toward her, addressing her for the first time. ‘Excuse me,’ Harry said. His voice seemed to be wavering. ‘Does he need to take his medication or something?’

‘Ah …’ Minerva had no idea what she could possibly say.

‘Well,’ said Dumbledore. He wiped away tears that had formed in his eyes. ‘Pardon me. I’m sorry for the interruption. Please continue with the blackmail.’

Harry opened his mouth, then closed it again. He now seemed a little unsteady. ‘Ah … he’s also to stop reading students’ minds.’

‘Minerva,’ Severus said, his voice deadly, ‘you –’

‘Sorting Hat warned me,’ said Harry.

‘What?’

‘Can’t say anything else. Anyway I think that’s it. I’m done.’

Silence.

‘Now what?’ Minerva said, when it became apparent that no one else was going to say anything.

‘Now what?’ Dumbledore echoed. ‘Why, now the hero wins, of course.’

‘What?’ said Severus, Minerva, and Harry.

‘Well, he certainly seems to have backed us into a corner,’ Dumbledore said, smiling happily. ‘But Hogwarts does need an evil Potions Master, or it just wouldn’t be a proper magical school, now would it? So how about if Professor Snape is only awful toward students in their fifth year and higher?’

‘What?’ said all three of them again.

‘If it’s the most vulnerable victims about whom you’re concerned. Maybe you’re right, Harry. Maybe I have forgotten over the decades what it’s like to be a child. So let’s compromise. Severus will continue to unfairly award points to Slytherin and impose lax discipline on his House, and he will be awful to non-Slytherin students in their fifth year and higher. To others he will be scary, but not abusive. He will promise to only read minds when the safety of a student requires it. Hogwarts will have its evil Potions Master, and the most vulnerable victims, as you put it, will be safe.’

Minerva McGonagall was as shocked as she’d ever been in her life. She glanced uncertainly at Severus, whose face had been left completely neutral, as though he couldn’t decide what sort of expression he ought to be wearing.

‘I suppose that is acceptable,’ Harry said. His voice sounded a bit odd.

‘You can’t be serious,’ Severus said, his voice as expressionless as his face.

‘I am very much in favour of this,’ Minerva said slowly. She was so much in favour that her heart was pounding wildly beneath her robes. ‘But what could we possibly tell the students? They might not have questioned this while Severus was … being awful to everyone, but –’

‘Harry can tell the other students that he discovered a terrible secret of Severus’s and did a bit of blackmail,’ said Dumbledore. ‘It’s true, after all; he discovered that Severus was reading minds, and he certainly did blackmail us.’

‘This is insanity!’ exploded Severus.

‘Bwah ha ha!’ said Dumbledore.

‘Ah …’ said Harry uncertainly. ‘And if anyone asks me why fifth years and above got shafted? I wouldn’t blame them for being irate, and that part wasn’t exactly my idea –’

‘Tell them,’ said Dumbledore, ‘that it wasn’t you who suggested the compromise, that it was all you could get. And then refuse to say anything more. That, too, is true. There’s an art to it, you’ll pick it up with practise.’

Harry nodded slowly. ‘And the points he took from Ravenclaw?’

‘They must not be given back.’

It was Minerva who said it.

Harry looked at her.

‘I’m sorry, Mr Potter,’ she said. She was sorry, but it had to be done. ‘There must be some consequences for your misbehaviour or this school will fall to pieces.’

Harry shrugged. ‘Acceptable,’ he said flatly. ‘But in the future Severus will not strike at my House connections by taking points from me, nor will he waste my valuable time with detentions. Should he feel that my behaviour requires correction, he may communicate his concerns to Professor McGonagall.’

‘Harry,’ Minerva said, ‘will you continue to submit to school discipline, or are you to be above the law now, as Severus was?’

Harry looked at her. Something warm touched his gaze, briefly before it was quashed. ‘I will continue to be an ordinary student to every member of the staff who is not insane or evil, provided that they do not come under pressure from others who are.’ Harry glanced briefly at Severus, then turned back to Dumbledore. ‘Leave Minerva alone, and I’ll be a regular Hogwarts student in her presence. No special privileges or immunities.’

‘Beautiful,’ Dumbledore said sincerely. ‘Spoken like a true hero.’

‘And,’ she said, ‘Mr Potter must publicly apologize for his actions of today.’

Harry gave her another look. This one was a bit skeptical.

‘The discipline of the school has been gravely injured by your actions, Mr Potter,’ Minerva said. ‘It must be restored.’

‘I think, Professor McGonagall, that you considerably overestimate the importance of what you call school discipline, as compared to having History taught by a live teacher or not torturing your students. Maintaining the current status hierarchy and enforcing its rules seems ever so much more wise and moral and important when you are on the top and doing the enforcing than when you are on the bottom, and I can cite studies to this effect if required. I could go on for several hours about this point, but I will leave it at that.’

Minerva shook her head. ‘Mr Potter, you underestimate the importance of discipline because you are not in need of it yourself –’ She paused. That hadn’t come out right, and Severus, Dumbledore, and even Harry were giving her strange looks. ‘To learn, I mean. Not every child can learn in the absence of authority. And it is the other children who will be hurt, Mr Potter, if they see your example as one to be followed.’

Harry’s lips curved into a twisted smile. ‘The first and last resort is the truth. The truth is that I shouldn’t have got angry, I shouldn’t have disrupted the class, I shouldn’t have done what I did, and I set a bad example for everyone. The truth is also that Severus Snape behaved in a fashion unbecoming a Hogwarts professor, and that from now on he will be more mindful of the injured feelings of students in their fourth year and under. The two of us could both get up and speak the truth. I could live with that.’

‘In your dreams, Potter!’ spat Severus.

‘After all,’ said Harry, smiling grimly, ‘if the students see that rules are for everyone … for professors too, not just for poor helpless students who get nothing but suffering out of the system … why, the positive effects on school discipline should be tremendous.’

There was a brief pause, and then Dumbledore chuckled. ‘Minerva is thinking that you’re righter than you have any right to be.’

Harry’s gaze jerked away from Dumbledore, down to the floor. ‘Are you reading her mind?’

‘Common sense is often mistaken for Legilimency,’ said Dumbledore. ‘I shall talk over this matter with Severus, and no apology will be required from you unless he apologizes as well. And now I declare this matter concluded, at least until lunchtime.’ He paused. ‘Although, Harry, I’m afraid that Minerva wished to speak with you about an additional matter. And that is not the result of any pressure on my part. Minerva, if you would?’

Minerva rose from her chair and almost fell. There was too much adrenaline in her blood, her heart was beating too fast.

‘Fawkes,’ said Dumbledore, ‘accompany her, please.’

‘I don’t –’ she started to say.

Dumbledore shot her a look, and she fell silent.

The phoenix soared across the room like a smooth tongue of flame leaping out, and landed on her shoulder. She felt the warmth through her robes, all through her body.

‘Please follow me, Mr Potter,’ she said, firmly now, and they left through the door.

They stood on the rotating stairs, descending in silence.

Minerva didn’t know what to say. She didn’t know this person who stood beside her.

And Fawkes began to croon.

It was tender, and soft, like a fireplace would sound if it had melody, and it washed over Minerva’s mind, easing, soothing, gentling what it touched …

‘What is that?’ Harry whispered beside her. His voice was unstable, wobbling, changing pitch.

‘The song of the phoenix,’ said Minerva, not really aware of what she was saying, her attention was all on that strange quiet music. ‘It, too, heals.’

Harry turned his face from her, but she caught a glimpse of something agonized.

The descent seemed to take a very long time, or maybe it was only that the music seemed to take a very long time, and when they stepped out through the gap where a gargoyle had been, she was holding Harry’s hand firmly in hers.

As the gargoyle stepped back into place, Fawkes left her shoulder, and swooped to hover in front of Harry.

Harry stared at Fawkes like someone hypnotized by the ever-changing light of a fire.

‘What am I to do, Fawkes?’ whispered Harry. ‘I couldn’t have protected them if I hadn’t been angry.’

The phoenix’s wings continued flapping, it continued hovering in place. There was no sound but the beating of the wings. Then there was a flash like a fire flaring up and going out, and Fawkes was gone.

Both of them blinked, like waking up from a dream, or maybe like falling asleep again.

Minerva looked down.

Harry Potter’s bright young face looked up at her.

‘Are phoenixes people?’ said Harry. ‘I mean, are they smart enough to count as people? Could I talk with Fawkes if I knew how?’

Minerva blinked hard. Then she blinked again. ‘No,’ Minerva said, her voice wavering. ‘Phoenixes are creatures of powerful magic. That magic gives their existence a weight of meaning which no simple animal could possess. They are fire, light, healing, rebirth. But in the end, no.’

‘Where can I get one?’

Minerva leaned down and hugged him. She hadn’t meant to, but she didn’t seem to have much choice in the matter.

When she stood up she found it hard to speak. But she had to ask. ‘What happened today, Harry?’

‘I don’t know the answers to any of the important questions either. Aside from that I’d really rather not think about it for a while.’

Minerva took his hand in hers again, and they walked the rest of the way in silence.

It was only a short trip, since naturally the office of the Deputy was close to the office of the Headmaster.

Minerva sat behind her desk.

Harry sat in front of her desk.

‘So,’ Minerva whispered. She would have given almost anything not to do this, or not to be the one who had to do it, or for it to be any time but right now. ‘There is a matter of school discipline. From which you are not exempt.’

‘Namely?’ said Harry.

He didn’t know. He hadn’t figured it out yet. She felt her throat tighten. But there was work to be done and she would not shirk it.

‘Mr Potter,’ said Professor McGonagall, ‘I need to see your Time-Turner, please.’

All the peace of the phoenix vanished from his face in an instant and Minerva felt like she had just stabbed him.

‘No!’ Harry said. His voice was panicked. ‘I need it, I won’t be able to attend Hogwarts, I won’t be able to sleep!’

‘You’ll be able to sleep,’ she said. ‘The Ministry has delivered the protective shell for your Time-Turner. I will enchant it to open only between the hours of 9PM and midnight.’

Harry’s face twisted. ‘But – but I –’

‘Mr Potter, how many times have you used the Time-Turner since Monday? How many hours?’

‘I …’ Harry said. ‘Hold on, let me add it up –’ He glanced down at his watch.

Minerva felt a rush of sadness. She’d thought so. ‘It wasn’t just two per day, then. I suspect that if I asked your dorm-mates, I would find that you were struggling to stay up long enough to go to sleep at a reasonable time, and waking up earlier and earlier every morning. Correct?’

Harry’s face said everything she needed to know.

‘Mr Potter,’ she said gently, ‘there are students who cannot be entrusted with Time-Turners, because they become addicted to them. We give them a potion which lengthens their sleep cycle by the necessary amount, but they end up using the Time-Turner for more than just attending their classes. And so we must take them back. Mr Potter, you have taken to using the Time-Turner as your solution to everything, often very foolishly so. You used it to get back a Remembrall. You vanished from a closet in a fashion apparent to other students, instead of going back after you were out and getting me or someone else to come and open the door.’

From the look on Harry’s face he hadn’t thought of that.

‘And more importantly,’ she said, ‘you should have simply sat in Professor Snape’s class. And watched. And left at the end of class. As you would have done if you had not possessed a Time-Turner. There are some students who cannot be entrusted with Time-Turners, Mr Potter. You are one of them. I am sorry.’

‘But I need it!’ Harry blurted. ‘What if there are Slytherins threatening me and I have to escape? It keeps me safe –’

‘Every other student in this castle runs the same risk, and I assure you that they survive. No student has died in this castle for fifty years. Mr Potter, you will hand over your Time-Turner and do so now.’

Harry’s face twisted in agony, but he drew out the Time-Turner from under his robes and gave it to her.

From her desk, Minerva drew out one of the protective shells that had been sent to Hogwarts. She snapped the cover into place around the Time-Turner’s turning hourglass, and then she laid her wand on the cover to complete the enchantment.

‘This isn’t fair!’ Harry shrieked. ‘I saved half of Hogwarts from Professor Snape today, is it right that I be punished for it? I saw the look on your face, you hated what he was doing!’

Minerva didn’t speak for a few moments. She was enchanting.

When she finished and looked up, she knew that her face was stern. Maybe it was the wrong thing to do. And then again maybe it was the right thing to do. There was an obstinate child in front of her, and that didn’t mean the universe was broken.

‘Fair, Mr Potter?’ she snapped. ‘I have had to file two reports with the Ministry on public use of a Time-Turner in two successive days! Be extremely grateful you were allowed to retain the Time-Turner even in restricted form! The Headmaster made a Floo call to plead with them personally and if you were not the Boy-Who-Lived even that would not have sufficed!’

Harry gaped at her.

She knew that he was seeing the angry face of Professor McGonagall.

Harry’s eyes filled up with tears.

‘I’m, sorry,’ he whispered, voice now choked and broken. ‘I’m sorry, to have, disappointed you …’

‘I’m sorry too, Mr Potter,’ she said sternly, and handed him the newly restricted Time-Turner. ‘You may go.’

Harry turned and fled from her office, sobbing. She heard his feet pattering away down the hall, and then the sound cut off as the door swung closed.

‘I’m sorry too, Harry,’ she whispered to the quiet room. ‘I’m sorry too.’

Fifteen minutes into lunch hour.

No one was speaking to Harry. Some of the Ravenclaws were shooting him looks of anger, others of sympathy, a few of the youngest students even had looks of admiration, but no one was talking to him. Even Hermione hadn’t tried to come over.

Fred and George had gingerly stepped near. They hadn’t said anything. The offer was clear, and its optionality. Harry had told them that he would come over when dessert started, no earlier. They had nodded and quickly walked away.

It was probably the utterly expressionless look on Harry’s face that was doing it.

The others probably thought he was controlling anger, or dismay. They knew, because they’d seen Flitwick come and get him, that he’d been called to the Headmaster’s office.

Harry was trying not to smile, because if he smiled, he would start laughing, and if he started laughing, he wouldn’t stop until the nice people in white jackets came to haul him away.

It was too much. It was just all too much. Harry had almost gone over to the Dark Side, his dark side had done things that seemed in retrospect insane, his dark side had won an impossible victory that might have been real and might have been a pure whim of a crazy Headmaster, his dark side had protected his friends. He just couldn’t handle it any more. He needed Fawkes to sing to him again. He needed to use the Time-Turner to go off and take a quiet hour to recover but that wasn’t an option any more and the loss was like a hole in his existence but he couldn’t think about that because then he might start laughing.

Twenty minutes. All the students who were going to eat lunch had arrived, almost none had departed.

The tapping of a spoon rang through the Great Hall.

‘If I may have your attention please,’ Dumbledore said. ‘Harry Potter has something he would like to share with us.’

Harry took a deep breath and got up. He walked over to the Head Table, with every eye staring at him.

Harry turned and looked out at the four tables.

It was becoming harder and harder not to smile, but Harry kept his face expressionless as he spoke his brief and memorized speech.

‘The truth is sacred,’ Harry said tonelessly. ‘One of my most treasured possessions is a button which reads “Speak the truth, even if your voice trembles”. This, then, is the truth. Remember that. I am not saying it because I am being forced to say it, I am saying it because it is true. What I did in Professor Snape’s class was foolish, stupid, childish, and an inexcusable violation of the rules of Hogwarts. I disrupted the classroom and deprived my fellow students of their irreplaceable learning time. All because I failed to control my temper. I hope that not a single one of you will ever follow my example. I certainly intend to try never to follow it again.’

Many of the students gazing at Harry now had solemn, unhappy looks upon their faces, such as one might see at a ceremony marking the loss of a fallen champion. At the younger parts of the Gryffindor table the look was almost universal.

Until Harry raised his hand.

He did not raise it high. That might have appeared peremptory. He certainly did not raise it toward Severus. Harry simply raised his hand to chest level, and softly snapped his fingers, a gesture that was seen more than heard. It was possible that most of the Head Table wouldn’t see it at all.

This seeming gesture of defiance won sudden smiles from the younger students and Gryffindors, and coldly superior sneers from Slytherin, and frowns and worried looks from all others.

Harry kept his face expressionless. ‘Thank you,’ he said. ‘That’s all.’

‘Thank you, Mr Potter,’ said the Headmaster. ‘And now Professor Snape has something to share with us as well.’

Severus smoothly stood up from his place at the Head Table. ‘It has been brought to my attention,’ he said, ‘that my own actions played a part in provoking the admittedly inexcusable anger of Mr Potter, and in the ensuing discussion I realized that I had forgotten how easily injured are the feelings of the young and immature –’

There was the sound of many people emitting muffled chokes at the same time.

Severus continued as if he had not heard. ‘The Potions classroom is a dangerous place, and I still feel that strict discipline is necessary, but henceforth I will be more aware of the … emotional fragility … of students in their fourth year and younger. My deduction of points from Ravenclaw still stands, but I will revoke Mr Potter’s detention. Thank you.’

There was a single clap from the direction of Gryffindor and faster than lightning Severus’s wand was in his hand and ‘Quietus!’ silenced the offender.

‘I will still demand discipline and respect in all my classes,’ Severus said coldly, ‘and anyone who trifles with me will regret it.’

He sat down.

‘Thank you too!’ Headmaster Dumbledore said cheerfully. ‘Carry on!’

And Harry, still expressionless, began to walk back to his seat in Ravenclaw.

There was an explosion of conversation. Two words were clearly identifiable in the beginning. The first was an initial ‘What –’ beginning many different sentences such as ‘What just happened –’ and ‘What the hell –’ The second was ‘Scourgify!’ as students cleaned up the dropped food and spit-out drinks from themselves, the tablecloth, and each other.

Some students were weeping openly. So was Professor Sprout.

At the Gryffindor table, where a cake waited with fifty-one unlit candles, Fred whispered, ‘I think we may be out of our league here, George.’

And from that day onward, no matter what Hermione tried to tell anyone, it would be an accepted legend of Hogwarts that Harry Potter could make absolutely anything happen by snapping his fingers.

Yes, Professor Quirrell had said, it must be in front of everyone, in front of your friends, because that is where Snape confronted you and that is where you must learn to lose.

So now the first year watched. In magically enforced silence, and with requests from both Harry and the professor not to intervene. Hermione had her face turned away, but she hadn’t spoken out or even given him any sort of significant look, maybe because she’d been there in Potions too.

Harry stood on a soft blue mat, such as might be found in a Muggle dojo, which Professor Quirrell had laid out upon the floor for when Harry was pushed down.

Harry was frightened of what he might do. If Professor Quirrell was right about his intent to kill …

Harry’s wand lay on Professor Quirrell’s desk, not because Harry knew any spells that could defend him, but because otherwise (Harry thought) he might have tried to jam it through someone’s eye socket. His pouch lay there, now containing his protected but still potentially fragile Time-Turner.

Harry had pleaded with Professor Quirrell to Transfigure him some boxing gloves and lock them on his hands. Professor Quirrell had given him a look of silent understanding, and refused.

I will not go for their eyes, I will not go for their eyes, I will not go for their eyes, it would be the end of my life in Hogwarts, I’ll be arrested, Harry chanted to himself, trying to hammer the thought into his brain, hoping it would stay there if his intent to kill took over.

Professor Quirrell returned, escorting thirteen older Slytherins of different years. Harry recognized one of them as the one he’d hit with a pie. Two others from that confrontation were also present. The one who’d said to stop, that they really shouldn’t do this, was missing.

‘I repeat,’ Professor Quirrell said, sounding very stern, ‘Potter is not to be really hurt. Any and all accidents will be treated as deliberate. Do you understand?’

The older Slytherins nodded, grinning.

‘Then please feel free to take the Boy-Who-Lived down a few pegs,’ Professor Quirrell said, with a twisted smile that only the first-years understood.

By some form of mutual consent, the pie-target was at the front of the group.

‘Potter,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘meet Mr Peregrine Derrick. He is better than you and he is about to show you that.’

Derrick strode forward and Harry’s brain screamed discordantly, he must not run away, he must not fight back –

Derrick stopped an arm’s length away from Harry.

Harry wasn’t angry yet, just frightened. And that meant he beheld a teenage boy fully half a metre taller than himself, with clearly defined muscles, facial hair, and a grin of terrible anticipation.

‘Ask him not to hurt you,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘Perhaps if he sees that you’re pathetic enough, he’ll decide that you’re boring, and go away.’

There was laughter from the watching older Slytherins.

‘Please,’ Harry said, his voice faltering, ‘don’t, hurt, me …’

‘That didn’t sound very sincere,’ said Professor Quirrell.

Derrick’s smile widened. The clumsy imbecile was looking very superior and …

… Harry’s blood temperature was dropping …

‘Please don’t hurt me,’ Harry tried again.

Professor Quirrell shook his head. ‘How in Merlin’s name did you manage to make that sound like an insult, Potter? There is only one response you can possibly expect from Mr Derrick.’

Derrick stepped forward deliberately, and bumped into Harry.

Harry staggered back a few feet and, before he could stop himself, straightened up icily.

‘Wrong,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘wrong, wrong, wrong.’

‘You bumped into me, Potter,’ Derrick said. ‘Apologize.’

‘I’m sorry!’

‘You don’t sound sorry,’ said Derrick.

Harry’s eyes widened in indignation, he had managed to make that sound pleading –

Derrick pushed him, hard, and Harry fell to the mat on his hands and knees.

The blue fabric seemed to waver in Harry’s vision, not far away.

He was beginning to doubt Professor Quirrell’s real motives in teaching this so-called lesson.

A foot rested on Harry’s buttocks and a moment later Harry was pushed hard to the side, sending him sprawling on his back.

Derrick laughed. ‘This is fun,’ he said.

All he had to do was say it was over. And report the whole thing to the Headmaster’s office. That would be the end of this Defence Professor and his ill-fated stay at Hogwarts and … Professor McGonagall would be angry about that, but …

(An image of Professor McGonagall’s face flashed before his eyes, she didn’t look angry, just sad –)

‘Now tell him that he’s better than you, Potter,’ said Professor Quirrell’s voice.

‘You’re, better, than, me.’

Harry started to raise himself and Derrick put a foot on his chest and shoved him back down to the mat.

The world was becoming transparent as crystal. Lines of action and their consequences stretched out before him in utter clarity. The fool wouldn’t be expecting him to strike back, a quick hit in the groin would stun him long enough for –

‘Try again,’ said Professor Quirrell and with a sudden sharp motion Harry rolled and sprang to his feet and whirled on where stood his real enemy, the Defence Professor –

Professor Quirrell said, ‘You have no patience.’

Harry faltered. His mind, well-honed in pessimism, drew a picture of a wizened old man with blood pouring from his mouth after Harry had ripped his tongue out –

A moment later, Derrick pushed Harry to the mat again and then sat down on him, sending Harry’s breath whooshing out.

‘Stop!’ Harry screamed. ‘Please stop!’

‘Better,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘That even sounded sincere.’

It had been. That was the horrible thing, the sickening thing, it had been sincere. Harry was panting rapidly, fear and cold anger both flushing through him –

‘Lose,’ said Professor Quirrell.

‘I, lose,’ Harry forced out.

‘I like it,’ Derrick said from on top of him. ‘Lose some more.’

Hands shoved Harry, sending him stumbling across the circle of older Slytherins to another set of hands that shoved him again. Harry had long since passed the point of trying not to cry, and was now just trying not to fall down.

‘What are you, Potter?’ said Derrick.

‘A, l-loser, I lose, I give up, you win, you’re b-better, than me, please stop –’

Harry tripped over a foot and went crashing to the ground, hands not quite able to catch himself. He was dazed for a moment, then began struggling to his feet again –

‘Enough!’ said Professor Quirrell’s voice, sounding sharp enough to cut iron. ‘Step away from Mr Potter!’

Harry saw the surprised looks on their faces. The chill in his blood, which had been flowing and ebbing, smiled in cold satisfaction.

Then Harry collapsed to the mat.

Professor Quirrell talked. There were gasps from the older Slytherins.

‘And I believe the scion of Malfoy has something he wants to explain to you as well,’ finished Professor Quirrell.

Draco’s voice started talking. His voice sounded almost as sharp as professor Quirrell’s, it had acquired the same cadence Draco had used to imitate his father, and it was saying things like could have put Slytherin House in jeopardy and who knows how many allies in this school alone and total lack of awareness, never mind cunning and dull thugs, useful for nothing but lackeys and something in Harry’s hindbrain, despite everything he knew, was designating Draco as an ally.

Harry ached all over, was probably bruised, his body felt cold, his mind utterly exhausted. He tried to think of Fawkes’s song, but without the phoenix present he couldn’t remember the melody and when he tried to imagine it he couldn’t seem to think of anything except a bird chirping.

Then Draco stopped talking and Professor Quirrell told the older Slytherins they were dismissed, and Harry opened his eyes and struggled to sit up, ‘Wait,’ Harry said, forcing the words out, ‘there’s something, I want, to say, to them –’

‘Wait on Mr Potter,’ Professor Quirrell said coldly to the departing Slytherins.

Harry swayed to his feet. He was careful not to look in the direction of his classmates. He didn’t want to see how they were looking at him now. He didn’t want to see their pity.

So instead Harry looked at the older Slytherins, who still seemed to be in a state of shock. They stared back at him. Dread was on their faces.

His dark side, when it was in control, had held to the imagination of this moment, and went on pretending to lose.

Harry said, ‘No one will –’

‘Stop,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘If that’s what I think it is, please wait until after they’re gone. They’ll hear about it later. We all have our lessons to learn, Mr Potter.’

‘All right,’ Harry said.

‘You. Go.’

The older Slytherins fled and the door closed behind them.

‘No one’s to take any revenge on them,’ Harry said hoarsely. ‘That’s a request to anyone who considers themselves my friend. I had my lesson to learn, they helped me learn it, they had their lesson to learn too, it’s over. If you tell this story, make sure you tell that part too.’

Harry turned to look at Professor Quirrell.

‘You lost,’ said Professor Quirrell, his voice gentle for the first time. It sounded strange coming from the professor, like his voice shouldn’t even be able to do that.

Harry had lost. There had been moments when the cold anger had faded entirely, replaced by fear, and during those moments he’d begged the older Slytherins and he’d meant it …

‘And are you yet alive?’ said Professor Quirrell, still with that strange gentleness.

Harry managed to nod.

‘Not all losing is like this,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘There are compromises and negotiated surrenders. There are other ways to placate bullies. There is a whole art form to manipulating others by letting them be dominant over you. But first, losing must be thinkable. Will you remember how you lost?’

‘Yes.’

‘Will you be able to lose?’

‘I … think so …’

‘I think so too.’ Professor Quirrell bowed so low that his thin hair almost touched the floor. ‘Congratulations, Harry Potter, you win.’

There was no single source, no first mover, the applause started all at once like a massive thunderclap.

Harry’s couldn’t keep the shock from his face. He risked a glance at his classmates, and he saw their faces showing not pity but awe. The applause was coming from Ravenclaw and Gryffindor and Hufflepuff and even Slytherin, probably because Draco Malfoy was applauding too. Some students were standing up from their chairs and half of Gryffindor was standing on their desks.

So Harry stood there, swaying, letting their respect wash over him, feeling stronger, and maybe even a little healed.

Professor Quirrell waited for the applause to die away. It took quite a while.

‘Surprised, Mr Potter?’ Professor Quirrell said. His voice sounded amused. ‘You have just found out that the real world does not always work like your worst nightmares. Yes, if you had been some poor anonymous boy being abused, then they would probably have respected you less afterwards, pitied you even as they comforted you from their loftier perches. That is human nature, I’m afraid. But you they already know for a figure of power. And they saw you confront your fear and keep confronting it, even though you could have walked away at any time. Did you think less of me when I told you that I had deliberately endured being spat upon?’

Harry felt a burning sensation in his throat and frantically clamped down. He didn’t trust this miraculous respect enough to start crying again in front of it.

‘Your extraordinary achievement in my class deserves an extraordinary reward, Harry Potter. Please accept it with my compliments on behalf of my House, and remember from this day forward that not all Slytherins are alike. There are Slytherins, and then there are Slytherins.’ Professor Quirrell was smiling quite broadly as he said this. ‘Fifty-one points to Ravenclaw.’

There was a shocked pause and then pandemonium broke out among the Ravenclaw students, howling and whistling and cheering.

(And in the same moment Harry felt something wrong about that, Professor McGonagall had been right, there should have been consequences, there should have been a cost and a price to be paid, you couldn’t just put everything back the way it was like that –)

But Harry saw the elated faces in Ravenclaw and knew he couldn’t possibly say no.

His brain made a suggestion. It was a good suggestion. Harry could not even believe his brain was still keeping him upright, let alone producing good suggestions.

‘Professor Quirrell,’ Harry said, as clearly as he could through his burning throat. ‘You are everything a member of your House should be, and I think you must be just what Salazar Slytherin had in mind when he helped found Hogwarts. I thank you and your House,’ Draco was very slightly nodding and subtly turning his finger, keep going, ‘and I think this calls for three cheers for Slytherin. With me, everyone?’ Harry paused. ‘Huzzah!’ Only a few people managed to join in on the first try. ‘Huzzah!’ This time most of Ravenclaw was in on it. ‘Huzzah!’ That was almost all of Ravenclaw, a scattering of Hufflepuffs and around a quarter of Gryffindor.

Draco’s hand moved into a small, quick, thumbs-up gesture.

Most of the Slytherins had expressions of sheer shock. A few were staring at Professor Quirrell in wonder. Blaise Zabini was looking at Harry with a calculating, intrigued expression.

Professor Quirrell bowed. ‘Thank you, Harry Potter,’ he said, still with that broad smile. He turned to the class. ‘Now, believe it or not, we still have half an hour left in this session, and that is enough to introduce the Simple Shield. Mr Potter, of course, is going off and taking a well-earned rest.’

‘I can –’

‘Idiot,’ Professor Quirrell said fondly. The class was already laughing. ‘Your classmates can teach you afterwards, or I’ll tutor you privately if that’s what it takes. But right now, you’re going through the third door from the left in the back of the stage, where you will find a bed, an assortment of exceptionally tasty snacks, and some extremely light reading from the Hogwarts library. You may not take anything else with you, particularly not your textbooks. Now go.’

Harry went.

Bayes's Theorem

Harry stared up at the grey ceiling of the small room, from where he lay on the portable yet soft bed that had been placed there. He’d eaten quite a lot of Professor Quirrell’s snacks – intricate confections of chocolate and other substances, dusted with sparkling sprinkles and jewelled with tiny sugar gems, looking highly expensive and proving, in fact, to be quite tasty. Harry hadn’t felt the least bit guilty about it either, this he had earned.

He hadn’t tried to sleep. Harry had a feeling that he wouldn’t like what happened when he closed his eyes.

He hadn’t tried to read. He wouldn’t have been able to focus.

Funny how Harry’s brain just seemed to keep on running and running, never shutting down no matter how tired it got. It got stupider but it refused to switch off.

But there was, there really and truly was a feeling of triumph.

Anti-Dark-Lord-Harry programme, +1 point didn’t begin to cover it. Harry wondered what the Sorting Hat would say now, if he could put it on his head.

No wonder Professor Quirrell had accused Harry of heading down the path of a Dark Lord. Harry had been too slow on the uptake, he should have seen the parallel right away –

Understand that the Dark Lord did not win that day. His goal was to learn martial arts, and yet he left without a single lesson.

Harry had entered the Potions class with the intent to learn Potions. He’d left without a single lesson.

And Professor Quirrell had heard, and understood with frightening precision, and reached out and yanked Harry off that path, the path that led to his becoming a copy of You-Know-Who.

There was a knock at the door. ‘Classes are over,’ said Professor Quirrell’s quiet voice.

Harry approached the door and found himself suddenly nervous. Then the tension diminished as he heard Professor Quirrell’s footsteps moving away from the door.

What on Earth is that about? Is it what’s going to get him fired eventually?

Harry opened the door, and saw that Professor Quirrell was now waiting several body-lengths away.

Does Professor Quirrell feel it too?

They walked across the now-deserted stage to Professor Quirrell’s desk, which Professor Quirrell leaned on; and Harry, as before, stopped short of the dais.

‘So,’ Professor Quirrell said. There was a friendly sense about him somehow, even though his face still kept its usual seriousness. ‘What was it you wanted to talk to me about, Mr Potter?’

I have a mysterious dark side. But Harry couldn’t just blurt it out like that.

‘Professor Quirrell,’ Harry said, ‘am I off the path to becoming a Dark Lord, now?’

Professor Quirrell looked at Harry. ‘Mr Potter,’ he said solemnly, with only a slight grin, ‘a word of advice. There is such a thing as a performance which is too perfect. Real people who have just been beaten and humiliated for fifteen minutes do not stand up and graciously forgive their enemies. It is the sort of thing you do when you’re trying to convince everyone you’re not Dark, not –’

‘I can’t believe this! You can’t have every possible observation confirm your theory!’

‘And that was a trifle too much indignation.’

‘What on Earth do I have to do to convince you?’

‘To convince me that you harbour no ambitions of becoming a Dark Lord?’ said Professor Quirrell, now looking outright amused. ‘I suppose you could just raise your right hand.’

‘What?’ Harry said blankly. ‘But I can raise my right hand whether or not I –’ Harry stopped, feeling rather stupid.

‘Indeed,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘You can just as easily do it either way. There is nothing you can do to convince me because I would know that was exactly what you were trying to do. And if we are to be even more precise, then while I suppose it is barely possible that perfectly good people exist even though I have never met one, it is nonetheless improbable that someone would be beaten for fifteen minutes and then stand up and feel a great surge of kindly forgiveness for his attackers. On the other hand it is less improbable that a young child would imagine this as the role to play in order to convince his teacher and classmates that he is not the next Dark Lord. The import of an act lies not in what that act resembles on the surface, Mr Potter, but in the states of mind which make that act more or less probable.’

Harry blinked. He’d just had the dichotomy between the representativeness heuristic and the Bayesian definition of evidence explained to him by a wizard.

‘But then again,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘anyone can want to impress their friends. That need not be Dark. So without it being any kind of admission, Mr Potter, tell me honestly. What thought was in your mind at the moment when you forbade any vengeance? Was that thought a true impulse to forgiveness? Or was it an awareness of how your classmates would see the act?’

Sometimes we make our own phoenix song.

But Harry didn’t say it out loud. It was clear that Professor Quirrell wouldn’t believe him, and would probably respect him less for trying to utter such a transparent lie.

After a few moments of silence, Professor Quirrell smiled with satisfaction. ‘Believe it or not, Mr Potter,’ said the professor, ‘you need not fear me for having discovered your secret. I am not going to tell you to give up on becoming the next Dark Lord. If I could turn back the hands of time and somehow remove that ambition from the mind of my child self, the self of this present time would not benefit from the alteration. For as long as I thought that was my goal, it drove me to study and learn and refine myself and become stronger. We become what we are meant to be by following our desires wherever they lead. That is the insight of Salazar. Ask me to show you to the library section which holds those same books I read as a thirteen-year-old, and I will happily lead the way.’

‘For the love of crap,’ Harry said, and sat down on the hard marble floor, and then lay back on the floor, staring up at the distant arches of the ceiling. It was as close as he could come to collapsing in despair without hurting himself.

‘Still too much indignation,’ observed Professor Quirrell. Harry wasn’t looking but he could hear the suppressed laughter in the voice.

Then Harry realized.

‘Actually, I think I know what’s confusing you here,’ Harry said. ‘That was what I wanted to talk to you about, in fact. Professor Quirrell, I think that what you’re seeing is my mysterious dark side.’

There was a pause.

‘Your … dark side …’

Harry sat up. Professor Quirrell was regarding him with one of the strangest expressions Harry had seen on anyone’s face, let alone anyone as dignified as Professor Quirrell.

‘It happens when I get angry,’ Harry explained. ‘My blood runs cold, everything gets cold, everything seems perfectly clear … In retrospect it’s been with me for a while – in my first year of Muggle school, someone tried to take away my ball during recess and I held it behind my back and kicked him in the solar plexus which I’d read was a weak point, and the other kids didn’t bother me after that. And I bit a maths teacher when she wouldn’t accept my dominance. But it’s only just recently that I’ve been under enough stress to notice that it’s an actual, you know, mysterious dark side, and not just an anger management problem like the school psychologist said. And I don’t have any super magical powers when it happens, that was one of the first things I checked.’

Professor Quirrell rubbed his nose. ‘Let me think about this,’ he said.

Harry waited in silence for a full minute. He used that time to stand up, which was more difficult than he had expected.

‘Well,’ Professor Quirrell said after a while. ‘I suppose there was something you could say that would convince me.’

‘I have already guessed that my dark side is really just another part of me and that the answer isn’t to never become angry but to learn to stay in control by accepting it, I’m not dumb or anything and I’ve seen this story enough times to know where it’s going, but it’s hard and you seem like the person to help me.’

‘Well … yes … very perspicacious of you, Mr Potter, I must say … that side of you is, as you seem to have already surmised, your intent to kill, which as you say is a part of you …’

‘And needs to be trained,’ Harry said, completing the pattern.

‘And needs to be trained, yes.’ That strange expression was still on Professor Quirrell’s face. ‘Mr Potter, if you truly do not wish to be the next Dark Lord, then what was the ambition which the Sorting Hat tried to convince you to abandon, the ambition for which you were Sorted into Slytherin?’

‘I was Sorted into Ravenclaw!’

‘Mr Potter,’ said Professor Quirrell, now with a much more usual-looking dry smile, ‘I know you are accustomed to everyone around you being a fool, but please do not mistake me for one of them. The likelihood that the Sorting Hat would play its first prank in eight hundred years while it was upon your head is so small as to not be worth considering. I suppose it is barely possible that you snapped your fingers and invented some simple and clever way to defeat the anti-tampering spells upon the Hat, though I myself can think of no such method. But by far the most probable explanation is that Dumbledore decided he was not happy with the Hat’s choice for the Boy-Who-Lived. This is evident to anyone with the tiniest smidgen of common sense, so your secret is safe at Hogwarts.’

Harry opened his mouth, then closed it again with a feeling of complete helplessness. Professor Quirrell was wrong, but wrong in such a convincing way that Harry was starting to think that it simply was the rational judgement given the evidence available to Professor Quirrell. There were times, never predictable times but still sometimes, when you would get improbable evidence and the best knowable guess would be wrong. If you had a medical test that was only wrong one time in a thousand, sometimes it would still be wrong anyway.

‘Can I ask you never to repeat what I’m about to say?’ said Harry.

‘Absolutely,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Consider me asked.’

Harry wasn’t a fool either. ‘Can I consider you to have said yes?’

‘Very good, Mr Potter. You may indeed so consider.’

‘Professor Quirrell –’

‘I won’t repeat what you’re about to say,’ Professor Quirrell said, smiling.

They both laughed, then Harry turned serious again. ‘The Sorting Hat did seem to think I was going to end up as a Dark Lord unless I went to Hufflepuff,’ Harry said. ‘But I don’t want to be one.’

‘Mr Potter …’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Don’t take this the wrong way. I promise you will not be graded on the answer. I only want to know your own, honest reply. Why not?’

Harry had that helpless feeling again. Thou shalt not become a Dark Lord was such an obvious theorem in his moral system that it was hard to describe the actual proof steps. ‘Um, people would get hurt?’

‘Surely you’ve wanted to hurt people,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘You wanted to hurt those bullies today. Being a Dark Lord means that people you want to hurt get hurt.’

Harry floundered for words and then decided to simply go with the obvious. ‘First of all, just because I want to hurt someone doesn’t mean it’s right –’

‘What makes something right, if not your wanting it?’

‘Ah,’ Harry said, ‘preference utilitarianism.’

‘Pardon me?’ said Professor Quirrell.

‘It’s the ethical theory that the good is what satisfies the preferences of the most people –’

‘No,’ Professor Quirrell said. His fingers rubbed the bridge of his nose. ‘I don’t think that’s quite what I was trying to say. Mr Potter, in the end people all do what they want to do. Sometimes people give names like “right” to things they want to do, but how could we possibly act on anything but our own desires?’

‘Well, obviously,’ Harry said. ‘I couldn’t act on moral considerations if they lacked the power to move me. But that doesn’t mean my wanting to hurt those Slytherins has the power to move me more than moral considerations!’

Professor Quirrell blinked.

‘Not to mention,’ Harry said, ‘being a Dark Lord would mean that a lot of innocent bystanders got hurt too!’

‘Why does that matter to you?’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘What have they done for you?’

Harry laughed. ‘Oh, now that was around as subtle as Atlas Shrugged.’

‘Pardon me?’ Professor Quirrell said again.

‘It’s a book that my parents wouldn’t let me read because they thought it would corrupt me, so of course I read it anyway and I was offended they thought I would fall for any traps that obvious. Blah blah blah, appeal to my sense of superiority, other people are trying to keep me down, blah blah blah.’

‘So you’re saying I need to make my traps less obvious?’ said Professor Quirrell. He tapped a finger on his cheek, looking thoughtful. ‘I can work on that.’

They both laughed.

‘But to stay with the current question,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘what have all these other people done for you?’

‘Other people have done huge amounts for me!’ Harry said. ‘My parents took me in when my parents died because they were good people, and to become a Dark Lord is to betray that!’

Professor Quirrell was silent for a time.

‘I confess,’ said Professor Quirrell quietly, ‘when I was your age, that thought could not ever have come to me.’

‘I’m sorry,’ Harry said.

‘Don’t be,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘It was long ago, and I resolved my parental issues to my own satisfaction. So you are held back by the thought of your parents’ disapproval? Does that mean that if they died in an accident, there would be nothing left to stop you from –’

‘No,’ Harry said. ‘Just no. It is their impulse to kindness which sheltered me. That impulse is not only in my parents. And that impulse is what would be betrayed.’

‘In any case, Mr Potter, you have not answered my original question,’ said Professor Quirrell finally. ‘What is your ambition?’

‘Oh,’ said Harry. ‘Um..’ He organized his thoughts. ‘To understand everything important there is to know about the universe, apply that knowledge to become omnipotent, and use that power to rewrite reality because I have some objections to the way it works now.’

There was a slight pause.

‘Forgive me if this is a stupid question, Mr Potter,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘but are you sure you did not just confess to wanting to be a Dark Lord?’

‘That’s only if you use your power for evil,’ explained Harry. ‘If you use the power for good, you’re a Light Lord.’

‘I see,’ Professor Quirrell said. He tapped his other cheek with a finger. ‘I suppose I can work with that. But Mr Potter, while the scope of your ambition is worthy of Salazar himself, how exactly do you propose to go about it? Is step one to become a great fighting wizard, or Head Unspeakable, or Minister of Magic, or –’

‘Step one is to become a scientist.’

Professor Quirrell was looking at Harry as if he’d just turned into a cat.

‘A scientist,’ Professor Quirrell said after a while.

Harry nodded.

‘A scientist?’ repeated Professor Quirrell.

‘Yes,’ Harry said. ‘I shall achieve my objectives through the power … of Science!’

‘A scientist!’ said Professor Quirrell. There was genuine indignation on his face, and his voice had grown stronger and sharper. ‘You could be the best of all my students! The greatest fighting wizard to come out of Hogwarts in five decades! I cannot picture you wasting your days in a white lab coat doing pointless things to rats!’

‘Hey!’ said Harry. ‘There’s more to science than that! Not that there’s anything wrong with experimenting on rats, of course. But science is how you go about understanding and controlling the universe –’

‘Fool,’ said Professor Quirrell, in a voice of quiet, bitter intensity. ‘You’re a fool, Harry Potter.’ He passed a hand over his face, and when that hand had passed, his face was calmer. ‘Or more likely you have not yet found your true ambition. May I strongly recommend that you try to become a Dark Lord instead? I will do anything I can to help as a matter of public service.’

‘You don’t like science,’ Harry said slowly. ‘Why not?’

‘Those fool Muggles will kill us all some day!’ Professor Quirrell’s voice had grown louder. ‘They will end it! End all of it!’

Harry was feeling a bit lost here. ‘What are we talking about here, nuclear weapons?’

‘Yes, nuclear weapons!’ Professor Quirrell was almost shouting now. ‘Even He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named never used those, perhaps because he didn’t want to rule over a heap of ash! They never should have been made! And it will only get worse with time!’ Professor Quirrell was standing up straight instead of leaning on his desk. ‘There are gates you do not open, there are seals you do not breach! The fools who can’t resist meddling are killed by the lesser perils early on, and the survivors all know that there are secrets you do not share with anyone who lacks the intelligence and the discipline to discover them for themselves! Every powerful wizard knows that! Even the most terrible Dark Wizards know that! And those idiot Muggles can’t seem to figure it out! The eager little fools who discovered the secret of nuclear weapons didn’t keep it to themselves, they told their fool politicians and now we must live under the constant threat of annihilation!’

This was a rather different way of looking at things than Harry had grown up with. It had never occurred to him that nuclear physicists should have formed a conspiracy of silence to keep the secret of nuclear weapons from anyone not smart enough to be a nuclear physicist. The thought was intriguing, if nothing else. Would they have had secret passwords? Would they have had masks?

(Actually, for all Harry knew, there were all sorts of incredibly destructive secrets which physicists kept to themselves, and the secret of nuclear weapons was the only one that had escaped into the wild. The world would look the same to him either way.)

‘I’ll have to think about that,’ Harry said to Professor Quirrell. ‘It’s a new idea to me. And one of the hidden secrets of science, passed down from a few rare teachers to their grad students, is how to avoid flushing new ideas down the toilet the instant you hear one you don’t like.’

Professor Quirrell blinked again.

‘Is there any sort of science you do approve of?’ said Harry. ‘Medicine, maybe?’

‘Space travel,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘But the Muggles seem to be dragging their feet on the one project which might have let wizardkind escape this planet before they blow it up.’

Harry nodded. ‘I’m a big fan of the space programme too. At least we have that much in common.’

Professor Quirrell looked at Harry. Something flickered in the professor’s eyes. ‘I will have your word, your promise and your oath never to speak of what follows.’

‘You have it,’ Harry said immediately.

‘See to it that you keep your oath or you will not like the results,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I will now cast a rare and powerful spell, not on you, but on the classroom around us. Stand still, so that you do not touch the boundaries of the spell once it has been cast. You must not interact with the magic which I am maintaining. Look only. Otherwise I will end the spell.’ Professor Quirrell paused. ‘And try not to fall over.’

Harry nodded, puzzled and anticipatory.

Professor Quirrell raised his wand and said something that Harry’s ears and mind couldn’t grasp at all, words that bypassed awareness and vanished into oblivion.

The marble in a short radius around Harry’s feet stayed constant. All the other marble of the floor vanished, the walls and ceilings vanished.

Harry stood on a small circle of white marble in the midst of an endless field of stars, burning terribly bright and unwavering. There was no Earth, no Moon, no Sun that Harry recognized. Professor Quirrell stood in the same place as before, floating in the midst of the star-field. The Milky Way was already visible as a great wash of light and it grew brighter as Harry’s vision adjusted to the darkness.

The sight wrenched at Harry’s heart like nothing he had ever seen.

‘Are we … in space … ?’

‘No,’ said Professor Quirrell. His voice was sad, and reverent. ‘But it is a true image.’

Tears came into Harry’s eyes. He wiped them away frantically, he would not miss this for some stupid water blurring his vision.

The stars were no longer tiny jewels set in a giant velvet dome, as they were in the night sky of Earth. Here there was no sky above, no surrounding sphere. Only points of perfect light against perfect blackness, an infinite and empty void with countless tiny holes through which shone the brilliance from some unimaginable realm beyond.

In space, the stars looked terribly, terribly, terribly far away.

Harry kept on wiping his eyes, over and over.

‘Sometimes,’ Professor Quirrell said in a voice so quiet it almost wasn’t there, ‘when this flawed world seems unusually hateful, I wonder whether there might be some other place, far away, where I should have been. I cannot seem to imagine what that place might be, and if I can’t even imagine it then how can I believe it exists? And yet the universe is so very, very wide, and perhaps it might exist anyway? But the stars are so very, very far away. It would take a long, long time to get there, even if I knew the way. And I wonder what I would dream about, if I slept for a long, long time …’

Though it felt like sacrilege, Harry managed a whisper. ‘Please let me stay here awhile.’

Professor Quirrell nodded, where he stood unsupported against the stars.

It was easy to forget the small circle of marble on which you stood, and your own body, and become a point of awareness which might have been still, or might have been moving. With all distances incalculable there was no way to tell.

There was a time of no time.

And then the stars vanished, and the classroom returned.

Rationalization

Hermione Granger had worried she was turning Bad.

The difference between Good and Bad was usually easy to grasp, she’d never understood why other people had so much trouble. At Hogwarts, ‘Good’ was Professor Flitwick and Professor McGonagall and Professor Sprout. ‘Bad’ was Professor Snape and Professor Quirrell and Draco Malfoy. Harry Potter … was one of those unusual cases where you couldn’t tell just by looking. She was still trying to figure out where he belonged.

But when it came to herself …

Hermione was having too much fun crushing Harry Potter.

She’d done better than him in every single class they’d taken. (Except for broomstick riding, which was like gym class, it didn’t count.) She’d got real House points almost every day of their first week, not for weird heroic things, but smart things like learning spells quickly and helping other students. She knew those kinds of House points were better, and the best part was, Harry Potter knew it too. She could see it in his eyes every time she won another real House point.

If you were Good, you weren’t supposed to enjoy winning this much.

It had started on the day of the train ride, though it had taken a while for the whirlwind to sink in. It wasn’t until later that night that Hermione had begun to realize just how much she’d let that boy walk all over her.

Before she’d met Harry Potter she hadn’t had anyone she’d wanted to crush. If someone wasn’t doing as well as her in class, it was her job to help them, not rub it in. That was what it meant to be Good.

And now …

… now she was winning, Harry Potter was flinching every time she got another House point, and it was so much fun, her parents had warned her against drugs and she suspected this was more fun than that.

She’d always liked the smiles that teachers gave her when she did something right. She’d always liked seeing the long row of ticks on a perfectly answered test. But now when she did well in class she would casually glance around and catch a glimpse of Harry Potter gritting his teeth, and it made her want to burst into song like a Disney film.

That was Bad, wasn’t it?

Hermione had worried she was turning Bad.

And then a thought had come to her which wiped away all her fears.

She and Harry were getting into a Romance! Of course! Everyone knew what it meant when a boy and a girl started fighting all the time. They were courting one another! There was nothing Bad about that.

It couldn’t be that she just enjoyed beating the living scholastic daylights out of the most famous student in the school, someone who was in books and talked like books, the boy who had somehow vanquished the Dark Lord and even crushed Professor Snape like a sad little bug, the boy who was, as Professor Quirrell would have put it, dominant, over everyone else in first-year Ravenclaw except for Hermione Granger who was utterly squishing the Boy-Who-Lived in all his classes besides broomstick riding.

Because that would have been Bad.

No. It was Romance. That was it. That was why they were fighting.

Hermione was glad she had figured this out in time for today, when Harry would lose their book-reading contest, which the whole school knew about, and she wanted to start dancing with the sheer overflowing joy of it.

It was 2:45pm on Saturday and Harry Potter had half of Bathilda Bagshot’s A History of Magic left to read and she was staring at her pocket watch as it ticked with dreadful slowness toward 2:47pm.

And the entire Ravenclaw common room was watching.

It wasn’t just the first-years, news had spread like spilled milk and fully half of Ravenclaw was crowded into the room, squeezed into sofas and leaning on bookcases and sitting on the arms of chairs. All six prefects were there including the Head Girl of Hogwarts. Someone had needed to cast an Air-Freshening Charm just so that there would be enough oxygen. And the din of conversation had died into whispers which had now faded into utter silence.

2:46pm.

The tension was unbearable. If it had been anyone else, anyone else, his defeat would have been a foregone conclusion.

But this was Harry Potter, and you couldn’t rule out the possibility that he would, sometime in the next few seconds, raise a hand and snap his fingers.

With sudden terror she realized how Harry Potter might be able to do exactly that. It would be just like him to have already finished reading the second half of the book earlier …

Hermione’s vision began to swim. She tried to make herself breathe, and found that she simply couldn’t.

Ten seconds left, and he still hadn’t raised his hand.

Five seconds left.

2:47pm.

Harry Potter carefully placed a bookmark into his book, closed it, and laid it aside.

‘I would like to note for the benefit of posterity,’ said the Boy-Who-Lived in a clear voice, ‘that I had only half a book left, and that I ran into a number of unexpected delays –’

‘You lost!’ shrieked Hermione. ‘You did! You lost our contest!’

There was a collective exhalation as everyone started breathing again.

Harry Potter shot her a Look of Flaming Fire, but she was floating in a halo of pure white happiness and nothing could touch her.

‘Do you realize what kind of week I’ve had?’ said Harry Potter. ‘Any lesser being would have been hard-pressed to read eight Dr Seuss books!’

‘You set the time limit.’

Harry’s Look of Flaming Fire grew even hotter. ‘I did not have any logical way of knowing I’d have to save the entire school from Professor Snape, or get beaten up in Defence class, and if I told you how I lost all the time between 5pm and dinner on Thursday you would think I was insane –’

‘Awww, it sounds like someone fell prey to the planning fallacy.’

Raw shock showed on Harry Potter’s face.

‘Oh that reminds me, I finished reading the first batch of books you lent me,’ Hermione said with her best innocent look. A couple of them had been hard books, too. She wondered how long it had taken him to finish reading them.

‘Someday,’ said the Boy-Who-Lived, ‘when the distant descendants of Homo sapiens are looking back over the history of the galaxy and wondering how it all went so wrong, they will conclude that the original mistake was when someone taught Hermione Granger how to read.’

‘But you still lose,’ said Hermione. She held a hand to her chin and looked contemplative. ‘Now what exactly should you lose, I wonder?’

‘What?’

‘You lost the bet,’ Hermione explained, ‘so you have to pay a forfeit.’

‘I don’t remember agreeing to this!’

‘Really?’ said Hermione Granger. She put a thoughtful look on her face. Then, as if the idea had only just then occurred to her, ‘We’ll take a vote, then. Everyone in Ravenclaw who thinks Harry Potter has to pay up, raise your hand!’

‘What?’ shrieked Harry Potter again.

He spun around and saw that he was surrounded by a sea of raised hands.

And if Harry Potter had looked more carefully, he would have noticed that an awful lot of the onlookers seemed to be girls and that practically every female in the room had their hand raised.

‘Stop!’ wailed Harry Potter. ‘You don’t know what she’s going to ask! Don’t you realize what she’s doing? She’s getting you to make an advance commitment now, and then the pressure of consistency will make you agree with whatever she says afterwards!’

‘Don’t worry,’ said the prefect Penelope Clearwater. ‘If she asks for something unreasonable, we can just change our minds. Right, everyone?’

And there were eager nods from all the girls whom Penelope Clearwater had told about Hermione’s plan.

A silent figure quietly slipped through the chilled halls of the Hogwarts dungeons. He was to be present in a certain room at 6:00pm to meet a certain someone, and if at all possible it was best to be early, to show respect.

But when his hand turned the doorknob and opened the door into that dark, silent, unused classroom, there was a silhouette already standing there amid the rows of dusty old desks. A silhouette which held a small green glowing rod, casting a pale light which hardly illuminated even he who held it, let alone the surrounding room.

The light of the hallway died as the door closed and shut behind him, and Draco’s eyes began the process of adjusting to the dim glow.

The silhouette slowly turned to behold him, revealing a shadowed face only partially lit by the eerie green light.

Draco liked this meeting already. Keep the chill green light, make them both taller, give them hoods and masks, move them from a classroom to a graveyard, and it would be just like the start of half the stories his father’s friends told about the Death Eaters.

‘I want you to know, Draco Malfoy,’ said the silhouette in tones of deadly calm, ‘that I do not blame you for my recent defeat.’

Draco opened his mouth in unthinking protest, there was no possible reason why he should be blamed –

‘It was due, more than anything else, to my own stupidity,’ continued that shadowy figure. ‘There were many other things I could have done, at any step along the way. You did not ask me to do exactly what I did. You only asked for help. I was the one who unwisely chose that particular method. But the fact remains that I lost the contest by half a book. The actions of your pet idiot, and the favour you asked for, and, yes, my own foolishness in going about it, caused me to lose time. More time than you know. Time which, in the end, proved critical. The fact remains, Draco Malfoy, that if you had not asked that favour, I would have won. And not … instead … lost.’

Draco had already heard about Harry’s loss, and the forfeit Granger had claimed from him. The news had spread faster than owls could have carried it.

‘I understand,’ Draco said. ‘I’m sorry.’ There was nothing else he could say if he wanted Harry Potter to be friends with him.

‘I am not asking for understanding or sorrow,’ said the dark silhouette, still with that deadly calm. ‘But I have just spent two full hours in the presence of Hermione Granger, dressed in such clothing as was provided me, visiting such fascinating places in Hogwarts as a tiny burbling waterfall of what looked to me like snot, accompanied by a number of other girls who insisted on such helpful activities as strewing our path with Transfigured rose petals. I have been on a date, scion of Malfoy. My first date. And when I call that favour due, you will pay it.’

Draco nodded solemnly. Before arriving he had taken the wise precaution of learning every available detail of Harry’s date, so that he could get all of his hysterical laughing done before their appointed meeting time, and would not commit a faux pas by giggling continuously until he lost consciousness.

‘Do you think,’ Draco said, ‘that something sad ought to happen to the Granger girl –’

‘Spread the word in Slytherin that the Granger girl is mine and anyone who meddles in my affairs will have their remains scattered over an area wide enough to include twelve different spoken languages. And since I am not in Gryffindor and I use cunning rather than immediate frontal attacks, they should not panic if I am seen smiling at her.’

‘Or if you’re seen on a second date?’ Draco said, allowing just a tiny note of skepticism into his voice.

‘There will be no second date,’ said the green-lit silhouette in a voice so fearsome that it sounded, not only like a Death Eater, but like Amycus Carrow that one time just before Father told him to stop it, he wasn’t the Dark Lord.

Of course it was still a young boy’s high unbroken voice and when you combined that with the actual words, well, it just didn’t work. If Harry Potter did become the next Dark Lord someday, Draco would use a Pensieve to store a copy of this memory somewhere safe, and Harry Potter would never dare betray him.

‘But let us talk of happier matters,’ said the green-shadowed figure. ‘Let us talk of knowledge and of power. Draco Malfoy, let us talk of Science.’

‘Yes,’ said Draco. ‘Let us speak.’

Draco wondered how much of his own face could be seen, and how much was in shadow, in that eerie green light.

And though Draco kept his face serious, there was a smile in his heart.

He was finally having a real grown-up conversation.

‘I offer you power,’ said the shadowy figure, ‘and I will tell you of that power and its price. The power comes from knowing the shape of reality and so gaining control over it. What you understand, you can command, and that is power enough to walk upon the Moon. The price of that power is that you must learn to ask questions of Nature, and far more difficult, accept Nature’s answers. You will do experiments, perform tests and see what happens. And you must accept the meaning of those results when they tell you that you are mistaken. You will have to learn how to lose, not to me, but to Nature. When you find yourself arguing with reality, you will have to let reality win. You will find this painful, Draco Malfoy, and I do not know if you are strong in that way. Knowing the price, is it still your wish to learn the human power?’

Draco took a deep breath. He’d thought about this. And it was hard to see how he could answer any other way. He’d been instructed to take every avenue of friendship with Harry Potter. It was just learning, he wasn’t promising to do anything. He could always stop the lessons at any time …

There were certainly any number of things about the situation which made it look like a trap, but in all honesty, Draco didn’t see how this could go wrong.

Plus Draco did kind of want to rule the world.

‘Yes,’ said Draco.

‘Excellent,’ said the shadowy figure. ‘I have had something of a crowded week, and it will take time to plan your curriculum –’

‘I’ve got a lot of things I need to do myself to consolidate my power in Slytherin,’ said Draco, ‘not to mention homework. Maybe we should just start in October?’

‘Sounds sensible,’ said the shadowy figure, ‘but what I meant to say is that to plan your curriculum, I need to know what I will be teaching you. Three thoughts come to me. The first is that I teach you of the human mind and brain. The second option is that I teach you of the physical universe, those arts which lie on the pathway to visiting the Moon. This involves a great deal of numbers, but to a certain kind of mind those numbers are more beautiful than anything else Science has to teach. Do you like numbers, Draco?’

Draco shook his head.

‘Then so much for that. You will learn your mathematics eventually, but not right away, I think. The third option is that I teach you of genetics and evolution and inheritance, what you would call blood –’

‘That one,’ said Draco.

The figure nodded. ‘I thought you might say as much. But I think it will be the most painful path for you, Draco. What if your family and friends, the blood purists, say one thing, and you find that the experimental test says another?’

‘Then I’ll figure out how to make the experimental test say the right answer!’

There was a pause, as the shadowy figure stood there with its mouth open for a short while.

‘Um,’ said the shadowy figure. ‘It doesn’t really work like that. That’s what I was trying to warn you about here, Draco. You can’t make the answer come out to be anything you like.’

‘You can always make the answer come out your way,’ said Draco. That had been practically the first thing his tutors had taught him. ‘It’s just a matter of finding the right arguments.’

‘No,’ said the shadowy figure, voice rising in frustration, ‘no, no, no! Then you get the wrong answer and you can’t go to the Moon that way! Nature isn’t a person, you can’t trick them into believing something else, if you try to tell the Moon it’s made of cheese you can argue for days and it won’t change the Moon! What you’re talking about is rationalization, like starting with a sheet of paper, moving straight down to the bottom line, using ink to write “and therefore, the Moon is made of cheese”, and then moving back up to write all sorts of clever arguments above. But either the Moon is made of cheese or it isn’t. The moment you wrote the bottom line, it was already true or already false. Whether or not the whole sheet of paper ends up with the right conclusion or the wrong conclusion is fixed the instant you write down the bottom line. If you’re trying to pick between two expensive trunks, and you like the shiny one, it doesn’t matter what clever arguments you come up with for buying it, the real rule you used to choose which trunk to argue for was “pick the shiny one”, and however effective that rule is at picking good trunks, that’s the kind of trunk you’ll get. Rationality can’t be used to argue for a fixed side, its only possible use is deciding which side to argue. Science isn’t for convincing anyone that the blood purists are right. That’s politics! The power of science comes from finding out the way Nature really is that can’t be changed by arguing! What science can do is tell us how blood really works, how wizards really inherit their powers from their parents, and whether Muggleborns are really weaker or stronger –’

‘Stronger!’ said Draco. He had been trying to follow this, a puzzled frown on his face, he could see how it sort of made sense but it certainly wasn’t like anything he’d ever heard before. And then Harry Potter had said something Draco couldn’t possibly let pass. ‘You think mudbloods are stronger?’

‘I think nothing,’ said the shadowy figure. ‘I know nothing. I believe nothing. My bottom line is not yet written. I will figure out how to test the magical strength of Muggleborns, and the magical strength of purebloods. If my tests tell me that Muggleborns are weaker, I will believe they are weaker. If my tests tell me that Muggleborns are stronger, I will believe they are stronger. Knowing this and other truths, I will gain some measure of power –’

‘And you expect me to believe whatever you say?’ Draco demanded hotly.

‘I expect you to perform the tests personally,’ said the shadowy figure quietly. ‘Are you afraid of what you will find?’

Draco stared at the shadowy figure for a while, his eyes narrowed. ‘Nice trap, Harry,’ he said. ‘I’ll have to remember that one, it’s new.’

The shadowy figure shook his head. ‘It’s not a trap, Draco. Remember, I don’t know what we’ll find. But you do not understand the universe by arguing with it or telling it to come back with a different answer next time. When you put on the robes of a scientist you must forget all your politics and arguments and factions and sides, silence the desperate clingings of your mind, and wish only to hear the answer of Nature.’ The shadowy figure paused. ‘Most people can’t do it. That’s why this is difficult. Are you sure you wouldn’t rather just learn about the brain?’

‘And if I tell you I’d rather learn about the brain,’ Draco said, his voice now hard, ‘you’ll go around telling people that I was afraid of what I’d find.’

‘No,’ said the shadowy figure. ‘I will do no such thing.’

‘But you might do the same sort of tests yourself, and if you got the wrong answer, I wouldn’t be there to say anything before you showed it to someone else.’ Draco’s voice was still hard.

‘I would still ask you first, Draco,’ the shadowy figure said quietly.

Draco paused. He hadn’t been expecting that, he’d thought he saw the trap but … ‘You would?’

‘Of course. How would I know who to blackmail or what we could ask from them? Draco, I say again that this is not a trap I set for you. At least not for you personally. If your politics were different, I would be saying, what if the test shows that purebloods are stronger.’

‘Really.’

‘Yes! That’s the price anyone has to pay to become a scientist!’

Draco held up a hand. He had to think.

The shadowy, green-lit figure waited.

It didn’t take long to think about, though. If you discarded all the confusing parts … then Harry Potter was planning to mess around with something that could cause a gigantic political explosion, and it would be insane to just walk away and let him do it on his own. ‘We’ll study blood,’ said Draco.

‘Excellent,’ said the figure, and smiled. ‘Congratulations on being willing to ask the question.’

‘Thanks,’ Draco said, not quite managing to keep the irony out of his voice.

‘Hey, did you think going to the Moon was easy? Be glad this just involves changing your mind sometimes, and not a human sacrifice!’

‘Human sacrifice would be way easier!’

There was a slight pause, and then the figure nodded. ‘Fair point.’

‘Look, Harry,’ said Draco without much hope, ‘I thought the idea was to take all the things that Muggles know, combine them with things that wizards know, and become masters of both worlds. Wouldn’t it be a lot easier to just study all the things that Muggles already found out, like the Moon stuff, and use that power –’

‘No,’ said the figure with a sharp shake of his head, sending green shadows moving around his nose and eyes. His voice had turned very grim. ‘If you cannot learn the scientist’s art of accepting reality, then I must not tell you what that acceptance has discovered. It would be like a powerful wizard telling you of those gates which must not be opened, and those seals which must not be broken, before you had proven your intelligence and discipline by surviving the lesser perils.’

A chill went down Draco’s spine and he shuddered involuntarily. He knew it had been visible even in the dim light. ‘All right,’ said Draco. ‘I understand.’ Father had told him that many times. When a more powerful wizard told you that you weren’t ready to know, you didn’t pry any further if you wanted to live.

The figure inclined his head. ‘Indeed. But there is something else you should understand. The first scientists, being Muggles, lacked your traditions. In the beginning they simply did not comprehend the notion of dangerous knowledge, and thought that all things known should be spoken freely. When their searches turned dangerous, they told their politicians of things that should have stayed secret – don’t look like that, Draco, it wasn’t simple stupidity. They did have to be smart enough to uncover the secret in the first place. But they were Muggles, it was the first time they’d found anything really dangerous, and they didn’t start out with a tradition of secrecy. There was a war going on, and the scientists on one side worried that if they didn’t talk, the scientists of the enemy country would tell their politicians first …’ The voice trailed off significantly. ‘They didn’t destroy the world. But it was close. And we are not going to repeat that mistake.’

‘Right,’ Draco said, his voice now very firm. ‘We won’t. We’re wizards, and studying science doesn’t make us Muggles.’

‘As you say,’ said the green-lit silhouette. ‘We will establish our own Science, a magical Science, and that Science will have smarter traditions from the very start.’ The voice grew hard. ‘The knowledge I share with you will be taught alongside the disciplines of accepting truth, the level of this knowledge will be keyed to your progress in those disciplines, and you will share that knowledge with no one else who has not learned those disciplines. Do you accept this?’

‘Yes,’ said Draco. What was he supposed to do, say no?

‘Good. And what you discover for yourself, you will keep to yourself unless you think that other scientists are ready to know it. What we do share among ourselves, we will not tell the world unless we agree it is safe for the world to know. And whatever our own politics and allegiances, we will all punish any of our number who reveal dangerous magics or give away dangerous weapons, no matter what sort of war is going on. From this day onward, that will be the tradition and the law of science among wizards. Are we agreed on that?’

‘Yes,’ said Draco. Actually this was starting to sound pretty attractive. The Death Eaters had tried to take power by being scarier than everyone else, and they hadn’t actually won yet. Maybe it was time to try ruling using secrets instead. ‘And our group stays hidden for as long as possible, and everyone in it has to agree to our rules.’

‘Of course. Definitely.’

There was a very short pause.

‘We’re going to need better robes,’ said the shadowy figure, ‘with hoods and so on –’

‘I was just thinking that,’ said Draco. ‘We don’t need whole new robes, though, just cowled cloaks to put on. I have a friend in Slytherin, she’ll take your measurements –’

‘Don’t tell her what it’s for, though –’

‘I’m not stupid!’

‘And no masks for now, not when it’s just you and me –’ said the shadowy figure.

‘Right! But later on we should have some sort of special mark that all our servants have, the Mark of Science, like a snake eating the Moon on their right arms –’

‘It’s called a PhD and wouldn’t that make it too easy to identify our people?’

‘Huh?’

‘I mean, what if someone is like “okay, now everyone pull up their robes over their right arms” and our guy is like “whoops, sorry, looks like I’m a spy” –’

‘Forget I said anything,’ said Draco, sweat suddenly springing out all over his body. He needed a distraction, fast – ‘And what do we call ourselves? The Science Eaters?’

‘No,’ said the shadowy figure slowly. ‘That doesn’t sound right …’

Draco wiped his robed arm across his forehead, wiping away beads of moisture. What had the Dark Lord been thinking? Father had said the Dark Lord was smart!

‘I’ve got it!’ said the shadowy figure suddenly. ‘You won’t understand yet, but trust me, it fits.’

Right now Draco would have accepted Malfoy Munchers as long as it changed the subject. ‘What is it?’

And standing amid the dusty desks in an unused classroom in the dungeons of Hogwarts, the green-lit silhouette of Harry Potter spread his arms dramatically and said, ‘This day shall mark the dawn of … the Bayesian Conspiracy.’

A silent figure trudged wearily through the halls of Hogwarts in the direction of Ravenclaw.

Harry had gone straight from the meeting with Draco to dinner, and stayed at dinner barely long enough to choke down a few fast gulps of food before going off to bed.

It wasn’t even 7pm yet, but it was well past bedtime for Harry. He’d realized last night that he wouldn’t be able to use the Time-Turner on Saturday until after the book-reading contest was already over. But he could still use the Time-Turner on Friday night, and gain time that way. So Harry had pushed himself to stay awake until 9pm on Friday, when the protective shell opened, and then used the four hours remaining on the Time-Turner to spin back to 5pm and collapse into sleep. He’d woken up around 2am on Saturday morning, just as planned, and read for the next twelve hours straight … and it still hadn’t been enough. And now Harry would be going to sleep rather early for the next few days, until his sleep cycle caught up again.

The portrait on the door asked Harry some dumb riddle meant for eleven-year-olds that he answered without the words even passing through his conscious mind, and then Harry staggered up the stairs to his dorm, changed into his pyjamas and collapsed into bed.

And found that his pillow seemed rather lumpy.

Harry groaned. He sat up reluctantly, twisted in bed, and lifted up his pillow.

This revealed a note, two golden Galleons, and a book titled Occlumency: The Hidden Arte.

Harry picked up the note and read:

My, you do get yourself into trouble and quickly. Your father was no match for you.

You have made a powerful enemy. Snape commands the loyalty, admiration, and fear of all House Slytherin. You cannot trust any of that House now, whether they come to you in friendly guise or fearsome.

From now on you must not meet Snape’s eyes. He is a Legilimens and can read your mind if you do. I have enclosed a book which may help you learn to protect yourself, though there is only so far you can get without a tutor. Still you may hope to at least detect intrusion.

So that you may find some extra time in which to study Occlumency, I have enclosed 2 Galleons, which is the price of answer sheets and homework for the first-year History of Magic class (Professor Binns having given the same tests and same assignments every year since he died). Your newfound friends the Weasley twins should be able to sell you a copy. It goes without saying that you must not get caught with it in your possession.

Of Professor Quirrell I know little. He is a Slytherin and a Defence Professor, and that is two marks against him. Consider carefully any advice he gives you, and tell him nothing you do not wish known.

Dumbledore only pretends to be insane. He is extremely intelligent, and if you continue to step into closets and vanish, he will certainly deduce your possession of an invisibility cloak if he has not done so already. Avoid him whenever possible, hide the Cloak of Invisibility somewhere safe (NOT your pouch) any time you cannot avoid him, and step with great care in his presence.

Please be more careful in the future, Harry Potter.

– Santa Claus

Harry stared at the note.

It did seem to be pretty good advice. Of course Harry wasn’t going to cheat in History class even if they gave him a dead monkey for a professor. But Severus’s Legilimency … whoever’d sent this note knew a lot of important, secret things and was willing to tell Harry about them. The note was still warning him against Dumbledore stealing the Cloak but at this point Harry honestly had no clue if that was a bad sign, it could just be an understandable mistake.

There seemed to be some sort of intrigue going on inside Hogwarts. Maybe if Harry compared stories between Dumbledore and the note-sender, he could work out a combined picture that would be accurate? Like if they both agreed on something, then …

… whatever …

Harry stuffed everything into his pouch and turned up the Quieter and pulled the cover over his head and died.

It was Sunday morning and Harry was eating pancakes in the Great Hall, sharp quick bites, glancing nervously at his watch every few seconds.

It was 8:02am, and in precisely two hours and one minute, it would be exactly one week since he’d seen the Weasleys and crossed over onto Platform Nine and Three-Quarters.

And the thought had occurred to him … Harry didn’t know if this was a valid way to think about the universe, he didn’t know anything any more, but it seemed possible …

That …

Not enough interesting things had happened to him over the last week.

When he was done eating breakfast, Harry planned to go straight up to his room and hide in the bottom level of his trunk and not talk to anyone until 10:03am.

And that was when Harry saw the Weasley twins walking toward him. One of them was carrying something concealed behind his back.

He should scream and run away.

He should scream and run away.

Whatever this was … it could very well be …

… the grand finale …

He really should just scream and run away.

With a resigned feeling that the universe would come and get him anyway, Harry continued slicing at the pancake with his fork and knife. He couldn’t muster the energy. That was the sad truth. Harry knew now how people felt when they were tired of running, tired of trying to escape fate, and they just fell to the ground and let the horrifically be-fanged and tentacled demons of the darkest abyss drag them off to their unspeakable destiny.

The Weasley twins drew closer.

And yet closer.

Harry ate another bite of pancake.

The Weasley twins arrived, grinning brightly.

‘Hello, Fred,’ Harry said dully. One of the twins nodded. ‘Hello, George.’ The other twin nodded.

‘You sound tired,’ said George.

‘You should cheer up,’ said Fred.

‘Look what we got you!’

And George took, from behind Fred’s back –

A cake with twelve flaming candles.

There was a pause, as the Ravenclaw table stared at them.

‘That’s not right,’ said someone. ‘Harry Potter was born on the thirty-first of Jul–’

‘He is coming,’ said a huge hollow voice that cut through all conversation like a sword of ice. ‘The one who will tear apart the very –’

Dumbledore had leapt out of his throne and run straight over the Head Table and seized hold of the woman speaking those awful words, Fawkes had appeared in a flash, and all three of them vanished in a crack of fire.

There was a shocked pause …

… followed by heads turning in the direction of Harry Potter.

‘I didn’t do it,’ Harry said in a tired voice.

‘That was a prophecy!’ someone at the table hissed. ‘And I bet it’s about you!’

Harry sighed.

He stood up from his seat, raised his voice, and said very loudly over the conversations that were starting up, ‘It’s not about me! Obviously! I’m not coming here, I’m already here!’

Harry sat back down again.

The people who had been looking at him turned away again.

Someone else at the table said, ‘Then who is it about?’

And with a dull, leaden sensation, Harry realized who wasn’t already at Hogwarts.

Call it a wild guess, but Harry had a feeling the undead Dark Lord would be showing up one of these days.

The conversation continued on around him.

‘Not to mention, tear apart the very what?’

‘I thought I heard Trelawney start to say something with an “S” just before the Headmaster grabbed her.’

‘Like … soul? Sun?’

‘If someone’s going to tear apart the Sun we’re really in trouble!’

That seemed rather unlikely to Harry, unless the world contained scary things which had heard of David Criswell’s ideas about star lifting.

‘So,’ Harry said in tired tones, ‘this happens every Sunday breakfast, does it?’

‘No,’ said a student who might have been in his seventh year, frowning grimly. ‘It doesn’t.’

Harry shrugged. ‘Whatever. Anyone want some birthday cake?’

‘But it’s not your birthday!’ said the same student who’d objected last time.

That was the cue for Fred and George to start laughing, of course.

Even Harry managed a weary smile.

As the first slice was served to him, Harry said, ‘I’ve had a really long week.’

And Harry was sitting in the cavern level of his trunk, slid shut and locked so no one could get in, a blanket pulled over his head, waiting for the week to be over.

10:01.

10:02.

10:03, but just to be sure …

10:04 and the first week was done.

Harry breathed a sigh of relief, and gingerly pulled the blanket off of his head.

A few moments later, he had emerged into the bright sunlit air of his dorm.

Shortly after, and he was in the Ravenclaw common room. A few people looked at him, but no one said anything or tried to talk to him.

Harry found a nice wide writing desk, pulled back a comfortable chair, and sat down. From his pouch he drew a sheet of paper and a pencil.

Mum and Dad had told Harry in no uncertain terms that while they understood his enthusiasm for leaving home and getting away from his parents, he was to write them every week without fail, just so that they knew he was alive, unharmed, and not in prison.

Harry stared down at the blank sheet of paper. Let’s see …

After leaving his parents at the train station, he’d …

… become acquainted with a boy raised by Darth Vader, become friends with the three most infamous pranksters in Hogwarts, met Hermione, then there’d been the Incident with the Sorting Hat … Monday he’d been given a time machine to treat his sleep disorder, got a legendary invisibility cloak from an unknown benefactor, rescued seven Hufflepuffs by staring down five scary older boys one of whom had threatened to break his finger, realized that he possessed a mysterious dark side, learned to cast Frigideiro in Charms class, and started his rivalry with Hermione … Tuesday had introduced Astronomy taught by Professor Aurora Sinistra who was nice, and History of Magic taught by a ghost who ought to be exorcised and replaced with a tape recorder … Wednesday, he’d been pronounced the Most Dangerous Student in the Classroom … Thursday, let’s not even think about Thursday … Friday, the Incident in Potions Class, followed by his blackmailing the Headmaster, followed by the Defence Professor having him beaten up in class, followed by the Defence Professor turning out to be the most awesome human being who still walked the face of the Earth … Saturday he’d lost a bet and gone on his first date and started redeeming Draco … and then this morning Professor Trelawney’s unheard prophecy might or might not indicate that an immortal Dark Lord was about to attack Hogwarts.

Harry mentally organized his material, and started writing.

Dear Mum and Dad:

Hogwarts is lots of fun. I learned how to violate the Second Law of Thermodynamics in Charms class, and I met a girl named Hermione Granger who reads faster than I do.

I’d better leave it at that.

Your loving son,
Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres.

Draco had heard of something called the Socratic Method, which was teaching by asking questions (named after an ancient philosopher who had been too smart to be a real Muggle and hence had been a disguised pureblood wizard). One of his tutors had used Socratic teaching a lot. It had been annoying but effective.

Then there was the Potter Method, which was insane.

To be fair, Draco had to admit that Harry Potter had tried the Socratic Method first and it hadn’t been working too well.

Harry Potter had asked how Draco would go about disproving the blood purist hypothesis that wizards couldn’t do the neat stuff now that they’d done eight centuries ago because they had interbred with Muggleborns and Squibs.

Draco had said that he did not understand how Harry Potter could sit there with a straight face and claim this was not a trap.

Harry Potter had replied, still with a straight face, that if it was a trap it would have been so pathetically obvious that he ought to be ground up and fed to pet snakes, but it was not a trap, it was simply a rule of how scientists operated that you had to try to disprove your own theories, and if you made an honest effort and failed, that was victory.

Draco had tried to point out the staggering stupidity of this by suggesting that the key to surviving a duel was to cast Avada Kedavra on your own foot and miss.

Harry Potter had nodded.

Draco had shaken his head.

Harry Potter had then presented the idea that scientists watched ideas fight to see which ones won, and you couldn’t fight without an opponent, so Draco needed to figure out opponents for the blood purist hypothesis to fight so that blood purism could win, which Draco understood a little better even though Harry Potter had said it with a rather distasteful look. Like, it was clear that if blood purism was the way the world really was, then the sky just had to be blue, and if some other theory was true, the sky just had to be green; and nobody had seen the sky yet; and then you went outside and looked and the blood purists won; and after this had happened six times in a row, people would start noticing the trend.

Harry Potter had then proceeded to claim that all the opponents Draco was inventing were too weak, so blood purism wouldn’t get credit for defeating them because the battle wouldn’t be impressive enough. Draco had understood that too. Wizards have become weaker because house elves are stealing our magic hadn’t sounded impressive to him either.

(Though Harry Potter had said that one at least was testable, in that they could try to check if house elves had become stronger over time, and even draw a picture representing the increasing strength of house elves and another picture representing the decreasing strength of wizards and if the two pictures matched that would point to the house elves, all said in such completely serious tones that Draco had felt an impulse to ask Dobby a few pointed questions under Veritaserum before snapping out of it.)

And Harry Potter had finally said that Draco couldn’t fix the battle, scientists weren’t dumb, it would be obvious if you fixed the battle, it had to be a real fight, between two different theories that might both really be true, with a test that only the true hypothesis would win, something that actually would come out different ways depending on which hypothesis was actually correct, and there would be experienced scientists watching to make sure that was exactly what happened. Harry Potter had claimed that he himself just wanted to know how blood really worked and for that he need to see blood purism really win and Draco wasn’t going to fool him with theories that were just there to be knocked down.

Even having seen the point, Draco hadn’t been able to invent any ‘plausible alternatives’, as Harry Potter put it, to the idea that wizards were getting less powerful because they were mixing their blood with mud. It was too obviously true.

It was then that Harry Potter had said, rather frustrated, that he couldn’t imagine Draco was really this bad at considering different viewpoints, surely there’d been Death Eaters who’d posed as enemies of blood purism and had come up with much more plausible-sounding arguments against their own side than Draco was offering. If Draco had been trying to pose as a member of Dumbledore’s faction, and come up with the house elf hypothesis, he wouldn’t have fooled anyone for a second.

Draco had been forced to admit this was a point.

Hence the Potter Method.

‘Please, Dr Malfoy,’ whined Harry Potter, ‘why won’t you accept my paper?’

Harry Potter had needed to repeat the phrase ‘just pretend to be pretending to be a scientist’ three times before Draco had understood.

In that moment Draco had realized that there was something deeply wrong with Harry Potter’s brain, and anyone who tried Legilimency on it would probably never come back out again.

Harry Potter had then gone into further and considerable detail: Draco was to pretend to be a Death Eater who was posing as the editor of a scientific journal, Dr Malfoy, who wanted to reject his enemy Dr Potter’s paper ‘On the Heritability of Magical Ability’, and if the Death Eater didn’t act like a real scientist would, he would be revealed as a Death Eater and executed, while Dr Malfoy was also being watched by his own rivals and needed to appear to reject Dr Potter’s paper for neutral scientific reasons or he would lose his position as journal editor.

It was a wonder the Sorting Hat wasn’t gibbering madly in St. Mungo’s.

It was also the most complicated thing anyone had ever asked Draco to pretend and there was no possible way he could have refused the challenge.

Right now they were, as Harry Potter had put it, getting in the mood.

‘I’m afraid, Dr Potter, that you wrote this in the wrong colour of ink,’ Draco said. ‘Next!’

Dr Potter’s face did an excellent job of crumpling in despair, and Draco couldn’t help but feel a flash of Dr Malfoy’s glee, even though the Death Eater was only pretending to be Dr Malfoy.

This part was fun. He could have done this all day long.

Dr Potter got up from the chair, slumped over in dismay, and trudged off, and turned into Harry Potter, who gave Draco a thumbs-up, and then turned back into Dr Potter again, now approaching with an eager smile.

Dr Potter sat down and presented Dr Malfoy with a piece of parchment on which was written:

On the Heritability of Magical Ability

Dr H. J. Potter-Evans-Verres, Institute for Sufficiently Advanced Science

My observation:

Today’s wizards can’t do things as impressive as
what wizards used to do 800 years ago.

My conclusion:

Wizardkind has become weaker by mixing
their blood with Muggleborns and Squibs.

‘Dr Malfoy,’ said Dr Potter with a hopeful look, ‘I was wondering if the Journal of Irreproducible Results could consider for publication my paper entitled “On the Heritability of Magical Ability”.’

Draco looked at the parchment, smiling while he considered possible rejections. If he was a professor, he would have refused the essay as too short, so –

‘It’s too long, Dr Potter,’ said Dr Malfoy.

For a moment there was genuine incredulity on Dr Potter’s face.

‘Ah …’ said Dr Potter. ‘How about if I get rid of the separate lines for observations and conclusions, and just put in a therefore –’

‘Then it’ll be too short. Next!’

Dr Potter trudged off.

‘All right,’ said Harry Potter, ‘you’re getting too good at this. Two more times to practise, and then third time is for real, no interruptions between, I’ll just come in straight at you and that time you’ll reject the paper based on the actual content, remember, your scientific rivals are watching.’

Dr Potter’s next paper was perfect in every way, a marvel of its kind, but unfortunately had to be rejected because Dr Malfoy’s journal was having trouble with the letter E. Dr Potter offered to rewrite it without those words, and Dr Malfoy explained that it was really more of a vowel problem.

The paper after that was rejected because it was Tuesday.

It was, in fact, Saturday.

Dr Potter tried to point this out and was told ‘Next!’

(Draco was starting to understand why Snape had used his hold over Dumbledore just to get a position that let him be awful to students.)

And then –

Dr Potter was approaching with a superior smirk on his face.

‘This is my latest paper, On the Heritability of Magical Ability,’ Dr Potter stated confidently, and thrust out the parchment. ‘I have decided to allow your journal to publish it, and have prepared it in perfect accordance with your guidelines so that you may publish it quickly.’

The Death Eater decided to track down and kill Dr Potter after his mission was done. Dr Malfoy kept a polite smile on his face, since his rivals were watching, and said …

(The pause stretched, with Dr Potter looking at him impatiently.)

…’Let me look at that, please.’

Dr Malfoy took the parchment and perused it carefully.

The Death Eater was starting to get nervous about the fact that he wasn’t a real scientist, and Draco was trying to remember how to talk like Harry Potter.

‘You, ah, need to consider other possible explanations for your, um, observation, besides just this one –’

‘Really?’ interrupted Dr Potter. ‘Like what, exactly? House elves are stealing our magic? My data admit of only one possible conclusion, Dr Malfoy. There are no other plausible hypotheses.’

Draco was trying furiously to order his brain to think, what would he say if he was posing as a member of Dumbledore’s faction, what did they claim was the explanation for wizardkind’s decline, Draco had never bothered to actually ask that …

‘If you can’t think of any other way to explain my data, you’ll have to publish my paper, Dr Malfoy.’

It was the sneer on Dr Potter’s face that did it.

‘Oh yeah?’ snapped Dr Malfoy. ‘How do you know that magic itself isn’t fading away?’

Time stopped.

Draco and Harry Potter exchanged looks of appalled horror.

Then Harry Potter spat something that was probably an extremely bad word if you’d been raised by Muggles. ‘I didn’t think of that!’ said Harry Potter. ‘And I should have. The magic goes away. Damn, damn, damn!’

The alarm in Harry Potter’s voice was contagious. Without even thinking about it, Draco’s hand went into his robes and clutched at his wand. He’d thought the House of Malfoy was safe, so long as you only married into families that could trace their bloodlines back four generations you were supposed to be safe, it had never occurred to him before that there might be nothing anyone could do to stop the end of magic. ‘Harry, what do we do?’ Draco’s voice was rising in panic. ‘What do we do?’

‘Let me think!’

After a few moments, Harry grabbed from a nearby desk the same quill and roll of parchment he’d used to write his pretend paper, and started scribbling something.

‘We’ll figure it out,’ Harry said, his voice tight, ‘if magic is fading out of the world we’ll figure out how fast it’s fading and how much time we have left to do something, and then we’ll figure out why it’s fading, and then we’ll do something about it. Draco, have wizarding powers been declining at a steady rate, or have there been sudden drops?’

‘I … I don’t know …’

‘You told me that no one had matched the four founders of Hogwarts. So it’s been going on for at least eight centuries, then? You can’t remember hearing anything about the problems suddenly appearing five centuries ago or anything like that?’

Draco was trying frantically to think. ‘I always heard that nobody was as good as Merlin and then after that nobody was as good as the Founders of Hogwarts.’

‘All right,’ Harry said. He was still scribbling. ‘Because three centuries ago is when Muggles started to not believe in magic, which I thought might have something to do with it. And about a century and a half ago was when Muggles began using a kind of technology that stops working around magic and I was wondering if it might also go the other way around.’

Draco exploded out of his chair, so angry he could hardly even speak. ‘It’s the Muggles –’

‘Damn it!’ roared Harry. ‘Weren’t you even listening to yourself? It’s been going on for eight centuries at least and the Muggles weren’t doing anything interesting then! We have to figure out the real truth! The Muggles might have something to do with this but if they don’t and you go blaming everything on them and that stops us from figuring out what’s really going on then one day you’re going to wake up in the morning and find out that your wand is just a stick of wood!’

Draco’s breath stopped in his throat. His father often said our wands will break in our hands in his speeches but Draco had never really thought before about what that meant, it wasn’t going to happen to him after all. And now suddenly it seemed very real. Just a stick of wood. Draco could imagine just what it would be like to take out his wand and try to cast a spell and find that nothing was happening …

That could happen to everyone.

There would be no more wizards, no more magic, ever. Just Muggles who had a few legends about what their ancestors had been able to do. Some of the Muggles would be called Malfoy, and that would be all that was left of the name.

For the first time in his life, Draco realized why there were Death Eaters.

He’d always taken for granted that becoming a Death Eater was something you did when you grew up. Now Draco understood, he knew why Father and Father’s friends had sworn to give their lives to prevent the nightmare from coming to pass, there were things you couldn’t just stand by and watch happen. But what if it was going to happen anyway, what if all the sacrifices, all the friends they’d lost to Dumbledore, the family they’d lost, what if it had all been for nothing …

‘Magic can’t be fading away,’ Draco said. His voice was breaking. ‘It wouldn’t be fair.’

Harry stopped scribbling and looked up. His face had an angry expression. ‘Your father never told you that life isn’t fair?’

Father had said that every single time Draco used the word. ‘But, but, it’s too awful to believe that –’

‘Draco, let me introduce you to something I call the Litany of Tarski. It changes every time you use it. On this occasion it runs like so: If magic is fading out of the world, I want to believe that magic is fading out of the world. If magic is not fading out of the world, I want not to believe that magic is fading out of the world. Let me not become attached to beliefs I may not want. If we’re living in a world where magic is fading, that’s what we have to believe, we have to know what’s coming, so we can stop it, or in the very worst case, be prepared to do what we can in the time we have left. Not believing it won’t stop it from happening. So the only question we have to ask is whether magic is actually fading, and if that’s the world we live in then that’s what we want to believe. Litany of Gendlin: What’s true is already so, owning up to it doesn’t make it worse. Got that, Draco? I’m going to make you memorize it later. It’s something you repeat to yourself any time you start wondering if it’s a good idea to believe something that isn’t actually true. In fact I want you to say it right now. What’s true is already so, owning up to it doesn’t make it worse. Say it.’

‘What’s true is already so,’ repeated Draco, his voice trembling, ‘owning up to it doesn’t make it worse.’

‘If magic is fading, I want to believe that magic is fading. If magic is not fading, I want not to believe that magic is fading. Say it.’

Draco repeated back the words, the sickness churning in his stomach.

‘Good,’ Harry said, ‘remember, it might not be happening, and then you won’t have to believe it, either. First we just want to know what’s actually going on, which world we actually live in.’ Harry turned back to his work, scribbled some more, and then turned the parchment so Draco could see it. Draco leaned over the desk and Harry brought the green light closer.

Observation:

Wizardry isn’t as powerful now as it was when Hogwarts was founded.

Hypotheses:

1. Magic itself is fading.
2. Wizards are interbreeding with Muggles and Squibs.
3. Knowledge to cast powerful spells is being lost.
4. Wizards are eating the wrong foods as children, or something else besides blood is making them grow up weaker.
5. Muggle technology is interfering with magic. (Since 800 years ago?)
6. Stronger wizards are having fewer children. (Draco = only child? Check if 3 powerful wizards, Quirrell / Dumbledore / Dark Lord, had any children.)

Tests:

‘All right,’ Harry said. His breathing sounded a little calmer. ‘Now when you’re dealing with a confusing problem and you have no idea what’s going on, the smart thing to do is figure out some really simple tests, things you can look at right away. We need fast tests that distinguish between these hypotheses. Observations that would come out a different way for at least one of them compared to all the other ones.’

Draco stared at the list in shock. He was suddenly realizing that he knew an awful lot of purebloods who were only children. Himself, Vincent, Gregory, practically everyone. The two most powerful wizards everyone talked about were Dumbledore and the Dark Lord and neither had any children just like Harry had suspected …

‘It’s going to be really hard to distinguish between 2 and 6,’ Harry said, ‘it’s in the blood either way, you’d have to try and track the decline of wizardry and compare that to how many kids different wizards were having and measure the abilities of Muggleborns compared to purebloods …’ Harry’s fingers were tapping nervously on the desk. ‘Let’s just lump 6 in with 2 and call them the blood hypothesis for now. 4 is unlikely because then everyone would notice a sudden drop when the wizards switched to new foods, it’s hard to see what would’ve changed steadily over 800 years. 5 is unlikely for the same reason, no sudden drop, Muggles weren’t doing anything 800 years back. 4 looks like 2 and 5 looks like 1 anyway. So mainly we should be trying to distinguish between 1, 2, and 3.’ Harry turned the parchment to himself, drew an ellipse around those three numbers, turned it back. ‘Magic is fading, blood is weakening, knowledge is disappearing. What test comes out differently depending on which of those is true? What could we see that would mean any one of these was false?’

‘I don’t know!’ blurted Draco. ‘Why are you asking me? You’re the scientist!’

‘Draco,’ Harry said, a note of pleading desperation in his voice, ‘I only know what Muggle scientists know! You grew up in the wizarding world, I didn’t! You know more magic than I do and you know more about magic than I do and you thought of this whole idea in the first place, so start thinking like a scientist and solve this!’

Draco swallowed hard and stared at the paper.

Magic is fading … wizards are interbreeding with Muggles … knowledge is being lost …

‘What does the world look like if magic is fading?’ said Harry Potter. ‘You know more about magic, you should be the one guessing not me! Imagine you’re telling a story about it, what happens in the story?’

Draco imagined it. ‘Charms that used to work stop working.’ Wizards wake up and find that their wands are sticks of wood …

‘What does the world look like if the wizarding blood gets weaker?’

‘People can’t do things their ancestors could do.’

‘What does the world look like if knowledge is being lost?’

‘People don’t know how to cast the Charms in the first place …’ said Draco. He stopped, surprised at himself. ‘That’s a test, isn’t it?’

Harry nodded decisively. ‘That’s one.’ He wrote it down on the parchment under Tests:

A. Are there spells we know but can’t cast (1 or 2) or are the lost spells no longer known (3)?

‘So that distinguishes between 1 and 2 on the one hand, and 3 on the other hand,’ said Harry. ‘Now we need some way to distinguish between 1 and 2. Magic fading, blood weakening, how could we tell the difference?’

‘What kind of Charms did students used to cast in their first year at Hogwarts?’ said Draco. ‘If they used to be able to cast much more powerful Charms, the blood was stronger –’

Harry Potter shook his head. ‘Or magic itself was stronger. We have to figure out some way of telling the difference.’ Harry stood up from his chair, began pacing nervously through the classroom. ‘No, wait, that might still work. Suppose different spells use up different amounts of magical energy. Then if the ambient magic weakened, the powerful spells would die first, but the spells everyone learns in their first year would stay the same …’ Harry’s nervous pacing sped up. ‘It’s not a very good test, it’s more about powerful wizardry being lost versus all wizardry being lost, someone’s blood could be too weak for powerful wizardry but strong enough for easy spells … Draco, do you know if more powerful wizards within a single era, like powerful wizards from just this century, are more powerful as children? If the Dark Lord had cast the Cooling Charm when he was eleven, could he have frozen the whole room?’

Draco’s face screwed up as he tried to recollect. ‘I can’t remember hearing anything about the Dark Lord but I think Dumbledore’s supposed to have done something amazing on his Transfiguration O.W.L.s in fifth year … I think other powerful wizards were good in Hogwarts too …’

Harry scowled, still pacing. ‘They could just be studying hard. Still, if first-year students learned the same spells and seemed about as powerful then as now, we could call that weak evidence favouring 1 over 2 … wait, hold on.’ Harry stopped where he stood. ‘I have another test that might distinguish between 1 and 2. It would take a while to explain, it uses some things that scientists know about blood and inheritance, but it’s an easy question to ask. And if we combine my test and your test and they both come out the same way, that’s a strong hint at the answer.’ Harry almost ran back to the desk, took the parchment and wrote:

B. Did ancient first-year students cast the same sort of spells, with the same power, as now? (Weak evidence for 1 over 2, but blood could also be losing powerful wizardry only.)

C. Additional test that distinguishes 1 and 2 using scientific knowledge of blood, will explain later.

‘Okay,’ said Harry, ‘we can at least try to tell the difference between 1 and 2 and 3, so let’s go with this right away, we can figure out more tests after we do the ones we already have. Now it’s going to look a little odd if Draco Malfoy and Harry Potter go around asking questions together, so here’s my idea. You’ll go through Hogwarts and find old portraits and ask them about what spells they learned to cast during their first years. They’re portraits so they won’t know there’s anything odd about Draco Malfoy doing that. I’ll ask recent portraits and living people about spells we know but can’t cast, no one will notice anything unusual if Harry Potter asks weird questions. And I’ll have to do complicated research about forgotten spells, so I want you to be the one to gather the data I need for my own scientific question. It’s a simple question and you should be able to find the answer by asking portraits. You might want to write this down, ready?’

Draco sat down again and scrabbled in his bookbag for parchment and quill. When it was laid down on the desk, Draco looked up, face determined. ‘Go ahead.’

‘Find portraits who knew a married Squib couple – don’t make that face, Draco, it’s important information. Just ask recent portraits who are Gryffindors or something. Find portraits who knew a married Squib couple well enough to know the names of all their children. Write down the name of each child and whether that child was a wizard, a Squib, or a Muggle. If they don’t know whether the child was a Squib or a Muggle, write down “non-wizard”. Write that down for every child the couple had, don’t leave any out. If the portrait only knows the name of the wizarding children, not the names of all the children, then don’t write down any data from that couple. It’s very important that you only bring me data from someone who knows all the children a Squib couple had, well enough to know them all by name. Try to get at least forty names total, if you can, and if you have time for more, even better. Have you got all that?’

‘Repeat it,’ Draco said, when he was done writing, and Harry repeated it.

‘I’ve got it,’ Draco said, ‘but why –’

‘It has to do with one of the secrets of blood that scientists already discovered. I’ll explain when you get back. Let’s split up and meet back here in an hour, 6:22pm that should be. Are we ready to go?’

Draco nodded decisively. It was all very rushed, but he’d long since been taught how to rush.

‘Then go!’ said Harry Potter and yanked off his cowled cloak and shoved it into his pouch, which began eating it, and, without even waiting for his pouch to finish, spun around and began striding rapidly toward the classroom door, bumping into a desk and almost falling over in his haste.

By the time Draco had managed to get his own cloak off and stow it in his bookbag, Harry Potter was gone.

Draco almost ran out the door.

‘Professor Quirrell,’ Draco said in his most formal voice, ‘I must protest your appointment of Hermione Granger as the third general.’

‘Oh?’ said Professor Quirrell, leaning back in his chair in a casual and relaxed manner. ‘Protest away, Mr Malfoy.’

‘Granger is unfit for the position,’ said Draco.

Professor Quirrell tapped a finger on his cheek thoughtfully. ‘Why yes, yes she is. Do you have any further protests?’

‘Professor Quirrell,’ said Harry Potter beside him, ‘with all due respect to Miss Granger’s many outstanding academic talents and the Quirrell points she has justly earned in your classes, her personality is not suited to military command.’

Draco had been relieved when Harry had agreed to accompany him to Professor Quirrell’s office. It wasn’t just that Harry was a gigantic blatant teacher’s pet where Professor Quirrell was concerned. Draco had also started to worry that Harry actually was friends with Granger, it had been a while now and he still hadn’t made his move … but this was more like it.

‘I agree with Mr Potter,’ said Draco. ‘Appointing her as a general turns it into a farce.’

‘Harshly put,’ said Harry, ‘but I cannot bring myself to disagree with Mr Malfoy. To be blunt, Professor Quirrell, Hermione Granger has around as much intent to kill as a bowl of wet grapes.’

‘That,’ said Professor Quirrell mildly, ‘is not a thing I would fail to notice myself. You are telling me nothing I do not already know.’

It was Draco’s turn to say something, but the conversation had suddenly hiccuped. That answer had not been in the possibilities he and Harry had brainstormed before coming here. What did you say after the teacher said that he knew everything you knew and he was still going to commit an obvious mistake?

The silence stretched.

‘Is this some sort of plot?’ Harry said slowly.

‘Must everything I do be some sort of plot?’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Can’t I ever create chaos just for the sake of chaos?’

Draco almost choked.

‘Not in your Battle Magic class,’ Harry said with calm certainty. ‘Other places, maybe, but not there.’

Professor Quirrell slowly raised his eyebrows.

Harry gazed steadily back at him.

Draco shivered.

‘Well then,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘Neither of you seem to have considered a very simple question. Who could I appoint instead of Miss Granger?’

‘Blaise Zabini,’ Draco said without hesitation.

‘Any other suggestions?’ said Professor Quirrell, sounding quite amused.

Anthony Goldstein and Ernie Macmillan, came the thought, before Draco’s common sense kicked in and ruled out mudbloods and Hufflepuffs no matter how aggressively they duelled. So instead Draco just said, ‘What’s wrong with Zabini?’

‘I see …’ Harry said slowly.

‘I don’t,’ said Draco. ‘Why not Zabini?’

Professor Quirrell looked at Draco. ‘Because, Mr Malfoy, no matter how hard he tries, he’ll never be able to keep up with you or Mr Potter.’

The shock of it staggered Draco. ‘You can’t believe Granger is going to –’

‘He’s gambling on her,’ Harry said quietly. ‘It’s not guaranteed. The odds aren’t even good. She’ll probably never give us a good fight, and even if she does, it may take her months to learn. But she’s the only one in our year with any chance at all of growing to beat us.’

Draco’s hands twitched but didn’t clench into fists. Showing up as your supporter and then backing out was a classic undermining tactic, so Harry Potter was in it with Granger and that implied –

‘But Professor,’ Harry went on smoothly, ‘I’m worried Hermione will be miserable as the general of an army. I’m speaking as her friend now, Professor Quirrell. The competition might be good for Draco and me, but what you’re asking her to do isn’t good for her!’

Never mind.

‘Your friendship for Hermione Granger does you credit,’ Professor Quirrell said dryly. ‘Especially as you are able to be friends with Draco Malfoy at the same time. Quite a feat, that.’

Harry suddenly looked a little nervous, meaning he probably felt a lot more nervous, and Draco silently swore to himself. Of course Harry wasn’t going to fool Professor Quirrell.

‘And I doubt Miss Granger would appreciate your friendly concern,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘She asked me for the position, Mr Potter, I did not ask her.’

Harry was quiet at this for a moment. Then he flashed Draco a quick look that mixed apology and warning, saying at the same time, Sorry, I did my best and We’d better not press it any further.

‘As for her being miserable,’ Professor Quirrell went on, a slight smile now playing about his lips, ‘I suspect that she will have a much easier time with the rigours of her position than either of you suspect, and that she will put up a good fight much sooner than you think.’

Harry and Draco both gasped in horror.

‘You’re not going to advise her, are you?’ said Draco, utterly aghast.

‘I never signed up to fight you!’ said Harry.

The smile playing around Professor Quirrell’s lips grew wider. ‘As a matter of fact, I did offer to share a few suggestions regarding Miss Granger’s first battles.’

‘Professor Quirrell!’ said Harry.

‘Oh, don’t worry,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘She turned me down. Just as I expected.’

Draco’s eyes narrowed.

‘Dear me, Mr Potter,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘didn’t anyone ever tell you it’s rude to stare?’

‘You’re not going to secretly help her some other way, are you?’ said Harry.

‘Would I do that?’ said Professor Quirrell.

‘Yes,’ said Draco and Harry at the same time.

‘I am wounded by your lack of trust. Well then, I promise not to help General Granger in any way that the two of you don’t know about. And now I suggest that both of you be about your military affairs. November approaches, and swiftly.’

Draco saw the implications before the door had closed all the way behind them on their way out of Professor Quirrell’s office.

Harry had once spoken dismissively of ‘people stuff’.

And now that was Draco’s only hope.

Let him not realize, let him not realize …

‘We should just attack the Granger girl first and get her out of our way,’ said Draco. ‘After we crush her, we can have our own contest without any distractions.’

‘Now that doesn’t really seem fair to her, does it?’ said Harry in a mild voice.

‘What do you care?’ said Draco. ‘She’s your rival, right?’ Then, with just the right note of suspicion in his voice, ‘Don’t tell me you’ve started really liking her, after being her rival all this time …’

‘Founders forbid,’ said Harry. ‘What can I say, Draco? I merely have a natural sense of justice. Granger does too, you know. She has a very firm grasp on good and evil, and she’s probably going to attack evil first. Having a name like “Malfoy” is just asking for it, you know.’

Damn it!

‘Harry,’ said Draco, sounding wounded and maybe a little superior, ‘don’t you want to fight fairly against me?’

‘You mean rather than attacking you after you’ve already lost some of your forces beating Granger?’ said Harry. ‘Oh, I don’t know. Maybe after I get bored with just winning I’ll try that “fair” thing.’

‘Maybe she’ll attack you,’ Draco said. ‘You’re her rival.’

‘But I’m her friendly rival,’ Harry said with an evil grin. ‘I bought her a nice birthday present and everything. You wouldn’t go around sabotaging your friendly rival like that.’

‘What about sabotaging your friend’s chance at a fair fight?’ said Draco angrily. ‘I thought we were friends!’

‘Let me rephrase that,’ said Harry. ‘Granger wouldn’t sabotage a friendly rival. But that’s because she has the killing intention of a bowl of wet grapes. You would. You totally would. And guess what, so would I.’

Damn it!

If it had been a play, there would have been dramatic music.

The hero, impeccably turned out in green-trimmed robes and perfectly combed white-blonde hair, faced the villain.

The villain, leaning back in a simple wooden chair with her buckteeth clearly visible and stray chestnut curls drifting over her cheeks, faced the hero.

It was Wednesday, October 30th, and the first battle was coming up on Sunday.

Draco was standing in General Granger’s office, a room the size of a small classroom. (Why each general’s office was so large, Draco wasn’t quite sure. A chair and a desk would have worked for him. He wasn’t even clear on why the generals needed offices at all, his soldiers knew where to find him. Unless Professor Quirrell had deliberately arranged the huge offices for them as a sign of status, in which case Draco was all for it.)

Granger sat on the room’s single chair like a throne, all the way on the other end of the office from where the door opened. There was a long oblong table stretched across the middle of the room between them, and four small circular tables scattered around the corners, but only that one single chair, all the way at the opposite end. The room had windows along one wall, and one beam of sunlight touched the top of Granger’s hair like a glowing crown.

It would have been nice if Draco could have walked slowly forward. But there was a table in the way, and Draco had to go around it diagonally, and there was no good way to do that in a dramatic and dignified fashion. Had that been deliberate? If it had been his father, it surely would have been; but this was Granger, so surely not.

There was nowhere for him to sit, and Granger hadn’t stood up, either.

Draco kept the outrage entirely off his face.

‘Well, Mr Draco Malfoy,’ Granger said once he stood before her, ‘you requested an audience with me and I have been so gracious as to grant it. What was your plea?’

Come with me to visit Malfoy Manor, my father and I would like to show you some interesting spells.

‘Your rival, Potter, came to me with an offer,’ said Draco, putting a serious look on his face. ‘He doesn’t mind losing to me, but would be humiliated if you won. So he wants to join with me and wipe you out immediately, not just in our first battle, all of them. If I won’t do that, Potter wants me to hold back or harass you, while he launches an all-out attack on you as his first move.’

‘I see,’ Granger said, looking surprised. ‘And you’re offering to help me against him?’

‘Of course,’ said Draco smoothly. ‘I didn’t think what he wanted to do to you was fair.’

‘Why, that’s very nice of you, Mr Malfoy,’ said Granger. ‘I’m sorry for how I spoke to you earlier. We should be friends. Can I call you Drakey?’

Alarm bells started to sound in Draco’s head, but there was a chance she meant it …

‘Of course,’ said Draco, ‘if I can call you Hermy.’

Draco was pretty sure he saw her expression flicker.

‘Anyway,’ Draco said, ‘I was thinking it would serve Potter right if we both attacked him and wiped him out.’

‘But that wouldn’t be fair to Mr Potter, would it?’ said Granger.

‘I think it’d be very fair,’ Draco said. ‘He was planning to do it to you first.’

Granger was giving him a stern look that could possibly have intimidated him if he’d been a Hufflepuff instead of a Malfoy. ‘You think I’m pretty stupid, don’t you, Mr Malfoy?’

Draco smiled charmingly. ‘No, Miss Granger, but I thought I’d at least check. So, what do you want?’

‘Are you offering to bribe me?’ said Granger.

‘Sure,’ said Draco. ‘Can I just slip you a Galleon and have you beat on Potter instead of me for the rest of the year?’

‘Nope,’ said Granger, ‘but you can offer me ten Galleons and have me attack both of you equally, instead of just you.’

‘Ten Galleons is a lot of money,’ Draco said cautiously.

‘I didn’t know the Malfoys were poor,’ said Granger.

Draco stared at Granger.

He was starting to get a strange feeling about this.

That particular reply didn’t seem like it should have come from this particular girl.

‘Well,’ said Draco, ‘you don’t get to be rich by wasting money, you know.’

‘I don’t know if you know what a dentist is, Mr Malfoy, but my parents are dentists and anything less than ten Galleons isn’t worth my time at all.’

‘Three Galleons,’ Draco said, more as a probe than anything else.

‘Nope,’ said Granger. ‘If you want an equal fight at all, I don’t believe that a Malfoy wants an equal fight less than he wants ten Galleons.’

Draco was starting to get a very strange feeling about this.

‘No,’ said Draco.

‘No?’ said Granger. ‘This is a limited time offer, Mr Malfoy. Are you sure you want to risk a whole year of being miserably crushed by the Boy-Who-Lived? That would be pretty embarrassing for the House of Malfoy, wouldn’t it?’

It was a very persuasive argument, one that was hard to refuse, but you didn’t get to be rich by spending money when your heart told you it was a setup.

‘No,’ said Draco.

‘See you on Sunday,’ said Granger.

Draco turned and walked out of the office without another word.

That had been not right …

‘Hermione,’ Harry said patiently, ‘we’re supposed to be plotting against each other. You could even betray me and it wouldn’t mean anything outside the battlefield.’

Hermione shook her head. ‘It wouldn’t be nice, Harry.’

Harry sighed. ‘I don’t think you’re getting into the spirit of this at all.’

It wouldn’t be nice. She’d actually said that. Hermione didn’t know whether to be insulted at what Harry thought of her, or worried about whether she really did sound like that much of a goody-two-shoes usually.

It was probably time to change the subject.

‘Anyway, are you doing anything special for tomorrow?’ said Hermione. ‘It’s –’

Her voice cut off abruptly as she realized.

‘Yes, Hermione,’ Harry said a little tightly, ‘what day is it?’

Interlude:

There was a time when October 31st had been called Halloween in magical Britain.

Now it was Harry Potter Day.

Harry had turned down all the offers, even the one from Minister Fudge which might have been good for future political favours and which he really should have gritted his teeth and taken. But to Harry, October 31st would always be The Dark Lord Killed My Parents Day. There should have been a quiet, dignified memorial service somewhere, and if there was one, he hadn’t been invited.

Hogwarts got the day off to celebrate. Even the Slytherins didn’t dare wear black outside their own dorm. There were special events and special foods and the teachers looked the other way if anyone ran through the hallways. It was the tenth anniversary, after all.

Harry spent the day in his trunk so as not to spoil it for anyone else, eating snack bars in place of meals, reading some of his sadder science fiction books (no fantasy), and writing a letter to Mum and Dad that was much longer than the ones he usually sent.

Working in Groups, Pt 1

The day was Sunday, November 3rd, and soon the three great powers of their school year, Harry Potter, Draco Malfoy, and Hermione Granger, would begin their struggle for supreme dominance.

(Harry was slightly annoyed by the way the Boy-Who-Lived had been demoted from supreme dominance to one of three equal rivals just by entering the contest, but he expected to get it back soon.)

The battleground was a section of non-Forbidden forest, dense with trees, because Professor Quirrell thought that being able to see all the enemy forces was too boring even for your very first battle.

All the students who were not actually in a first-year army were camped out nearby and watching on screens that Professor Quirrell had set up. Except for three Gryffindors in their fourth year, who were currently sick and confined to healer’s beds by Madam Pomfrey. Aside from that, everyone was there.

The students were dressed, not in their ordinary school robes, but in Muggle camouflage uniforms that Professor Quirrell had obtained somewhere and supplied in sufficient quantity and variety to fit everyone. It wasn’t that students would have worried about stains and rips, that was what Charms were for. But as Professor Quirrell had explained to the surprised wizardborn, nice dignified clothing was not efficient for hiding in forests or dodging around trees.

And on each uniform’s breast, a patch bearing the name and insignia of your army. A small patch. If you wanted your soldiers to wear, say, coloured ribbons so that they could identify each other at a distance, and risk the enemy getting their hands on the ribbons, that was all up to you.

Harry had tried to get the name Dragon Army.

Draco had pitched a fit and said that would confuse everyone completely.

Professor Quirrell had ruled that Draco could lay prior claim to the name, if he wished.

So now Harry was fighting Dragon Army.

This probably wasn’t a good sign.

For their insignia, instead of the too-obvious dragon’s head breathing fire, Draco had elected to simply go with the fire. Elegant, understated, deadly: This is what’s left after we’ve passed. Very Malfoy.

Harry, after considering alternate choices such as the 501st Provisional Battalion and Harry’s Minions o’ Doom, had decided that his army would be known by the simple and dignified appellation of the Chaos Legion.

Their insignia was a hand poised with fingers ready to snap.

It was universally agreed that this wasn’t a good sign.

Harry had earnestly advised Hermione that the young boys serving under her were probably nervous about her being a girl with a reputation for being nice, and that she should pick something scary that would reassure them of her toughness and make them proud to be part of her army, like the Blood Commandos or something.

Hermione had named her army the Sunshine Regiment.

Their insignia was a smiley face.

And in ten minutes, they would be at war.

Harry stood in the bright forest clearing that was their assigned starting location, an area of open space with old and rotting tree stumps that had been cleared away for some unknown purpose, ground coated with a small scattering of blown leaves and the dried grey remnants of grass that had failed the test of summer’s heat, and the Sun shining down brilliantly from above.

Around him were the twenty-three soldiers that Professor Quirrell had assigned to him. Nearly all of Gryffindor had signed up, of course, and more than half of Slytherin, and less than half of Hufflepuff, and a handful of Ravenclaw. In Harry’s army there were twelve Gryffindors and six Slytherins and four Hufflepuffs and one Ravenclaw besides himself … not that there was any way to tell that by looking at the uniforms. No red, no green, no yellow, no blue. Just Muggle camouflage patterns, and a patch on the breast with the device of a hand poised to snap its fingers.

Harry looked upon his twenty-three soldiers, all wearing the same uniforms with no marks of group identity save that single patch.

And lo, Harry smiled, because he understood what this part of Professor Quirrell’s master plan was about; and Harry was taking full advantage of it for his own purposes, too.

There was a legendary episode in social psychology called the Robbers Cave experiment. It had been set up in the bewildered aftermath of World War II, with the intent of investigating the causes and remedies of conflicts between groups. The scientists had set up a summer camp for 22 boys from 22 different schools, selecting them to all be from stable middle-class families. The first phase of the experiment had been intended to investigate what it took to start a conflict between groups. The 22 boys had been divided into two groups of 11 –

– and this had been quite sufficient.

The hostility had started from the moment the two groups had become aware of each others’ existences in the state park, insults being hurled on the first meeting. They’d named themselves the Eagles and the Rattlers (they hadn’t needed names for themselves when they thought they were the only ones in the park) and had proceeded to develop contrasting group stereotypes, the Rattlers thinking of themselves as rough-and-tough and swearing heavily, the Eagles correspondingly deciding to think of themselves as upright-and-proper.

The other part of the experiment had been testing how to resolve group conflicts. Bringing the boys together to watch fireworks hadn’t worked at all. They’d just shouted at each other and stayed apart. What had worked was warning them that there might be vandals in the park, and the two groups needing to work together to solve a failure of the park’s water system. A common task, a common enemy.

Harry had a strong suspicion Professor Quirrell had understood this principle very well indeed when he had chosen to create three armies per year.

Three armies.

Not four.

And definitely not segregated by House … except that no Slytherins had been assigned to Draco besides Mr Crabbe and Mr Goyle.

It was things like this which reassured Harry that Professor Quirrell, despite his affected Dark atmosphere and his pretence of neutrality in the conflict between Good and Evil, was secretly backing Good, not that Harry would ever dare say that out loud.

And Harry had decided to take full advantage of Professor Quirrell’s plan to define a group identity his way.

The Rattlers, once they’d met the Eagles, had started thinking of themselves as rough-and-tough, and they’d conducted themselves accordingly.

The Eagles had thought of themselves as good-and-proper.

And in that bright forest clearing, scattered around the old and rotting tree stumps, outlined in the Sun shining down brilliantly from above, General Potter and his twenty-three soldiers were arranged in nothing remotely resembling a formation. Some soldiers stood, some soldiers sat, some stood on one leg just to be different.

It was the Chaos Legion, after all.

And if there wasn’t a reason to stand in neat little lines, Harry had said disdainfully, there weren’t going to be neat little lines.

Harry had divided the army into 6 squads of 4 soldiers each, each squad commanded by a Squad Suggester. All troops were under strict orders to disobey any orders they were given if it seemed like a good idea at the time, including that one … unless Harry or the Squad Suggester prefixed the order with ‘Merlin says’, in which case you were supposed to actually obey.

The Chaos Legion’s chief attack was to split up and run in from multiple directions, randomly changing vectors and firing the approved sleep spell as rapidly as you could rebuild the magical strength. And if you saw a chance to distract or confuse the enemy, you took it.

Fast. Creative. Unpredictable. Non-homogeneous. Don’t just obey orders, think about whether what you’re doing right now makes sense.

Harry wasn’t quite as sure as he’d pretended that this was the optimum of military efficiency … but he’d been given a golden opportunity to change how some students thought about themselves, and that was how he intended to use it.

Five minutes to wartime, according to Harry’s watch.

General Potter walked (not marched) over to where his air force was waiting tensely, broomsticks already clutched firmly in their hands.

‘All wings report in,’ said General Potter. They’d rehearsed this during their one training session on Saturday.

‘Red Leader standing by,’ said Seamus Finnigan, who had no idea what it meant.

‘Red Five standing by,’ said Dean Thomas, who’d waited his entire life to say it.

‘Green Leader standing by,’ Theodore Nott said rather stiffly.

‘Green Forty-One standing by,’ Tracey Davis said.

‘I want you in the air the instant we hear the bell,’ said General Potter. ‘Do not engage, repeat, do not engage. Evade if under fire.’ (Of course you did not aim sleep spells at broomsticks; you fired a spell that gave a temporary red glow to whatever it hit. If you hit the broomstick or the rider, they were out of the war.) ‘Red Leader and Red Five, fly toward Malfoy’s army as fast as you can, stay as high as you can while still seeing them, return the instant you know for sure what they’re doing. Green Leader, do the same for Granger’s army. Green Forty-One, fly above us and watch for any approaching broomsticks or soldiers, you and only you are authorized to fire. And remember, I didn’t say “Merlin says” for any of that, but we do really need the information. For Chaos!’

‘For Chaos!’ the four echoed with varying degrees of enthusiasm.

Harry expected Hermione to launch an immediate attack on Draco, in which case he’d move his troops into position and start supporting her, but only after she’d taken severe losses and caused some damage. He would frame it as a heroic rescue, if possible; it wouldn’t do to have Sunshine thinking that Chaos wasn’t their friend, after all.

But just in case she didn’t … well, that was why the Chaos Legion was staying put until Green Leader reported back.

Draco’s moves would be in his own self-interest. He would predictably ready his army to defend against Hermione; he might or might not realize that Harry had been lying about waiting to attack until after that battle finished. Harry had still put two broomsticks on Dragon Army, just in case they were doing something, and just in case Draco or Mr Goyle or Mr Crabbe was good enough to shoot a broomstick out of the sky.

But General Granger was the unpredictable one, and Harry couldn’t move until he knew how she was moving.

In the heart of the forest, with shadow patterns dancing on the ground as leafy canopies swayed high above, General Malfoy stood where the trees were relatively sparser, and looked out on his troops with calm satisfaction. Six units of three troops each, the Aerial Unit of four (to which Gregory was assigned), and the Command Unit, which was himself and Vincent. They’d only drilled for a short time on the previous Saturday, but Draco was confident that he’d managed to explain the basics. Stay with your mates, watch their back and trust them to watch yours. Move as a single body. Obey orders and show no fear. Aim, fire, move, aim again, fire again.

The six units were formed up in a defensive perimeter around Draco, watchfully gazing outward into the forest. Back-to-back they stood, wands gripped low until they needed to strike.

They already looked remarkably like the Auror units whose training Draco had watched during his father’s inspections.

Chaos and Sunshine weren’t going to know what hit them.

‘Attention,’ said General Malfoy.

The six units unfolded and spun toward Draco; the faces of his broomstick riders turned from where they stood with broomsticks already in hand.

Draco had decided to wait on demanding salutes until after they won their first battle, when Gryffindors and Hufflepuffs would be more willing to salute a Malfoy.

But his soldiers were already standing straight enough, especially the Gryffindors, that Draco wondered if he’d even needed to delay. Gregory had quietly listened, and reported back that Draco’s volunteering to stand by Harry Potter in Defence class, that time when Professor Quirrell had taught Harry how to lose, had marked Draco as an acceptable commander. At least if you happened to be assigned to his army. Not all Slytherins are alike; there are Slytherins, and then there are Slytherins was what the Gryffindors in Draco’s army were quoting to their Housemates.

Draco was frankly astounded at how incredibly easy that had been. Draco had protested at first about not being assigned any Slytherins, and Professor Quirrell had told him that if he wanted to be the first Malfoy to gain complete political control of the country, he needed to learn how to govern the other three-quarters of the population. It was things like this which reassured Draco that Professor Quirrell had a great deal more sympathy for the good guys than Professor Quirrell was letting on.

The actual battle wouldn’t be easy, especially if Granger did attack the Dragons first. Draco had agonized over whether to commit all his forces against Granger immediately in a pre-emptive strike, but had worried that (1) Harry had been misleading him completely about what Granger was likely to do, and (2) Harry had been misleading him about waiting until after Granger’s attack to join the battle.

Though Dragon Army had a secret weapon, three of them in fact, which might be enough to win even if they were attacked by both armies at once …

It was almost time, and that meant it was time for the pre-battle speech that Draco had composed and memorized.

‘The battle is about to begin,’ Draco said. His voice was calm and precise. ‘Remember everything that I and Mr Crabbe and Mr Goyle showed you. An army wins because it is disciplined and deadly. General Potter and the Chaos Legion will not be disciplined. Granger and the Sunshine Regiment will not be deadly. We are disciplined, we are deadly, we are Dragons. The battle is about to begin, and we are about to win it.’

(Ex tempore speech given by General Potter to the Chaos Legion, immediately before their first battle, on November 3rd, 1991, at 2:56pm:)

My troops, I’m not going to lie to you, our situation today is very grim. Dragon Army has never lost a single battle. And Hermione Granger … has a very good memory. The truth is, most of you are probably going to die. And the survivors will envy the dead. But we have to win this. We have to win this so that some day, our children can enjoy the taste of chocolate again. Everything is at stake here. Literally everything. If we lose, the whole universe just blinks out like a light bulb. And now I realize that most of you don’t know what a light bulb is. Well, take it from me, it’s bad. But if we have to go down, let’s go down fighting, like heroes, so that as the darkness closes in, we can think to ourselves, at least we had fun. Are you afraid to die? I know I am. I can feel those cold shivers of fear like someone is pumping ice cream into my shirt. But I know … that history is watching us. It was watching us when we changed into our uniforms. It was probably taking pictures. And history, my troops, is written by the victors. If we win this, we can write our own history. A history in which Hogwarts was founded by four renegade house elves. We can make everyone study that history, even though it isn’t true, and if they don’t answer the right way on our tests … they’ll fail the class. Isn’t that worth dying for? No, don’t answer that. Some things are better left unknown. None of us knows why we’re here. None of us knows why we’re fighting. We just woke up in these uniforms in this mysterious forest, knowing only that there was no way to get our names and memories back except victory. The students in those other armies out there … they’re just like us. They don’t want to die. They’re fighting to protect each other, the only friends they have left. They’re fighting because they know they have families who’ll miss them, even if they can’t remember now. They may even be fighting to save the world. But we have a better reason to fight than they do. We fight because we like it. We fight to amuse eldritch monstrosities from beyond Space and Time. We fight because we’re Chaos. Soon the final battle will begin, so let me say now, because I won’t get a chance later, that it was an honour to be your commander, however briefly. Thank you, thank you all. And remember, your goal isn’t just to cut down the enemy, it’s to make them afraid.

A great booming gong echoed over the forest.

And the Sunshine Regiment began to march.

Whoosh, hiss, chime; glorp, pop, bubble –

‘What?’ said Dumbledore.

‘Death is bad,’ said Harry, discarding wisdom for the sake of clear communication. ‘Very bad. Extremely bad. Being scared of death is like being scared of a great big monster with poisonous fangs. It actually makes a great deal of sense, and does not, in fact, indicate that you have a psychological problem.’

The Headmaster was staring at him as though he’d just turned into a cat.

‘Okay,’ said Harry, ‘let me put it this way. Do you want to die? Because if so, there’s this Muggle thing called a suicide prevention hotline –’

‘When it is time,’ the old wizard said quietly. ‘Not before. I would never seek to hasten the day, nor seek to refuse it when it comes.’

Harry was frowning sternly. ‘That doesn’t sound like you have a very strong will to live, Headmaster!’

‘Harry …’ The old wizard’s voice was starting to sound a little helpless; and he had paced to a spot where his silver beard, unnoticed, had drifted into a crystalline glass goldfish bowl, and was slowly taking on a greenish tinge that crept up the hairs. ‘I think I may have not made myself clear. Dark Wizards are not eager to live. They fear death. They do not reach up toward the Sun’s light, but flee the coming of night into infinitely darker caverns of their own making, without moon or stars. It is not life they desire, but immortality; and they are so driven to grasp at it that they will sacrifice their very souls! Do you want to live forever, Harry?’

‘Yes, and so do you,’ said Harry. ‘I want to live one more day. Tomorrow I will still want to live one more day. Therefore I want to live forever, proof by induction on the positive integers. If you don’t want to die, it means you want to live forever. If you don’t want to live forever, it means you want to die. You’ve got to do one or the other … I’m not getting through here, am I.’

The two cultures stared at each other across a vast gap of incommensurability.

‘I have lived a hundred and ten years,’ the old wizard said quietly (taking his beard out of the bowl, and jiggling it to shake out the colour). ‘I have seen and done a great many things, too many of which I wish I had never seen or done. And yet I do not regret being alive, for watching my students grow is a joy that has not begun to wear on me. But I would not wish to live so long that it does! What would you do with eternity, Harry?’

Harry took a deep breath. ‘Meet all the interesting people in the world, read all the good books and then write something even better, celebrate my first grandchild’s tenth birthday party on the Moon, celebrate my first great-great-great grandchild’s hundredth birthday party around the Rings of Saturn, learn the deepest and final rules of Nature, understand the nature of consciousness, find out why anything exists in the first place, visit other stars, discover aliens, create aliens, rendezvous with everyone for a party on the other side of the Milky Way once we’ve explored the whole thing, meet up with everyone else who was born on Old Earth to watch the Sun finally go out, and I used to worry about finding a way to escape this universe before it ran out of negentropy but I’m a lot more hopeful now that I’ve discovered the so-called laws of physics are just optional guidelines.’

‘I did not understand much of that,’ said Dumbledore. ‘But I must ask if these are things that you truly desire so desperately, or if you only imagine them so as to imagine not being tired, as you run and run from death.’

‘Life is not a finite list of things that you check off before you’re allowed to die,’ Harry said firmly. ‘It’s life, you just go on living it. If I’m not doing those things it’ll be because I’ve found something better.’

Dumbledore sighed. His fingers drummed on a clock; as they touched it, the numerals changed to an indecipherable script, and the hands briefly appeared in different positions. ‘In the unlikely event that I am permitted to tarry until a hundred and fifty,’ said the old wizard, ‘I do not think I would mind. But two hundred years would be entirely too much of a good thing.’

‘Yes, well,’ Harry said, his voice a little dry as he thought of his Mum and Dad and their allotted span if Harry didn’t do something about it, ‘I suspect, Headmaster, that if you came from a culture where people were accustomed to living four hundred years, that dying at two hundred would seem just as tragically premature as dying at, say, eighty.’ Harry’s voice went hard, on that last word.

‘Perhaps,’ the old wizard said peacefully. ‘I would not wish to die before my friends, nor live on after they had all gone. The hardest time is when those you loved the most have gone on before you, and yet others still live, for whose sake you must stay …’ Dumbledore’s eyes were fixed on Harry, and growing sad. ‘Do not mourn me too greatly, Harry, when my time comes; I will be with those I have long missed, on our next great adventure.’

‘Oh!’ Harry said in sudden realization. ‘You believe in an afterlife. I got the impression wizards didn’t have religion?’

Toot. Beep. Thud.

‘How can you not believe it?’ said the Headmaster, looking completely flabbergasted. ‘Harry, you’re a wizard! You’ve seen ghosts!’

‘Ghosts,’ Harry said, his voice flat. ‘You mean those things like portraits, stored memories and behaviours with no awareness or life, accidentally impressed into the surrounding material by the burst of magic that accompanies the violent death of a wizard –’

‘I’ve heard that theory,’ said the Headmaster, his voice growing sharp, ‘repeated by wizards who mistake cynicism for wisdom, who think that to look down upon others is to elevate themselves. It is one of the silliest ideas I have heard in a hundred and ten years! Yes, ghosts do not learn or grow, because this is not where they belong! Souls are meant to move on, there is no life remaining for them here! And if not ghosts, then what of the Veil? What of the Resurrection Stone?’

‘All right,’ Harry said, trying to keep his voice calm, ‘I’ll hear out your evidence, because that’s what a scientist does. But first, Headmaster, let me tell you a little story.’ Harry’s voice was trembling. ‘You know, when I got here, when I got off the train from King’s Cross, I don’t mean yesterday but back in September, when I got off the train then, Headmaster, I’d never seen a ghost. I wasn’t expecting ghosts. So when I saw them, Headmaster, I did something really dumb. I jumped to conclusions. I, I thought there was an afterlife, I thought no one had ever really died, I thought that everyone the human species had ever lost was really fine after all, I thought that wizards could talk to people who’d passed on, that it just took the right spell to summon them, that wizards could do that, I thought I could meet my parents who died for me, and tell them that I’d heard about their sacrifice and that I’d begun to call them my mother and father –’

‘Harry,’ whispered Dumbledore. Water glittered in the old wizard’s eyes. He took a step closer across the office –

‘And then,’ spat Harry, the fury coming fully into his voice, the cold rage at the universe for being like that and at himself for being so stupid, ‘I asked Hermione and she said that they were just after-images, burned into the stone of the castle by the death of a wizard, like the silhouettes left on the walls of Hiroshima. And I should have known! I should have known without even having to ask! I shouldn’t have believed it even for all of thirty seconds! Because if people had souls there wouldn’t be any such thing as brain damage, if your soul could go on speaking after your whole brain was gone, how could damage to the left cerebral hemisphere take away your ability to talk? And Professor McGonagall, when she told me about how my parents had died, she didn’t act like they’d just gone away on a long trip to another country, like they’d emigrated to Australia back in the days of sailing ships, which is the way people would act if they actually knew that death was just going somewhere else, if they had hard evidence for an afterlife, instead of making stuff up to console themselves, it would change everything, it wouldn’t matter that everyone had lost someone in the war, it would be a little sad but not horrible! And I’d already seen that people in the wizarding world didn’t act like that! So I should have known better! And that was when I knew that my parents were really dead and gone forever and ever, that there wasn’t anything left of them, that I’d never get a chance to meet them and, and, and the other children thought I was crying because I was scared of ghosts –’

The old wizard’s face was horrified, he opened his mouth to speak –

‘So tell me, Headmaster! Tell me about the evidence! But don’t you dare exaggerate a single tiny bit of it, because if you give me false hope again, and I find out later that you lied or stretched things just a little, I won’t ever forgive you for it! What’s the Veil?’

Harry reached up and wiped at his cheeks, while the glass things of the office stopped vibrating from his last shriek.

‘The Veil,’ said the old wizard with only a slight tremble in his voice, ‘is a great stone archway, kept in the Department of Mysteries; a gateway to the land of the dead.’

‘And how does anyone know that?’ said Harry. ‘Don’t tell me what you believe, tell me what you’ve seen!’

The physical manifestation of the barrier between worlds was a great stone archway, old and tall and coming to a sharp point, with a tattered black veil like the surface of a pool of water, stretched between the stones; rippling, always, from the constant and one-way passage of the souls. If you stood by the Veil you could hear the voices of the dead calling, always calling in whispers barely on the wrong side of comprehension, growing louder and more numerous if you stayed and tried to hear, as they tried to communicate; and if you listened too long, you would go to meet them, and in the moment you touched the Veil you would be sucked through, and never be heard from again.

‘That doesn’t even sound like an interesting fraud,’ Harry said, his voice calmer now that there was nothing there to make him hope, or make him angry for having hopes dashed. ‘Someone built a stone archway, made a little black rippling surface between it that Vanished anything it touched, and enchanted it to whisper to people and hypnotize them.’

‘Harry …’ the Headmaster said, starting to look rather worried. ‘I can tell you the truth, but if you refuse to hear it …’

Also not interesting. ‘What’s the Resurrection Stone?’

‘I would not tell you,’ the Headmaster said slowly, ‘save that I fear what this disbelief may do to you … so listen, then, Harry, please listen …’

The Resurrection Stone was one of the three legendary Deathly Hallows, kin to Harry’s cloak. The Resurrection Stone could call souls back from the dead – bring them back into the world of the living, though not as they were. Cadmus Peverell used the stone to call back his lost beloved from the dead, but her heart stayed with the dead, and not in the world of the living. And in time it drove him mad, and he killed himself to be truly with her once more …

In all politeness, Harry raised his hand.

‘Yes?’ the Headmaster said reluctantly.

‘The obvious test to see if the Resurrection Stone is really calling back the dead, or just projecting an image from the user’s mind, is to ask a question whose answer you don’t know, but the dead person would, and that can be definitely verified in this world. For example, call back –’

Then Harry paused, because this time he’d managed to think it through one step ahead of his tongue, fast enough to not say the first name and test that had sprung to mind.

‘… your dead wife, and ask her where she left her lost earring, or something like that,’ Harry finished. ‘Did anyone do any tests like that?’

‘The Resurrection Stone has been lost for centuries, Harry,’ the Headmaster said quietly.

Harry shrugged. ‘Well, I’m a scientist, and I’m always willing to be convinced. If you really believe the Resurrection Stone calls back the dead – then you must believe a test like that will succeed, right? So do you know anything about where to find the Resurrection Stone? I got one Deathly Hallow already under highly mysterious circumstances, and, well, we both know how the rhythm of the world works on that sort of thing.’

Dumbledore stared at Harry.

Harry gazed equably back at the Headmaster.

The old wizard passed a hand across his forehead and muttered, ‘This is madness.’

(Somehow, Harry managed to stop himself from laughing.)

And Dumbledore told Harry to draw forth the Cloak of Invisibility from his pouch; at the Headmaster’s direction, Harry stared at the inside and back of the hood until he saw it, faintly drawn against the silvery mesh in faded scarlet like dried blood, the symbol of the Deathly Hallows: a triangle, with a circle drawn inside, and a line dividing them both.

‘Thank you,’ Harry said politely. ‘I shall be sure to keep an eye out for a stone so marked. Do you have any other evidence?’

Dumbledore appeared to be fighting a struggle within himself. ‘Harry,’ the old wizard said, his voice rising, ‘this is a dangerous road you are walking, I am not sure I do the right thing by saying this, but I must wrench you from this way! Harry, how could Voldemort have survived the death of his body if he did not have a soul?’

And that was when Harry realized that there was exactly one person who’d originally told Professor McGonagall that the Dark Lord was still alive in the first place; and it was the crazy Headmaster of their madhouse of a school, who thought the world ran on cliches.

‘Good question,’ Harry said, after some internal debate about how to proceed. ‘Maybe he found some way of duplicating the power of the Resurrection Stone, only he loaded it in advance with a complete copy of his brain state. Or something like that.’ Harry was suddenly far from sure that he was trying to come up with an explanation for something that had actually happened. ‘Actually, can you just go ahead and tell me everything you know about how the Dark Lord survived and what it might take to kill him?’ If he even still exists as more than Quibbler headlines.

‘You are not fooling me, Harry,’ said the old wizard; his face looked ancient now, and lined by more than years. ‘I know why you are truly asking that question. No, I do not read your mind, I do not have to, your hesitation gives you away! You seek the secret of the Dark Lord’s immortality in order to use it for yourself!’

‘Wrong! I want the secret of the Dark Lord’s immortality in order to use it for everyone!’

Tick, crackle, fzzzt …

Albus Percival Wulfric Brian Dumbledore just stood there and stared at Harry with his mouth gaping open dumbly.

(Harry awarded himself a tally mark for Monday, since he’d managed to blow someone’s mind completely before the day was over.)

‘And in case it wasn’t clear,’ said Harry, ‘by everyone I mean all Muggles too, not just all wizards.’

‘No,’ said the old wizard, shaking his head. His voice rose. ‘No, no, no! This is insanity!’

‘Bwa ha ha!’ said Harry.

The old wizard’s face was tight with anger and worry. ‘Voldemort stole the book from which he gleaned his secret; it was not there when I went to look for it. But this much I know, and this much I will tell you: his immortality was born of a ritual terrible and Dark, blacker than pitchest black! And it was Myrtle, poor sweet Myrtle, who died for it; his immortality took sacrifice, it took murder –’

‘Well obviously I’m not going to popularize a method of immortality that requires killing people! That would defeat the entire point!’

There was a startled pause.

Slowly the old wizard’s face relaxed out of its anger, though the worry was still there. ‘You would use no ritual requiring human sacrifice.’

‘I don’t know what you take me for, Headmaster,’ Harry said coldly, his own anger rising, ‘but let’s not forget that I’m the one who wants people to live! The one who wants to save everyone! You’re the one who thinks death is awesome and everyone ought to die!’

‘I am at a loss, Harry,’ said the old wizard. His feet once more began trudging across his strange office. ‘I know not what to say.’ He picked up a crystal ball that seemed to hold a hand in flames, looked into it with a sad expression. ‘Only that I am greatly misunderstood by you … I don’t want everyone to die, Harry!’

‘You just don’t want anyone to be immortal,’ Harry said with considerable irony. It seemed that elementary logical tautologies like All x: Die(x) = Not Exist x: Not Die(x) were beyond the reasoning abilities of the world’s most powerful wizard.

The old wizard nodded. ‘I am less afraid than I was, but still greatly worried for you, Harry,’ he said quietly. His hand, a little wizened by time, but still strong, placed the crystal ball firmly back into its stand. ‘For the fear of death is a bitter thing, an illness of the soul by which people are twisted and warped. Voldemort is not the only Dark Wizard to go down that bleak road, though I fear he has taken it further than any before him.’

‘And you think you’re not afraid of death?’ Harry said, not even trying to mask the incredulity in his voice.

The old wizard’s face was peaceful. ‘I am not perfect, Harry, but I think I have accepted my death as part of myself.’

‘Uh huh,’ Harry said. ‘See, there’s this little thing called cognitive dissonance, or in plainer English, sour grapes. If people were hit on the heads with truncheons once a month, and no one could do anything about it, pretty soon there’d be all sorts of philosophers, pretending to be wise as you put it, who found all sorts of amazing benefits to being hit on the head with a truncheon once a month. Like, it makes you tougher, or it makes you happier on the days when you’re not getting hit with a truncheon. But if you went up to someone who wasn’t getting hit, and you asked them if they wanted to start, in exchange for those amazing benefits, they’d say no. And if you didn’t have to die, if you came from somewhere that no one had ever even heard of death, and I suggested to you that it would be an amazing wonderful great idea for people to get wrinkled and old and eventually cease to exist, why, you’d have me hauled right off to a lunatic asylum! So why would anyone possibly think any thought so silly as that death is a good thing? Because you’re afraid of it, because you don’t really want to die, and that thought hurts so much inside you that you have to rationalize it away, do something to numb the pain, so you won’t have to think about it –’

‘No, Harry,’ the old wizard said. His face was gentle, his hand trailed through a lighted pool of water that made small musical chimes as his fingers stirred it. ‘Though I can understand how you must think so.’

‘Do you want to understand the Dark Wizard?’ Harry said, his voice now hard and grim. ‘Then look within the part of yourself that flees not from death but from the fear of death, that finds that fear so unbearable that it will embrace Death as a friend and cozen up to it, try to become one with the night so that it can think itself master of the abyss. You have taken the most terrible of all evils and called it good! With only a slight twist that same part of yourself would murder innocents, and call it friendship. If you can call death better than life then you can twist your moral compass to point anywhere –’

‘I think,’ said Dumbledore, shaking water droplets from his hand to the sound of tiny tinkling bells, ‘that you understand Dark Wizards very well, without yet being one yourself.’ It was said in perfect seriousness, and without accusation. ‘But your comprehension of me, I fear, is sorely lacking.’ The old wizard was smiling now, and there was a gentle laughter in his voice.

Harry was trying not to go any colder than he already was; from somewhere there was pouring into his mind a blazing fury of resentment, at Dumbledore’s condescension, and all the laughter that wise old fools had ever used in place of argument. ‘Funny thing, you know, I thought Draco Malfoy was going to be this impossible to talk to, and instead, in his childish innocence, he was a hundred times stronger than you.’

A look of puzzlement crossed the old wizard’s face. ‘What do you mean?’

‘I mean,’ Harry said, his voice biting, ‘that Draco actually took his own beliefs seriously and processed my words instead of throwing them out the window by smiling with gentle superiority. You’re so old and wise, you can’t even notice anything I’m saying! Not understand, notice!’

‘I have listened to you, Harry,’ said Dumbledore, looking more solemn now, ‘but to listen is not always to agree. Disagreements aside, what is it that you think I do not comprehend?’

That if you really believed in an afterlife, you’d go down to St. Mungo’s and kill Neville’s parents, Alice and Frank Longbottom, so they could go on to their next great adventure, instead of letting them linger here in their damaged state –

Harry barely, barely kept himself from saying it out loud.

‘All right,’ Harry said coldly. ‘I’ll answer your original question, then. You asked why Dark Wizards are afraid of death. Pretend, Headmaster, that you really believed in souls. Pretend that anyone could verify the existence of souls at any time, pretend that nobody cried at funerals because they knew their loved ones were still alive. Now can you imagine destroying a soul? Ripping it to shreds so that nothing remains to go on its next great adventure? Can you imagine what a terrible thing that would be, the worst crime that had ever been committed in the history of the universe, which you would do anything to prevent from happening even once? Because that’s what Death really is – the annihilation of a soul!’

The old wizard was staring at him, a sad look in his eyes. ‘I suppose I do understand now,’ he said quietly.

‘Oh?’ said Harry. ‘Understand what?’

‘Voldemort,’ said the old wizard. ‘I understand him now at last. Because to believe that the world is truly like that, you must believe there is no justice in it, that it is woven of darkness at its core. I asked you why he became a monster, and you could give no reason. And if I could ask him, I suppose, his answer would be: why not?’

They stood there gazing into each other’s eyes, the old wizard in his robes, and the young boy with the lightning-bolt scar on his forehead.

‘Tell me, Harry,’ said the old wizard, ‘will you become a monster?’

‘No,’ said the boy, an iron certainty in his voice.

‘Why not?’ said the old wizard.

The young boy stood very straight, his chin raised high and proud, and said: ‘There is no justice in the laws of Nature, Headmaster, no term for fairness in the equations of motion. The universe is neither evil, nor good, it simply does not care. The stars don’t care, or the Sun, or the sky. But they don’t have to! We care! There is light in the world, and it is us!’

‘I wonder what will become of you, Harry,’ said the old wizard. His voice was soft, with a strange wonder and regret in it. ‘It is enough to make me wish to live just to see it.’

The boy bowed to him with heavy irony, and departed; and the oaken door slammed shut behind him with a thud.

Seamus Finnigan was ashen and trembling as he rejoined the students milling about on the withered and snow-spotted grass. Seamus’s Patronus Charm had been successful, but there was still that interval between when the Headmaster dispelled his own Patronus and when you were supposed to cast your own, when you faced the Dementor’s fear unshielded.

Up to twenty seconds of exposure at five paces was certainly safe, even for an eleven-year-old wizard with weak resistance and a still-maturing brain. There was a lot of variance in how hard the Dementor’s power hit people, which was another thing not quite understood; but twenty seconds was definitely safe.

Forty seconds of Dementor exposure at five paces might possibly have been enough to cause permanent damage, though only to the most sensitive subjects.

It was harsh training even by the standards of Hogwarts, where the way you learned to fly on a hippogriff was by being tossed on one and told to get going. Harry was no fan of over-protectiveness, and if you looked at the difference in maturity between a fourth-year in Hogwarts and a fourteen-year-old Muggle, it was clear that Muggles were smothering their children … but even Harry had started to wonder if this was pushing it. Not every hurt could be healed afterwards.

But if you couldn’t cast the spell under those conditions, it meant you couldn’t rely on using the Patronus Charm to defend yourself; overconfidence was even more dangerous to wizards than to Muggles. Dementors could drain your magic and your physical vitality, not just your happy thoughts, which meant you might not be able to Apparate away if you waited too long, or if you didn’t recognize the approaching fear until the Dementor was within range for its attack. (During his reading, Harry had discovered with considerable horror that some books claimed the Dementor’s Kiss would eat your soul and that this was the reason for the permanent mindless coma into which it put the victims. And that wizards who believed this had deliberately used the Dementor’s Kiss to execute criminals. It was a certainty that some called criminals were innocent, and even if they weren’t, destroying their souls? If Harry had believed in souls, he would have … drawn a blank, he just couldn’t think of an appropriate response to that.)

The Headmaster was taking security seriously, and so were the three Aurors standing guard. Their leader was an Asian-looking man, solemn without being grim, Auror Komodo, whose wand never left his hand. His Patronus, an orang-utan of solid moonlight, paced back and forth between the Dementor and the first-years awaiting their turn; beside the orang-utan moved the bright white panther of Auror Butnaru, a man with a piercing gaze, long black hair in a ponytail, and a long braided goatee. Those two Aurors, and their two Patronuses, were all watching the Dementor. On the opposite side of the students was the resting Auror Goryanof, tall and thin and pale and unshaven, sitting back on a chair he’d conjured without word or wand, and maintaining an absent-minded poker face as he scanned the entire scene. Professor Quirrell had shown up not long after the first-years began their attempts, and his eyes never strayed far from Harry. The tiny Professor Flitwick, who had been a champion duellist, was fiddling absently with his wand; and his eyes, peering out from within the huge puffy beard that served as his face, stayed focused on Professor Quirrell.

And it must have been Harry’s imagination, but Professor Quirrell seemed to wince slightly each time the Headmaster’s Patronus winked out to test the next student. Maybe Professor Quirrell was imagining the same placebo effect as Harry, that backwash of emptiness caressing at his mind.

‘Anthony Goldstein,’ called the voice of the Headmaster.

Harry quietly walked toward Seamus, even as Anthony began to approach the shining silver phoenix, and … whatever it was beneath the tattered cloak.

‘What did you see?’ Harry asked Seamus in a low voice.

A lot of students hadn’t answered Harry, when he’d tried to gather the data; but Seamus was Finnigan of Chaos, one of Harry’s lieutenants. Maybe that wasn’t fair, but …

‘Dead,’ said Seamus in a whisper, ‘greyish and slimy … dead and left in water for a while …’

Harry nodded. ‘That’s what a lot of people see,’ Harry said. He projected confidence, even though it was fake, because Seamus needed it. ‘Go eat some chocolate, you’ll feel better.’

Seamus nodded and stumbled off toward the table of healing sweets.

‘Expecto Patronum!’ cried a young boy’s voice.

Then there were gasps of shock, even from the Aurors.

Harry spun around to look –

There was a brilliant silver bird standing between Anthony Goldstein and the cage. The bird reared its head and let out a cry, and the cry was also silver, as bright and hard and beautiful as metal.

And something in the back of Harry’s mind said, if that’s a peregrine falcon, I’m going to strangle him in his sleep.

Shut up, Harry said to the thought, do you want us to be a Dark Wizard?

What’s the point? You’re going to end up as one eventually.

That … wasn’t something Harry would usually have thought …

It’s a placebo effect, Harry told himself again. The Dementor can’t actually get to me through three corporeal Patronuses, I’m just imagining what I think it’s like. When I actually face the Dementor, it’ll feel completely different, and then I’ll know I was just being silly before.

A slight chill went down Harry’s spine then, because he had a feeling that yes, it would be completely different, and not in a positive direction.

The blazing silver phoenix sprang back into existence from the Headmaster’s wand, the lesser bird vanished; and Anthony Goldstein began to walk back.

The Headmaster was coming with Anthony instead of calling out the next name, the Patronus waiting behind to guard the Dementor.

Harry glanced over to where Hermione was standing, just behind the glowing panther. Hermione’s turn would have come next, but had apparently just been delayed.

She looked stressed.

Earlier, she’d politely asked Harry to please stop trying to de-stress her.

Dumbledore was smiling slightly as he escorted Anthony back toward the others; smiling only slightly, because the Headmaster looked very, very tired.

‘Unbelievable,’ said Dumbledore in a voice that sounded much weaker than his accustomed boom. ‘A corporeal Patronus, in his first year. And an astounding number of successes among the other young students. Quirinus, I must acknowledge that you have proved your point.’

Professor Quirrell inclined his head. ‘A simple enough guess, I should think. A Dementor attacks through fear, and children are less afraid.’

‘Less afraid?’ said Auror Goryanof from where he was sitting.

‘So I said as well,’ said Dumbledore. ‘And Professor Quirrell pointed out that adults had more courage, not less to fear; which thought, I confess, had never occurred to me before.’

‘That was not my precise phrasing,’ Professor Quirrell said dryly, ‘but it will do. And the rest of our agreement, Headmaster?’

‘As you say,’ Dumbledore said reluctantly. ‘I admit I was not expecting to lose that wager, Quirinus, but you have proven your wisdom.’

All the students were looking at them, puzzled; except Hermione, who was staring in the direction of the cage and the tall decaying robes; and Harry, who was watching everyone, since he was imagining himself feeling paranoid.

Professor Quirrell said, in tones that did not invite further comments, ‘I am allowed to teach the Killing Curse to students who wish to learn it. Which will render them considerably safer from Dark Wizards and other pests, and it is foolish to think they will otherwise know no deadly magics.’ Professor Quirrell paused, his eyes narrowing. ‘Headmaster, I respectfully observe that you are not looking well. I suggest leaving the remainder of the day’s task to Professor Flitwick.’

Dumbledore shook his head. ‘We are almost done for the day, Quirinus. I will last.’

Hermione had approached Anthony. ‘Captain Goldstein,’ she said, and her voice trembled only a little, ‘can you give me any advice?’

‘Don’t be afraid,’ Anthony said firmly. ‘Don’t think about anything it tries to make you think about. You’re not just holding up the wand in front of you as a shield against the fear, you’re brandishing your wand to drive the fear away, that’s how you make a happy thought into something solid …’ Anthony shrugged helplessly. ‘I mean, I heard all that before, but …’

Other students were starting to congregate around Anthony, with their own questions.

‘Miss Granger?’ the Headmaster said. His voice might have been gentle, or just weakened.

Hermione straightened her shoulders, and followed him.

‘What did you see under the cloak?’ Harry said to Anthony.

Anthony looked at Harry, surprised, and then answered, ‘A very tall man who was dead, I mean, sort of dead-shaped and dead-coloured … it hurt to see him and I knew that was the Dementor trying to get at me.’

Harry looked back out at where Hermione was confronting the cage and the cloak.

Hermione raised her wand into position for the first gestures.

The Headmaster’s phoenix winked out of existence.

And Hermione gave a tiny, pathetic shriek, flinched –

– took a step back, Harry could see her wand moving, and then she brandished it and said ‘Expecto Patronum!’

Nothing happened.

Hermione turned and ran.

‘Expecto Patronum!’ said the Headmaster’s deeper voice, and the silver phoenix blazed back to life.

The young girl stumbled, and kept running, strange sounds beginning to come from her throat.

‘Hermione!’ Susan yelled it, and Hannah, and Daphne, and Ernie, and they all started to run toward her; even as Harry, who was always thinking one step ahead, spun on his own heel and ran for the table with the chocolate.

Even after Harry had shoved the chocolate into Hermione’s mouth and she’d chewed and swallowed, she was still breathing in great gasps and crying, her eyes still seemed unfocused.

She can’t have been permanently Demented, Harry thought desperately at the confusion inside him, the horrible fear and deathly fury beginning to twist around each other, she can’t have been, she wasn’t exposed for even ten seconds let alone forty –

But she could be temporarily Demented, as Harry realized in that moment, there wasn’t any rule that you couldn’t be temporarily injured by a Dementor in just ten seconds if you were sensitive enough.

Then Hermione’s eyes seemed to focus, and dart around, and settle on him.

‘Harry,’ she gasped, and the other students went silent. ‘Harry, don’t. Don’t!’

Harry was suddenly afraid to ask what he shouldn’t do, was he in her worst memories, or some sleep’s nightmare that she was now reliving in waking life?

‘Don’t go near it!’ said Hermione. Her hand reached out, grabbed him by the lapel of his robes. ‘You mustn’t go near it, Harry! It spoke to me, Harry, it knows you, it knows you’re here!’

‘What –’ Harry said, and then cursed himself for asking.

‘The Dementor!’ said Hermione. Her voice rose to a shriek. ‘Professor Quirrell wants it to eat you!’

In the sudden hush, Professor Quirrell came forward a few steps; but he didn’t approach any closer (Harry was there, after all). ‘Miss Granger,’ he said, and his voice was grave, ‘I think you should have some more chocolate.’

‘Professor Flitwick, don’t let Harry try, send him back!’

The Headmaster had arrived by then, and he and Professor Flitwick were exchanging worried looks.

‘I did not hear the Dementor speak,’ the Headmaster said. ‘Still …’

‘Just ask,’ said Professor Quirrell, sounding a little weary.

‘Did the Dementor say how it would get to Harry?’ said the Headmaster.

‘All his tastiest parts first,’ said Hermione, ‘it would – it would eat –’

Hermione blinked. Some sanity seemed to come back into her eyes.

Then she started crying.

‘You were too brave, Hermione Granger,’ the Headmaster said. His voice was gentle, and clearly audible. ‘Too much braver than I comprehended. You should have turned and run, not endured and tried to complete your Charm. When you are older and stronger, Miss Granger, I know that you will try again, and I know that you will succeed.’

‘I’m sorry,’ Hermione said in gasps, ‘I’m sorry, I’m sorry, I’m sorry … I’m sorry, Harry, I can’t tell you what I saw, I didn’t look at it, I didn’t dare look at it, I knew it was too horrible to ever be seen …’

It should have been Harry, but he’d hesitated, because his hands were all chocolatey; and then Ernie and Susan were there, helping Hermione from where she’d fallen on the grass, leading her toward the snacks table.

Five bars of chocolate later, Hermione seemed to be all right again, and she went over and apologized to Professor Quirrell; but she was always watching Harry, every time that he glanced in her direction. He’d stepped toward her only once, and stopped when she’d stepped away. Her eyes had silently apologized, and silently pleaded for him to leave her be.

Neville Longbottom had seen something dead and half-dissolved, oozing and running with a face like a squashed sponge.

It was the worst thing anyone had yet described seeing. Neville had been able to produce a small flicker of light from his wand before, but he had, intelligently and with great presence of mind, turned and run away instead of trying to cast his own Patronus Charm.

(The Headmaster had said nothing to the other students, told no one else to be less brave; but Professor Quirrell had calmly observed that if you made the mistake after being warned, that was when ignorance became stupidity.)

‘Professor Quirrell?’ Harry said in a low voice, having come as close to the Defence Professor as he dared. ‘What do you see when you –’

‘Don’t ask.’ The voice was very flat.

Harry nodded respectfully. ‘What was your original phrasing to the Headmaster, if I can ask?’

Dryly. ‘Our worst memories can only grow worse as we grow older.’

‘Ah,’ Harry said. ‘Logical.’

Something strange flickered in Professor Quirrell’s eyes, then, as he looked at Harry. ‘Let us hope,’ Professor Quirrell said, ‘that you succeed upon this try, Mr Potter. For if you do, the Headmaster may teach you his trick of using a Patronus to send messages that cannot be forged or intercepted, and the military importance of that is impossible to overstate. It would be a tremendous advantage to the Chaos Legion, and some day, I suspect, this entire country. But if you do not succeed, Mr Potter … well, I shall understand.’

Morag MacDougal had said, in a wavering voice, ‘Ouch’, and Dumbledore had recast his Patronus right away.

Parvati Patil had produced a corporeal Patronus in the form of a tiger, larger than Dumbledore’s phoenix, though not nearly as bright. There had been a great burst of applause from all the watchers, though not the same shock as when Anthony had done it.

And then it was Harry’s turn.

The Headmaster called the name of Harry Potter, and Harry was afraid.

Harry knew, he knew that he was going to fail, and he knew that it was going to hurt.

But he still had to try; because sometimes, in the presence of a Dementor, a wizard went from not a flicker of light to a full corporeal Patronus, and no one understood why.

And because if Harry couldn’t defend himself from Dementors, he had to be able to recognize their approach, recognize the feeling of them in his mind, and run before it was too late.

What is my worst memory … ?

Harry had expected the Headmaster to give him a worried look, or a hopeful look, or deeply wise advice; but instead Albus Dumbledore only watched him with quiet calm.

He thinks I’m going to fail, but he won’t sabotage me by telling me so, thought Harry, if he had true words of encouragement to speak, he would speak them …

The cage came closer. It was already tarnished, but not rusted away to nothing, not yet.

The cloak came closer. It was unravelling and shot through with unpatched holes; it had been new that morning, Auror Goryanof had said.

‘Headmaster?’ Harry said. ‘What do you see?’

The Headmaster’s voice was also calm. ‘The Dementors are creatures of fear, and as your fear of the Dementor diminishes, so does the fearsomeness of its form. I see a tall, thin, naked man. He is not decaying. He is only slightly painful to look upon. That is all. What do you see, Harry?’

… Harry couldn’t see under the cloak.

Or that wasn’t right, it was that his mind was refusing to see what was under the cloak …

No, his mind was trying to see the wrong thing under the cloak, Harry could feel it, his eyes trying to force a mistake. But Harry had done his best to train himself to notice that tiny feeling of confusion, to automatically flinch away from making stuff up; and every time his mind tried to start inventing a lie about what was under the cloak, that reflex was fast enough to shut it down.

Harry looked under the cloak and saw …

An open question. Harry wouldn’t let his mind see something false, and so he didn’t see anything, like the part of his visual cortex getting that signal was just ceasing to exist. There was a blind spot under the cloak. Harry couldn’t know what was under there.

Just that it was far worse than any decaying mummy.

The unseeable horror beneath the cloak was very close, now, but the blazing bird of moonlight, the white phoenix, yet lay between them.

Harry wanted to run away like some of the other students had. Half the ones who’d had no luck with their Patronus Charms just hadn’t shown up today in the first place. Of those remaining, half had fled before the Headmaster had even dispelled his own Patronus, and no one had said a word. There’d been a little laughter when Terry had turned and walked back before his own try; and Susan and Hannah, who’d gone before, had yelled at everyone to shut up.

But Harry was the Boy-Who-Lived, and he would lose much respect if he was seen to give up without even trying …

Pride and roles seemed to diminish and fall away, in the presence of whatever lay beneath the cloak.

Why am I still here?

It wasn’t the shame of others thinking him cowardly, that kept Harry’s feet in place.

It wasn’t the hope of repairing his reputation that brought up his wand.

It wasn’t the desire to master the Patronus Charm as magic, that moved his fingers into the initial position.

It was something else, something that had to oppose whatever lay beneath the cloak, this was the true darkness and Harry had to find out whether it lay within him, the power to drive it back.

Harry had planned to try one final time to think of his book-shopping spree with his father, but instead, at the last minute, facing the Dementor, a different memory occurred to him, something he hadn’t tried before; a thought that wasn’t warm and happy in the ordinary way, but felt righter, somehow.

And Harry remembered the stars, remembered them burning terribly bright and unwavering in the Silent Night; he let that image fill him, fill all of him like an Occlumency barrier across his entire mind, became once again the bodiless awareness of the void.

The bright silver shining phoenix vanished.

And the Dementor smashed into his mind like the fist of God.

FEAR / COLD / DARKNESS

There was an instant when the two forces clashed head-on, when the peaceful starlit memory held its own against the fear, even as Harry’s fingers began the wand motions, practised until they had become automatic. They weren’t warm and happy, those blazing points of light in perfect blackness; but it was an image the Dementor could not easily pierce. For the silent burning stars were vast and unafraid, and to shine in the cold and darkness was their natural state.

But there was a flaw, a crack, a fault-line in the immovable object trying to resist that irresistible force. Harry felt a twinge of anger at the Dementor for trying to feed on him, and it was like slipping on wet ice. Harry’s mind began to slide sideways, into bitterness, black fury, deathly hatred –

Harry’s wand came up in the final brandish.

It felt wrong.

‘Expecto Patronum,’ his voice spoke, the words hollow and pointless.

And Harry fell into his dark side, fell down into his dark side, further and faster and deeper than ever before, down down down as the slide accelerated, as the Dementor latched onto the exposed and vulnerable parts and fed on them, eating away the light. A fading reflex scrabbled for warmth, but even as an image of Hermione came to him, or an image of Mum and Dad, the Dementor twisted it, showed him Hermione lying dead on the ground, the corpses of his mother and father, and then even that was sucked away.

Into the vacuum rose the memory, the worst memory, something forgotten so long ago that the neural patterns shouldn’t have still existed.

‘Lily, take Harry and go! It’s him!’ shouted a man’s voice. ‘Go! Run! I’ll hold him off!’

And Harry couldn’t help but think, in the empty depths of his dark side, how ridiculously overconfident James Potter had been. Hold off Lord Voldemort? With what?

Then the other voice spoke, high-pitched like the hiss of a teakettle, and it was like dry ice laid on Harry’s every nerve, like a brand of metal cooled to liquid helium temperatures and laid on every part of him. And the voice said:

‘Avadakedavra.’

(The wand flew from the boy’s nerveless fingers as his body began to convulse and fall, the Headmaster’s eyes widening in alarm as he began his own Patronus Charm.)

‘Not Harry, not Harry, please not Harry!’ screamed the woman’s voice.

Whatever was left of Harry listened with all the light drained out of him, in the dead void of his heart, and wondered if she thought that Lord Voldemort would stop because she asked politely.

‘Step aside, woman!’ said the shrill voice of burning cold. ‘For you I am not come, only the boy.’

‘Not Harry! Please … have mercy … have mercy …’

Lily Potter, Harry thought, seemed not to understand what type of people became Dark Lords in the first place; and if this was the best strategy she could conceive to save her child’s life, that was her final failure as a mother.

‘I give you this rare chance to flee,’ said the shrill voice. ‘But I will not trouble myself to subdue you, and your death here will not save your child. Step aside, foolish woman, if you have any sense in you at all!’

‘Not Harry, please no, take me, kill me instead!’

The empty thing that was Harry wondered if Lily Potter seriously imagined that Lord Voldemort would say yes, kill her, and then depart leaving her son unharmed.

‘Very well,’ said the voice of death, now sounding coldly amused, ‘I accept the bargain. Yourself to die, and the child to live. Now drop your wand so that I can murder you.’

There was a hideous silence.

Lord Voldemort began to laugh, horrible contemptuous laughter.

And then, at last, Lily Potter’s voice shrieked in desperate hate, ‘Avada ke-’

The lethal voice finished first, the curse rapid and precise.

‘Avadakedavra.’

A blinding flare of green marked the end of Lily Potter.

And the boy in the crib saw it, the eyes, those two crimson eyes, seeming to glow bright red, to blaze like miniature suns, filling Harry’s whole vision as they locked to his own –

The other children saw Harry Potter fall, they heard Harry Potter scream, a thin high-pitched scream that seemed to pierce their ears like knives.

There was a brilliant silver flash as the Headmaster bellowed ‘Expecto Patronum!’ and the blazing phoenix returned to being.

But Harry Potter’s horrible scream went on and on and on, even as the Headmaster scooped up the boy in his arms and bore him away from the Dementor, even as Neville Longbottom and Professor Flitwick both went for the chocolate at the same time and –

Hermione knew it, she knew it as she saw it, she knew that her nightmare had been real, it was coming true, somehow it was coming true.

‘Get him chocolate!’ demanded the voice of Professor Quirrell, pointlessly, because Professor Flitwick’s tiny form was already cannonballing toward where the Headmaster was racing toward the students.

Hermione was moving forward herself, though she didn’t know what else she meant to do –

‘Cast Patronuses!’ shouted the Headmaster, as he brought Harry behind the Aurors. ‘Everyone who can! Get them between Harry and the Dementor! It’s still feeding on him!’

There was a moment of frozen horror.

‘Expecto Patronum!’ shouted Professor Flitwick and Auror Goryanof, and then Anthony Goldstein, but he failed the first time, and then Parvati Patil, who succeeded, and then Anthony tried again and his silver bird spread its wings and screamed at the Dementor, and Dean Thomas roared the words like they had been written in letters of fire and his wand gave birth to a towering white bear; there were eight blazing Patronuses all in a line between Harry and the Dementor, and Harry went on screaming and screaming as the Headmaster laid him on the dried grass.

Hermione couldn’t cast a Patronus Charm, so she ran toward where Harry lay. In her mind, something tried to guess how long it had been already. Was it twenty seconds? More?

There was a dreadful agony and bewilderment on the face of Albus Dumbledore. His long black wand was in his hand, but he spoke no spells, only looked down at Harry’s convulsing body in horror –

Hermione didn’t know what to do, she didn’t know what to do, she didn’t understand what was happening, and the most powerful wizard in the world seemed equally at a loss.

‘Use your phoenix!’ bellowed Professor Quirrell. ‘Take him far away from that Dementor!’

Without a single word the Headmaster scooped up Harry in his arms and vanished in a crack of fire along with the suddenly appearing Fawkes; and the Headmaster’s Patronus winked out, where it had guarded the Dementor.

Horror and confusion and sudden babble.

‘Mr Potter should recover,’ Professor Quirrell said, raising his voice, but his tone now calm once again, ‘I think it was just over twenty seconds.’

Then the blazing white phoenix appeared again, like it was flying before them from elsewhere, to Hermione Granger came the creature of moonlight, and it cried to her in Albus Dumbledore’s voice:

‘It still feeds on him, even here! How? If you know, Hermione Granger, you must tell me! Tell me!’

The senior Auror turned to stare at her, and so did many students. Professor Flitwick didn’t turn, he was now levelling his wand on Professor Quirrell, who was holding out clearly empty hands.

Seconds ticked past, uncounted.

She couldn’t remember it, she couldn’t remember the nightmare clearly, she couldn’t remember why she had thought it was possible, why she had been afraid –

Hermione realized then what she ought to do, and it was the hardest decision of her life.

What if whatever had happened to Harry, happened to her too?

All her limbs cold as death, her vision gone dark, fear overwhelming everything; she’d seen Harry dying, Mum and Dad dying, all her friends dying, everyone dying, so that in the end, when she died, she would be alone. That was her secret nightmare she’d never talked about with anyone, that had given the Dementor its power over her, the loneliest thing was to die alone.

She didn’t want to go to that place again, she, she didn’t, she didn’t want to stay there forever –

You have courage enough for Gryffindor, said the calm voice of the Sorting Hat in her memory, but you will do what is right in any House I give you. You will learn, you will stand by your friends, in any House you choose. So don’t be afraid, Hermione Granger, just decide where you belong …

There was no time for deciding, Harry was dying.

‘I can’t remember now,’ said Hermione, her voice cracking, ‘but just hold on, I’ll go in front of the Dementor again …’

She started to run toward the Dementor.

‘Miss Granger!’ squeaked Professor Flitwick, but he made no move to stop her, only kept holding his wand on Professor Quirrell.

‘Everyone!’ shouted Auror Komodo in a voice of military command. ‘Get your Patronuses out of her way!’

‘Flitwick!’ roared Professor Quirrell. ‘Summon Potter’s wand!’

Even as Hermione understood, Professor Flitwick was already crying ‘Accio!’, and she saw the stick of wood zooming up from where it had lain almost touching the Dementor’s cage.

The eyes opened, dead and vacant.

‘Harry!’ gasped a voice in the colourless world. ‘Harry! Speak to me!’

The face of Albus Dumbledore leaned over into the field of vision, which had been occupied by a distant marble ceiling.

‘You’re annoying,’ said the empty voice. ‘You should die.’

From behind Draco came the sound of the door opening again.

Draco heard Harry’s footsteps entering the classroom, but Draco didn’t turn to look.

Harry didn’t say anything either. The silence stretched.

Finally –

‘What does this mean?’ Draco said. His voice wavered a bit.

‘It means you love your father,’ Harry’s voice said. Which was just what Draco had been thinking, and trying not to cry in front of Harry. It was too right, just too right –

Before Draco, on the floor, was the shining form of a snake that Draco recognized; a Blue Krait, a snake first brought to their manor by Lord Abraxas Malfoy after a visit to some faraway land, and Father had kept a Blue Krait in the ophidarium ever since. The thing about the Blue Krait was that the bite wouldn’t hurt much. Father had said that, and told Draco that he was never allowed to pet the snake, no matter who was watching. The venom killed your nerves so fast that you didn’t have time to feel pain as the poison spread. You could die of it even after using Healing Charms. It ate other snakes. It was as Slytherin as any creature could possibly be.

That was why a Blue Krait head had been forged into the handle of Father’s cane.

The bright snake darted out its tongue, which was also silver; and seemed to smile somehow, in a warmer way than any reptile should.

And then Draco realized –

‘But,’ Draco said, still staring at the beautifully radiant snake, ‘you can’t cast the Patronus Charm.’ Now that Draco had cast it himself, he understood why that was important. You could be evil, like Dumbledore, and still cast the Patronus Charm, so long as you had something bright left inside you. But if Harry Potter didn’t have a single thought inside him that shone like that –

‘The Patronus Charm is more complicated than you think, Draco,’ Harry said seriously. ‘Not everyone who fails at casting it is a bad person, or even unhappy. But anyway, I can cast it. I did it on my second try, after I realized what I’d done wrong facing the Dementor my first time. But, well, my life gets a little peculiar sometimes, and my Patronus came out strange, and I’m keeping it a secret for now –’

‘Am I supposed to just believe that?’

‘You can ask Professor Quirrell if you don’t believe me,’ said Harry. ‘Ask him whether Harry Potter can cast a corporeal Patronus, and tell him that I told you to ask. He’d know the request was from me, no one else would know.’

Oh, and now Draco was to trust Professor Quirrell? Still, knowing Harry, it might be true; and Professor Quirrell wouldn’t lie for trivial reasons.

The glowing snake turned its head back and forth, as though seeking a prey that wasn’t there, and then coiled itself into a circle, as though to rest.

‘I wonder,’ Harry said softly, ‘when it was, which year, which generation, that Slytherins stopped trying to learn the Patronus Charm. When it was that people started to think, that Slytherins themselves started to think, that being cunning and ambitious was the same as being cold and unhappy. And if Salazar knew that his students didn’t even bother showing up to learn the Patronus Charm any more, I wonder, would he wish that he’d never been born? I wonder how it all went wrong, when Slytherin’s House went wrong.’

The shining creature winked out, the turmoil rising in Draco making it impossible to sustain the Charm. Draco spun on Harry, he had to control himself not to raise his wand. ‘What do you know about Slytherin House or Salazar Slytherin? You were never Sorted into my House, what gives you the right to –’

And that was when Draco finally realized.

‘You did get Sorted into Slytherin!’ Draco said. ‘You did, and afterwards you, you somehow, you snapped your fingers –’ Draco had once asked Father if it would be cleverer to get Sorted into some other House so that everyone would trust him, and Father had smiled and said that he’d thought of that too at Draco’s age, but there was no way to fool the Sorting Hat …

… not until Harry Potter came along.

How had he ever bought for one minute that Harry was a Ravenclaw?

‘An interesting hypothesis,’ Harry said equably. ‘Do you know, you’re the second person in Hogwarts to come up with a theory along those lines? At least you’re the second that’s actually said so to my face –’

‘Snape,’ Draco said with certainty. His Head of House was no fool.

‘Professor Quirrell, of course,’ said Harry. ‘Though come to think, Severus did ask me how I managed to stay out of his House, and whether I had something the Sorting Hat wanted. I suppose you could say you’re number three. Oh, but Professor Quirrell’s theory was a little different than yours, though. May I have your word not to repeat it?’

Draco nodded without even really thinking about it. What was he supposed to do, say no?

‘Professor Quirrell thought that Dumbledore wasn’t happy with the Hat’s choice for the Boy-Who-Lived.’

And the instant Harry said it, Draco knew, he knew that it was true, it was just obvious. Who did Dumbledore even think he was fooling?

… well, besides every single other person in Hogwarts except Snape and Quirrell, Harry might even believe it himself …

Draco stumbled back over to his desk in something of a daze, and sat down hard enough to hurt slightly. This sort of thing happened around once a month with Harry, and it hadn’t happened yet in January, so it was time.

His fellow Slytherin, who might or might not think himself a Ravenclaw, sat back down in the chair he’d used earlier, now sitting on it crosswise, and looking up intently at Draco.

Draco didn’t know what he should be doing now, whether he should be trying to persuade the lost Slytherin boy that, no, he wasn’t actually a Ravenclaw … or trying to figure out whether Harry was in league with Dumbledore, though that suddenly seemed less likely … but then why had Harry set up the whole thing with him and Granger …

He really should have remembered that Harry was too weird for any normal plots.

‘Harry,’ Draco said. ‘Did you deliberately antagonize me and General Sunshine just so we’d work together against you?’

Harry nodded without hesitation, as though it was the most normal thing in the world, and nothing to be ashamed of.

‘The whole thing with the gloves and making us climb up the walls of Hogwarts, the only point was to make me and Granger more friendly toward each other. And even before then. You’ve been plotting it for a really long time. Since the beginning.’

Again the nod.

‘WHYYYYY?’

Harry’s eyebrows lifted for a moment, the only reaction he showed to Draco shrieking so loudly in the closed classroom that it hurt his own ears. Why, why, why did Harry Potter Do this sort of thing …

Then Harry said, ‘So that Slytherins will be able to cast the Patronus Charm again.’

‘That … doesn’t … make … Sense!’ Draco was aware that he was losing control of his voice, but he didn’t seem able to stop himself. ‘What does that have to do with Granger?’

‘Patterns,’ Harry said. His face was very serious now, and very grave. ‘Like a quarter of children born to Squib couples being wizards. A simple, unmistakable pattern you would recognize instantly, if you knew what you were looking at; even though, if you didn’t know, you wouldn’t even realize it was a clue. The poison in Slytherin House is something that’s been seen before in the Muggle world. This is an advance prediction, Draco, I could have written it down for you before our first day of school, just from hearing you talk in King’s Cross Station. Let me describe some really pathetic sorts of people that hang around at your father’s political rallies, pureblood families that would never be invited to dinner at Malfoy Manor. Bearing in mind that I’ve never met them, I’m just predicting it from recognizing the pattern of what’s happening to Slytherin House –’

And Harry Potter proceeded to describe the Parkinsons and Montagues and Boles with a calmly cutting accuracy that Draco wouldn’t have dared think to himself in case there was a Legilimens around, it was beyond insult, they would kill Harry if they ever heard …

‘To sum up,’ Harry finished, ‘they don’t have any power themselves. They don’t have any wealth themselves. If they didn’t have Muggleborns to hate, if all the Muggleborns vanished the way they say they want, they’d wake up one morning and find they had nothing. But so long as they can say purebloods are superior, they can feel superior themselves, they can feel like part of the master class. Even though your father would never dream of inviting them to dinner, even though there’s not one Galleon in their vaults, even if they did worse on their OWLs than the worst Muggleborn in Hogwarts. Even if they can’t cast the Patronus Charm any more. Everything is the Muggleborns’ fault to them, they have someone besides themselves to blame for their own failures, and that makes them even weaker. That’s what Slytherin House is becoming, pathetic, and the root of the problem is hating Muggleborns.’

‘Salazar Slytherin himself said that mudbloods needed to be cast out! That they were weakening our blood –’ Draco’s voice had risen to a shout.

‘Salazar was wrong as a question of simple fact! You know that, Draco! And that hatred is poisoning your whole House, you couldn’t cast the Patronus Charm using a thought like that!’

‘Then why could Salazar Slytherin cast the Patronus Charm?’

Harry was wiping sweat from his forehead. ‘Because things have changed between then and now! Listen, Draco, three hundred years ago you could find great scientists, as great as Salazar in their own way, who would have told you that some other Muggles were inferior because of their skin colour –’

‘Skin colour?’ said Draco.

‘I know, skin colour instead of anything important like blood purity, isn’t it ridiculous? But then something in the world changed, and now you can’t find any great scientists who still think skin colour should matter, only saddos like the ones I told you about. Salazar Slytherin made the mistake when everyone else was making it, because he grew up believing it, not because he was desperate for someone to hate. There were a few people who did better than everyone else around them, and they were exceptionally good. But the ones who just accepted what everyone else thought weren’t exceptionally evil. The sad fact is that most people just don’t notice a moral issue at all unless someone else is pointing it out to them; and once they’re as old as Salazar was when he met Godric, they’ve lost the ability to change their minds. Only then Hogwarts was built, and Hogwarts started sending acceptance letters to Muggleborns like Godric insisted, and more and more people began to notice that Muggleborns weren’t any different. Now it’s a big political issue instead of something that everyone just believes without thinking about it. And the correct answer is that Muggleborns aren’t any weaker than purebloods. So now the people who end up siding with what Salazar once believed, are either people who grew up in very closed pureblood environments like you, or people who are so pathetic themselves that they’re desperate for someone to feel superior to, people who love to hate.’

‘That doesn’t … that doesn’t sound right …’ Draco’s voice said. His ears listened, and wondered that he couldn’t come up with anything better to say.

‘It doesn’t? Draco, you know now there’s nothing wrong with Hermione Granger. You had trouble dropping her off a roof, I hear. Even though you knew she’d taken a Feather-Falling Potion, even though you knew she was safe. What sort of person do you think wants to kill her, not for any wrong she did to them, just because she’s a Muggleborn? Even though she’s, she’s just a young girl who would help them with their homework in a second, if they ever asked her,’ Harry’s voice broke, ‘what sort of person wants her to die?’

Father –

Draco felt split in two, he seemed to be having a problem with dual vision, Granger is a mudblood, she should die and a girl hanging from his hand on the rooftop, like seeing double, seeing double –

‘And anyone who doesn’t want Hermione Granger to die, won’t want to hang around the sort of people who do! That’s all people think Slytherin is now, not clever planning, not trying to achieve greatness, just hating Muggleborns! I paid Morag a Sickle to ask Padma why she hadn’t gone to Slytherin, we both know she got the option. And Morag told me that Padma just gave her a look and said that she wasn’t Pansy Parkinson. You see? The best students with the virtues of more than one House, the students with choices, they go under the Hat thinking anywhere but Slytherin, and someone like Padma ends up in Ravenclaw. And … I think the Sorting Hat tries to maintain a balance in the Sorting, so it fills out the ranks of Slytherin with anyone who isn’t repelled by all the hatred. So instead of Padma Patil, Slytherin gets Pansy Parkinson. She’s not very cunning, and she’s not very ambitious, but she’s the sort of person who doesn’t mind what Slytherin is turning into. And the more Padmas go to Ravenclaw and the more Pansies go to Slytherin, the more the process accelerates. It’s destroying Slytherin House, Draco!’

It had a ring of awful truth, Padma had belonged in Slytherin … and instead Slytherin got Pansy … Father rallied lesser families like the Parkinsons because they were convenient sources of support, but Father hadn’t realized the consequences of associating Slytherin’s name with them …

‘I can’t –’ Draco said, but he wasn’t even sure what he couldn’t do – ‘What do you want from me?’

‘I’m not sure how to heal Slytherin House,’ Harry said slowly. ‘But I know it’s something you and I will end up having to do. It took centuries for science to dawn over the Muggle world, it only happened slowly, but the stronger science got, the further that sort of hatred retreated.’ Harry’s voice was quiet, now. ‘I don’t know exactly why it worked that way, but that’s how it happened historically. As though there’s something in science like the shine of the Patronus Charm, driving back all sorts of darkness and madness, not right away, but it seems to follow wherever science goes. The Enlightenment, that was what it was called in the Muggle world. It has something to do with seeking the truth, I think … with being able to change your mind from what you grew up believing … with thinking logically, realizing that there’s no reason to hate someone because their skin is a different colour, just like there’s no reason to hate Hermione Granger … or maybe there’s something to it that even I don’t understand. But the Enlightenment is something that you and I belong to now, both of us. Fixing Slytherin House is just one of the things we have to do.’

‘Let me think,’ Draco said, his voice coming out in something of a croak, ‘please,’ and he rested his head in his hands, and thought.

Draco thought for a while, with his palms over his eyes to shut out the world, no sound but his and Harry’s breathing. All the persuasive reasonableness of what Harry said, the evident grains of truth that it contained; and against that, the obvious, the perfectly and entirely obvious hypothesis about what was really going on …

After a time, Draco finally raised his head.

‘It sounds right,’ Draco said quietly.

A huge smile broke out on Harry’s face.

‘So,’ Draco continued, ‘is this where you bring me to Dumbledore, to make it official?’

He kept his voice very casual as he said it.

‘Oh, yeah,’ Harry said. ‘That was the thing I was going to ask you about, actually –’

Draco’s blood froze in his veins, froze solid and shattered –

‘Professor Quirrell said something to me that got me thinking, and, well, no matter how you answer this question, I’m already stupid for having not asked you a lot earlier. Everyone in Gryffindor thinks Dumbledore is a saint, the Hufflepuffs think he’s crazy, the Ravenclaws are all proud of themselves for having worked out that he’s only pretending to be crazy, but I never asked anyone in Slytherin. I’m supposed to know better than to make that sort of mistake. But if even you think Dumbledore’s okay to conspire with on fixing Slytherin House, I guess I didn’t miss anything important.’

…

…

…

‘You know,’ Draco said, his voice remarkably calm, all things considered, ‘every time I wonder if you do things like this just to annoy me, I tell myself that it has to be accidental, no one could possibly do this sort of thing on purpose even if they tried until blood trickled out of their ears. That’s the only reason I’m not going to strangle you now.’

‘Huh?’

And then strangle himself, because Harry had grown up with Muggles, and then Dumbledore had smoothly diverted him from Slytherin to Ravenclaw, so it was perfectly plausible that Harry might not know anything, and Draco had never thought to tell him.

Or else Harry had guessed that Draco wouldn’t join up with Dumbledore so readily, and this itself was just the next step of Dumbledore’s plan …

But if Harry really didn’t know about Dumbledore, then warning him had to take precedence over everything.

‘All right,’ Draco said, after he’d had a chance to organize his thoughts. ‘I don’t know where to start, so I’ll just start somewhere.’ Draco drew a deep breath. This was going to take a while. ‘Dumbledore murdered his little sister, and got away with it because his brother wouldn’t testify against him –’

Harry listened with increasing worry and dismay. Harry had been prepared, he’d thought, to take the blood purist side of the story with a grain of salt. The trouble was that even after you added an enormous amount of salt, it still didn’t sound good.

Dumbledore’s father had been convicted of using Unforgivable Curses on children, and died in Azkaban. That was no sin of Dumbledore’s, but it would be a matter of public record. Harry could check that part, and see whether all of this had been made up out of thin air by the blood purists.

Dumbledore’s mother had died mysteriously, shortly before his younger sister died in what the Aurors had ruled to be murder. Supposedly that sister had been brutalized by Muggles and never spoken again after that; which, Draco pointed out, sounded remarkably like a botched Obliviation.

After Harry’s first few interruptions, Draco had seemed to pick up on the general principle, and was now presenting the observations first and the inferences afterwards.

‘– so you don’t have to take my word for it,’ said Draco, ‘you can see it, right? Anyone in Slytherin can. Dumbledore waited to fight his duel with Grindelwald until the exact moment when it would look best for Dumbledore, after Grindelwald had ruined most of Europe and built up a reputation as the most terrible Dark Wizard in history, and just when Grindelwald had lost the gold and blood sacrifices he was getting from his Muggle pawns and was about to start heading downhill. If Dumbledore was really the noble wizard he pretended to be, he’d have fought Grindelwald long before that. Dumbledore probably wanted Europe ruined, it was probably part of their plan together, he only attacked Grindelwald after his puppet failed him. And that big flashy duel wasn’t real, there’s no way two wizards would be so exactly matched that they’d fight for twenty whole hours until one of them fell over from exhaustion, that was just Dumbledore making it look more spectacular.’ Here Draco’s voice became more indignant. ‘And that got Dumbledore made Chief Warlock of the Wizengamot! The Line of Merlin Unbroken, corrupted after fifteen hundred years! And then he became Supreme Mugwump on top of that, and he already had Hogwarts to use as an invincible fortress – Headmaster and Chief Warlock and Supreme Mugwump, no normal person would try to do all that at once, how can anyone not see that Dumbledore’s trying to take over the world?’

‘Pause,’ Harry said, and closed his eyes to think.

It wasn’t any worse than what you would have heard about the West in Stalin’s Russia, and none of that would have been true. Though the blood purists wouldn’t be able to get away with making stuff up entirely … or would they? The Daily Prophet had shown a pronounced tendency to make stuff up … but then again, when they stuck out their neck too far on the Weasley betrothal, they had been called on it and they had been embarrassed …

Harry opened his eyes, and saw that Draco was watching him with a steady, waiting gaze.

‘So when you asked me if it was time to join up with Dumbledore, that was just a test.’

Draco nodded.

‘And before that, when you said it sounded right –’

‘It sounds right,’ said Draco. ‘But I don’t know if I can trust you. Are you going to complain about my testing you, Mr Potter? Are you going to say that I fooled you? That I led you on?’

Harry knew he should smile like a good sport, but he couldn’t really, it was too much of a disappointment.

‘You’re right, it’s fair, I can’t complain,’ Harry said instead. ‘So what about He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named? Not as bad as he was made out to be?’

Draco looked bitter, at that. ‘So you think it’s all just making Father’s side look good and Dumbledore’s side look bad, and that I believe it all myself just because Father told me.’

‘It’s a possibility I’m considering,’ Harry said evenly.

Draco’s voice was low and intense. ‘They knew. My father knew, his friends knew. They knew the Dark Lord was evil. But he was the only chance anyone had against Dumbledore! The only wizard anywhere who was powerful enough to fight him! Some of the other Death Eaters were truly evil too, like Bellatrix Black – Father isn’t like that – but Father and his friends had to do it, Harry, they had to, Dumbledore was taking over everything, the Dark Lord was the only hope anyone had left!’

Draco was staring hard at Harry. Harry met the gaze, trying to think. Nobody ever thought of themselves as the villain of their own story – maybe Lord Voldemort did, maybe Bellatrix did, but Draco certainly didn’t. That the Death Eaters were bad guys was not in question. The question was whether they were the bad guys; whether there was one villain in the story, or two …

‘You’re not convinced,’ Draco said. He looked worried, and a little angry. Which didn’t surprise Harry. He was pretty sure Draco himself believed all this.

‘Should I be convinced?’ Harry said. He didn’t look away. ‘Just because you believe it? Are you a strong enough rationalist now that your belief is strong evidence to me, because you’d be very unlikely to believe it if it weren’t true? When I met you, you weren’t that strong. Everything you told me, did you rethink it after you awakened as a scientist, or is it just something you grew up believing? Can you look me in the eyes and swear to me upon the honour of House Malfoy that if there’s one untruth buried in what you said, one thing that got added on just to make Dumbledore look a little worse, you would have noticed?’

Draco started to open his mouth, and Harry said, ‘Don’t. Don’t stain the honour of House Malfoy. You’re not that strong yet, and you should know it. Listen, Draco, I’ve started to notice some worrying things myself. But there’s nothing definite, nothing certain, it’s all just deductions and hypotheses and untrustworthy witnesses … And there’s nothing certain in your story, either. Dumbledore might’ve had some other good reason not to fight Grindelwald years earlier – though it would have to be a pretty good excuse, especially considering what was happening on the Muggle side of things … but still. Is there one clearly evil thing that Dumbledore’s done for certain, so I don’t have to wonder?’

Draco’s breathing was harsh. ‘All right,’ Draco said in an uneven voice, ‘I’ll tell you what Dumbledore did.’ From Draco’s robes came a wand, and Draco said ‘Quietus’, then ‘Quietus’ again, but he got the pronunciation wrong a second time, and finally Harry took out his own wand and did it.

‘There,’ said Draco hoarsely, ‘once upon a time there, there was a girl, and her name was Narcissa, and she was the prettiest, the smartest, the most cunning girl that was ever Sorted into Slytherin, and my father loved her, and they married, and she wasn’t a Death Eater, she wasn’t a fighter, all she ever did was love Father –’ Draco stopped there, because he was crying.

Harry felt sick to his stomach. Draco had never talked about his mother, not once, he should have noticed that earlier. ‘She … got in the way of a curse?’

Draco’s voice came out in a scream. ‘Dumbledore burned her to death in her own bedroom!’

In a classroom filled with soft silver light, one boy is staring at another boy, who is sobbing, wiping frantically at his eyes with the sleeves of his robes.

It was hard for Harry to stay balanced, to keep withholding judgement, it was too emotional, there was something that either wanted to start tears from his own eyes in sympathy with Draco, or know that it wasn’t true …

Dumbledore burned her to death in her own bedroom!

That …

… didn’t sound like Dumbledore’s style …

… but you could only think that thought so many times, before you started to wonder about the trustworthiness of that whole style concept.

‘It, it must have hurt horribly,’ Draco said, his voice shaking, ‘Father never talks about it at all, you don’t ever talk about it in front of him, but Mr Macnair told me, there were scorch marks all over the bedroom, from how Mother must have struggled while Dumbledore burned her alive. That is the debt Dumbledore owes to House Malfoy and we will have his life for it!’

‘Draco,’ Harry said, he let all of the hoarseness into his own voice, it would be wrong to sound calm, ‘I’m sorry, I’m so sorry for asking, but I have to know, how do you know it was Dumble–’

‘Dumbledore said he did it, he told Father it was a warning! And Father couldn’t testify under Veritaserum because he was an Occlumens, he couldn’t even get Dumbledore put on trial, Father’s own allies didn’t believe him after Dumbledore just denied everything in public, but we know, the Death Eaters know, Father wouldn’t have any reason to lie about that, Father would want us to take revenge on the right person, can’t you see that Harry?’ Draco’s voice was wild.

Unless Lucius did it himself, of course, and found it more convenient to blame Dumbledore.

Although … it also didn’t seem like Lucius’s style. And if he had murdered Narcissa, it would have been smarter to pin the blame on an easier victim instead of losing political capital and credibility by going after Dumbledore …

In time, Draco stopped crying, and looked at Harry. ‘Well?’ said Draco, sounding like he wanted to spit the words. ‘Is that evil enough for you, Mr Potter?’

Harry looked down at where his arms rested on the back of his chair. He couldn’t meet Draco’s eyes any more, the pain in them was too raw. ‘I wasn’t expecting to hear that,’ Harry said softly. ‘I don’t know what to think any more.’

‘You don’t know?’ Draco’s voice rose to a shriek, and he stood up abruptly from his desk –

‘I remembered the Dark Lord killing my parents,’ Harry said. ‘When I went in front of the Dementor the first time, that was what I remembered, the worst memory. Even though it was so long ago. I heard them dying. My mother begged the Dark Lord not to kill me, not Harry, please no, take me, kill me instead! That’s what she said. And the Dark Lord mocked her, and laughed. Then, I remember, the flash of green light –’

Harry looked up at Draco.

‘So we could fight,’ Harry said, ‘we could just keep on with the same fight. You could tell me that it was right for my mother to die, because she was the wife of James, who killed a Death Eater. But bad for your mother to die, because she was innocent. And I could tell you that it was right for your mother to die, that Dumbledore must have had some reason that made it okay to burn her alive in her own bedroom; but bad for my mother to die. But you know, Draco, either way, wouldn’t it be obvious that we were just being biased? Because the rule that says that it’s wrong to kill innocent people, that rule can’t switch on for my mother and off for yours, and it can’t switch on for your mother and off for mine. If you tell me that Lily was an enemy of the Death Eaters and it’s right to kill your enemies, then the same rule says that Dumbledore was right to kill Narcissa, since she was his enemy.’ Harry’s voice went hoarse. ‘So if the two of us are going to agree on anything, it’s going to be that neither of their deaths were right and that no one’s mother should die any more.’

The fury boiling inside Draco was so great that he could barely stop himself from storming out of the room; all that halted him was the recognition of a critical moment; and a small remnant of friendship, a tiny flash of sympathy, for he had forgotten, he’d forgotten, that Harry’s mother and father were dead by the Dark Lord’s hand.

The silence stretched.

‘You can talk,’ Harry said, ‘Draco, talk to me, I won’t get angry – are you thinking, I don’t know, that Narcissa dying was much worse than Lily dying? That it’s wrong for me even to make the comparison?’

‘I guess I was stupid too,’ Draco said. ‘All this time, all this time I forgot that you must hate the Death Eaters for killing your parents, hate Death Eaters the way I hate Dumbledore.’ And Harry had never said anything, never reacted when Draco talked about Death Eaters, kept it hidden – Draco was a fool.

‘No,’ Harry said. ‘It’s not – it’s not like that, Draco, I, I don’t even know how to explain to you, except to say that a thought like that, wouldn’t,’ Harry’s voice choked, ‘you wouldn’t ever be able to use it, to cast the Patronus Charm …’

Draco felt a sudden wrench in his heart, unwanted but he felt it. ‘Are you pretending you’re just going to forget about your own parents? Are you saying I should just forget about Mother?’

‘So you and I have to be enemies then?’ Now Harry’s voice was growing equally wild. ‘What have we ever done to each other that means we have to be enemies? I refuse to be trapped like that! Justice can’t mean that both of us should attack each other, it doesn’t make sense!’ Harry stopped, took a deep breath, ran his fingers back through the deliberate mess of his hair – the fingers came away sweaty, Draco could see it. ‘Draco, listen, we can’t expect to meet on everything right away, you and I. So I won’t ask you to say that the Dark Lord was wrong to kill my mother, just say that it was … sad. We won’t talk about whether or not it was necessary, whether it was justified. I’ll just ask you to say that it was sad that it happened, that my mother’s life was valuable too, you’ll just say that for now. And I’ll say it was sad that Narcissa died, because her life was also worth something. We can’t expect to agree on everything right away, but if we start out by saying that every life is precious, that it’s sad when anyone dies, then I know we’ll meet someday. That’s what I want you to say. Not who was right. Not who was wrong. Just that it was sad when your mother died, and sad when my mother died, and it would be sad if Hermione Granger died, every life is precious, can we agree on that and let the rest go by for now, is it enough if we just agree on that? Can we, Draco? That seems … more like a thought someone could use to cast the Patronus Charm.’

There were tears in Harry’s eyes.

And Draco was getting angry again. ‘Dumbledore killed Mother, it’s not enough to just say it’s sad! I don’t understand what you think you have to do, but the Malfoys have to take revenge!’ Not avenging the deaths of family went beyond weakness, beyond dishonour, you might as well not exist.

‘I’m not arguing with that,’ Harry said quietly. ‘But will you say that Lily Potter’s death was sad? Just say that one thing?’

‘That’s …’ Draco was having difficulty finding words again. ‘I know, I know how you feel, but don’t you see Harry, even if I just say that Lily Potter’s death was sad, that’s already going against the Death Eaters!’

‘Draco, you’ve got to be able to say the Death Eaters were wrong about some things! You have to, you can’t progress as a scientist otherwise, there’ll be a roadblock in your way, an authority you can’t contradict. Not every change is an improvement, but every improvement is a change, you can’t do anything better unless you can manage to do it differently, you’ve got to let yourself do better than other people! Even your father, Draco, even him. You’ve got to be able to point to something your father did and say it was mistaken, because he wasn’t perfect, and if you can’t say that, you can’t do better.’

Father had warned him, every night before he went to sleep for a month before he went to Hogwarts, that there would be people with this goal.

‘You’re trying to break me loose of Father.’

‘Trying to break a part of you loose,’ said Harry. ‘Trying to let you fix some things your father got mistaken. Trying to let you do better. But not … trying to break your Patronus!’ Harry’s voice got softer. ‘I wouldn’t want to break something bright like that. Who knows, fixing Slytherin House might need that, too …’

It was getting to Draco, that was the thing, despite everything it was getting to him, you had to be really careful around Harry because his arguments sounded so convincing even when he was wrong. ‘And what you’re not admitting is that Dumbledore told you that you could avenge your parents’ deaths by taking Lord Malfoy’s son from him –’

‘No. No. That part’s just wrong.’ Harry took a deep breath. ‘I did not know who Dumbledore was, or who the Dark Lord was, or who the Death Eaters were, or how my parents died, until three days before I came to Hogwarts. The day you and I first met in the clothes shop, that was the day I learned. And Dumbledore doesn’t even like Muggle science, or he says he doesn’t, I got a chance to probe him on it once. The thought of taking revenge on the Death Eaters through you has never crossed my mind, not even once until now. I didn’t know who the Malfoys were when I met you in the clothes shop, and then I liked you.’

There was a long silence.

‘I wish I could trust you,’ Draco said. His voice was shaking. ‘If I could just know you were telling the truth, everything would be so much simpler –’

And then suddenly it came to Draco.

The way to know whether Harry Potter really meant everything he said, about wanting to fix Slytherin House, about being sad that Mother had died.

It would be illegal, and since he’d have to do it without Father’s help, it would be dangerous, he couldn’t even trust Harry Potter to help, but …

‘All right,’ Draco said. ‘I’ve thought of a definitive experiment.’

‘What is it?’

‘I want to give you a drop of Veritaserum,’ Draco said. ‘Just one drop, so you can’t lie, but not enough to make you answer anything. I don’t know where I’ll get it, but I’ll make certain it’s safe –’

‘Um,’ Harry said. There was a helpless look on his face. ‘Draco, um –’

‘Don’t say it,’ Draco said. His voice was firm and calm. ‘If you say no, that’s my experimental result right there.’

‘Draco, I’m an Occlumens –’

‘Oh that is such a lie – ’

‘I was trained by Mr Bester. Professor Quirrell set it up. Look, Draco, I’ll take one drop of Veritaserum if you can get it, I’m just warning you that I’m an Occlumens. Not a perfect Occlumens, but Mr Bester said I was putting up a complete block, and I could probably beat Veritaserum.’

‘You’re in your first year at Hogwarts! That’s just crazy!’

‘Know a Legilimens you can trust? I’ll be happy to demonstrate – look, Draco, I’m sorry, but doesn’t the fact that I told you count for something? I could have just let you do it, you know.’

‘WHY? Why are you always like this, Harry? Why do you have to mess everything up even when it’s Impossible? And stop smiling, this isn’t funny!’

‘I’m sorry, I’m sorry, I know it’s not funny, I –’

It took a while for Draco to get himself under control.

But Harry was right. Harry could have just let Draco administer the Veritaserum. If he really was an Occlumens … Draco didn’t know who he could ask to try Legilimency, but he could at least ask Professor Quirrell if it was true … Could Draco trust Professor Quirrell? Maybe Professor Quirrell would just say anything Harry asked him to.

Then Draco remembered the other thing Harry had told him to ask Professor Quirrell, and thought of a different test.

‘You know,’ said Draco. ‘You know what it costs me, if I agree that the poison in Slytherin’s House is hating Muggleborns, and say that Lily Potter’s death was sad. And that’s part of your plan, don’t tell me it’s not.’

Harry said nothing, which was wise of him.

‘There’s something I want from you in return,’ said Draco. ‘And before then, an experimental test I want to try –’

Draco pushed open the door to which the portraits had directed them, and this time it was the right door. Before them was a small empty place of stone set against the night sky. Not a roof like the one he’d dropped Harry from, but a tiny and proper courtyard, far above the ground. With proper railings, elaborate traceries of stone that flushed seamlessly into the stone floor … How so much artistry had been infused into the creation of Hogwarts was something that still awed Draco every time he thought about it. There must have been some way to do it all at once, no one could have detailed so much piece by piece, the castle changed and every new piece was like that. It was so far beyond the wizardry of these fading days that no one would have believed it if they hadn’t seen the proof in Hogwarts itself.

Cloudless and cold, the winter night sky; it got dark long before students’ curfew, in the final days of January.

The stars shining brightly, in the clear air.

Harry had said that being under the stars would help him.

Draco touched his chest with his wand, slid his fingers in a practised motion, and said, ‘Thermos.’ A warmth spread through him, starting from his heart; the wind went on blowing on his face, but he was no longer cold.

‘Thermos,’ Harry’s voice said behind him.

They went together to the railing, to look down at the ground a long way below. Draco tried to figure if they were in one of the towers that could be seen from outside, and found that right now he couldn’t quite seem to picture how Hogwarts looked from outside. But the ground below was always the same; he could see the Forbidden Forest as a vague outline, and moonlight glittering from the Hogwarts Lake.

‘You know,’ Harry’s voice said quietly from beside him where his arms leaned on the railing next to Draco’s, ‘one of the things that Muggles get really wrong, is that they don’t turn all their lights out at night. Not even for one hour every month, not even for fifteen minutes once a year. The photons scatter in the atmosphere and wash out all but the brightest stars, and the night sky doesn’t look the same at all, not unless you go far away from any cities. Once you’ve looked up at the sky over Hogwarts, it’s hard to imagine living in a Muggle city, where you wouldn’t be able to see the stars. You certainly wouldn’t want to spend your whole life in Muggle cities, once you’d seen the night sky over Hogwarts.’

Draco glanced at Harry, and found that Harry was craning his neck to stare up at where the Milky Way arched across the darkness.

‘Of course,’ Harry went on, his voice still quiet, ‘you can’t ever see the stars properly from Earth, either, the air always gets in the way. You have to look from somewhere else, if you want to see the real thing, the stars burning hard and bright, like their true selves. Have you ever wished that you could just whisk yourself up into the night sky, Draco, and go and look at what there is to see around other Suns than ours? If there were no limit to the power of your magic, is that one of the things you would do, if you could do anything?’

There was a silence, and then Draco realized that he was expected to answer. ‘I didn’t think of it before,’ Draco said. Without any conscious decision, his voice came out as soft and hushed as Harry’s. ‘Do you really think anyone would ever be able to do that?’

‘I don’t think it’ll be that easy,’ said Harry. ‘But I know I don’t mean to spend my whole life on Earth.’

It would have been something to laugh at, if Draco hadn’t known that some Muggles had already left, without even using magic.

‘To pass your test,’ Harry said, ‘I’m going to have to say what it means to me, that thought, the whole thing, not the shorter version I tried to explain to you before. But you should be able to see it’s the same idea, only more general. So my version of the thought, Draco, is that when we go out into the stars, we might find other people there. And if so, they certainly won’t look like we do. There might be things out there that are grown from crystal, or big pulsating blobs … or they might be made of magic, now that I think about it. So with all that strangeness, how do you recognize a person? Not by the shape, not by how many arms or legs it has. Not by the sort of substance it’s made out of, whether that’s flesh or crystal or stuff I can’t imagine. You would have to recognize them as people from their minds. And even their minds wouldn’t work just like ours do. But anything that lives and thinks and knows itself and doesn’t want to die, it’s sad, Draco, it’s sad if that person has to die, because it doesn’t want to. Compared to what might be out there, every human being who ever lived, we’re all like brothers and sisters, you could hardly even tell us apart. The ones out there who met us, they wouldn’t see British or French, they wouldn’t be able to tell the difference, they’d just see a human being. Humans who can love, and hate, and laugh, and cry; and to them, the ones out there, that would make us all as alike as peas in the same pod. They would be different, though. Really different. But that wouldn’t stop us, and it wouldn’t stop them, if we both wanted to be friends together.’

Harry raised his wand then, and Draco turned, and looked away, as he had promised; looked toward the stone floor and stone wall in which the door was set. For Draco had promised not to look, and not to tell anyone of what Harry had said, or anything at all of what happened here this night, though he didn’t know why it was to be so secret.

‘I have a dream,’ said Harry’s voice, ‘that one day sentient beings will be judged by the patterns of their minds, and not their colour or their shape or the stuff they’re made of, or who their parents were. Because if we can get along with crystal things someday, how silly would it be not to get along with Muggleborns, who are shaped like us, and think like us, as alike to us as peas in a pod? The crystal things wouldn’t even be able to tell the difference. How impossible is it to imagine that the hatred poisoning Slytherin House would be worth taking with us to the stars? Every life is precious, everything that thinks and knows itself and doesn’t want to die. Lily Potter’s life was precious, and Narcissa Malfoy’s life was precious, even though it’s too late for them now, it was sad when they died. But there are other lives that are still alive to be fought for. Your life, and my life, and Hermione Granger’s life, all the lives of Earth, and all the lives beyond, to be defended and protected, expecto patronum!’

And there was light.

Everything turned to silver in that light, the stone floor, the stone wall, the door, the railings, so dazzling just in the reflection that you could hardly even see them, even the air seemed to shine, and the light grew brighter, and brighter, and brighter –

When the light ended it was like a shock, Draco’s hand went automatically to his robe to bring out a handkerchief, and it was only then that he realized he was crying.

‘There is your experimental result,’ Harry’s voice said quietly. ‘I really did mean it, that thought.’

Draco slowly turned toward Harry, who had lowered his wand now.

‘That, that’s got to be a trick, right?’ Draco said. He couldn’t take many more of these shocks. ‘Your Patronus – can’t really be that bright –’ And yet it had been Patronus light, once you knew what you were looking at, you couldn’t mistake it for anything else.

‘That was the true form of the Patronus Charm,’ Harry said. ‘Something that lets you put all your strength into the Patronus, without hindrance from within yourself. And before you ask, I did not learn it from Dumbledore. He does not know the secret, and could not cast the true form if he did. I solved the puzzle for myself. And I knew, once I understood, that this spell must not be spoken of. For your sake, I undertook your test; but you must not speak of it, Draco.’

Draco didn’t know any more, he didn’t know where the true strength lay, or the right of things. Double vision, double vision. Draco wanted to call Harry’s ideals weakness, Hufflepuff foolishness, the sort of lie that rulers told to placate the populace and that Harry had been silly enough to believe for himself, foolishness taken seriously and raised up to insane heights, projected out onto the stars themselves –

Something beautiful and hidden, mysterious and bright –

‘Will I,’ whispered Draco, ‘be able to cast a Patronus like that, someday?’

‘If you always keep seeking the truth,’ Harry said, ‘and if you don’t refuse the warm thoughts when you find them, then I’m sure you will. I think a person could get anywhere if they just kept going long enough, even to the stars.’

Draco wiped his eyes with his handkerchief again.

‘We should go back inside,’ Draco said in an unsteady voice, ‘someone could’ve seen it, all that light –’

Harry nodded, and moved to and through the door; and Draco looked up at the night sky one last time before he followed.

Who was the Boy-Who-Lived, that he was already an Occlumens, and could cast the true form of the Patronus Charm, and do other strange things? What was Harry’s Patronus, why must it stay unseen?

Draco didn’t ask any of those questions, because Harry might have answered, and Draco just couldn’t take any more shocks today. He just couldn’t. One more shock and his head was going to just fall right off his shoulders and go bounce, bounce, bounce down the corridors of Hogwarts.

They’d ducked into a small alcove, instead of going all the way back to the classroom, at Draco’s request; he was feeling too nervous to put it off any longer.

Draco put up a Quieting barrier, and then looked at Harry in silent question.

‘I’ve been thinking about it,’ Harry said. ‘I’ll do it, but there are five conditions –’

‘Five?’

‘Yes, five. Look, Draco, a pledge like this is just begging to go terribly wrong somehow, you know it would go wrong if this were a play –’

‘Well, it’s not!’ Draco said. ‘Dumbledore killed Mother. He’s evil. It’s one of those things you talk about that doesn’t have to be complicated.’

‘Draco,’ Harry said, his voice careful, ‘all I know is that you say that Lucius says that Dumbledore says he killed Narcissa. To believe that unquestioningly, I have to trust you and Lucius and Dumbledore. So like I said, there are conditions. The first one is that at any point you can release me from the pledge, if it no longer seems like a good idea. It has to be a deliberate and intended decision on your part, of course, not a trick of wording or something.’

‘Okay,’ said Draco. That sounded safe enough.

‘Condition two is that I’m pledging to take as an enemy whoever actually did kill Narcissa, as determined to the honest best of my ability as a rationalist. Whether that’s Dumbledore, or someone else. And you have my word that I’ll exercise my best ability as a rationalist to keep that judgement honest, as a question of simple fact. Agreed?’

‘I don’t like it,’ said Draco. He didn’t, the whole point was to make sure Harry never went with Dumbledore. Still, if Harry was honest, he’d catch on to Dumbledore soon enough; and if dishonest, he’d already broken his word … ‘But I’ll agree.’

‘Condition three is that Narcissa has to have been burned alive. If that part of the story turns out to be something exaggerated just to make it sound a little worse, then I get to decide for myself whether or not to still go through with the pledge. Good people sometimes have to kill. But they don’t ever torture people to death. It’s because Narcissa was burned alive that I know whoever did that was evil.’

Draco kept his temper, barely.

‘Condition four is that if Narcissa got her own hands dirty, and, say, Crucioed someone’s child into insanity, and that person burned Narcissa for revenge, the deal might be off again. Because then it was still wrong for them to burn her, they still should’ve just killed her without pain; but it wasn’t evil the same way as if she was just Lucius’s love who never did anything herself, like you said. Condition five is that if whoever killed Narcissa was tricked somehow into doing it, then my enemy is whoever tricked them, not the person who was tricked.’

‘All this really sounds like you’re planning to weasel out of it –’

‘Draco, I won’t take a good person as an enemy, not for you or anyone. I have to really believe they’re in the wrong. But I’ve thought about it, and it seems to me that if Narcissa didn’t do any evil with her own hands, just fell in love with Lucius and chose to stay his wife, then whoever burned her alive in her own bedroom isn’t likely to be good. And I’ll pledge to take as my enemy whoever made that happen, whether it’s Dumbledore or anyone else, unless you deliberately release me from that pledge. Hopefully that won’t go wrong the way it would if this were a play.’

‘I’m not happy,’ said Draco. ‘But okay. You pledge to take my mother’s murderer as your enemy, and I’ll –’

Harry waited, with a patient look on his face, while Draco tried to make his voice work again.

‘I’ll help you fix the problem with Slytherin House hating Muggleborns,’ Draco finished in a whisper. ‘And I’ll say it was sad that Lily Potter died.’

‘So be it,’ said Harry.

And it was done.

The break, Draco knew, had just widened a little more. No, not a little, a lot. There was a sensation of drifting away, of being lost, further and further from shore, further and further from home …

‘Excuse me,’ Draco said. He turned away from Harry, and then tried to calm himself, he had to do this test, and he didn’t want to fail it from being nervous or ashamed.

Draco raised his wand into the starting position for the Patronus Charm.

Remembered falling from his broomstick, the pain, the fear, imagined it coming from a tall figure in a cloak, looking like a dead thing left in water.

And then Draco closed his eyes, the better to remember Father holding his small, cold hands in his own warm strength.

Don’t be frightened, my son, I’m here …

The wand swung up in a broad brandish, to drive the fear away, and Draco was surprised at the strength of it; and he remembered in that moment that Father wasn’t lost, would never be lost, would always be there and strong in his own person, no matter what happened to Draco, and his voice cried, ‘Expecto Patronum!’

Draco opened his eyes.

A shining snake looked back at him, no less bright than before.

Behind him, he heard Harry exhale a breath, as though in relief.

Draco gazed into the white light. It seemed he wasn’t lost completely, after all.

‘That reminds me,’ said Harry after a while. ‘Can we test my hypothesis about how to use a Patronus to send messages?’

‘Is it going to surprise me?’ said Draco. ‘I don’t want any more surprises today.’

Harry had claimed that the idea wasn’t all that strange and he didn’t see how it could possibly shock Draco in any way, which made Draco feel even more nervous, somehow; but Draco could see how important it was to have a way of sending messages in emergencies.

The trick – or so Harry hypothesized – was wanting to spread the good news, wanting the recipient to know the truth of whatever happy thought you’d used to cast the Patronus Charm. Only instead of telling the recipient in words, the Patronus itself was the message. By wanting them to see that, the Patronus would go to them.

‘Tell Harry,’ said Draco to the luminous snake, even though Harry was standing only a few paces away on the other side of the room, ‘to, um, beware the green monkey,’ this being a sign from a play Draco had once seen.

And then, just like at King’s Cross station, Draco wanted Harry to know that Father had always cared for him; only this time he didn’t try to say it in words, but wanted to say it with the happy thought itself.

The bright snake slithered across the room, looking more like it was slithering through the air rather than the stone itself; it got to Harry after travelling that short distance –

– and said to Harry, in a strange voice that Draco recognized as how he himself probably sounded to other people, ‘Beware the green monkey.’

‘Hsssss ssss sshsshssss,’ said Harry.

The snake slithered back across the floor to Draco.

‘Harry says the message is received and acknowledged,’ said the shining Blue Krait in Draco’s voice.

‘Huh,’ Harry said. ‘Talking to Patronuses feels odd.’

…

…

…

…

‘Why are you looking at me like that?’ said the Heir of Slytherin.

Harry stared at Draco.

‘You mean just magical snakes, right?’

‘N-no,’ said Draco. He was looking rather pale, and was still stammering, but had at least stopped the incoherent noises he’d been making earlier. ‘You’re a Parselmouth, you can speak Parseltongue, it’s the language of all snakes everywhere. You can understand any snake when it talks, and they can understand when you talk to them … Harry, you can’t possibly believe you were Sorted into Ravenclaw! You’re the Heir of Slytherin!’

…

…

…

…

…

‘Snakes are sentient?’

Harry had only just sat down at the Ravenclaw table for the first time, hoping to grab a quick bite of food. He knew he needed to go off and think about things, but there was a tiny remaining bit of phoenix’s peace (even after the encounter with Draco) that he still wanted to cling to, some beautiful dream of which he remembered nothing but the beauty; and the part of him that wasn’t feeling peaceful was waiting for all the anvils to finish dropping on him, so that when he went off to think and be by himself for a while, he could batch-process all the disasters at once.

Harry’s hand grasped a fork, lifted a bite of mashed potatoes toward his mouth –

And there was a shriek.

Every now and then someone would shout when they heard the news, but Harry’s ears recognized this one –

Harry was up from the bench in an instant, heading toward the Hufflepuff table, a horrible sick feeling dawning in the pit of his stomach. It was one of those things he hadn’t considered when he’d decided to commit the crime, because Professor Quirrell had planned for no one to know; and now, afterwards, Harry just – hadn’t thought of it –

This, Hufflepuff said with bitter intensity, is also your fault.

But by the time Harry got there, Neville was sitting down and eating fried sausage patties with Snippyfig Sauce.

The Hufflepuff boy’s hands were trembling, but he cut the food, and ate it, without dropping it.

‘Hello, General,’ Neville said, his voice wavering only slightly. ‘Did you fight a duel with Bellatrix Black last night?’

‘No,’ Harry said. His own voice was also wavering, for some reason.

‘Didn’t think so,’ said Neville. There was a scraping sound as his knife cut the sausage again. ‘I’m going to hunt her down and kill her, can I count on you to help?’

There were startled gasps from the mass of Hufflepuffs who had gathered around Neville.

‘If she comes after you,’ Harry said hoarsely, if it was all a terrible mistake, if it was all a lie, ‘I’ll defend you even with my life,’ won’t let you get hurt for what I did, no matter what, ‘but I won’t help you go after her, Neville, friends don’t help friends commit suicide.’

Neville’s fork paused on the way to his mouth.

Then Neville put the bite of food in his mouth, chewed again.

And Neville swallowed it.

And Neville said, ‘I didn’t mean right now, I mean after I graduate Hogwarts.’

‘Neville,’ Harry said, keeping his voice under very careful control, ‘I think, even after you graduate, that might still be a just plain stupid idea. There’s got to be much more experienced Aurors tracking her –’ oh, wait, that’s not good –

‘Listen to him!’ said Ernie Macmillan, and then an older-looking Hufflepuff girl standing close to Neville said, ‘Nevvy, please, think about it, he’s right!’

Neville stood up.

Neville said, ‘Please don’t follow me.’

Neville walked away from all of them; Harry and Ernie reaching out involuntarily toward him, and some of the other Hufflepuffs as well.

And Neville sat down at the Gryffindor table, and distantly (though they had to strain to hear) they heard Neville say, ‘I’m going to hunt her down and kill her after I graduate, anyone want to help?’ and at least five voices said ‘Yes’ and then Ron Weasley said loudly, ‘Get in line, you lot, I got an owl from Mum this morning, she says to tell everyone she’s called dibs’ and someone said ‘Molly Weasley against Bellatrix Black? Who does she even think she’s kidding –’ and Ron reached over to a plate and hefted a muffin –

Someone tapped Harry on the shoulder, and he turned around and saw an unfamiliar green-trimmed older girl, who handed him a parchment envelope and then quickly strode away.

Harry stared at the envelope for a moment, then started walking toward the nearest wall. That wasn’t very private, but it should be private enough, and Harry didn’t want to give the impression of having much to hide.

That had been a Slytherin System delivery, what you used if you wanted to communicate with someone without anyone else knowing that the two of you had talked. The sender gave an envelope to someone who had a reputation for being a reliable messenger, along with ten Knuts; that first person would take five Knuts and pass the envelope to another messenger along with the other five Knuts, and the second messenger would open up that envelope and find another envelope with a name written on it and deliver that envelope to that person. That way neither of the two people passing the message knew both the sender and the recipient, so no one else knew that those two parties had been in contact …

When Harry reached the wall, he put the envelope inside his robes, opened it beneath the folds of cloth, and carefully sneaked a peek at the parchment he drew forth.

It said,

Classroom to the left of Transfiguration, 8 in the morning.

– LL.

Harry stared at it, trying to remember if he knew anyone with the initials LL.

His mind searched …

Searched …

Retrieved –

‘The Quibbler girl?’ Harry whispered incredulously, and then shut his mouth. She was only ten years old, she shouldn’t be in Hogwarts at all!

Harry was standing in the unused classroom next to Transfiguration at 8AM, waiting, he’d at least managed to get some food into himself before facing the next disaster, Luna Lovegood …

The door to the classroom opened, and Harry saw, and gave himself a really hard mental kick.

One more thing he hadn’t thought of, one more thing he really should have.

The older boy’s green-trimmed formal robes were askew, there were red spots on them looking very much like small dots of fresh blood, and one corner of his mouth had the look of a place that had been cut and healed, by Episkey or some other minor medical Charm that didn’t quite erase all the damage.

Lesath Lestrange’s face was streaked with tears, fresh tears and half-dried tears, and there was water in his eyes, a promise of still more on the way. ‘Quietus,’ said the older boy, and then ‘Hominem Revelio’ and some other things, while Harry thought frantically and without much luck.

And then Lesath lowered his wand and sheathed it in his robes, and slowly this time, formally, the older boy dropped to his knees on the dusty classroom floor.

Bowed his head all the way down, until his forehead also touched the dust, and Harry would have spoken but he was voiceless.

Lesath Lestrange said, in a breaking voice, ‘My life is yours, my Lord, and my death as well.’

‘I,’ Harry said, there was a huge lump in his throat and he was having trouble speaking, ‘I –’ didn’t have anything to do with it, he should have been saying, should be saying right now, but then again the innocent Harry would have had trouble speaking too –

‘Thank you,’ whispered Lesath, ‘thank you, my Lord, oh, thank you,’ the sound of a choked-off sob came from the kneeling boy, all Harry could see of him was the hair on the back of his head, nothing of his face. ‘I’m a fool, my Lord, an ungrateful bastard, unworthy to serve you, I cannot abase myself enough, for I – I shouted at you after you helped me, because I thought you were refusing me, and I didn’t even realize until this morning that I’d been such a fool as to ask you in front of Longbottom –’

‘I didn’t have anything to do with it,’ Harry said.

(It was still very hard to tell an outright lie like that.)

Slowly Lesath raised his head from the floor, looked up at Harry.

‘I understand, my Lord,’ said the older boy, his voice wavering a little, ‘you do not trust my cunning, and indeed I have shown myself a fool … I only wanted to say to you, that I am not ungrateful, that I know it must have been hard enough to save only one person, that they’re alerted now, that you can’t – get Father – but I am not ungrateful, I will never be ungrateful to you again. If ever you have a use for this unworthy servant, call me wherever I am, and I will answer, my Lord –’

‘I was not involved in any way.’

(But it got easier each time.)

Lesath gazed up at Harry, said uncertainly, ‘Am I dismissed from your presence, my Lord … ?’

‘I am not your Lord.’

Lesath said, ‘Yes, my Lord, I understand,’ and pushed himself back up from the floor, stood straight and bowed deeply, then backed away from Harry until he turned to open the classroom door.

As Lesath’s hand touched the doorknob, he paused.

Harry couldn’t see Lesath’s face, as the older boy’s voice said, ‘Did you send her to someone who would take care of her? Did she ask about me at all?’

And Harry said, his voice perfectly level, ‘Please stop that. I was not involved in any way.’

‘Yes, my Lord, I’m sorry, my Lord,’ said Lesath’s voice; and the Slytherin boy opened the door and went out and shut the door behind him. His feet sped up as he ran away, but not fast enough that Harry couldn’t hear him start sobbing.

Would I cry? wondered Harry. If I knew nothing, if I was innocent, would I cry right now?

Harry didn’t know, so he just kept looking at the door.

And some unbelievably tactless part of him thought, Yay, we completed a quest and got a minion –

Shut up. If you ever want to vote on anything ever again … shut up.

‘Then his life isn’t in danger, I take it,’ said Amelia.

The healer, a stern-eyed old man who wore his robes white (he was a Muggleborn and honouring some strange tradition of Muggles, of which Amelia had never asked, although privately she thought it made him look too much like a ghost), shook his head and said, ‘Definitely not.’

Amelia looked at the human form resting unconscious on the healer’s bed, the burned and blasted flesh, the thin sheet that covered him for modesty’s sake having been peeled back at her command.

He might make a full recovery.

He might not.

The healer had said it was too early to say.

Then Amelia looked at the other witch in the room, the detective.

‘And you say,’ Amelia said, ‘that the burning matter was Transfigured from water, presumably in the form of ice.’

The detective nodded her head, and said, sounding puzzled, ‘It could have been much worse, if not for –’

‘How very nice of them,’ she spat, and then pressed a weary hand to her forehead. No … no, it had been intended as a kindness. By the final stage of the escape there would be no point in trying to fool anyone. Whoever had done this, then, had been trying to mitigate the damage – and they’d been thinking in terms of Aurors breathing the smoke, not of anyone being attacked with the fire. If it had been them still in control, no doubt, they would have steered the rocker more mercifully.

But Bellatrix Black had ridden the rocker out of Azkaban alone, all the watching Aurors had agreed on that, they’d had their Anti-Disillusionment Charms active and there had been only one woman on that rocker, though the rocker had sported two sets of stirrups.

Some good and innocent person, capable of casting the Patronus Charm, had been tricked into rescuing Bellatrix Black.

Some innocent had fought Bahry One-Hand, carefully subduing an experienced Auror without significantly injuring him.

Some innocent had Transfigured the fuel for the Muggle artefact on which the two of them had been to ride out of Azkaban, making it from frozen water for the benefit of her Aurors.

And then their usefulness to Bellatrix Black had ended.

You would have expected anyone capable of subduing Bahry One-Hand to have foreseen that part. But then you wouldn’t have expected anyone who could cast the Patronus Charm to try rescuing Bellatrix Black in the first place.

Amelia passed her hand down over her eyes, closing them for a moment in silent mourning. I wonder who it was, and how You-Know-Who manipulated them … what story they could possibly have been told …

She didn’t even realize until a moment later that the thought meant she was starting to believe. Perhaps because, no matter how difficult it was to believe Dumbledore, it was becoming more difficult not to recognize the hand of that cold, dark intelligence.

It might have been only fifty-seven seconds before breakfast ended and he might have needed four twists of his Time-Turner, but in the end, Albus Dumbledore did make it.

‘Headmaster?’ squeaked the polite voice of Professor Filius Flitwick, as the old wizard passed him by on his way to his seat. ‘Mr Potter left a message for you.’

The old wizard stopped. He looked inquiringly at the Charms Professor.

‘Mr Potter said that after he woke up, he realized how unfair had been the things he said to you after Fawkes screamed. Mr Potter said that he wasn’t saying anything about anything else, just apologizing for that one part.’

The old wizard kept looking at his Charms Professor, and still did not speak.

‘Headmaster?’ squeaked Filius.

‘Tell him I said thank you,’ said Albus Dumbledore, ‘but that it is wiser to listen to phoenixes than to wise old wizards,’ and sat down at his place three seconds before all the food vanished.

‘No,’ Madam Pomfrey snapped at the child, ‘you may not see him! You may not pester him! You may not ask him one little question! He is to rest in bed and do nothing for at least three days!’

She was heading toward the infirmary, and Harry Potter was leaving it, when they passed each other.

The look he gave her wasn’t angry.

It wasn’t sad.

It didn’t say much at all.

It was like … like he was looking at her just long enough to make it clear that he wasn’t deliberately avoiding looking at her.

And then he looked away before she could figure out what look to give him in return; as though he wanted to spare her that, as well.

He didn’t say anything as he walked past her.

Neither did she.

What could there possibly be to say?

They actually yelped out loud, when they turned the corner and saw Dumbledore.

It wasn’t that the Headmaster had popped up out of nowhere and was staring at them with a stern expression. Dumbledore was always doing that.

But the wizard was dressed in formal black robes and looking very ancient and very powerful and he was giving the two of them a sharp look.

‘Fred and George Weasley!’ spake Dumbledore in a Voice of Power.

‘Yes, Headmaster!’ they said, snapping upright and giving him a crisp military salute they’d seen in some old pictures.

‘Hear me well! You are the friends of Harry Potter, is this so?’

‘Yes, Headmaster!’

‘Harry Potter is in danger. He must not go beyond the wards of Hogwarts. Listen to me, sons of Weasley, I beg you listen: you know that I am as Gryffindor as yourselves, that I too know there are higher rules than rules. But this, Fred and George, this one thing is of the most terrible importance, there must be no exception this time, small or great! If you help Harry to leave Hogwarts he may die! Does he send you on a mission, you may go, does he ask you to bring him items, you may help, but if he asks you to smuggle his own person out of Hogwarts, you must refuse! Do you understand?’

‘Yes, Headmaster!’ They said it without even thinking, really, and then exchanged uncertain looks with each other –

The bright blue eyes of the Headmaster were intent upon them. ‘No. Not without thinking. If Harry asks you to bring him out, you must refuse, if he asks you to tell him the way, you must refuse. I will not ask you to report him to me, for that I know you would never do. But beg him on my behalf to go to me, if it is of such importance, and I will guard him as he walks. Fred, George, I am sorry to strain your friendship so, but it is his life.’

The two of them looked at each other for a long while, not communicating, only thinking the same things at the same time.

They looked back at Dumbledore.

They said, with a chill running through them as they spoke the name, ‘Bellatrix Black.’

‘You may safely assume,’ said the Headmaster, ‘that it is at least that bad.’

‘Okay –’

‘- got it.’

When Alastor Moody had lost his eye, he had commandeered the services of a most erudite Ravenclaw, Samuel H. Lyall, whom Moody mistrusted slightly less than average because Moody had refrained from reporting him as an unregistered werewolf; and he had paid Lyall to compile a list of every known magical eye, and every known hint to their location.

When Moody had got the list back, he hadn’t bothered reading most of it; because at the top of the list was the Eye of Vance, dating back to an era before Hogwarts, and currently in the possession of a powerful Dark Wizard ruling over some tiny forgotten hellhole that wasn’t in Britain or anywhere else he’d have to worry about silly rules.

That was how Alastor Moody had lost his left foot and acquired the Eye of Vance, and how the oppressed souls of Urulat had been liberated for a period of around two weeks before another Dark Wizard moved in on the power vacuum.

He’d considered going after the Left Foot of Vance next, but had decided against it after he realized that would be just what they were expecting.

Now Mad-Eye Moody was turning slowly, always turning, surveying the graveyard of Little Hangleton. It should have been a lot gloomier, that place, but in the broad daylight it seemed like nothing but a grassy place marked by ordinary tombstones, demarcated by the chained twists of fragile, easily climbable metal that Muggles used instead of wards. (Moody could not comprehend what the Muggles were thinking on that score, if they were pretending to have wards, or what, and he had decided not to ask whether Muggle criminals respected the pretence.)

Moody didn’t actually need to turn to survey the graveyard.

The Eye of Vance saw the full globe of the world in every direction around him, no matter where it was pointing.

But there was no particular reason to let a former Death Eater like Severus Snape know that.

Sometimes people called Moody paranoid.

Moody always told them to survive a hundred years of hunting Dark Wizards and then get back to him about that.

Mad-Eye Moody had once worked out how long it had taken him, in retrospect, to achieve what he now considered a decent level of caution – weighed up how much experience it had taken him to get good instead of lucky – and had begun to suspect that most people died before they got there. Moody had once expressed this thought to Lyall, who had done some ciphering and figuring, and told him that a typical Dark Wizard hunter would die, on average, eight and a half times along the way to becoming paranoid. This explained a great deal, assuming Lyall wasn’t lying.

Yesterday, Albus Dumbledore had told Mad-Eye Moody that the Dark Lord had used unspeakable dark arts to survive the death of his body, and was now awake and abroad, seeking to regain his power and begin the Wizarding War anew.

Someone else might have reacted with incredulity.

‘I can’t believe you lot never told me about this resurrection thing,’ Mad-Eye Moody said with considerable acerbity. ‘D’you realize how long it’ll take me to do the grave of every ancestor of every Dark Wizard I’ve ever killed who could’ve been smart enough to make a horcrux? You’re not just now doing this one, are you?’

‘I re-dose this one every year,’ Severus Snape said calmly, uncapping the third flask of what the man had claimed would be seventeen bottles, and beginning to wave his wand over it. ‘The other ancestral graves we’ve been able to locate were poisoned with only the long-lasting substances, since some of us have less free time than yourself.’

Moody watched the fluid spiralling out of the vial and vanishing, to appear within the bones where marrow had once been. ‘But you think it’s worth the effort of the trap, instead of just Vanishing the bones.’

‘He does have other avenues to life, should he perceive this one blocked,’ Snape said dryly, uncapping a fourth bottle. ‘And before you ask, it must be the original grave, the place of first burial, the bone removed during the ritual and not before. Thus he cannot have retrieved it earlier; and also there is no point in substituting the skeleton of a weaker ancestor. He would notice it had lost all potency.’

‘Who else knows about this trap?’ Moody demanded.

‘You. Me. The Headmaster. No one else.’

Moody snorted. ‘Pfah. Did Albus tell Amelia, Bartemius, and that McGonagall woman about the resurrection ritual?’

‘Yes –’

‘If Voldie finds out that Albus knows about the resurrection ritual and that Albus told them, Voldie’ll figure that Albus told me, and Voldie knows I’d think of this.’ Moody shook his head in disgust. ‘What’re these other ways Voldie could come back to life?’

Snape’s hand paused on the fifth bottle (it was all Disillusioned, of course, the whole operation was Disillusioned, but that meant less than nothing to Moody, it just marked you in his Eye’s sight as trying-to-hide), and the former Death Eater said, ‘You don’t need to know.’

‘You’re learning, son,’ said Moody with mild approval. ‘What’s in the bottles?’

Snape opened the fifth bottle, gestured with his wand to begin the substance flowing toward the grave, and said, ‘This one? A Muggle narcotic called LSD. A conversation yesterday put me in mind of Muggle things, and LSD seemed the most interesting option, so I hurried to obtain some. If it is incorporated into the resurrection potion, I suspect its effects will be permanent.’

‘What does it do?’ said Moody.

‘It is said that the effects are impossible to describe to anyone who has not used it,’ drawled Snape, ‘and I have not used it.’

Moody nodded approval as Snape opened the sixth flask. ‘What about that one?’

‘Love potion.’

‘Love potion?’ said Moody.

‘Not of the standard sort. It is meant to trigger a two-way bond with an unbearably sweet Veela woman named Verdandi who the Headmaster hopes might be able to redeem even him, if they truly loved each other.’

‘Gah!’ said Moody. ‘That bloody sentimental fool –’

‘Agreed,’ Severus Snape said calmly, his attention focused on his work.

‘Tell me you’ve at least got some Malaclaw venom in there.’

‘Second flask.’

‘Iocane powder.’

‘Either the fourteenth or fifteenth bottle.’

‘Bahl’s Stupefaction,’ Moody said, naming an extremely addictive narcotic with interesting side effects on people with Slytherin tendencies; Moody had once seen an addicted Dark Wizard go to ridiculous lengths to get a victim to lay hands on a certain exact portkey, instead of just having someone toss the target a trapped Knut on their next visit to town; and after going to all that work, the addict had gone to the further effort to lay a second Portus, on the same portkey, which had, on a second touch, transported the victim back to safety. To this day, even taking the drug into account, Moody could not imagine what could have possibly been going through the man’s mind at the time he had cast the second Portus.

‘Tenth vial,’ said Snape.

‘Basilisk venom,’ offered Moody.

‘What?’ spat Snape. ‘Snake venom is a positive component of the resurrection potion! Not to mention that it would dissolve the bone and all the other substances! And where would we even get –’

‘Calm down, son, I was just checking to see if you could be trusted.’

Mad-Eye Moody continued his (secretly unnecessary) slow turning, surveying the graveyard, and the Potions Master continued pouring.

‘Hold on,’ Moody said suddenly. ‘How do you know this is really where –’

‘Because it says “Tom Riddle” on the easily moved headstone,’ Snape said dryly. ‘And I have just won ten Sickles from the Headmaster, who bet you would think of that before the fifth bottle. So much for constant vigilance.’

There was a pause.

‘How long did it take Albus to reali–’

‘Three years after we learned of the ritual,’ said Snape, in a tone not quite like his usual sardonic drawl. ‘In retrospect, we should have consulted you earlier.’

Snape uncapped the ninth bottle.

‘We poisoned all the other graves as well, with long-lasting substances,’ remarked the former Death Eater. ‘It is possible that we are in the correct graveyard. He may not have planned this far ahead back when he was slaughtering his family, and he cannot move the grave itself –’

‘The true location doesn’t look like a graveyard any more,’ Moody said flatly. ‘He moved all the other graves here and Memory-Charmed the Muggles. Not even Bellatrix Black would be told anything about that until just before the ritual started. No one knows the true location now except him.’

They continued their futile work.

Plausible Deniability

The winter Sun had well set by the time dinner ended, and so it was amid the peaceful light of stars twinkling down from the enchanted ceiling of the Great Hall that Hermione left for the Ravenclaw Tower alongside her study partner Harry Potter, who lately seemed to have a ridiculous amount of time for studying. She hadn’t the faintest idea of when Harry was doing his actual homework, except that it was getting done, maybe by house elves while he slept.

Nearly every single pair of eyes in the whole Hall lay on them as they passed through the mighty doors of the dining-room, which were more like siege gates of a castle than anything students ought to go through on the way back from supper.

They went out without speaking, and walked until the distant babble of student conversation had faded into silence; and then the two of them went on a little further through the stone corridors before Hermione finally spoke.

‘Why’d you do that, Harry?’

‘Do what?’ said the Boy-Who-Lived in an abstracted tone, as if his mind were quite elsewhere, thinking about vastly more important things.

‘I mean, why didn’t you just tell them no?’

‘Well,’ Harry said, as their shoes pattered across the tiles, ‘I can’t just go around saying “no” every time someone asks me about something I haven’t done. I mean, suppose someone asks me, “Harry, did you pull the prank with the invisible paint?” and I say “No” and then they say “Harry, do you know who messed with the Gryffindor Seeker’s broomstick?” and I say “I refuse to answer that question.” It’s sort of a giveaway.’

‘And that’s why,’ Hermione said carefully, ‘you told everyone …’ She concentrated, remembering the exact words. ‘That if hypothetically there was a conspiracy, you could not confirm or deny that the true master of the conspiracy was Salazar Slytherin’s ghost, and in fact you wouldn’t even be able to admit the conspiracy existed so people ought to stop asking you questions about it.’

‘Yep,’ said Harry Potter, smiling slightly. ‘That’ll teach them to take hypothetical scenarios too seriously.’

‘And you told me not to answer anything –’

‘They might not believe you, if you deny it,’ said Harry. ‘So it’s better to say nothing, unless you want them to think you’re a liar.’

‘But –’ Hermione said helplessly. ‘But – but now people think I’m doing things for Salazar Slytherin!’ The way the Gryffindors had been looking at her – the way the Slytherins had been looking at her –

‘It goes along with being a hero,’ Harry said. ‘Have you seen what the Quibbler says about me?’

For a brief second Hermione imagined her parents reading a newspaper article about her, and instead of the story being about her winning a nationwide spelling bee or any of the other ways she’d imagined getting into the papers, the headline said ‘Hermione Granger gets Draco Malfoy pregnant’.

It was enough to make you think twice about the whole heroine business.

Harry’s voice turned a bit more formal. ‘Speaking of which, Miss Granger, how goes your latest quest?’

‘Well,’ said Hermione, ‘unless the ghost of Salazar Slytherin really does show up and tell us where to find bullies, I don’t think we’re going to have much luck.’ Not that she was sorry about that.

She glanced over at Harry, and saw the boy giving her a peculiarly intense look.

‘You know, Hermione,’ the boy said quietly, as though to make sure that nobody else in the world heard, ‘I think you’re right. I think some people get a lot more help than others in becoming heroes. And I don’t think that’s fair, either.’

And Harry grabbed at her witch’s robes where they lay over her arm, and hustled her into a side-hall of the corridor they were walking through, her mouth gaping open in surprise even as Harry’s wand came into his hand, they rounded a curve of the side-hall and it was so narrow that it was almost pushing her and Harry into each other, even as Harry pointed to the way they’d come and softly said ‘Quietus’, then a moment later, in the other direction, ‘Quietus’ again.

The boy looked searchingly around them, not just to every side, but even upward toward the ceiling and down toward the floor.

And then Harry stuck a hand in his pouch and said, ‘Invisibility cloak.’

‘Gleep?’ said Hermione.

Harry was already drawing out folds of shimmering black fabric from the mokeskin device. ‘Don’t worry,’ the boy said with a small grin, ‘they’re so rare that nobody bothered to make a school rule against them …’

And then Harry held out the dark velvet mesh to her, and said, his voice strangely formal, ‘I do not give you, but loan you, my cloak, unto Hermione Jean Granger. Protect her well.’

She stared at the shimmering velvet of the cloak, cloth that swallowed all the light that fell on it except what glinted from small strange reflections, fabric so perfectly black it should’ve shown dust or lint or something but it didn’t, the longer you looked the more you felt like what you were seeing wasn’t really there at all, but then you blinked again and it was just a black cloak.

‘Take it, Hermione.’

Hardly even thinking, Hermione stretched out her hand to grasp the fabric; and then just as her brain woke up and she started to pull her hand back, Harry let go of the cloak and it started to fall and she grabbed at it without thinking. And the instant her fingers touched and held the cloak she felt an intangible jolt run through her like picking up her wand for the first time; and it was like she heard a song being sung, ever so faintly, in the back of her mind.

‘That’s one of my quest items, Hermione,’ Harry said softly. ‘It belonged to my father, and it’s not something I can replace, if it’s lost. Don’t loan it to anyone else, don’t show it to anyone, don’t tell anyone it exists … but if you want to borrow it for a while, just come to me and ask.’

Hermione finally tore her eyes loose from the depthless black folds and stared back up at Harry.

‘I can’t –’

‘You certainly can,’ Harry said. ‘Because there’s nothing even the tiniest bit fair about my finding this gift-wrapped in a box next to my bed one morning, and you … not.’ Harry paused thoughtfully. ‘Unless you did get your own invisibility cloak, in which case never mind.’

Then the implications of invisibility cloak finally dawned on her, and she pointed a shocked finger at Harry, though they were close enough together that she couldn’t quite straighten her arm properly, and her voice rose with considerable indignation as she said, ‘So that’s how you disappeared from the Potions closet! And the time when –’ and then she trailed off, because even with an invisibility cloak she still couldn’t see how Harry had …

Harry buffed his fingernails on his robes with artful nonchalance, and said, ‘Well, you knew there had to be some trick to it, right? And now the heroine will mysteriously know where and when to find bullies – just like she listened to the bullies planning it, even though nobody her age could possibly have turned herself invisible to spy on them.’

There was a pause and a silence.

‘Harry –’ she said. ‘I’m – I’m not sure any more that fighting bullies is such a good idea.’

Harry’s eyes stayed steady on hers. ‘Because the other girls might get hurt?’

She nodded, just nodded.

‘That’s their choice, Hermione, just like it’s yours. I decided not to do the obvious stupid thing that everyone does in books, try to keep you safe and protected and helpless, and have you get really angry at me, and push me away while you go off on your own and get into even more trouble, and then heroically pull through it successfully, after which I’d finally have my epiphany and realize that blah blah blah etcetera. I know how that part of my life story goes, so I’m just skipping over it. If I can predict what I’m going to think later, I might as well go ahead and think it now. Anyway, my point is, you shouldn’t smother your friends to keep them safe, either. Just tell them up front it’s predictably going to go horribly wrong, and if they still want to be heroines after that, fine.’

It was at times like this that Hermione wondered if she was ever going to get used to the way Harry thought. ‘Harry, I really,’ her voice stuck for a second, ‘really, really don’t want them getting hurt! Especially because of something I started!’

‘Hermione,’ Harry said seriously, ‘I’m pretty sure you did the right thing. I don’t see what could realistically happen to them that would be worse for them, in the long run, than not trying.’

‘What if they get badly hurt?’ Hermione said. Her voice felt blocked in her throat; she remembered Captain Ernie saying how Harry had just stared straight into the eyes of a bully as the bully bent his finger back, before Professor Sprout had arrived to save him; and there was another thought that came after that, about Hannah and her delicate hands with the fingernails that she carefully painted in Hufflepuff yellow every morning, but that wasn’t allowed to be imagined. ‘And then – they’ll never do anything courageous, ever again –’

‘I don’t think it works like that,’ Harry said steadily. ‘Even if it all goes mind-bogglingly wrong, I don’t think it works like that inside a human mind. The important thing is believing about yourself that you’re someone who can break your boundaries. Trying and getting hurt can’t possibly be worse for you than being … stuck.’

‘What if you’re wrong, Harry?’

Harry paused for a moment, and then shrugged a little sadly, and said, ‘What if I’m right?’

Hermione looked back at the black mesh running over her hand. From the inside the cloak felt strangely soft and yet firm against her palm, as if it was trying to give her hand a reassuring hug.

Then she lifted her arm back up, holding the cloak back to Harry.

Harry didn’t move to take it.

‘I –’ said Hermione. ‘I mean, thank you, thank you a lot, but I’m still thinking about it, so you can take it back for now. And … Harry, I don’t think it’s right to spy on people –’

‘Not even on known bullies, to rescue their victims?’ Harry said. ‘I’ve never been bullied, but I’ve been through a realistic simulation, and it didn’t feel very pleasant. Have you ever been bullied, Hermione?’

‘No,’ she said in a quiet voice, and went on holding out Harry’s invisibility cloak to him.

Finally Harry took back his cloak – she felt a small twitch of loss as the inaudible song vanished from the back of her mind – and started to stuff the black material back into his pouch.

As the pouch ate the last of the fabric, Harry turned from her, to break the Quieting Barrier –

‘And, um,’ Hermione said. ‘That’s not the Cloak of Invisibility, is it? The one we read about in the library on page eighteen of Paula Vieira’s translation of Gottschalk’s An Illustrated Scroll of Lost Devices?’

Harry turned his head back, grinning slightly, and said in exactly the same tone of voice he’d used earlier with the other students at dinner, ‘I cannot confirm or deny that I possess magical artifacts of incredible power.’

When Hermione climbed into bed that night she was still trying to decide. Her life had been simpler at dinnertime, back when there hadn’t been any practical way for them to find bullies; and now she had to choose again; not for herself, this time, but for her friends. In her mind’s eye she kept seeing Dumbledore’s lined face and the pain it hadn’t quite hidden, and in her mind’s ears she kept hearing Harry’s voice saying That’s their choice, Hermione, just like it’s yours.

And her hand kept remembering the sensation of the cloak against her fingers, replaying it over and over in her mind. There was a power to the feeling that compelled her thoughts to return to it, and to the song she’d heard / hadn’t heard in a part of her mind and magic which now lay silent once more.

Harry had spoken to the cloak like it was a person, telling it to take good care of her. Harry had said the cloak had belonged to his father, that he couldn’t replace it if it was lost …

But … Harry wouldn’t really do that, would he?

Just hand her one of the three Deathly Hallows created centuries before Hogwarts?

She could say that she felt flattered, but this went way beyond feeling flattered, into making her wonder just what she was to Harry, exactly.

Maybe Harry was the sort of person who went around loaning ancient lost magical artifacts to anyone he considered a friend, but –

But when she thought about which part of his life Harry had said he’d skipped over, the part where he tried to keep her safe and protected …

Hermione stared up at the ceiling of the Ravenclaw dorm. Somewhere beyond her bed, Mandy and Su were talking. She’d turned up her Quieting Charm to where she couldn’t hear the exact words, but could still hear their faint murmur; there was something comforting about sleeping in a dorm with the other girls. Harry kept his own Quieter turned up all the way, she knew.

She was starting to wonder if maybe Harry actually did, well …

You know …

Like her.

It took Hermione Granger a long time to fall asleep that night.

And when she woke up the next morning there was a small slip of parchment peeking out from under her pillow which said At half-past ten you will find a bully in the fourth passageway to the left of the hall leaving the Potions classroom – S.

When Hermione entered the Great Hall that morning, her stomach was filled with flying butterflies the size of Hippogriffs; even as she approached the Ravenclaw breakfast table she still hadn’t decided what to do.

There was an empty place next to Padma, she saw. That would be where to sit down, if she was going to tell Padma and then ask Padma to tell Daphne and Tracey.

Hermione walked toward the empty place next to Padma.

There were words waiting in her throat, Padma, I got a mysterious message –

And she could feel a huge brick wall inside her, stopping the words from coming out. She’d be putting Hannah and Susan and Daphne in danger. Taking them and leading them by the hand straight into trouble. That was Wrong.

Or she could just go try to handle the bully herself, without telling her friends anything, and that, quite obviously, was also Wrong.

Hermione knew she was being faced with a Moral Dilemma, just like all those wizards and witches she’d read about in stories. Only in stories people always got a right choice and a wrong choice, not two wrong ones, which seemed a bit unfair. But she had the sense, somehow – maybe it came from the way Harry always talked about how the history books would see them – that she was faced with a Heroic Decision, and that her whole life might end up going one way or another, depending on what she chose right now, this morning.

Hermione sat down at the table without looking to either side, just gazing at the plate and silverware like they might have answers hidden inside, thinking as hard as she ever had, and a few seconds later she heard Padma’s voice whispering almost in her ear, ‘Daphne says she knows where a bully’s going to be at ten-thirty today.’

Doomed.

They were all doomed, in Susan Bones’s opinion.

Auntie sometimes told stories which started out like this, people doing something they knew was stupid, and the stories usually ended with someone being doomed all over the floor and all over the walls and getting on Auntie’s shoes.

‘Hey, Padma,’ muttered Parvati, her voice just barely audible over the soft impacts of eight girls tiptoeing through the corridor leading to the Potions classroom, ‘d’you know why Hermione’s been sighing all morning –’

‘No talking!’ hissed Lavender, the harsh whisper sounding much louder than Parvati’s mutter. ‘You never know when Evil might be listening!’

‘Shhh!’ said three other girls even more loudly.

Utterly, totally, quite extremely doomed.

As they approached the fourth passageway to the left of the Potions classroom, where Daphne’s mysterious informant had said the bullying would take place, the eight of them moved slower, the sound of their feet got softer, and finally General Granger made the gesture that meant Halt, I’ll look ahead.

Lavender raised a hand, then, and when Hermione turned to look at her, Lavender, looking puzzled, pointed straight down the corridor, gestured to herself, and then tried to sign something else that Susan didn’t understand –

General Granger shook her head, and once again, this time with slower, more exaggerated movements, made the sign for Halt, I’ll look ahead.

Lavender, looking even more puzzled, pointed back the way they’d come, and made a bouncing gesture with her other hand.

Now everyone else was looking even more confused than Lavender, and Susan thought with some acerbity that evidently one hour of practise done two days ago wasn’t enough to remember a new set of code signals.

Hermione pointed at Lavender, then at the floor beneath Lavender’s feet, the expression on her face making it very clear that the intended meaning was You. Stay. Here.

Lavender nodded.

Doom doom doom, went the words of the Chaos Legion’s marching song through Susan’s mind, doom doom doom doom doom doom …

Hermione reached into her robes, and drew out a little rod with a mirror on the end of it and an eyepiece. Very very softly indeed, the Ravenclaw girl crept up to the wall, right next to where the passageway opened off the corridor, and peeked just the tip of the eyepiece around the corner.

Then a little more.

Then a little more.

Then General Granger cautiously stuck her head around the side.

General Granger turned back to them, nodded, and made the hand gesture for follow me.

Susan felt a little better as she crept forward. The part of the Plan which called for them to arrive thirty minutes before the bully had, apparently, actually worked. Maybe they were only slightly doomed … ?

At ten-twenty-nine, almost on the dot, the bully showed up. If anyone had been present to hear – though the corridor was apparently empty – they would have heard his shoes clicking solidly through the main corridor, entering the passageway, walking toward where the passageway turned its first corner, turning that corner, and then stopping in some surprise upon seeing that the passageway now terminated in a solid brick wall where no wall had been before.

Then the bully shrugged and turned away, as he leaned back to watch the main passage from just around the corner.

It was the castle Hogwarts, after all.

Behind the hastily Transfigured thin panels they’d assembled into the outward appearance of a brick wall, the girls waited; not speaking, not moving, hardly even breathing, but watching through the eyeholes they’d left themselves.

As Susan’s gaze took in the bully, she could feel the tightening of her chest all the way into her toes. The boy looked to be in his seventh-year if not older, and his robes were trimmed in green instead of the red they’d been hoping for, and he had muscles, and after staring for a bit longer, Susan realized his stance had the balance that meant that he duelled.

Then they all heard the sound of more feet approaching from the corridor. The fourth-year Gryffindors and Slytherins had just been let out of Potions class.

The footsteps pattered past, and diminished and faded, and the bully didn’t do anything. For a moment Susan felt an instant of relief –

Then another, smaller group of footsteps approached.

The bully still didn’t do anything, as the footsteps went past.

That happened a few more times.

And then, as there approached the faintly audible sound of one last set of footsteps, the seven girls heard the bully’s voice saying, clear and cold and quiet, ‘Protego’.

Someone did gasp then, though fortunately very very quietly. If they couldn’t get in even a single shot –

The bullies were learning already, Susan realized, she hadn’t expected S.P.H.E.W. to be able to do this very often before the bullies caught on – but – Hermione had already defeated three bullies – and the school had been buzzing with speculation about Salazar Slytherin’s ghost, yesterday –

He’s expecting us!

Susan would have whispered to give up, to abort the plan, only there was no way to convey a message to –

‘Silencio,’ said the bully in a soft, deliberate voice with his wand pointed toward the corridor, the blue haze of his Shielding Charm shimmering around him. ‘Accio victim.’

When the fourth-year boy came into their field of vision he was dangling upside down as if an invisible hand were holding him high by one leg, his red-trimmed robes beginning to slide down his thighs to reveal the trousers beneath. His mouth was opening and closing helplessly, no sound coming out.

‘I suppose you’re wondering what’s going on,’ the seventh-year Slytherin said in a quiet, cold voice. ‘Don’t worry. It’s so simple even a Gryffindor could understand.’

With that, the Slytherin’s left hand formed a fist and drove hard into the Gryffindor’s belly. The fourth-year boy’s body jerked around frantically, but still no words left his mouth.

‘You’re my victim,’ said the older Slytherin. ‘I’m a bully. I’m going to beat you up. And we’ll see if anyone stops me.’

It was at that moment that Susan realized it was a trap.

And in almost the same moment, there rang out the mighty and high-pitched voice of a young girl, crying, ‘Stop, evildoer! Finite Incantatem!’

Lavender, thought Susan, agonized. The Gryffindor girl had volunteered to be a distraction, while the rest of them executed a flank attack from where the bully wouldn’t expect it, that had been the plan, only now –

‘In the name of Hogwarts,’ cried Lavender’s voice, though they couldn’t see her, ‘and in the name of heroines everywhere, I command you to let go of that Eek!’

‘Expelliarmus,’ said the bully. ‘Stupefy. Accio stupid heroine.’

When Lavender floated into their vision, dangling by one foot and unconscious, Susan blinked; the girl was dressed in a bright crimson-and-gold skirt and blouse, instead of her usual Hogwarts robes.

The bully was also giving the girl’s upside-down body an odd look, and then he pointed his wand at her and said ‘Finite Incantatem,’ but the clothes stayed the same.

Then the bully shrugged, and, still facing in the direction of Lavender instead of the dangling fourth-year boy, drew back his fist –

‘Lagann!’ yelled five voices, and five green spirals blasted from five wands aimed through five holes in the false wall, and an instant later Hermione’s voice shouted ‘Stupefy!’

Five green spirals shattered ineffectually on blue haze, and Hermione’s red bolt bounced off the haze and struck the fourth-year boy, who jerked and then was still.

And the seventh-year bully turned around, smiling grimly, as the first-year girls screamed and charged.

Susan’s eyes flew open and instantly she was rolling away from where she’d lain on the floor, her lungs still on fire and her whole body still aching from when she’d been hit, the battle had only moved forward a few seconds from what she could see, Hannah’s body falling with her arm still stretched out toward Susan, ‘Glisseo!’ shouted Hermione but the older boy just slashed his wand down leaving a trail of green glow behind and Hermione’s Charm visibly disrupted into a shower of blue-white sparks, then in almost the same motion the bully said ‘Stupefy!’ and Hermione was blown backward and Susan summoned up all the magic she had left and shouted ‘Innervate!’ at Hermione’s body even as the bully turned toward her, the bully’s wand pointed in her direction again and then Padma yelled ‘Prismatis!’ just before the bully shouted ‘Impedimenta!’, the rainbow sphere forming around the bully and the seventh-year Slytherin staggered as his own hex was reflected back at him, but an instant later the bully’s wand swept back to tap himself and then Padma’s Prismatic Sphere shattered like a blown soap bubble as the bully’s wand cut through it and ‘Innervate!’ yelled Parvati at Hannah’s body and Tracey and Lavender screamed at the same time, ‘Wingardium Leviosa!’ –

Hannah Abbott held out her wand with a hand that trembled with exhaustion, she didn’t have enough magic left for even one Innervate, now.

The rest of the passageway was silent, scattered bodies lying across the ground, Padma and Tracey and Lavender, Hermione and Parvati in a heap against one wall, Susan standing in petrified rigor as her eyes tracked it all helplessly, even the Gryffindor boy lying sprawled and motionless (Hermione had woken him and he’d fought, but it hadn’t been enough).

It had been a very short battle.

The bully was still smiling, the only signs of his exertion a wavering ripple in the blue glow surrounding him, and a few beads of sweat on his forehead.

The bully raised his arm, wiped the sweat off his forehead, and stalked toward her like a man-shaped living Lethifold.

Hannah turned and fled, spun and ran with screams kept bound in her choking throat, sprinted past the fallen panelling of the fake brick wall, ran down the passageway with all the speed she could muster, weaving as much as she could –

Just before Hannah got to the turn in the passageway, the bully’s voice from behind her said ‘Cluthe!’ and she got awful cramps all through her legs, she fell down and slid and hit her head against the wall, only she didn’t even notice the pain of the smack as she started to scream with the twisting muscles –

The bully was still stalking toward her, Hannah saw as she turned her head; approaching her slowly, still wearing that dreadful smile.

And she rolled, despite the pain as her leg muscles knotted up around themselves, she rolled around the corner of the passageway, and screamed, ‘Go away!’

‘I think not,’ said the bully, his voice deep and scary like that of a grown man, sounding very close at hand now.

The bully walked around the corner and Daphne Greengrass stabbed her Most Ancient Blade directly into his groin.

There was a flash that lit up the whole corridor –

It was with a subdued mien that seven girls left Madam Pomfrey’s office, leaving one of their own behind in a hospital bed.

Hannah would be all right in about thirty-five minutes, the healer had said; torn muscles were easy to mend.

Daphne had done all the talking, and according to her, Hannah had suffered a mishap with a Road-Running Charm which had caused the leg cramps. Madam Pomfrey had given them a sharp look but hadn’t argued, even though that Charm was around six years above their level.

Madam Pomfrey had also given Daphne a potion to help with her state of total magical exhaustion, and warned her not to cast any spells for the next three hours. That, supposedly, was from Daphne using up too much magic trying to Finite Hannah, rather than the Most Ancient Blade drawing out all of her power to break the Protego.

The rest of them had decided not to say anything about the bruises under their robes until they could get some older girls to cast Episkey. There were limits to what Daphne could talk around.

The whole thing, Susan thought, had been too close, much too close. If the bully had so much as looked around the corner – if he’d taken a moment to recast his Shielding Charm –

‘We should stop,’ said Susan, as soon as the seven of them were out of hearing range of the healer’s office. ‘We should stop doing this.’

For some reason, then, even though they were supposed to vote on this sort of thing, everyone turned to look at General Granger.

The Sunshine General didn’t seem to see them looking at her, she just strode on, gazing off straight ahead.

After a little while, Hermione Granger said, in a voice that sounded thoughtful and a little sad, ‘Hannah said she didn’t want us to stop. I’m not sure it’s right for us to … be less brave for her, than she is.’

All the other girls, except Susan, nodded at that.

‘I think that’s got to be as bad as it gets,’ said Parvati. ‘And we can handle it. We’ve proved that now.’

Susan couldn’t think of anything to say to that. She didn’t think that shrieking at the top of her lungs about blatant stupidity and doom would be persuasive. And she couldn’t just leave the other girls, either. Wasn’t it enough to be cursed with hard work, why did Hufflepuffs have to be loyal on top of everything else?

‘By the way, Lavender,’ said Padma. ‘What in the name of Merlin’s underpants were you wearing back there?’

‘My hero outfit,’ said the Gryffindor girl.

Daphne sounded weary, as she spoke without turning her own head from where she was plodding through the hall. ‘It’s the costume of the Soldier of Gryffindor from the play Chronicles of the Lunarian Soldiers.’

‘Did you Transfigure it?’ said Parvati, looking puzzled. ‘But the bully cast Finite on you –’

‘Nope!’ Lavender said. ‘It’s real! See, I just Transfigured my hero outfit into a regular shirt and skirt beforehand, so all I had to do was cast Finite on myself after I saw the bully. Do you want your own, Parvati? I got mine made yesterday by Katarina and Joshua in sixth-year, for twelve Sickles –’

‘I think,’ General Granger said in a careful voice, ‘that would make us all look a little silly.’

‘Well,’ said Lavender, ‘we should vote on whether to –’

‘I think,’ General Granger said, ‘that no matter what anyone votes, I’m not going to be caught dead wearing one of those costumes –’

Susan ignored the argument. She was trying to think up some sort of clever strategy for being less doomed.

The whole Great Hall went silent, even if only for a moment, as the seven of them walked into lunch.

Then the applause started.

It was scattered, not the massive applause of everyone applauding at once. A lot of it came from the Gryffindor table, less from Hufflepuff and Ravenclaw, and none from Slytherin.

Daphne felt her face tightening. She’d hoped – well, maybe after they found a Gryffindor bully to stop and a Slytherin to rescue, her fellow Slytherins would realize –

She looked at the Hufflepuff table.

Neville Longbottom was applauding with his hands held high above his head, although he wasn’t smiling. Maybe he’d heard about Hannah, or maybe he was wondering why Hannah wasn’t there.

Then, not quite able to help herself, she glanced toward the Head Table.

Professor Sprout’s face was lined with concern. She and Professor McGonagall were leaning their heads toward Headmaster Dumbledore, who had a solemn look, and all their lips were moving quickly. Professor Flitwick looked more resigned than anything else, and Quirrell, face slack, was taking trembling stabs at his soup using a spoon gripped in a fist.

Professor Snape was looking directly at –

Her?

Or – at Hermione Granger, standing next to her?

A small, thin smile crossed the Potions Master’s face, and he raised his hands, brought them together once in a motion that was too slow to be a real clap; and then the Potions Master turned back to his plate, ignoring the conversations around him.

Daphne felt a little chill go down her spine, and she hastily turned to walk toward the Slytherin table. Susan and Lavender and Parvati peeled off from their group, heading toward the Hufflepuff and Gryffindor tables on the other side of the Great Hall.

It happened as they were passing the part of the Slytherin table where the Slytherin Quidditch team sat.

That was when Hermione stumbled suddenly, stumbled hard like she was being yanked off her feet, and went sprawling into the gap between where Marcus Flint and Lucian Bole sat, and there was a sad little splutching sound as Hermione’s face ended up in Flint’s plate of steak and mashed potatoes.

Everything seemed to happen too quickly then, or maybe it was just Daphne herself who was thinking too slow, as Flint let out a bellow of indignation and his hand yanked Hermione back and threw her into the Ravenclaw table, and she bounced off a student’s back and collapsed onto the ground –

The quiet spread out in ripples.

Hermione pushed herself up on her hands, though she didn’t get all the way to her feet, Daphne could see that her whole body was shaking, and that her face was still covered with mashed potatoes with scattered pieces of steak.

For a long moment, nobody spoke, nobody moved. Like nobody in the whole Great Hall could imagine, any more than Daphne could, what happened next.

Then Flint’s powerful voice, the voice of the Slytherin Captain that bellowed commands on the Quidditch pitch, said in a dangerous rumble, ‘You ruined my food, girl.’

Another moment of frozen silence. Hermione’s head – Daphne could see it trembling – turned to look at the Slytherin Quidditch Captain.

‘Apologize to me,’ said Flint.

Harry Potter started to push himself up from the Ravenclaw table, and then stopped abruptly, halfway to his feet, as if he’d just thought of something –

Then five other people stood up from the Ravenclaw table.

All of the Slytherin Quidditch team stood up, their wands coming into their hands, and then students stood up at the Gryffindor table and at the Hufflepuff table and without thinking Daphne turned to look at the Head Table and she saw that the Headmaster was still sitting down, watching, just watching, Dumbledore was just watching and he had one hand out as though to restrain Professor McGonagall – in just one second someone would shout a spell and then it would be too late, why wasn’t the Headmaster doing anything –

And a voice said, ‘My apologies.’

Daphne turned back to look, her mouth gaping open in absolute shock.

‘Scourgify,’ said that smooth voice, and the mashed potatoes vanished from Hermione’s face, revealing the Ravenclaw’s surprised expression as Draco Malfoy approached her, sheathed his wand again, and then knelt to one knee beside her and offered her a hand.

‘Sorry about that, Miss Granger,’ said Draco Malfoy’s polite voice. ‘I guess someone thought they were being funny.’

Hermione took Draco’s hand, and Daphne suddenly realized what was about to happen –

But Draco Malfoy didn’t raise Hermione halfway up and then drop her.

He just pulled her to her feet.

‘Thanks,’ said Hermione.

‘You’re welcome,’ Draco Malfoy said in a loud voice, not looking to either side to see where all four Houses of Hogwarts were staring at him in total shock. ‘Just remember, being cunning and ambitious doesn’t mean you have to be like that.’

And then Draco Malfoy went back to his seat at the Slytherin bench and sat down like he hadn’t – he hadn’t just – he’d just –

Hermione went to the nearest empty place at the Ravenclaw bench and sat down.

A number of other people, rather slowly, sat down.

‘Daphne?’ said Tracey. ‘Are you all right?’

Draco’s heart was hammering in his chest so hard he worried it might explode right out of his chest in a shower of blood, like that curse Amycus Carrow had used once on a puppy.

Draco’s face stayed completely controlled, because he knew (it’d been drilled into him over and over) that if he showed the slightest sign of the fear he was feeling, his Housemates would rip him apart like a swarm of Acromantulas.

There’d been no time to check with Harry Potter, no time to plot, no time to think, just the instant of realizing that the time to start rescuing Slytherin’s reputation was right then.

From all sides of the long Slytherin table, angry faces stared at Draco.

But they were outnumbered by the faces that just looked puzzled.

‘All right, I give up,’ said a sixth-year boy that Draco didn’t recognize, sitting across from him and two places to his right. ‘Why did you do that, Malfoy?’

Although his mouth was very dry, Draco didn’t swallow. That would have been a sign of fear. Instead he took a bite of carrots, which had the most moisture of anything on his plate, and chewed and swallowed, thinking as rapidly as he could.

‘You know,’ Draco said, making his voice as cutting as he could – as his heart thumped even harder in his chest, as everyone around him stopped talking to listen – ‘there’s probably some way to make Slytherin look even worse than attacking eight first-year girls from all four Houses who are working together to stop bullies, but I can’t think of how. This way we get the benefit of what Greengrass is doing.’

The puzzled faces stayed puzzled.

‘What?’ said the sixth-year boy, and ‘Wait, what benefit?’ said a fifth-year girl sitting to his right.

‘It makes Slytherin House look better,’ said Draco.

The Slytherins around him were giving him quizzical gazes like he’d just tried to explain algebra.

‘Look better to who?’ said the sixth-year boy.

‘But you just helped a mudblood,’ said the fifth-year girl. ‘How’s that supposed to look good?’

Draco’s throat closed up. His brain was experiencing a hideous malfunction during which it couldn’t think of anything to say except the truth –

Then, ‘It’s probably some kind of tremendously clever scheme Malfoy’s got going,’ said a fifth-year boy. ‘You know, like in The Tragedy of Light, where everything that looks like a setback is part of the plot. And it ends with Granger’s head on a stick and nobody suspecting that it was him.’

‘That makes sense,’ someone said from further down the table, and there was a lot of nodding.

‘Do you know what the boss’s up to?’ Vincent muttered in an undertone.

Gregory Goyle didn’t reply. In his mind he could hear very clearly his master’s voice, saying, I can’t believe I believed every word of that, the day the rumour had started about Salazar Slytherin showing Potter and Granger where to find bullies.

‘Mr Goyle?’ whispered Vincent.

Gregory Goyle’s lips shaped the words, Oh no, but no sound came out.

Hermione had left lunch early that day, for some reason she hadn’t felt hungry. Those few seconds of horrible humiliation had kept burning through her mind, over and over, the feeling of her face squishing into the mashed potatoes and then being thrown through the air and then the Slytherin’s boy’s voice saying Apologize to me … it might have been the first time in her whole life that she’d felt like hating someone. The boy who’d thrown her (Marcus Flint, they’d said his name was) and whoever had cast the tripping Jinx on her in the first place … she’d felt it, for one horrible instant she’d wanted to go tell Harry that if he started getting creative on her behalf, she wouldn’t object.

She hadn’t been a minute out of the Great Hall before she’d heard the sound of running feet behind, and turned to see Daphne racing toward her.

And listened to what her Sunshine Soldier had to say …

‘Don’t you understand?’ Daphne’s voice was barely below a shriek. ‘Just because someone’s nice to you doesn’t mean they’re your friend! He’s Draco Malfoy! His father’s a Death Eater, all the parents of all his friends are Death Eaters – Nott, Goyle, Crabbe, everyone around him, do you get it? They all despise Muggleborns, they want everyone like you to die, they think you’re good for nothing but being a sacrifice in horrible Dark rituals! Draco is the next Lord Malfoy, he’s been raised from birth to hate you and he’s been raised from birth to lie!’ Daphne’s grey-green eyes stared fiercely at her, demanding assent and understanding.

‘He –’ Hermione said falteringly. She remembered the rooftop, the awful jolt as she started to fall, Draco Malfoy’s hand grabbing hers and holding it so hard that she’d had bruises afterwards. She’d had to tell him twice before he finally let her fall. ‘Maybe Draco Malfoy isn’t like them –’

Daphne’s whisper was almost a scream. ‘If he doesn’t end up hurting you ten times as hard as he just helped you, his life is over, do you understand? I mean Lucius Malfoy would literally disinherit him! D’you know what the chance is that he’s not up to something?’

‘Tiny?’ said Hermione in a small voice.

‘Zero!’ hissed Daphne. ‘I mean none! I mean less than zero! I mean the chance is so small that you couldn’t find it with three Magnifying Charms and a Point-Me spell and – and – and an ancient map and a centaur prophet! Everyone in Slytherin knows he’s plotting to do something to you and doesn’t want to be suspected, I heard someone say he was seen pointing his wand at you just before you tripped – don’t you see? This is all part of Malfoy’s plan!’

Draco sat eating his steak with roasted cauliflower florets and Ashwinder sauce (it wasn’t made from real Ashwinder eggs, it just tasted like fire), trying not to laugh and trying not to cry.

He’d heard about plausible deniability, but hadn’t realized how much it mattered until he found that Malfoys didn’t have any.

‘You want to know my plot?’ said Draco. ‘Here’s my plot. I’m not going to do anything and then the next time people think I’m plotting something, they won’t be sure.’

‘Huh …’ said the fifth-year boy. ‘I don’t think I believe you, that doesn’t sound cunning enough to be really it –’

‘That’s what he wants you to think,’ said the fifth-year girl.

‘Albus,’ Minerva said dangerously, ‘did you plan all this?’

‘Well, if I did snap my fingers under the table, I wouldn’t just tell you that –’

The Defence Professor’s quavering hand dropped his spoon into the soup again.

‘What do you mean, set you up?’ said Millicent. The two of them were sitting cross-legged on Daphne’s bed, having come there straight from the Great Hall after lunch. ‘With my Seer’s eyes that stare through Time Itself, I saw you winning.’

Daphne stared at Millicent, her own merely mortal eyes rather narrowed at the moment. ‘That boy was expecting us.’

‘Well, yeah!’ said Millicent. ‘Everyone knows you’re hunting bullies!’

‘Hannah got hit by a really painful hex,’ Daphne said. ‘She had to visit a healer, Millicent! If we’re friends you should’ve warned me!’

‘Look, Daphne, I told you –’ The Slytherin girl paused, as if trying to remember something, and then said, ‘I mean, I told you, what I See has to come to pass. If I try to change it, if anyone tries to change it, really terrible, awful, no good, extremely bad things will happen. And then it’ll come to pass anyway. If I See you getting beaten up, I can’t tell you that, because then you’d try to not go, and then –’ Millicent stopped.

‘And then?’ Daphne said skeptically. ‘I mean, what happens if we just don’t go?’

‘I don’t know!’ said Millicent. ‘But it probably makes being eaten by Lethifolds look like a tea party!’

‘Look, even I know that’s not how prophecies work,’ Daphne said, then paused. ‘At least prophecies don’t work like that in plays …’ Admittedly, there were all sorts of tragedies where trying to avoid a prophecy made it happen, or where, on the other hand, trying to go along with a prophecy was the only reason why it happened. But you could make prophecies happen your own way if you were clever enough; or someone who loved you enough could take your place; or with enough effort it was possible to break a prophecy outright … Then again, in plays the Seers never remembered what they Saw, either …

Millicent must have seen Daphne’s hesitation, because the other girl started looking a little more confident. ‘Well,’ Millicent said sharply, ‘this isn’t a play! Look, I’ll tell you if I See it being a hard battle or an easy one. But that’s all I can do, you understand? And if I say “hard” you can’t not show up! Or – or –’ Millicent’s eyes rolled back in her head, and she intoned hollowly, ‘Those who try to cheat their destinies will come to sad and gloomy ends –’

Professor Sprout shook her head, her face looking tight.

‘But –’ said Susan. ‘But you helped Harry Potter that one time –’

‘And it was made quite clear to me,’ Professor Sprout said in a voice that sounded like someone was using a Shrinking Charm to squeeze her throat, ‘that it was Professor Snape’s job, and not mine, to keep order in Slytherin House – Miss Bones, please, you don’t have to do this if –’

‘Yes, I do have to,’ Susan said unhappily. ‘I’m a Hufflepuff, we have to be loyal.’

‘A mysterious parchment under your pillow?’ said Harry Potter, looking up from where he was sitting, in the Quieted nook where they were studying. Then the boy’s green eyes narrowed. ‘It wasn’t from Santa Claus, was it?’

Pause.

‘Okay,’ said Hermione. ‘I’m not going to ask, and you’re not going to tell me, and we’re both going to pretend you never said that and I don’t know anything about it –’

Susan approached the table as soon as the older girl was alone, glancing around the Hufflepuff common room to make sure nobody was watching (the way Auntie had taught her to do it, so that it wouldn’t be obvious that she was looking).

‘Hey, Susie,’ said the seventh-year Hufflepuff. ‘Do you already need more –’

‘Can I please talk to you privately for a bit?’ Susan said.

Jaime Astorga, seventh-year of Slytherin, and until recently considered a promising upstart on the youth duelling circuit, stood ramrod straight in Professor Snape’s office, with his teeth clenched tight and sweat trickling down his spine.

‘I distinctly recall,’ said the Head of his House in a sardonic drawl, ‘that I warned you, and a number of others this very morning, that there were certain first-year girls who might prove annoying, if a fighter were incautious and allowed himself to be taken by surprise.’

Professor Snape stalked in a slow circle around him.

‘I –’ said Jaime, as more sweat beaded on his forehead. He knew how ridiculous it sounded, how much of a pathetic excuse. ‘Sir, they shouldn’t have been able to –’ One first-year-girl shouldn’t have been able to break his Protego, no matter what sort of ancient Charm she used – Greengrass must have had help –

But it was very clear that his Head of House wouldn’t believe that.

‘Oh, I quite agree,’ murmured Snape in a low tone, instinct with menace. ‘They shouldn’t have. I begin to wonder if Mr Malfoy, whatever his plotting, has a point, Astorga. It cannot be good for the repute of Slytherin’s House if our fighters, rather than demonstrating their strength, lose to little girls!’ Snape’s voice had risen. ‘It is well that you had the good taste to be defeated by a little girl who is a fellow Slytherin of a Noble House, Astorga, or I would deduct points from you myself!’

Jaime Astorga’s fists clenched at his side, but he couldn’t think of a thing to say.

It was some time before Jaime Astorga was allowed to leave the presence of his Head of House.

And afterwards, only the walls, the floor, and the ceiling saw Severus Snape’s smile.

That evening Draco was visited by his father’s owl, Tanaxu, who wasn’t green but only because there weren’t such things as green owls. The best Father had been able to find was an owl of the purest silver feathers, with great luminous green eyes, and a beak as sharp and cruel as any snake’s fang. The parchment wrapped around Tanaxu’s leg was short and to the point:

What are you doing, my son?

The parchment that Draco sent back was equally short, and it said,

I am trying to stop harm done to Slytherin’s reputation, father.

In as much time as it took for an owl to fly from Hogwarts to Malfoy Manor and back again, the family owl bore another message to Draco, and this one said only:

What are you really doing?

Draco stared at the parchment he’d unwrapped from the owl’s leg. His hands trembled, as he held up the parchment to the light of his fireplace. Five words, carved in black ink, shouldn’t have been scarier than death.

There wasn’t very much time to think. Father knew exactly how long it took for a message to go from Malfoy Manor to Hogwarts and back again; he would know if Draco delayed to compose a careful lie.

But Draco still waited until his hand stopped trembling, before he wrote his reply, the only answer he’d thought of that Father might accept.

I am preparing for the next war.

Draco wrapped that parchment around the owl’s leg and tied it, and then sent Tanaxu winging out from his room, through the halls of Hogwarts, into the night.

He waited, but no reply came.

‘Every single one of you had better be absolutely clear on this,’ said Susan Bones. The Hufflepuff girl, or whatever strange power had possessed her, wasn’t even pretending to act normal any more. The round-faced girl was striding through the halls with a firm, confident gait. ‘If we get there and it’s just one bully, that’s fine, you can fight them the regular way. My mysterious superpowers won’t activate if there are no innocents in danger. But if five seventh-year bullies jump out of a closet, you know what you do? That’s right, you run away and let me fight them. Finding a teacher is optional, the important thing is that you run away as soon as I create an opening. In a fight like that you are liabilities. You are civilian targets I have to worry about protecting. So you will get away as fast as possible and you will not try to do anything heroic or so help me, the hour you get out of your healer’s beds I will personally show up and kick your arses right back in. Are we all clear on that?’

‘Yes,’ squeaked most of the girls, though in Hannah’s case it came out, ‘Yes, Lady Susan!’

‘Don’t call me that,’ snapped Susan. ‘And I don’t think I heard you, Miss Brown! I’m warning you, I have friends who write plays and if you do anything dumb, posterity will remember you as Lavender, the Amazing Stupid Hostage.’

(Hermione was beginning to worry about just how many other Hogwarts students besides Harry had mysterious dark sides, and whether she was likely to develop one if she kept hanging out with them.)

‘Alright, Captain Bones,’ said Lavender in an unusually respectful tone, as they turned another corner along the shortest way to the library, passing through a rather large corridor studded with six sets of double doors, three sets on either side. ‘Can I ask if there’s any way for me to become a double witch?’

‘Sign up for Auror preparation in your sixth year,’ said Susan. ‘It’s the next best thing. Oh, and if a famous Auror offers to oversee your summer internship, just ignore anyone who warns you that he’s a terrible influence or that you’re almost certainly going to die.’

Lavender was nodding rapidly. ‘Got it, got it.’

(Padma, who hadn’t actually been there last time, was giving Susan very skeptical looks.)

Then Susan suddenly stopped in place and her wand snapped up and she said, ‘Protego Maximus!’

A jolt of adrenaline went through Hermione, she was instantly drawing her wand and spinning around –

But she couldn’t see anything wrong, through the greater blue haze now surrounding them all.

The other girls, who had likewise pulled into formation, were also looking puzzled.

‘Sorry!’ said Susan. ‘Sorry, girls. Give me a moment to check this place out. Thinking of a certain person has just reminded me that this hall we’re in right now, with all those doors, would be an excellent place for an ambush.’

There was a moment of silence.

‘Now,’ said a harsh male voice, blurred into unidentifiability by a buzzing undertone.

All six sets of double doors slammed open.

White robes filed silently forward, all-concealing white robes without marks of House affiliation and white cloth hiding the faces beneath the hoods. They marched out, and marched out, crowding the great corridor in numbers too high to count easily. Less than fifty robes, probably. Certainly more than thirty. All of them already surrounded by blue haze.

Susan said some Extremely Bad Words, so awful that at almost any other time, Hermione would have noticed.

‘That message!’ Daphne cried in sudden horror. ‘It wasn’t from –’

‘Millicent Bulstrode?’ said the voice and its buzzing undertone. ‘No, it wasn’t. You see, Miss Greengrass, if the same girl sends off a Slytherin message every day you fight a bully, pretty soon someone else will notice. We’ll have a talk with her after we’re done with you.’

‘Miss Susan,’ said Hannah in a voice just starting to quaver, ‘can you be super enough to –’

Wands rose in many hands. There came a series of blinding flashes of green light, a massive volley of shieldbreakers, at the end of which there was no more protective blue dome surrounding them, and Susan had fallen to her knees, clutching her head.

Barriers of solid blackness had sprung into being at both ends of the corridor. Behind the double doors that Hermione could see into, there were only unused classrooms, very dead ends.

‘No,’ said the male voice with that buzz overlaid, ‘she can’t. In case you haven’t noticed, you’ve made quite a lot of people very angry with you and we have no intention of losing this time. All right everyone, prepare to fire.’

The wands around the perimeter aimed again, low enough that their enemies wouldn’t hit each other if they missed.

And then another male voice, with a similar buzz accompanying it, suddenly said ‘Hominem Revelio!’

An instant later there was another massive volley of shieldbreakers and hexes, fired on reflex at the suddenly revealed figure, shattering the shields which had almost immediately begun to form around it –

And then, as that same figure fell to the ground, a stunned silence.

‘Professor Snape?’ said the second voice. ‘He’s the one who’s been interfering?’

It was the Potions Master of Hogwarts who now lay unconscious on the stone floor, the dirt-spotted robes stirring for a final moment before they settled in place, his fallen hand outstretched toward where his wand was slowly rolling away.

‘No,’ said the first male voice, now sounding a bit more uncertain. Then it rallied, ‘No, that can’t possibly be it. He heard us passing the word, of course, and came along to make sure nobody screwed it up again. We’ll wake him up afterwards and apologize and he’ll Memory-Charm the children so they don’t remember, he’s a Professor so he can do that. Anyway, we should make sure we’re really alone now. Veritas Oculum!’

Fully two dozen different Charms must have been spoken, then, but no more invisible people showed up. One of them in particular made Hermione’s heart sink; she recognized it as the Charm which had been listed alongside the description of the True Cloak of Invisibility, which would not reveal the Cloak, but would tell you whether it or certain other artifacts were nearby.

‘Girls?’ whispered Susan. She was slowly pushing herself to her feet, though Hermione could see her limbs swaying and quivering. ‘Girls, I’m sorry for what I said before. If you’ve got anything clever and heroic to try, you might as well try it.’

‘Oh, yeah,’ Tracey Davis said then, her voice trembling. ‘I almost forgot.’ The Slytherin girl raised her voice, and spoke.

‘Hey, all of you!’ yelled Tracey in a high-pitched shaky shout. ‘Hey, are you planning to hurt me too?’

‘Yes, actually,’ said the buzzing voice of the leader. ‘We are.’

‘I’m under Harry Potter’s protection, you know! Anyone who tries to hurt me will learn the true meaning of Chaos! So are you going to let me go?’ It should have sounded defiant. It came out sounding terrified.

There was a pause. Some of the hoods of the robes turned to face each other, then turned back to face the girls.

‘Hm …’ said the buzzing male voice. ‘Hm … no.’

Tracey Davis put her wand away into her robes.

Slowly, deliberately, she raised her right hand high in the air, and pressed her thumb and forefingers together.

‘Go ahead,’ said that voice.

Tracey Davis snapped her fingers.

There was a long, awful pause.

Nothing happened.

‘Yes, well,’ said the voice –

Tracey said, her voice sounding even higher and shakier, ‘Acathla, mundatus sum.’ Her hand, stretching up still further, snapped its fingers a second time.

A nameless chill went down Hermione’s spine then, a frisson of fear and disorientation like she’d just felt the floor tilt beneath her, threatening to spill her into some darkness lying beneath.

‘What’s she –’ began a buzzing female voice.

Tracey’s face looked pale, twisted with fear, but her lips moved, spilled forth sound in a high chant, ‘Mabra, brahoring, mabra …’

A chill wind seemed to spring up within the confines of the corridor, a dark breath that caressed their faces and touched their hands with ice.

‘Fire at her on my count!’ shouted the leading voice. ‘One, two, three!’ and maybe-forty voices roared spells, creating a huge concentric array of fiery bolts that lit the wide corridor brighter than the Sun –

– for the short moment before the bolts struck and vanished upon a dark red octagon that appeared in the air around the girls, and then disappeared a moment later.

Hermione saw it, she saw it but she still couldn’t imagine it; she couldn’t imagine a Shielding Charm that powerful, a spell that would withstand an army.

And Tracey’s voice went on chanting, her voice sounding louder and more confident, and her face screwed up like she was trying to remember something very exactly.

‘Shuffle, duffle, muzzle, muff.
Fista, wista, mista-cuff.’

Now all those present could feel it, heroines and bullies alike, the sensation of some dark will pressing down on them, a tingling in the air as something built and built and built. All the blue hazes around the white robes, all the shielding spells, had died out without any visible hex touching them. There were more flashes of light as more desperate spells were fired, but they fizzled out in mid-air like candle-flames touching water.

The black barriers at the two ends of the corridor had dissipated like smoke beneath the growing pressure, but their evaporation revealed the exits sealed, blocked by tiled slats of dark metal that looked stained as though with blood; and as Tracey chanted ‘Lemarchand, Lament, Lemarchand,’ a dreadful blue light began to shine out from beneath the metal slats and between them; and the six sets of double doors slammed shut all at once, as panicked white-robed bullies began to pound on them and howl.

Then Tracey’s hand slashed to her left, and she cried ‘Khornath!’, then her hand pointed below her and ‘Slaaneth!’, above her ‘Nurgolth!’, and then, to her right, ‘Tzintchi!’

Tracey paused, took a deep breath; and Hermione found her voice and cried, ‘Stop! Tracey, stop!’

But there was a strange wild smile on Tracey’s face. She raised her hand still higher, and snapped her fingers a third time; and when she spoke again, beneath her high girlish voice there was an undertone as though some lower chorus were chanting along with her.

‘Darkness beyond darkness, deeper than pitchest black.
Buried beneath the flow of time …
From darkness to darkness, your voice echoes in the emptiness,
Unknown to death, nor known to life.’

‘What are you doing?’ shrieked Parvati, and the Gryffindor girl stretched out a hand as though to pull down the Slytherin, who was now starting to float upward into the air; and both Daphne and Susan grabbed Parvati’s arm at the same time and Daphne cried out, ‘Don’t, we don’t know what will happen if the ritual is interrupted!’

‘Well what happens if it gets COMPLETED?’ screamed Hermione, as close as she’d ever come to total brain meltdown.

Susan’s face was white as chalk, and she whispered, ‘I’m sorry, Mad-Eye …’

And Tracey spoke on, her body floating higher and higher off the floor, her black hair whipping wildly around her in the chill winds.

‘You who know the gate, who are the gate, the key and guardian of the gate:
I bid you open the way for him, and manifest his power before me!’

The corridor was plunged then into utter darkness and silence, so that only Tracey could be seen and heard, like there was nothing left in the universe except her and the light illuminating her from some nameless source.

The shining girl raised her hand one final time, and with dreadful gravity, pressed her thumb and forefinger together.

And within the darkness Hermione looked at Tracey’s face and saw that the Slytherin girl’s eyes were now, to the exact shade, the green of Harry Potter’s.

‘Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres!
Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres!
Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres!’

There was a snap like thunder, and then –

Cheating

It was Saturday, on the 4th of April, in the year 1992.

Mr and Mrs Davis looked rather nervous, as they sat in a certain special section of the Hogwarts Quidditch stands – though today the cushioned benches did not look upon flying broomsticks, but rather viewed a gigantic square of something like parchment; a great white blankness soon to flicker with windows into grass and soldiers. For now it showed only the reflected dull grey colour of the surrounding overcast skies. (Looking rather stormy, though the weather-wizards had promised that the rain wouldn’t break before nightfall.)

Ordinarily it was the ancient tradition of Hogwarts that mere parents were to Stay Out – for much the same reason that impatient children are told to get out of the kitchen and not meddle in the cook’s affairs. The only reason for a parent-teacher conference was if a teacher felt that a parent wasn’t shaping up properly. It took an exceptional circumstance to make the Hogwarts administration feel that it had to justify itself to you. On any given occasion, generally speaking, the Hogwarts administration was backed up by eight hundred years of distinguished history and you were not.

Thus it had been with some trepidation that Mr and Mrs Davis had insisted on an audience with Deputy Headmistress McGonagall. It was hard to muster a proper sense of indignation when you were confronting the same dignified witch who, twelve years and four months earlier, had given both of you two weeks’ detention after catching you in the act of conceiving Tracey.

On the other hand, Mr and Mrs Davis’ courage had been helped by angrily waving about a copy of The Quibbler whose headline showed, in bright bold text for all the world to see:

Pacts with Potter?
Bones, Davis, Granger
in love rectangle of fear

And so Mr and Mrs Davis had argued their way into the Faculty Box of the Hogwarts Quidditch stands, where they were now ensconced with an excellent view of Professor Quirrell’s enchanted screens, so that the two of them could see for themselves ‘Just what the Fiddly-Snocks has been going on in this school, if you’ll pardon the expression, Deputy Headmistress McGonagall!’

Seated to the left of Mr Davis was another concerned parent, a white-haired man in elegant black robes of unmatchable quality, one Lucius Malfoy, political leader of the strongest faction of the Wizengamot.

To the left of Lord Malfoy, a sneeringly aristocratic man with a scarred face who had been introduced to them as Lord Jugson.

Then an elderly but sharp-eyed fellow named Charles Nott, rumoured to be nearly as wealthy as Lord Malfoy, seated on Lord Jugson’s left.

On the right of Mrs Davis, one would find the comely Lady and yet handsomer Lord of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Greengrass. Young they were as wizards counted age, garbed in grey silken robes set with tiny dark emeralds embroidered into the shape of grass blades. The Lady Greengrass was considered a key swing vote on the Wizengamot, her own mother having retired from the body with surprising speed. Her charming husband, though his family was not noble or wealthy of itself, had taken a seat on the Hogwarts Board of Governors.

To their right, a square-jawed and incredibly tough-looking old witch, who had shaken hands with Mr and Mrs Davis without the slightest hint of condescension. This was Amelia Bones, Director of the Department of Magical Law Enforcement.

To Amelia’s right was a oldish woman who had set the fashion scene of magical Britain on its ear by integrating a live vulture into her hat, one Augusta Longbottom. Though she was not addressed as Lady, Madam Longbottom would exercise the full rights of the Longbottom family for so long as their last scion had yet to attain his majority, and she was considered a prominent figure in a minority faction of the Wizengamot.

At the side of Madam Longbottom was seated none other than Chief Warlock Supreme Mugwump Headmaster Albus Percival Wulfric Brian Dumbledore, legendary defeater of Grindelwald, protector of Britain, rediscoverer of the fabled twelve uses of dragon’s blood, the most powerful wizard in the world &c.

And finally, on the far right, one would find the enigmatic Defence Professor of Hogwarts, Quirinus Quirrell, who was leaning back on the cushioned benches as though resting; seeming entirely and naturally at ease in the rarefied company of a voting quorum of the Hogwarts Board of Governors, which had dropped by on this fine Saturday to learn just what the Fiddly-Snocks had been going on at Hogwarts in general and with Draco Malfoy, Theodore Nott, Daphne Greengrass, Susan Bones, and Neville Longbottom in particular. The name of Harry Potter had also been much discussed.

Oh, and one mustn’t forget Tracey Davis, of course. Director Bones’s eyebrows had climbed in some interest upon hearing the young couple introduced as her parents. Lord Jugson had given them a brief, incredulous stare before dismissing them with a snort. Lucius Malfoy had greeted them politely, his smile containing a hint of grim amusement mixed with pity.

Mr and Mrs Davis, whose last vote on anything of significance had been touching their wands to the name of Minister Fudge, who had all of three hundred Galleons stored in their Gringotts vault, and who respectively worked at selling cauldrons in a Potions shop and enchanting Omnioculars, were pressed up tightly against each other, sitting rigidly erect upon their cushioned benches, and desperately wishing they’d worn nicer robes.

The sky above was a solid mass of cloud dispersed into darker and lighter greys, grim with the promise of future storms; though no lightning flickered as yet, nor distant rumbles of thunder echoed; and only a few threatening droplets had fallen.

To their designated starting place in a certain forest, the Sunshine Regiment marched, though it was really more like a slow walk; you wouldn’t want to tire yourself out before the battle even started, and the breezes of April were annoyingly humid, though cool. Ahead of them, a yellow flame wandered slowly through the air, guiding them according to their pace.

Susan Bones kept throwing worried glances toward the Sunshine General as they marched through the greyly illuminated forest. Professor Snape’s going after Hermione seemed to have really shaken her. Hermione had even missed her Sunshine Regiment Official Planning Meeting, which seemed understandable enough; but when Susan had offered her sympathy afterwards, Hermione had stammered that she’d lost track of time, which wasn’t at all a usual thing for her to say, and the girl had looked exhausted and frightened like she’d just spent three days locked in a bathroom stall with a Dementor. Even now, when all the Sunshine General’s focus should’ve been on the coming battle, the Ravenclaw girl’s gaze was constantly darting in all directions, as though she expected Dark Wizards to jump out of the bushes and sacrifice her.

‘The ban on Muggle artifacts cuts down our options a lot,’ Anthony Goldstein was saying in the dour tones the boy used to denote deliberate pessimism. ‘I had the idea of trying to Transfigure nets to throw on people, but –’

‘No good,’ said Ernie Macmillan. The Hufflepuff boy shook his head, looking even more serious than Anthony. ‘I mean, it’s just like throwing a hex, they’d dodge.’

Anthony nodded. ‘That’s what I figured, too. Do you have any ideas, Seamus?’

The former Chaotic Lieutenant still looked a bit nervous and out-of-place, marching along with his new comrades in the Sunshine Regiment. ‘Sorry,’ said the newly minted Captain Finnigan. ‘I’m more the strategic master type.’

‘I’m the strategic master type,’ said Ron Weasley, sounding put-off.

‘There are three armies,’ the Sunshine General said acerbically, ‘which means we fight two armies at once, which means we need more than one strategist, which means shut up, Ron!’

Ron gave their General a surprised and worried look. ‘Hey,’ the Gryffindor boy said in a calming tone, ‘you shouldn’t let Snape get to you so much –’

‘What do you think we ought to do, General?’ Susan said very loudly and quickly. ‘I mean, we don’t really have a plan at this point.’ Their official planning session had failed amazingly with Hermione gone and both Ron and Anthony thinking they were in charge.

‘Do we really need a plan?’ the Sunshine General said, sounding a little distracted. ‘We’ve got you and me and Lavender and Parvati and Hannah and Daphne and Ron and Ernie and Anthony and Captain Finnigan.’

‘That –’ began Anthony.

‘Sounds like a pretty good strategy,’ Ron said with an approving nod. ‘We’ve got as many strong soldiers now as both other armies put together. Chaos’s only got Potter and Longbottom and Nott left – well, and Zabini too, I suppose –’

‘And Tracey,’ said Hermione.

Several people swallowed nervously.

‘Oh, stop it,’ Susan said sharply. ‘She’s just a battle-hardened member of S.P.H.E.W., that’s all General Sunshine means.’

‘Still,’ Ernie said, turning to look seriously at Susan, ‘I think you’d better go with whatever group fights Chaos, Captain Bones. I know you can’t use your double magical powers except when innocents are in danger, but I mean – just in case Miss Davis does, you know, go out of control and try to eat someone’s soul –’

‘I can handle her,’ Susan told him, keeping her voice reassuring. Admittedly, Susan hadn’t been replaced by a Metamorphmagus at the moment, but then Tracey probably wasn’t Polyjuiced Dumbledore or whoever.

Captain Finnigan intoned in a deep, sort-of-rumbling voice, ‘I find your lack of skepticism disturbing.’ He raised his hand with his thumb and forefinger almost touching, pointed at Ernie.

For some reason Anthony Goldstein seemed to be having a sudden choking fit. ‘What’s that supposed to mean?’ said Ernie.

‘It’s just something General Potter says sometimes,’ said Captain Finnigan. ‘Funny, when you first join the Chaos Legion it all seems crazy, and then after a couple of months you realize that actually everyone who isn’t in the Chaos Legion is crazy –’

‘I said,’ Ron said loudly, ‘it sounds like good strategy. We don’t Transfigure anything, we don’t tire ourselves out, we handle whatever they throw at us, and then we just overrun them.’

‘Okay,’ said Hermione. ‘Let’s do that.’

‘But –’ said Anthony, shooting a glare at Ron. ‘But General, Harry Potter’s got sixteen people left in his army. Dragon and us each have twenty-eight. Harry knows that, he knows he’s got to come up with something incredible –’

‘Like what?’ demanded Hermione, sounding stressed. ‘If we don’t know what he’s planning, we might as well save our magic for doing massed Finites. Like we should’ve done last time!’

Susan touched Hermione gently on the shoulder. ‘General Granger?’ said Susan. ‘I think you should take a break for a bit before the battle.’

She’d been expecting Hermione to argue, but Hermione just nodded and then walked a little faster, pulling away from the Sunshine Regiment Official Officer Group, her eyes still watching the forest, and sometimes the sky.

Susan followed her. It wouldn’t do, having it look like the Sunshine General was being ejected from her own Official Officer Group.

‘Hermione?’ Susan said softly, after they’d walked a bit away. ‘You’ve got to focus. Professor Quirrell’s in charge here, not Snape, and he won’t let anything bad happen to you or anyone.’

‘You’re not helping,’ Hermione said, sounding shaky. ‘You’re not helping at all, Captain Bones.’

The two of them walked faster, circling around some of the other soldiers, inspecting the marching perimeter and glancing at the surrounding trees.

‘Susan?’ Hermione said in a small voice, when they were further away from all the others. ‘Do you think Daphne’s right about Draco Malfoy plotting something?’

‘Yes,’ Susan said at once, not even thinking about it. ‘You can tell, because his name’s got the letters M-A-L-F-O and Y in it.’

Hermione looked around, as if to make sure that nobody was watching, although of course that was a wonderful way to get other people to pay attention to you. ‘Could Malfoy have been behind what Snape did?’

‘Snape could be behind Malfoy,’ Susan said thoughtfully, remembering dinner-table conversations she’d heard at Auntie’s, ‘or Lucius Malfoy could be behind both of them.’ A slight chill went down Susan’s spine as this last thought occurred to her. Suddenly, telling Hermione to just focus on the coming battle seemed a lot less reasonable. ‘Why, did you find some sort of clue about that?’

Hermione shook her head. ‘No,’ the Ravenclaw girl said, in a voice that sounded almost like she was about to cry. ‘I was – just thinking about it myself – that’s all.’

In their designated place in a forest near Hogwarts, the Dragon General and the warriors of Dragon Army waited where their red flame had led them, beneath grey skies.

At Draco’s right side stood Padma Patil, his second-in-command, who had once led all of Dragon Army after Draco had been stunned. At Draco’s back was Vincent, the son of Crabbe, a family which had served the Malfoys into the distance of forgotten memory; the muscular boy was watchful as he was always watchful, whether battle had been declared or no. Further back, Gregory of the Goyles stood waiting beside one of the two broomsticks Dragon Army had been given; if the Goyles had not served the Malfoys so long as the Crabbes, yet they had served no less well.

And at Draco’s left side, now, stood one Dean Thomas of Gryffindor, a mudblood or possible half-blood who knew nothing of his father.

Sending Dean Thomas to Dragon Army had been a quite deliberate move on Harry’s part, Draco was certain. Three other former Chaotics had also been transferred to Dragon Army, and all were watching Draco hawklike to see if he offered the former Lieutenant the slightest insult.

Some might have called it sabotage, but Draco knew better. Harry had also sent Lieutenant Finnigan to the Sunshine Regiment, even though Professor Quirrell’s mandate had only required that Harry give up one Lieutenant. That too had been a deliberate move, making crystal clear to everyone that Harry wasn’t dumping his least-favoured soldiers.

In one sense, it might have been easier for Draco to win the true loyalties of his new soldiers if they’d thought Harry hadn’t wanted them. In another sense … well, it wasn’t easy to put into words. Harry had given him good soldiers with their pride intact, but it was more than that. Harry had showed kindliness toward his soldiers, but it was more than that. It wasn’t just Harry playing fair, it was something that … that you couldn’t help but contrast with the way the game was played in Slytherin House.

So Draco hadn’t offered the slightest insult to Mr Thomas, but brought him straight to his side, subordinate to himself and Padma but no one else. It was a test, Draco had told Mr Thomas and everyone, not a promotion. Mr Thomas would have to show himself worthy of rank within Dragon Army – but he would be given a chance, and the chance would be fair. Mr Thomas had looked surprised at the ceremony of it (the Chaos Legion, from what Draco had heard, didn’t stand on formality) but the Gryffindor boy had stood a little straighter, and nodded.

And then, after Mr Thomas had done well enough in one of Dragon Army’s training sessions, he’d been brought into the strategy session in Dragon Army’s huge military office. And a few minutes into the session, Padma had happened to ask – as though it was a perfectly normal question – whether Mr Thomas had any ideas about how to defeat the Chaos Legion.

The Gryffindor boy had said cheerfully that Harry had predicted that General Malfoy would get one of his soldiers to ask him that, and that Harry had given him the message that General Malfoy should ask himself where his relative advantage lay – what Draco Malfoy could do, or what Dragon Army could do, that the Chaos Legion couldn’t match – and then try to exploit it for all it was worth. Dean Thomas couldn’t think of what that advantage might be, but if he did come up with any ideas for beating Chaos, he’d share them. Harry had ordered him to, after all.

Sigh, Draco had thought, since he couldn’t actually sigh out loud. But it was good advice, and Draco had followed it, sitting at his bedroom desk with quill and parchment listing out everything that might be a relative advantage.

And, almost to Draco’s own surprise, he’d had an idea, a real one. In fact he’d had two.

The hollow bell sounded through the forest, somehow sounding more ominous than ever before. On the instant, the two pilots cried ‘Up!’ and leapt onto their broomsticks, heading into the grey sky.

Mr and Mrs Davis had now slumped slightly against each other, more from sheer muscle exhaustion than from any decrease of tension. Before them, the vast blank white parchment flickered with three great windows, as though holes had been cut through into the forest, showing three armies on the march. Lesser windows showed the six riders upon their broomsticks, and the corner of the parchment showed a view of the entire forest, with glowing dots to indicate armies and scouts.

The window into Sunshine showed General Granger and her Captains marching in the centre of the Sunshine Regiment, protected by Contego screens along with a number of other young witches. The Sunshine Regiment, the Defence Professor had remarked, knew well that it had now acquired a strong advantage in experienced soldiers, and it meant to protect those soldiers from a surprise attack. Aside from that, the Sunshine Soldiers were moving forward at a steady march, conserving their strength.

The soldiers in General Malfoy’s army, at least those with higher Transfiguration scores, were picking up leaves and Transfiguring them into … well, if you looked at Padma Patil, who was almost done with hers, it looked like her leaf was becoming a left-handed glove bearing a dangling strap. (The window had zoomed in to show this.)

Lord Jugson was watching the screen with a flat expression; his voice, when he spoke, seemed to ooze and drip with disdain. ‘What is your son doing, Lucius?’

The foreign-born witch who stood at Draco Malfoy’s right side had finished Transfiguring her glove, and was now bringing it before the Dragon General like a sacrifice.

‘I do not know,’ said Lucius Malfoy, his tone calm though no less aristocratic, ‘but I must trust that he has good reason for doing it.’

All Dragon Army stopped for a moment as Padma slid the glove over her left hand, strapped it in place, and presented it before Draco Malfoy; who also stopped in place, took several deep breaths, raised his wand, executed a precise set of eight movements and bellowed ‘Colloportus!’

The Dragon Warrior raised her gloved hand, flexed it, and gave a small bow to Draco Malfoy, who returned it more shallowly, though the Dragon General was staggering slightly. Padma then returned to her place at Draco’s side, and the Dragons began marching once more.

‘Well,’ remarked Augusta Longbottom. ‘I don’t suppose someone would care to explain?’ Amelia Bones was frowning slightly as she gazed at the screen.

‘For some reason or other,’ said the amused voice of Professor Quirrell, ‘it seems that the scion of Malfoy is able to cast surprisingly strong magic for a first-year student. Due to the purity of his blood, of course. Certainly the good Lord Malfoy would not have openly flouted the underage magic laws by arranging for his son to receive a wand before his acceptance into Hogwarts.’

‘I suggest you be careful in your implications, Quirrell,’ Lucius Malfoy said coldly.

‘Oh, I am,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘A Colloportus cannot be dispelled by Finite Incantatem; it requires an Alohomora of equal strength. Until then, a glove so Charmed will resist lesser material forces, deflect the Sleep Hex and the Stunning Hex. And as neither Mr Potter nor Miss Granger can cast a counter-spell powerful enough, that Charm is invincible upon this battlefield. It is not the original intent of the Charm, nor the intent of whoever taught Mr Malfoy an emergency spell for evading his enemies. But it would seem that Mr Malfoy has been learning creativity.’

Lucius Malfoy had straightened as the Defence Professor spoke; he now sat erect upon his cushioned bench, his head held perceptibly higher than before, and when he spoke it was with quiet pride. ‘He will be the greatest Lord Malfoy that has yet lived.’

‘Faint praise,’ Augusta Longbottom said under her breath; Amelia Bones chuckled, as did Mr Davis for a tiny, fatal fraction of a second before he stopped with a strangled gargle.

‘I quite agree,’ said Professor Quirrell, though it wasn’t clear to whom he spoke. ‘Unfortunately for Mr Malfoy, he is still new to the art of creativity, and so he has committed a classic error of Ravenclaw.’

‘And what might that be?’ said Lucius Malfoy, his voice now turned chill once more.

Professor Quirrell had leaned back in his seat, the pale blue eyes briefly unfocusing as one of the windows shifted its viewpoint within the greater screen, zooming in to show the sweat now on Draco Malfoy’s forehead. ‘It is such a beautiful idea that Mr Malfoy has quite overlooked its pragmatic difficulties.’

‘Would someone care to explain that?’ said Lady Greengrass. ‘Not all of us present are experts at such … affairs.’

Amelia Bones spoke, the old witch’s voice somewhat dry. ‘It will tempt them to try to catch hexes that they would be wiser to simply dodge. The more so, if they have had little practise catching them. And the casting of so many Charms will tire their strongest warrior.’

Professor Quirrell gave the DMLE Director a half-nod of acknowledgement. ‘As you say, Madam Bones. Mr Malfoy is new to the business of having ideas, and so when he has one, he becomes proud of himself for having it. He has not yet had enough ideas to unflinchingly discard those that are beautiful in some aspects and impractical in others; he has not yet acquired confidence in his own ability to think of better ideas as he requires them. What we are seeing here is not Mr Malfoy’s best idea, I fear, but rather his only idea.’

Lord Malfoy simply turned to watch the screens again, as though the Defence Professor had used up his right to exist.

‘But –’ said Lord Greengrass. ‘But what in Merlin’s name is Harry Potter –’

Sixteen remaining soldiers of the Chaos Legion – or fifteen plus Blaise Zabini, rather – marched confidently through the forest, their shoes thudding over the still-dry ground. Their camouflage uniforms blended into the forest even more than usual, all colours washed out by the tints of an overcast day.

Sixteen Chaos Legionnaires, against twenty-eight Dragon Warriors and twenty-eight Sunshine Soldiers.

The common consensus had been that, with odds that bad, it was practically impossible for them to lose. After all, General Chaos was bound to come up with something really spectacular, facing odds like that.

There was something almost nightmarish about how everyone seemed to now expect Harry to pull miracles out of his hat, on demand, any time one was needed. It meant that if you couldn’t do the impossible, you were disappointing your friends and failing to live up to your potential …

Harry hadn’t bothered complaining to Professor Quirrell about too much pressure. Harry’s mental model of the Defence Professor had predicted him looking severely annoyed, saying things along the lines of You are perfectly capable of solving this problem, Mr Potter; did you even try? and then deducting several hundred Quirrell points.

From above, from where two broomsticks watched their march, the high young voice of Tess Walsh cried ‘Friend!’ and after another moment, ‘Gingersnap!’

A handful of seconds later, the soldier who’d code-named herself Gingersnap returned bearing a double handful of acorns, sweating slightly in the cool but humid air from the jog that had taken her to the oak tree Neville had spotted. Gingersnap approached to where Shannon was holding a uniform-shirt with the neck tied off, in lieu of anyone having to Transfigure a bag. When Gingersnap brought her hands forward to try and dump her acorns into the holding-shirt, Chaotic Shannon, giggling, jerked the shirt to the right, then to the left again as Gingersnap made another effort to dump the acorns, until a sharp ‘Miss Friedman!’ from Lieutenant Nott caused Shannon to sigh and hold the shirt still. Gingersnap dumped her acorns into those accumulated, and then headed out for more.

Somewhere in the background, Ellie Knight was singing her very own version of the Chaos Legion’s marching song, and around half the other soldiers were trying to step along with it despite not knowing the tune in advance. Nearby, Nita Berdine, who had a high Transfiguration score, finished creating yet another pair of green sunglasses, and handed them to Adam Beringer, who folded up the sunglasses before tucking them into his uniform pocket. Other soldiers were already wearing their own green sunglasses, despite the cloudy day.

You might guess that there was some sort of incredibly complicated and fascinating explanation behind this, and you would be right.

Two days earlier Harry had been sitting amid his bookcases in the comfy rocking-chair he’d obtained for his trunk’s cavern level, pondering silently in the quiet span between classes and dinnertime, thinking about power.

For sixteen Chaotics to defeat twenty-eight Sunnies and twenty-eight Dragons they would need a force amplifier. There were limits to what you could do with manoeuvre. There had to be a secret weapon and it had to be invincible, or at least moderately unstoppable.

Muggle artifacts were now illegal in Hogwarts’s mock battles, banned by Ministry edict. And the trouble with finding some other clever and unusual spell was that an army twice your own size could brute-force Finite almost anything you tried. The Sunshine Regiment might have missed that tactic with the Transfigured chain mail, but nobody would miss it again now that Professor Quirrell had pointed it out. And Finite Incantatem was a brute-force counter-spell which required at least as much magic as the spell being cancelled … which, if you were severely outnumbered, made it a whole new order of military challenge. The enemy could Finite anything you tried, and still have enough magic left over for shields and volleys of Sleep Hexes.

Unless, somehow, you could invoke potencies beyond the ordinary strength of first-year Hogwarts students, something too powerful for the enemy to Finite.

So Harry had asked Neville if he’d ever heard of any small, safe sacrificial rituals –

And then, after the screaming and the shouting had subsided, after Harry had stopped trying to argue about Unbreakable Vows and just given up the whole thing as impossible from a public relations standpoint, Harry had realized that he hadn’t even needed to go there. They taught you how to invoke potencies far beyond your own strength in ordinary Hogwarts classes.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question.

Defence. Charms. Transfiguration. Potions. History of Magic. Astronomy. Broomstick Flying. Herbology …

‘Foe!’ screamed the voice from above.

It was a good thing that Neville Longbottom hadn’t the tiniest idea that his grandmother was watching; or he would’ve been more self-conscious about screaming scary battlecries at the top of his lungs while casting Luminos every three seconds as he rocketed through a dense forest of trees, hot on the tail of Gregory Goyle.

(‘But –’ Augusta Longbottom said, her expression showing almost as much astonishment as worry. ‘But Neville is afraid of heights!’)

(‘Not all fears last,’ said Amelia Bones. The old witch was favouring the great screen before them with a measuring gaze. ‘Or perhaps he has found courage. It is much the same, in the end.’)

A glimmer of red –

Neville dodged, very nearly into a tree but he did dodge; and then Neville somehow also managed to dodge almost all of the branches before they smacked him in the face.

Now Mr Goyle’s broomstick was pulling further and further away – even though the two of them were riding exactly the same broomstick and Mr Goyle weighed more, somehow Neville was still falling behind. So Neville slowed down, pulled back, angled up out of the forest and began to accelerate back toward where the Chaos Legion still marched.

Twenty seconds later – it hadn’t been a long chase, just an exciting one – Neville was back among his fellow Chaotics, and dismounted his broom to walk on the ground for a little bit.

‘Neville –’ said General Potter. Harry’s voice was a little distant, as he walked carefully and steadily through the forest, his wand still applied to the almost-finished Form of the object he was slowly Transfiguring. Beside him, Blaise Zabini, working a smaller version of the same Transfiguration, looked like a shambling Inferi as he stumbled forward. ‘I told you – Neville – you don’t have to –’

‘Yes, I do,’ said Neville. He looked down at where his fingers grasped the broomstick, and saw that not just his hands, but his whole arms were shaking. But unless anyone else in Chaos had been practising duelling for an hour a day with Mr Diggory, and then practising their aim in private for another hour afterwards, Neville was probably the best shot from a broomstick even after taking into account that he wasn’t a very good flyer.

‘Good show, Neville,’ Theodore said from where he was walking ahead of them all, leading the Chaos Legion forward through the forest while wearing only his under-shirt.

(Augusta Longbottom and Charles Nott exchanged brief astonished glances and then wrenched their gazes away from one another as though stung.)

Neville took a few deep breaths, trying to steady his hands, trying to think; Harry might not be good for deep strategic thinking while he was in the middle of an extended Transfiguration. ‘Lieutenant Nott, do you have any idea why Dragon Army just did that? They lost a broom –’ The Dragons had started the combat with a feint to provide a distraction for Mr Goyle’s approach through the forest; Neville hadn’t realized there were two brooms attacking until almost too late. But the Chaos Legion had got the other pilot. That was why broomsticks usually didn’t attack before armies met, it meant a whole army would concentrate fire on the broomstick. ‘And the Dragons didn’t even get anyone, did they?’

‘Nope!’ Tracey Davis said proudly. She too was now marching by General Potter’s side, her wand gripped low and watchful as her eyes scanned the surrounding forest. ‘I threw up a Prismatic Sphere like a split second before Mr Goyle’s hex got Zabini, and the way Mr Goyle had his other arm stretched out I think he planned to knock down the General, too.’ The Slytherin witch smiled with vicious confidence. ‘Mr Goyle tried a Breaking Drill Hex, but learned to his dismay that his weak magic was no match for my newfound dark powers, hahahaha!’

Some Chaotics laughed with her, but a queasy sensation was starting in Neville’s stomach as he realized how close the Chaos Legion had come to complete disaster. If Mr Goyle had managed to disrupt both Transfigurations –

‘Report!’ snapped the Dragon General, doing his best to conceal the fatigue he felt after casting seventeen Locking Charms, with more yet to come.

Beads of sweat now dotted Gregory’s forehead. ‘The enemy downed Dylan Vaughan,’ Gregory said formally. ‘Harry Potter and Blaise Zabini were each Transfiguring something dark-grey and roundish, I don’t think it was finished but it looked like it would be big and hollow, sort of cauldron-shaped. Zabini’s was smaller than Potter’s. I couldn’t get either of them or disrupt their Transfigurations, Tracey Davis blocked me. Neville Longbottom is on a broomstick and he’s still a terrible flyer but his aim is really good.’

Draco listened, frowning, and then he glanced at Padma and Dean Thomas, who both shook their own heads, indicating that they also couldn’t think of what might be big and grey and shaped like a cauldron.

‘Anything else?’ said Draco. If that was it, they’d lost a broom for nothing –

‘The only other weird thing I saw,’ Gregory said, sounding puzzled, ‘was that some Chaotics were wearing … sort of like goggles?’

Draco thought about this, not noticing that he’d stopped marching or that all of Dragon Army had automatically stopped with him.

‘Was there anything special about the goggles?’ Draco said.

‘Um …’ Gregory said. ‘They were … greenish, maybe?’

‘Okay,’ said Draco. Again without thinking, he began walking once more and his Dragons followed. ‘Here’s our new strategy. We’re only going to send eleven Dragons against the Chaos Legion, not fourteen. That should be enough to beat them, now that we can neutralize their special advantage.’ It was a gamble, but you had to take gambles sometimes, if you wanted to come in first in a three-way battle.

‘You figured out Chaos’s plan, General Malfoy?’ said Mr Thomas with considerable surprise.

‘What are they doing?’ said Padma.

‘I haven’t the faintest idea,’ said Draco, with a smirk of the most refined smugness. ‘We’ll just do the obvious thing.’

Minerva couldn’t possibly have stood still, she paced back and forth through the Headmaster’s office, the back of her mind half-expecting Severus or Harry to tell her to shut up and sit down, but neither the Potions Master or the Boy-Who-Lived seemed much concerned with her, both of their gazes focused on Albus Dumbledore where he had emerged from the Floo. There were sounds in the background that nobody heard. Severus seemed as passionless as ever, sitting in a small cushioned chair beside the Headmaster’s desk. The old wizard stood terrible and upright by the still-burning fireplace, robed in black like a starless night, radiating power and dismay. All her own thoughts were of utter confusion and horror. Harry Potter sat on a wooden stool with his fingers gripping the seat, and his eyes were fury and freezing ice.

At 6:33am, Quirinus Quirrell had Flooed St. Mungo’s from his office for immediate pickup of Draco Malfoy. Professor Quirrell had found Mr Malfoy in the trophy room of Hogwarts, on the verge of death from the continuing effects of the Blood-Cooling Charm slowly lowering his body temperature. Professor Quirrell had immediately dispelled the Charm, cast stabilizing spells on Mr Malfoy, and levitated him to his office to Floo him to St. Mungo’s for further treatment. After this, Professor Quirrell had informed the Headmaster, stating the facts briefly before vanishing through the Floo; the Aurors, notified by St. Mungo’s, had demanded his presence for questioning.

The clear intent of the Blood-Cooling Charm had been to kill Draco Malfoy so slowly that the wards of Hogwarts, set to detect sudden injury, would not trigger. Under interrogation, Professor Quirrell had told the Aurors that he had cast several tracking Charms upon Mr Malfoy’s person in January, shortly after Mr Malfoy’s return to Hogwarts from the Christmas holidays. Professor Quirrell had cast tracking Charms because he had learned of a person with a motive to harm Mr Malfoy. Professor Quirrell had refused to identify this person. The tracking Charms which Professor Quirrell had cast were triggered by Mr Malfoy’s health falling below an absolute level, rather than by sudden changes, and had therefore alerted Professor Quirrell before Mr Malfoy had died.

Two drops of Veritaserum, sufficient to prevent Mr Malfoy from withholding any meliorating or moderating information in his statements, had shown that Mr Malfoy had – legally under the laws of Noble Houses, illegally under the regulations of Hogwarts – challenged Hermione Granger to a duel. Mr Malfoy had won the duel but had then, as he left, been attacked from behind by Miss Granger with a Stunning Hex. After this Mr Malfoy knew nothing.

Three drops of Veritaserum, requiring her to volunteer all relevant information, had caused Hermione Granger to confess that she had stunned Draco Malfoy from behind, and then, in a fit of anger, cast the Blood-Cooling Charm on him, with the deliberate intention of killing him slowly enough to evade identification from the Hogwarts wards, whose workings she had read about in Hogwarts: A History. She had been horrified at herself upon awakening the next morning, but had not told anyone of what she’d done, believing Draco Malfoy to be already dead – as he certainly would have been after seven hours, had his body’s own magic not been resisting the effects of the Blood-Cooling Charm.

‘Her trial,’ said Albus Dumbledore, ‘is set for tomorrow at noon.’

‘What?’ the word burst out of Harry Potter. The Boy-Who-Lived didn’t rise from his chair, but Minerva saw his fingers whiten where they gripped the wooden seat beneath him. ‘That’s insane! You can’t do a police investigation in one day –’

The Potions Master raised his voice. ‘This is not Muggle Britain, Mr Potter!’ Severus’s face was as expressionless as ever, but the bite in his voice was sharp. ‘The Aurors have an accusation under Veritaserum and a confession under Veritaserum. So far as they are concerned, the investigation is done.’

‘Not quite,’ said Dumbledore, just as Harry seemed ready to explode. ‘I have insisted to Amelia that this matter be given the utmost scrutiny. Unfortunately, as the ill-fated duel was at midnight –’

‘Supposed duel,’ Harry said sharply.

‘As the supposed duel was at midnight – yes, you’re quite right, Harry – it is beyond the range of any Time-Turner –’

‘Also supposedly,’ the Boy-Who-Lived said coldly. ‘And rather suspiciously, since the alleged murder suspect doesn’t know about Time-Turners. I hope that an invisible Auror was immediately sent back in time as far as possible to observe –’

Dumbledore inclined his head. ‘I went myself, Harry, the moment I heard. But by the time I reached the trophy room, Mr Malfoy was already unconscious and Miss Granger had gone –’

‘No,’ said Harry Potter. ‘You reached the trophy room and saw Draco unconscious. That is all you observed, Headmaster. You did not observe Hermione there, or watch her leave. Let us distinguish observation from inference.’ The boy’s head turned to look at her. ‘Imperius, Obliviation, False Memory Charm, Legilimency. Professor McGonagall, am I leaving out any mind-affecting spell that could have made Hermione do this or make her believe she’d done it?’

‘The Confundus Charm,’ she said. And the Dark Arts had never been her study, but she knew – ‘And certain Dark rituals. But none of those could be performed in Hogwarts without alarm.’

The boy nodded, his eyes still directly addressing her. ‘Which of those spells can be detected? Which would the Aurors try to detect?’

‘The Confundus Charm would wear off in a few hours,’ she said, after a moment to gather her thoughts. ‘Miss Granger would remember the Imperius. Obliviation cannot be detected by any known means, but only a Professor could have cast that spell upon a student without alarm from the Hogwarts wards. Legilimency – can only be detected by another Legilimens, I think –’

‘I requested that Miss Granger be examined by the court Legilimens,’ said Dumbledore. ‘The examination showed –’

‘Do we trust him?’ said Harry.

‘Her,’ said Dumbledore. ‘Sophie McJorgenson, whom I remember as an honest student of Ravenclaw, and she is bound by the Unbreakable Vow to tell the truth of what she sees –’

‘Could someone else be Polyjuiced as her?’ Harry Potter interrupted again. ‘What did you observe, Headmaster?’

Albus said heavily, ‘A person who looked like Madam McJorgenson told us that a single Legilimens had lightly touched Miss Granger’s mind some months ago. That is from January, Harry, when I communicated with Miss Granger about the matter of a certain Dementor. That was expected; but what I did not expect was the rest of what Sophie found.’ The old wizard turned to gaze into the Floo fire, letting the orange flames reflect on his face. ‘As you say, Harry, a False Memory Charm is one possibility; they are, when cast perfectly, indistinguishable from true memory –’

‘That doesn’t surprise me,’ Harry interrupted. ‘Studies show that human memories are more or less rewritten every time we remember them –’

‘Harry,’ Minerva said softly, and the boy’s mouth clamped shut.

The old wizard continued. ‘– but a False Memory Charm of such quality requires as much time to create as a true memory. Creating a detailed memory of ten minutes would be ten minutes’ work. And according to the court Legilimens,’ Albus’s face now seemed more tired and lined than before, ‘Miss Granger has been obsessing over Mr Malfoy since the day that Severus … yelled at her. She has been thinking of how Mr Malfoy might be in league with Professor Snape, how he might be planning to harm her and harm Harry – imagining it for hours every day – it would be impossible to create false memories for so much time.’

‘The appearance of insanity …’ Severus murmured softly, as though he were speaking to himself. ‘Could it be natural? No, it is too disastrous to be pure accident; too convenient for someone, I have no doubt. A Muggle drug, perhaps? But that would not be enough – Miss Granger’s madness would have to be guided –’

‘Ah!’ Harry said suddenly. ‘I get it now. The first False Memory Charm was cast on Hermione after Professor Snape yelled at her, and showed, say, Draco and Professor Snape plotting to kill her. Then last night that False Memory was removed by Obliviation, leaving behind the memories of her obsessing about Draco for no apparent reason, at the same time she and Draco were given false memories of the duel.’

Minerva blinked in astonishment. It would have been a thousand years before she thought of that possibility.

The Potions Master was frowning thoughtfully, eyes intent. ‘The reaction to a False Memory Charm is hard to predict in advance, Mr Potter, without Legilimency. The subjects do not always act as expected, when they first remember the false memories. It would have been a risky ploy. But I suppose that is one way Professor Quirrell could have done it.’

‘Professor Quirrell?’ said Harry. ‘What motive does he have to –’

The Potions Master said dryly, ‘The Defence Professor is always a suspect, Mr Potter. You will notice a trend, given time.’

Albus raised up a hand, a silencing gesture, and their heads all turned to look at him. ‘But in this case there is another suspect,’ Albus said quietly. ‘Voldemort.’

That deadliest of unspeakable words seemed to echo around the room, cancelling all the heat from the orange flames of the fireplace.

‘I do not know,’ the old wizard said slowly, ‘I know all too little of the methods of Voldemort’s immortality. He searched out those books before I did, I think. All I could find were ancient tales, scattered across too many volumes for him to remove. But to find truth among many stories is also a wizard’s mastery, and this I have endeavoured to do. There is a human sacrifice, a murder, of that I am certain; committed in coldest blood, the victim dying in horror. And old, old tales of wizards possessed, doing mad deeds, claiming the names of Dark Lords thought defeated; and there is usually a device, of that Dark Lord, which they wield …’ Albus looked at Harry, the ancient eyes searching the younger. ‘I think, Harry – though you will call it only inference – that the act of murder splits the soul. That by ritual of blackest horror, the torn fragment of soul is chained to this world. To a material thing of this world. Which must be, or which then becomes, a device of power.’

Horcrux. The terrible name echoed in Minerva’s mind, though it seemed that – for what reason she did not know – Albus would not speak that word in front of Harry.

‘And therefore,’ the old wizard finished quietly, ‘the remainder of the soul is bound to its chained part, lingering here when its body is destroyed. A sad and painful existence, I think it would be; less than spirit, less than the meanest ghost …’ The old wizard’s eyes were locked on Harry, who gazed back with his eyes narrowed. ‘It would take time for that mutilated soul to regain a mockery of life. That is why we have had our ten-year reprieve, I believe; why Voldemort did not return at once. But in time … that revenant would become capable of rising again.’ The old wizard spoke with grim precision. ‘It is clear, from the stories, that the Dark Lords who return by possessing another’s form, wield lesser magics than they once knew. I do not think Voldemort would be satisfied with that. He would take some other avenue to life. But Voldemort was more Slytherin than Salazar, grasping at every opportunity. He would use his pitiful state, use his power of possession, if he had reason. If he could benefit by another’s … inexplicable fury.’ Albus’s voice had fallen to almost a whisper. ‘That is what I suspect happened to Miss Granger.’

Minerva’s throat was very dry. ‘He’s here,’ she gasped. ‘Here, in Hogwarts –’

And stopped, because the reason Voldemort had come to Hogwarts –

The old wizard glanced at her only briefly, and said, still in that whisper, ‘I am sorry, Minerva, you were right.’

Harry’s voice was edged. ‘Right about what?’

‘Voldemort’s strongest avenue to life,’ Dumbledore said heavily. ‘The most desirable road for him, by which he would rise greater and more terrible than ever before. It is guarded here, within this castle –’

‘Excuse me,’ Harry said politely. ‘Are you stupid?’

‘Harry,’ she said, but there was no force in her voice.

‘I mean, maybe you haven’t noticed this, Headmaster Dumbledore, but this castle is full of children –’

‘I had no choice!’ bellowed Dumbledore. The blue eyes were blazing now, beneath the half-moon spectacles. ‘I do not own it, that thing which Voldemort desires. It belongs to another, and is held here by his consent! I asked if it could be kept in the Department of Mysteries. But he would not permit that – he said it must be within the wards of Hogwarts, in the place of the Founders’ protection –’ Dumbledore passed his hand across his forehead. ‘No,’ the old wizard said in a quieter voice. ‘I cannot pass this blame to him. He is right. There is too much power in that thing, too much that men desire. I agreed that the trap should be laid behind the wards of Hogwarts, in the place of my own power.’ The old wizard bowed his head. ‘I knew Voldemort would worm his way here somehow, and planned to trap him. I did not think – I did not dream – that he would tarry in an enemy fortress one minute longer than he must.’

‘But,’ said Severus in some puzzlement, ‘what would the Dark Lord possibly gain by killing Lucius’s only heir?’

‘Point of order,’ Harry Potter said, a hard edge in his voice. ‘The motives of whoever’s behind this are not the primary issue. Our top priority at this point is that an innocent Hogwarts student is in trouble!’

The green eyes locked with the blue, as Albus Dumbledore gazed back at the Boy-Who-Lived –

‘Quite right, Mr Potter,’ Minerva said, she hadn’t even thought about it, the words just seemed to pop out of her lips. ‘Albus, who is watching over Miss Granger now?’

‘Professor Flitwick has gone to her,’ the Headmaster said.

‘She needs a lawyer,’ Harry said. ‘Anyone who just blurts out “I did it” to the police –’

‘Unfortunately,’ Minerva said, her tone taking on some of Professor Dumbledore’s sternness without thinking, ‘I doubt an attorney will be any use to Miss Granger at this point, Mr Potter. She is to face the judgement of the Wizengamot, and they would be exceedingly unlikely to free her on a technicality.’

Harry was looking at her with an utterly incredulous expression, as though suggesting that Hermione Granger didn’t need an attorney was akin to suggesting that she be set on fire.

‘She is correct, Mr Potter,’ Severus said quietly. ‘Few court processes in this country involve solicitors.’

Harry lifted his glasses and rubbed his eyes, briefly. ‘Fine. How do we get Hermione off the hook, exactly? I suppose it’s too much to hope that with all the lawyers gone, the judges understand the concept of “common sense” and “prior probability” well enough to realize that twelve-year-old girls basically never commit cold-blooded murders?’

‘It is the Wizengamot that she faces,’ said Severus. ‘The oldest Noble Houses, and certain other wizards of influence.’ Severus’s face twisted in something approaching his customary sarcasm. ‘As for them showing common sense – you might as well expect them to make you a bacon sandwich, Potter.’

Harry nodded, his mouth set. ‘Exactly what sort of penalty is Hermione facing? Snapped wand and expulsion –’

‘No,’ Severus said. ‘Nothing that light. Are you wilfully misunderstanding, Potter? She is facing the Wizengamot. There is no set penalty. There is only the vote.’

Harry Potter murmured, ‘The rule of law, in complex times, has proved itself deficient; we much prefer the rule of men, it’s vastly more efficient … There’s no constraining legal rules at all, then?’

Light glinted off the old wizard’s half-moon glasses; he spoke carefully, and not without anger. ‘Legally, Harry, we are dealing with a blood debt from Hermione Granger to the House of Malfoy. The Lord of Malfoy proposes a repayment of that debt, and then the Wizengamot votes on his proposal. That is all.’

‘But …’ Harry said slowly. ‘Lucius was Sorted into Slytherin, he’s got to realize that Hermione was just a pawn. Not the one he should actually be angry at. Right?’

‘No, Harry Potter,’ Albus Dumbledore said heavily. ‘That is how you wish Lucius Malfoy would think. Lucius Malfoy himself … will not share your desire that he think that way.’

Harry gazed at the Headmaster, his eyes growing colder, at the same time that Minerva herself had to clamp down harder on her own emotions, stop her pacing and try to breathe. She’d been trying not to think about it, trying to turn her thoughts away from it, but she knew. She’d known since the instant she’d heard. She could see it in Albus’s eyes –

‘Is she facing capital punishment?’ Harry said quietly, and chills went all the way down Minerva’s spine at the undertones of that voice.

‘No!’ Albus said. ‘No, not the Kiss, not Azkaban, not for a first-year in Hogwarts. Our country is not so lost, not yet.’

‘But Lucius Malfoy,’ Severus said tonelessly, ‘certainly will not be satisfied with only snapping her wand.’

‘All right,’ Harry said commandingly. ‘As I see it, we’ve got two essential lines of attack. Line one, find the real culprit. Line two, other leverage over Lucius. Professor Quirrell saved Draco’s life, does that create a blood debt from House Malfoy to him that he could redeem to cancel Hermione’s?’

Minerva blinked in astonishment again.

‘No,’ Dumbledore said. The old wizard shook his head. ‘It was a clever thought – but no, Harry, I’m afraid not. There is an exception when the Wizengamot suspects that the circumstances of a life-debt may have been created deliberately. And the Defence Professor is hardly above suspicion. Thus Lucius would argue.’

Harry nodded once, face set. ‘Headmaster, I know I said I wouldn’t – but under the circumstances – that time Draco cast that torture hex on me, is that debt enough –’

‘No,’ the old wizard said (even as she blurted ‘What?’ and Severus lifted an eyebrow). ‘It would not have been enough, and now it is no debt at all. You are an Occlumens and cannot testify under Veritaserum. Draco Malfoy could be Obliviated of his own memory before he could testify –’ Albus hesitated. ‘Harry … whatever you have done with Draco, you must assume that Lucius Malfoy will soon know of it.’

Harry’s head sank into his hands. ‘He’ll give Draco Veritaserum.’

‘Yes,’ Albus said quietly.

The Boy-Who-Lived didn’t say anything, as he sat with his head in his hands.

The Potions Master looked genuinely shocked. ‘Draco really was trying to help Miss Granger,’ Severus said. ‘You – Potter, you actually –’

‘Turned him?’ Harry said from between his hands. ‘I was about three-quarters done. Taught him the Patronus Charm and everything. I don’t know what will happen now, though.’

‘Voldemort has struck a grave blow against us, this day,’ Albus said. The sound of old wizard’s voice was like the look of the boy with his head in his hands. ‘He has taken two of our pieces, with one … No. I should have seen it earlier. He has taken two of Harry’s pieces with one move. Voldemort has begun his game again, not against myself, but against Harry. Voldemort knows the prophecy, he knows who his last foe shall be. He is not waiting to face Hermione Granger and Draco Malfoy at Harry’s side when they are grown. He is striking at them now.’

‘Maybe it’s You-Know-Who and maybe it isn’t,’ Harry said, his voice sounding a little unsteady. ‘Let’s not narrow down the hypothesis space prematurely.’ Harry took a breath and lowered his hands. ‘The other thing we can try is to nail the real culprit before the trial – or at least find solid evidence that someone else did it.’

‘Mr Potter,’ said Minerva, ‘Professor Quirrell told the Aurors that he knew of someone with a motive to harm Mr Malfoy. Do you know who he was talking about?’

‘Yes,’ Harry said, after a hesitation. ‘But I think I shall conduct that part of my investigation with the Defence Professor – just as I would not have Professor Quirrell in the room while we were discussing how to investigate him.’

‘He suspects me?’ Severus said, then gave a short laugh. ‘Why, of course he does.’

‘My own plan,’ said Harry, ‘is to go and look at the trophy room where the supposed duel took place and see if I can discover anything anomalous. If you can tell the investigating Aurors to let me through –’

‘What investigating Aurors?’ Severus said tonelessly.

Harry Potter took a deep breath, slowly let it out, and then spoke again. ‘In mystery books it usually takes longer than one day to solve a crime, but twenty-four hours is – no, thirty hours is eighteen hundred minutes. And I can think of at least one other important place to look for clues – though it’ll have to be someone who can get into the Ravenclaw girls’ dorm. Back when Hermione was fighting bullies, she was finding notes under her pillow each morning, telling her where to go –’

‘Albus …’ ground out Minerva.

‘I did not send them,’ said the old wizard. His white eyebrows had lifted in surprise. ‘I knew nothing of this. You think she was being played, Harry?’

‘It’s a possibility,’ Harry said. ‘More so, because there’s a part of this puzzle that you don’t know about yet.’ Harry’s voice lowered, grew more intense. ‘Headmaster, you already know that I got my father’s invisibility cloak from someone who left a note under my pillow, saying it was an early Christmas present. I think we have to assume that’s the same person who left notes for Hermione –’

‘Harry,’ the old wizard said, and hesitated momentarily. ‘Returning your father’s cloak to you, does not seem to me like the act of a villain –’

‘Listen,’ Harry Potter said urgently. ‘The part you don’t know is that after Bellatrix Black escaped from Azkaban, I found another note under my pillow, signed “Santa Claus”, saying that they’d heard you were shutting me up inside Hogwarts, and that they were giving me an escape route to the Salem Witches’ Institute in America. That note came with a deck of cards, in which the King of Hearts was supposedly a portkey –’

‘Mr Potter!’ cried Professor McGonagall, she hadn’t even thought before she spoke. ‘That could well be a kidnapping attempt! You should have told – ’

‘Yes, Professor, I did the sensible thing,’ the boy said levelly. ‘As adapted to the circumstances, I did the sensible thing. I told Professor Quirrell. And according to Professor Quirrell, that portkey goes to somewhere in London – it’s definitely not strong enough to be an international portkey. Now it’s possible that the person who sent the note is honest, and that the point in London is just a way station.’ The boy reached into his robes and took out a deck of cards, along with a folded paper note. ‘I will trust you not to go in guns blazing – I mean wands blazing – just in case the sender is an ally of mine, if not yours. But if this is a trap, I say we spring it now. And whoever it is, take them alive so we can exhibit them before the Wizengamot, I cannot overemphasize that part.’

Severus rose from his chair, his eyes now intent, and moved toward Harry. ‘I’ll need a hair of yours for Polyjuice, Mr Potter –’

‘Let us not be hasty!’ said Albus. ‘We have not yet examined the notes sent to Miss Granger; there may be no resemblance after all. Severus, would you enter her dorm and see if you can find those?’

Harry Potter’s eyebrows had raised, even as he stood to offer the Potions Master better access to his unruly hair. ‘You think two different people are running around Hogwarts leaving notes beneath pillows?’

Severus gave a brief sardonic laugh, as his hand moved forward and plucked a hair, which soon was being carefully wrapped in silk. ‘Quite possibly. If I have learned anything in my tenure as Head of Slytherin, I have learned what ridiculous messes arise when there is more than one plotter and more than one plan. But Headmaster – I think Mr Potter is correct that I should follow this portkey and see where it leads.’

Albus hesitated, and then nodded reluctantly. ‘I will speak to you before you go, then.’

Taboo Tradeoffs, Aftermath 2

When Hermione Granger woke, she found herself lying in a soft, comfortable bed of the Hogwarts infirmary, with a square of setting sunlight falling on her midriff, warm through the thin blanket. Memory said that there would be a screen-sheet above her, either drawn around her bed or open, and that the rest of Madam Pomfrey’s domain would lie beyond: the other beds, occupied or unoccupied, and bright windows set in the curvily-carven stone of Hogwarts.

When Hermione opened her eyes, the first thing she saw was the face of Professor McGonagall, sitting on the left side of her bed. Professor Flitwick wasn’t there, but that was understandable, he’d stayed by her side all morning in the detention cell, his silver raven standing extra guard against the Dementor and his stern little face always turned outward toward the Aurors. The Head of Ravenclaw had surely spent way too much time on her, and probably had to get back to teaching his classes, instead of keeping watch on a convicted attempted-murderess.

She felt horribly, horribly sick and she didn’t think it was because of any potions. Hermione would’ve started crying again, only her throat hurt, her eyes still burned, and her mind just felt tired. She couldn’t have borne to weep again, couldn’t find the strength for tears.

‘Where are my parents?’ Hermione whispered to the Head of House Gryffindor. Somehow it seemed like the worst thing in the world to face them, even worse than everything else; and yet she still wanted to see them.

The gentle look on Professor McGonagall’s face Transfigured into something sadder. ‘I’m sorry, Miss Granger. Though it was not always so, we have found in recent years that it is wiser not to tell the parents of Muggleborns about any danger their child has faced. I should advise you also to remain silent, if you wish to stay at Hogwarts without trouble from them.’

‘I’m not being expelled?’ the girl whispered. ‘For what I did?’

‘No,’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘Miss Granger … surely you heard … I hope you heard Mr Potter, when he said that you were innocent?’

‘He was just saying that,’ she said dully. ‘To get me free, I mean.’

The older witch shook her head firmly. ‘No, Miss Granger. Mr Potter believes you were Memory-Charmed, that the whole duel never happened. The Headmaster suspects even Darker magics may have been involved – that your own hand might have cast the spell, but not your own will. Even Professor Snape finds the affair completely unbelievable, though he may not be able to say so publicly. He was wondering if Muggle drugs might have been used on you.’

Hermione’s eyes went on staring distantly at the Transfiguration Professor; she knew that she’d just been told something significant, but she couldn’t find the energy to propagate any changes through her mind.

‘Surely you don’t believe it?’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘Miss Granger, you cannot believe of yourself that you would turn to murder!’

‘But I –’ Her excellent memory helpfully replayed it for the thousandth time, Draco Malfoy telling her with a sneer that she’d never beat him when he wasn’t tired, and then proceeding to prove just that, dancing like a duellist between the warded trophies while she frantically scrambled, and dealing the ending blow with a hex that sent her crashing against the wall and drew blood from her cheek – and then – then she’d –

‘But you remember doing it,’ said the older witch, who was watching over her with kindly understanding. ‘Miss Granger, there is no need for a twelve-year-old girl to bear such dreadful memories. Say the word and I shall be happy to lock them away for you.’

It was like a glass of warm water thrown into her face. ‘What?’

Professor McGonagall took out her wand, a gesture so practised and quick that it seemed like pointing a finger. ‘I can’t offer to rid you of the memories entirely, Miss Granger,’ the Transfiguration Professor said with her customary precision. ‘There may be important facts buried there. But there is a form of the Memory Charm which is reversible, and I shall be happy to cast that on you.’

Hermione stared at the wand, feeling the stirrings of hope for the first time in almost two days.

Make it not’ve happened … she’d wished that over and over again, for the hands of time to turn back and erase the horrible choice that could never, ever be undone. And if erasing the memory wasn’t that, it was still a kind of release …

She looked back at Professor McGonagall’s kindly face.

‘You really don’t think I did it?’ Hermione said, her voice trembling.

‘I am quite certain you would never do such a thing of your own will.’

Beneath her blankets, Hermione’s hands clutched at the sheets. ‘Harry doesn’t think I did it?’

‘Mr Potter is of the opinion that your memories are entire fabrications. I can rather see his point.’

Then Hermione’s clutching fingers let go of the sheet, and she slumped back into the bed, from which she’d partially risen.

No.

She hadn’t said anything.

She’d woken up and remembered what had happened last night, and it had been like – like – she couldn’t find words even in her own thoughts for what it had been like. But she’d known that Draco Malfoy was already dead, and she hadn’t said anything, hadn’t gone to Professor Flitwick and confessed. She’d just dressed herself and gone down to breakfast and tried to act normal so that nobody would ever know, and she’d known it was wrong and Wrong and horribly horribly WRONG but she’d been so, so scared –

Even if Harry Potter was right, even if the duel with Draco Malfoy was a lie, she’d made that choice all by herself. She didn’t deserve to forget that, or be forgiven for it.

And if she had done the right thing, gone straight to Professor Flitwick, maybe that would’ve – helped, somehow, maybe everyone would’ve seen then that she regretted it, and Harry wouldn’t have had to give away all his money to save her –

Hermione shut her eyes, squeezed them shut really tight, she couldn’t bear to start crying again. ‘I’m a horrible person,’ she said in a wavering voice. ‘I’m awful, I’m not heroic at all –’

Professor McGonagall’s voice was very sharp, like Hermione had just made some dreadful mistake on her Transfiguration homework. ‘Stop being foolish, Miss Granger! Horrible is whoever did this to you. And as for being heroic – well, Miss Granger, you have already heard my opinion about young girls trying to involve themselves in such things before they are even fourteen, so I shall not lecture you on it again. I shall say only that you have just had an absolutely dreadful experience, which you survived as well as any witch in your year possibly could. Today you are allowed to cry as much as you like. Tomorrow you are going back to class.’

That was when Hermione knew that Professor McGonagall couldn’t help her. She needed someone to scold her, she couldn’t be absolved if she couldn’t be blamed, and Professor McGonagall would never do that for her, would never ask so much of a little Ravenclaw girl.

It was something Harry Potter wouldn’t help her with either.

Hermione turned over in the infirmary bed, huddling into herself, away from Professor McGonagall. ‘Please,’ she whispered. ‘I want to talk – to the Headmaster –’

‘Hermione.’

When Hermione Granger opened her eyes a second time, she saw the care-lined face of Albus Dumbledore leaning over her bedside, looking almost as though he’d been crying, though that was impossible; and Hermione felt another stabbing pang of guilt for having bothered him so.

‘Minerva said you wished to speak with me,’ the old wizard said.

‘I –’ Suddenly Hermione didn’t know at all what to say. Her throat locked up, and all she could do was stammer, ‘I – I’m –’

Somehow her tone must have communicated the other word, the one she couldn’t even say any more.

‘Sorry?’ said Dumbledore. ‘Why, for what should you be sorry?’

She had to force the words out of her throat. ‘You were telling Harry – that he shouldn’t pay – so I shouldn’t – have done what Professor McGonagall said, I shouldn’t have touched his wand –’

‘My dear,’ said Dumbledore, ‘had you not pledged yourself to the House of Potter, Harry would have attacked Azkaban single-handedly, and quite possibly won. That boy may choose his words carefully, but I have never yet known him to lie; and in the Boy-Who-Lived there is power that the Dark Lord never knew. He would indeed have tried to break Azkaban, even at cost of his life.’ The old wizard’s voice grew gentler, and kinder. ‘No, Hermione, you have nothing at all for which to blame yourself.’

‘I could have made him not do it.’

In Dumbledore’s eyes a small twinkle appeared before it was lost to weariness. ‘Really, Miss Granger? Perhaps you should be Headmistress in my place, for I myself have no such power over stubborn children.’

‘Harry promised –’ Her voice stopped. The awful truth was very hard to speak. ‘Harry Potter promised me – that he would never help me – if I told him not to.’

There was a pause. The distant noises of the infirmary that had accompanied Professor McGonagall had ceased, Hermione realized, when Dumbledore had awoken her. From where she lay in bed she could see only the ceiling, and the top of one wall’s windows, but nothing in her range of vision moved, and if there were sounds, she could not hear them.

‘Ah,’ said Dumbledore. The old wizard sighed heavily. ‘I suppose it is possible that the boy would have kept his promise.’

‘I should – I should’ve –’

‘Gone to Azkaban of your own will?’ Dumbledore said. ‘Miss Granger, that is more than I would ever ask anyone to take upon themselves.’

‘But –’ Hermione swallowed. She couldn’t help but notice the loophole, anyone who wanted to get through the portrait-door to the Ravenclaw dorm quickly learned to pay attention to exact wordings. ‘But it’s not more than you’d take on yourself.’

‘Hermione –’ the old wizard began.

‘Why?’ said Hermione’s voice, it seemed to be running on without her mind, now. ‘Why couldn’t I be braver? I was going to run in front of the Dementor – for Harry – before, I mean, in January – so why – why – why couldn’t I –’ Why had the thought of being sent to Azkaban just completely unglued her, why had she forgotten everything about being Good –

‘My dear girl,’ Dumbledore said. The blue eyes behind the half-moon glasses showed a complete understanding of her guilt. ‘I would have done no better myself, in my first year in Hogwarts. As you would be kind to others, be kinder to yourself as well.’

‘So I did do the wrong thing.’ Somehow she needed to say that, to be told that, even though she already knew.

There was a pause.

‘Listen, young Ravenclaw,’ the old wizard said, ‘hear me well, for I shall speak to you a truth. Most ill-doers do not think of themselves as evil; indeed, most conceive themselves the heroes of the stories they tell. I once thought that the greatest evil in this world was done in the name of the greater good. I was wrong. Terribly wrong. There is evil in this world which knows itself for evil, and hates the good with all its strength. All fair things does it desire to destroy.’

Hermione shivered in her bed, somehow it seemed very real, when Dumbledore said it.

The old wizard continued speaking. ‘You are one of the fair things of this world, Hermione Granger, and so that evil hates you as well. If you had stayed firm through even this trial, it would have struck you harder and yet harder, until you shattered. Do not think that heroes cannot be broken! We are only more difficult to break, Hermione.’ The old wizard’s eyes had grown sterner than she had ever seen. ‘When you have been exhausted for many hours, when pain and death is not a passing fear but a certainty, then it is harder to be a hero. If I must speak the truth – then today, yes, I would not waver in the face of Azkaban. But when I was a first-year in Hogwarts – I would have fled from the Dementor that you confronted, for my father had died in Azkaban, and I feared them. Know this! The evil that struck at you could have broken anyone, even myself. Only Harry Potter has it within him to face that horror, when he has come fully into his power.’

Hermione’s neck couldn’t stare at the old wizard any longer; she let her head fall back, back to the pillow, where she stared up at the ceiling, absorbing what she could.

‘Why?’ Her voice trembled again. ‘Why would anyone be that evil? I don’t understand.’

‘I, too, have wondered,’ said Dumbledore’s voice, a deep sadness in it. ‘For thrice ten years I wondered, and I still do not understand. You and I will never understand, Hermione Granger. But at least I know now what true evil would say for itself, if we could speak to it and ask why it was evil. It would say, Why not?’

A brief flare of indignation inside her. ‘There’s got to be a million reasons why not!’

‘Indeed,’ said Dumbledore’s voice. ‘A million reasons and more. We will always know those reasons, you and I. If you insist on putting it that way – then yes, Hermione, this day’s trial broke you. But what happens after you break – that, too, is part of being a hero. Which you are, Hermione Granger, and will always be.’

She raised her head again, staring at him.

The old wizard got up from beside her bed. His silver beard dipped down, as Dumbledore bowed to her gravely, and left.

She went on looking at where the old wizard had gone.

It should have meant something to her, should have touched her. Should have made her felt better inside, that Dumbledore, who had seemed so reluctant before, had now acknowledged her as a hero.

She felt nothing.

Hermione let her head fall back to the bed, as Madam Pomfrey came and made her drink something that seared her lips like the afterburn of spicy food, and smelled even hotter, and didn’t taste like anything at all. It meant nothing to her. She went on staring up at the distant stone tiles of the ceiling.

Hypothesis: Hermione Granger
(April 8th, 1992, 6:53pm)

Meanwhile in the Great Hall of Hogwarts, as the students who didn’t have secret meetings with the Headmaster bustled about their dinner around four huge tables –

‘It’s funny,’ Dean Thomas said thoughtfully. ‘I didn’t believe the General when he said that what we learned would change us forever, and we’d never be able to return to a normal life afterwards. Once we knew. Once we saw what he could see.’

‘I know!’ said Seamus Finnigan. ‘I thought it was just a joke too! Like, you know, everything else General Chaos ever said ever.’

‘But now –’ Dean said sadly. ‘We can’t go back, can we? It’d be like going back to a Muggle school after having been to Hogwarts. We’ve just … we’ve just got to stay around each other. That’s all we can do, or we’ll go crazy.’

Seamus Finnigan, next to him, just nodded wordlessly and ate another bite of veldbeest.

Around them, the conversation at the Gryffindor table continued. It wasn’t as relentless as it’d been yesterday, but now and then the topic wandered back.

‘Well, there must’ve been some sort of love triangle,’ said a second-year witch named Samantha Crowley (she never answered when asked if there was any relation). ‘The question is, which ways was it going before it all went wrong? Who was in love with who – and whether or not that person loved them back – I don’t know how many possibilities there are –’

‘Sixty-four,’ said Sarah Varyabil, a blossoming beauty who probably should’ve been Sorted into Ravenclaw or Hufflepuff instead. ‘No, wait, that’s wrong. I mean, if nobody loved Malfoy and Malfoy didn’t love anyone then he wouldn’t really be part of the love triangle … this is going to take Arithmancy, could you all wait two minutes?’

‘I, for one, think it perfectly clear that Granger is Potter’s moirail, and that Potter was auspisticing between Malfoy and Granger.’ The witch who’d spoken nodded with the self-satisfaction of someone who has just precisely nailed down a complicated issue.

‘Those aren’t even words,’ objected a young wizard. ‘You’re just making them up as you go.’

‘Sometimes you can’t describe a thing using real words.’

‘It’s so sad,’ said Sherice Ngaserin, who actually had tears in her eyes. ‘They were just – they were just so obviously meant to be together!’

‘You mean Potter and Malfoy?’ said a second-year named Colleen Johnson. ‘I know – their families hated each other so much, there’s no way they couldn’t fall in love –’

‘No, I mean all three of them,’ said Sherice.

This produced a brief pause in the huddled conversation. Dean Thomas was quietly choking on his lemonade, trying not to make any sounds as it trickled out of his mouth and soaked into his shirt.

‘Wow,’ said a dark-haired witch by the name of Nancy Hua. ‘That’s really … sophisticated of you, Sherice.’

‘Look, all of you, we need to keep this realistic,’ said Eloise Rosen, a tall witch who’d been General of an army and hence spoke with an air of authority. ‘We know – because she kissed him – that Granger was in love with Potter. So the only reason she’d try to kill Malfoy is if she knew that she was losing Potter to him. There’s no need to make it all sound so complicated – you’re all acting like this is a play instead of real life!’

‘But even if Granger was in love, it’s still funny that she’d just snap like that,’ said Chloe, whose black robes combined with her night-black skin to make her look like a darkened silhouette. ‘I don’t know … I think maybe there’s more to this than just a romance novel gone wrong. I think maybe most people haven’t got any idea at all what’s going on.’

‘Yes! Thank you!’ burst out Dean Thomas. ‘Look – don’t you realize – like Harry Potter told us all – if you didn’t predict that something would happen, if it took you completely by surprise, then what you believed about the world when you didn’t see it coming, isn’t enough to explain …’ Dean’s voice trailed off, as he saw that nobody was listening. ‘It’s completely hopeless, isn’t it?’

‘You hadn’t figured that out yet?’ said Lavender Brown, who was sitting across the table from her two fellow former Chaotics. ‘How’d you ever make Lieutenant?’

‘Oh, you two be quiet!’ Sherice snapped at them. ‘It’s obvious you both want the three of them for yourselves!’

‘I mean it!’ Chloe said. ‘What if what’s really going on is different from all the, you know, normal things that all the ordinary people are talking about? What if somebody – made Granger do what she did, just like Potter was trying to tell everyone?’

‘I think Chloe’s right,’ said a foreign-looking boy wizard who always introduced himself as Adrian Turnipseed, though his parents had actually named him Mad Drongo. ‘I think this whole time there’s been …’ Adrian lowered his voice ominously, ‘… a hidden hand …’ Adrian raised his voice again, ‘shaping all that’s happened. One person who’s been behind everything, from the beginning. And I don’t mean Professor Snape, either.’

‘You don’t mean –’ gasped Sarah.

‘Yes,’ Adrian said. ‘The real one behind it all is – Tracey Davis!’

‘That’s what I think too,’ Chloe said. ‘After all –’ She glanced around rapidly. ‘Ever since that thing with the bullies and the ceiling – even the trees in the forests around Hogwarts look like they’re shaking, like they’re afraid –’

Seamus Finnigan was frowning thoughtfully. ‘I think I see where Harry gets his … you know … from,’ Seamus said, lowering his voice so that only Lavender and Dean could hear.

‘Oh, I totally know what you mean,’ Lavender said. She didn’t bother to lower her own voice. ‘It’s a wonder he didn’t crack and just start killing everyone ages ago.’

‘Personally,’ Dean said, also in a quieter voice, ‘I’d say the really scary part is – that could’ve been us.’

‘Yeah,’ said Lavender. ‘It’s a good thing we’re all perfectly sane now.’

Dean and Seamus nodded solemnly.

Hypothesis: G. L. (April 8th, 1992, 8:08pm)

The Floo-Fire of the Headmaster’s office blazed a bright pale-green, the fire concentrating in on itself into a spinning emeraldine whirlwind, and then flared even brighter and spat a human figure into the air –

There was a blur of motion as the resolving figure snapped up a wand, smoothly spinning with the Floo’s momentum like a ballet dance step, so that his firing arc covered the entire 360-degree arc of the room; and then just as abruptly, the figure stopped in place.

In the first instant that Harry saw that man, before Harry even took in the eye, he noticed the scars on the hands, the scars on the face, like the man had been burned and cut over his entire body; though only the man’s hands and face were visible, of all his flesh. The rest of the man’s body was hidden, encased not in robes, but in leather that looked more like armour than clothing; dark grey leather, matching the man’s mop of greyed hair.

The next thing that Harry’s vision comprehended was the brilliant blue eye occupying the right side of the man’s face.

One part of Harry’s mind realized that the person whom Professor McGonagall had named Mad-Eye Moody was the same as the one Dumbledore had called Alastor, within the memory Dumbledore had shown Harry; an image from before whatever event had scarred every inch of the man’s body and taken a chunk out of his nose –

And another part of his mind noticed the jolt of adrenaline. Harry had drawn his wand in sheer reflex when the man had spun out of the Floo like that, there’d been something about it that felt like ambush, Harry’s hand had already started to level his wand for a Somnium before he’d managed to stop himself. Even now the armoured man was holding his wand level, not pointed at any particular person but covering the whole room, and that wand was already in perfect line with his eyes, like a soldier sighting down a gun. There was danger in the man’s stance and the set of his boots, danger in the leather armour he wore and danger in that brilliant blue eye.

When the scarred man spoke, addressing the Headmaster, his voice was edged. ‘I suppose you think this room is secure?’

‘There are only friends here,’ Dumbledore said.

The man’s head jerked toward Harry. ‘That include him?’

‘If Harry Potter is not our friend,’ Dumbledore said gravely, ‘then we are all certainly doomed; so we may as well assume that he is.’

The man’s wand stayed level, not quite pointing at Harry. ‘Boy almost drew on me just then.’

‘Er …’ Harry said. He noticed that his hand was still tightly holding the wand, and consciously relaxed his hand and dropped it back to his side. ‘Sorry about that, you looked a bit … combat-ready.’

The scarred man’s wand moved slightly away from where it had almost pointed at Harry, though it didn’t lower, and the man let out a short bark of laughter. ‘Constant vigilance, eh, lad?’ said the man.

‘It’s not paranoia if they really are out to get you,’ Harry recited the proverb.

The man turned fully toward Harry; and insofar as Harry could read any expression on the scarred face, the man now looked interested.

Dumbledore’s eyes had regained some of the brilliant twinkle that they’d had before the Azkaban breakout, a smile beneath his silver moustache as though that smile had never left. ‘Harry, this is Alastor Moody, called also Mad-Eye, who will command the Order of the Phoenix after me – if anything should happen to me, that is. Alastor, this is Harry Potter. I have every hope the two of you shall get along fantastically.’

‘I’ve heard a good deal about you, boy,’ said Mad-Eye Moody. His one dark natural eye stayed fixed on Harry, while the point of brilliant blue spun frantically, seeming to rotate all the way around within its socket. ‘Not all of it good. Heard they’re calling you the Dementor Spooker, in the Department.’

After some consideration, Harry decided to reply with a knowing smile.

‘How’d you pull off that one, boy?’ the man said softly. Now his blue eye was fixed on Harry as well. ‘I had a little chat with one of the Aurors who escorted the Dementor there from Azkaban. Beth Martin said it came straight from the pit, and no-one gave it any special instructions along the way. Of course, she could be lying.’

‘There wasn’t any sneaky trick to that one,’ Harry said. ‘I just did it the hard way. Of course, I could also be lying.’

Dumbledore was leaning back in his chair, chuckling in the background, like he was just another device in the Headmaster’s Office and that was the sound he made.

The scarred man turned back to face the Headmaster, though his wand stayed pointed low and in Harry’s general direction. When he spoke his voice was gruff and businesslike. ‘I have a lead on a recent host of Voldie’s. You’re certain his shade is in Hogwarts now?’

‘Not certain –’ Dumbledore began.

‘Say what?’ Harry interrupted. After having nearly concluded that the Dark Lord didn’t exist, it was a shock to hear it being discussed that matter-of-factly.

‘Voldie’s host,’ Moody said shortly. ‘The one he possessed before he took over Granger.’

‘If the tales speak true,’ Dumbledore said, ‘there is some device of power which binds Voldemort’s shade to this world; and by that means he may bargain with a host for possession of their body, conferring on them some portion of his power and his pride –’

‘So the obvious question is who’s gained too much power too quickly,’ Moody said abruptly. ‘And it turns out that there’s a fellow who’s gone and banished the Bandon Banshee, staked an entire rogue vampire clan in Asia, tracked down the Wagga-Wagga Werewolf, and exterminated a pack of ghouls using a tea-strainer. And he’s milking it for all it’s worth; there’s been talk of the Order of Merlin. Seems to have turned into a charmer and a politician, not just a powerful wizard.’

‘Dear me,’ murmured Dumbledore. ‘Are you certain that he is not relying on his own skills?’

‘Checked his grades,’ Moody said. ‘Record shows Gilderoy Lockhart received a Troll in his Defence O.W.L.s, didn’t bother with the N.E.W.T. Just the sort of sucker to take the deal Voldie was offering.’ The blue eye whirled crazily within its socket. ‘Unless you remember Lockhart as a student, and think he had enough potential to do all that by himself?’

‘No,’ said Professor McGonagall. She frowned. ‘Not a chance, I should say.’

‘I fear I must agree,’ Dumbledore said with an undertone of pain. ‘Ah, Gilderoy, you poor fool …’

Moody’s grin was more like a snarl. ‘Three in the morning work for you, Albus? Lockhart should be at his home tonight.’

Harry listened to this with increasing alarm, wondering if even the Ministry had any rules about magistrates needing to issue warrants – never mind the illegal vigilante organization Harry now seemed to have joined. ‘Excuse me,’ Harry said. ‘What exactly happens at three in the morning?’

There must have been something in Harry’s voice that gave him away, because the scarred man whirled on him. ‘You have a problem with that, boy?’

Harry paused, trying to figure out how to phrase this to the stranger –

‘You want to take him down yourself?’ pressed the scarred man. ‘Get revenge for your parents, eh?’

‘No,’ Harry said as politely he could. ‘Honestly – look, if we knew for certain he was a willing host for You-Know-Who, that’s one thing, but if we’re not sure and you’re heading off to kill him –’

‘Kill?’ Mad-Eye Moody snorted. ‘It’s what’s locked up in his head,’ Moody tapped his forehead, ‘that we need from him, boy. If we’re lucky, Voldie can’t wipe the sucker’s memories as easy as in his living days, and Lockhart will remember what the horcrux looked like.’

Harry mentally noted down the word horcrux for future research, and said, ‘I’m just worried that someone innocent – what sounds like a pretty decent person, if he did do all that himself – might be about to get hurt.’

‘Aurors hurt people,’ the scarred man said shortly. ‘Bad people, if you’re lucky. Some days you won’t be lucky, and that’s all there is to it. Just remember, Dark Wizards hurt a lot more people than we do.’

Harry took a deep breath. ‘Can you at least try not to hurt this person, in case he’s not –’

‘What is a first-year doing in this room, Albus?’ demanded the scarred man, now whirling to face the Headmaster. ‘And don’t tell me it’s for what he did when he was a baby.’

‘Harry Potter is not an ordinary first-year,’ the Headmaster said quietly. ‘He has already accomplished feats impossible enough to shock even me, Alastor. His is the only intellect in the Order which might someday match that of Voldemort himself, as you or I never could.’

The scarred man leaned over the Headmaster’s desk. ‘He’s a liability. Naive. Doesn’t know a bloody thing about what war’s like. I want him out of here and all his memories of the Order wiped before one of Voldie’s servants plucks them straight out of his mind –’

‘I’m an Occlumens, actually.’

Mad-Eye Moody directed a narrow look at the Headmaster, who nodded.

And then the scarred man turned to face Harry, their gazes meeting.

The sudden fury of the Legilimency attack almost made Harry fall off his chair, as a blade of white-hot steel cut into the imaginary person at the forefront of his mind. Harry hadn’t had a chance to practise since Mr Bester’s training, and Harry very nearly lost his grip on the imaginary person the back-of-his-mind was pretending to be, as that person’s world turned into searing lava and a furious probe of questions. Harry almost lost his grip on only pretending to hallucinate, only pretending to be the imaginary person that was screaming in shock and pain as the Legilimency tore apart his sanity and reshaped him to believe that he was on fire –

Harry managed to break eye contact, dropping his eyes to Moody’s chin.

‘You’re out of practise, boy,’ Moody said. Harry wasn’t looking at the man’s face, but his voice was deadly grim. ‘And I’ll warn you of this but once. Voldie isn’t like any other Legilimens in recorded history. He doesn’t need to look you in the eyes, and if your shields are that rusty he’d creep in so softly you’d never notice a thing.’

‘Duly noted,’ Harry said to the scarred chin. Harry was more shaken than he’d have admitted; Mr Bester hadn’t been anywhere near that powerful, and had never tested Harry like that. Pretending to be someone hurting that much had … Harry couldn’t find words for describing what it felt like to contain an imaginary person in that much pain, but it hadn’t been normal. ‘Do I get any credit for being an Occlumens in the first place?’

‘So you’re think you’re all grown up already, eh? Look me in the eyes!’

Harry strengthened his shields, and looked once more into the dark grey eye and the brilliant blue.

‘Ever watched someone die?’ asked Mad-Eye Moody.

‘My parents,’ Harry said evenly. ‘I recovered the memory in January when I went in front of a Dementor to learn the Patronus Charm. I remember You-Know-Who’s voice –’ A chill went through Harry’s body, his wand twitching in his hand. ‘My main tactical report is that You-Know-Who could speak the Killing Curse in less than half a second, but you probably already knew that.’

There was a gasp from Professor McGonagall’s direction, and Severus’s face had tightened.

‘All right,’ Mad-Eye Moody said softly. A strange, thin grin twisted up the lips within the scarred face. ‘I’ll make you the same offer I’d make to any trainee Auror. Land one touch on me, boy – one hit, one spell – and I’ll concede your right to talk back to me.’

‘Alastor!’ exclaimed Professor McGonagall’s voice. ‘Surely that’s an unreasonable test! Mr Potter, whatever his other merits, does not have a hundred years of fighting experience!’

Harry’s eyes made a lightning dart around the room, passing over the peculiar devices, glancing past Dumbledore and Severus and the Sorting Hat, settling briefly here and there. Harry couldn’t see Professor McGonagall from where he was, but that didn’t matter. There was only one device he’d really wanted to look at, and the point of all the other glances had just been to conceal which one.

‘All righty,’ Harry said, and hopped off his chair, ignoring Professor McGonagall’s inhalation and the Potions Master’s snort of disbelief. Dumbledore’s eyebrows had lifted, and Moody was grinning like a tiger. ‘Be sure to wake me up in forty minutes if he does get me.’ Harry settled into a duellist’s starting stance, his wand held low. ‘Let’s go, then –’

Harry opened his eyes, his head feeling like it had been stuffed with cotton wool.

Everyone else was gone from the Headmaster’s office, the Floo-Fire dimmed; only Dumbledore still waited behind the desk.

‘Hello, Harry,’ the Headmaster said quietly.

‘I didn’t even see him move,’ Harry marvelled, muscles creaking as he sat up.

‘You were standing two paces away from Alastor Moody,’ said Dumbledore, ‘and you took your eye off his wand.’

Harry nodded, as he took the Cloak of Invisibility out of his pouch. ‘I mean – I was taking the duelling stance so that he’d think I was a standard idiot and underestimate me – but I have to admit, that was impressive.’

‘So you planned it all along, Harry?’ Dumbledore said.

‘Of course,’ Harry said. ‘Note how I’m doing this as soon as I wake up, rather than pausing to think of it.’

Harry drew the hood of the Cloak over his head, and glanced back up at the wall clock he’d surreptitiously glanced at earlier.

It had then shown around twenty-three minutes after eight, and now it was five minutes after nine.

Minerva stared as the boy put himself into the duelling stance, his wand held low. For a second Minerva wondered if Harry might possibly – no, that was completely ridiculous, it was Mad-Eye Moody and that was beyond impossible. Of course that was what she’d thought about his partial Transfiguration, too …

‘Let’s go, then,’ Harry said and fell over.

Severus gave a single chuckle. ‘Mr Potter has his points, I must confess,’ the Potions Master said. ‘Though I would never say it while he was awake, and if you repeat the words I shall deny them, for the boy’s ego is quite large enough already. Mr Potter does have his points, Mad-Eye, but duelling is not among them.’

Mad-Eye’s own chuckle was lower and grimmer. ‘Oh, yes,’ said Mad-Eye. ‘Only fools duel. Standing like that and waiting for me to attack, what was the boy thinking? Why, I ought to give him a scar, to remember this occasion –’

‘Alastor!’ barked Albus, just as she cried ‘Stop!’, Severus dashed forward, and Mad-Eye Moody deliberately levelled his wand on Harry Potter’s body.

‘Stupefy!’

Mad-Eye’s body seemed to almost flicker as he spun on his wooden foot like lightning, faster than she’d ever seen anyone move without magic, the red Stunning Hex passing through the suddenly empty air and barely missing Severus to crash into the opposite wall, and by the time her eyes jerked back to Moody there were seventeen radiant orbs in the pattern of a Sagitta Magica, visible for only an instant before they streaked brilliance and struck something that fell to the floor with a thud –

‘Hello again, Harry,’ said Dumbledore.

‘I cannot believe that guy’s reaction time,’ Harry said, brushing off his Cloak as he stood up from where he’d been lying invisible on the floor, unseen by his previous self. ‘I can’t believe his movement speed either. I’m going to have to figure out some way to zap him without speaking an incantation that gives it away …’

– and then Mad-Eye ducked hard and fast, his hands hitting flat on the floor. She almost didn’t see the two tiny white threads passing through the space he’d been, but her eyes went to the blue spark when the threads impacted on one of the Headmaster’s devices, and by the time she managed to turn her eyes back, Mad-Eye had spun smoothly up to his feet, his wand was dancing unseeably fast and there was another thudding sound –

‘Hello again, Harry.’

‘Pardon me, Headmaster, but could you let me go down your stairs, and then come back up again, before I make the final jump backward? This is going to take longer than one hour of preparation –’

Minerva gaped at Mad-Eye Moody, who hadn’t lowered his wand in the slightest; and Severus had a look on his face that was almost like shock.

‘Well, boy?’ said Mad-Eye Moody. ‘What else have you got?’

Harry Potter’s head appeared, floating in mid-air as an invisible hand drew back the hood of his invisibility cloak.

‘That eye,’ said Harry Potter. There was a strange fierce light in the boy’s eyes. ‘That isn’t any ordinary device. It can see right through my invisibility cloak. You dodged my Transfigured taser as soon as I started raising it, even though I didn’t speak any incantations. And now that I’ve watched it again – you spotted all my Time-Turned selves the moment you Flooed into this room, didn’t you?’

Mad-Eye Moody was smiling, the same teeth-bared grin she’d seen him wear as they’d faced off against Voldemort himself. ‘Spend a hundred years hunting Dark wizards, and you see everything,’ said Moody. ‘I once arrested a young Japanese who tried a similar trick. He found out the hard way that his shadow replica technique was no match for this eye of mine.’

‘You see in all directions,’ Harry Potter said, that strange fierce light still in his gaze. ‘No matter where that eye is pointing, it sees everything around you.’

Moody’s tiger-grin grew wider. ‘There’s no more of you in this room, now,’ Mad-Eye said. ‘Think that’s because you’ll give up after this time, or because you’ll win? Any bets, boy?’

‘It’s my final attempt because I decided to stake my last three hours on one shot,’ said Harry Potter. ‘As for whether I win –’

There was a blur filling the whole air of the Headmaster’s office. Mad-Eye Moody leapt to one side with blinding speed and an instant later Harry’s head darted backward as he cried ‘Stuporfy!’

Three shimmers in the air went past Harry’s moving head, just as a red bolt erupted from Harry’s location, shooting past Moody as he dodged in yet another direction –

If she’d blinked, she would have missed it, the red bolt making an angled turn in mid-air and slamming into Moody’s ear.

Moody fell.

Harry Potter’s floating head dropped to the height of a first-year on their hands and knees, then dropped further to the ground, his face showing sudden exhaustion.

Minerva McGonagall said, ‘What in Merlin’s name just –’

‘So you went to Flitwick, then,’ Moody said. The retired Auror was now sitting in a chair, drinking long draughts from a restorative in a bottle he’d taken off his belt.

Harry Potter nodded, now sitting in his own chair instead of perched on an armrest. ‘I tried the Defence Professor first, but –’ The boy grimaced. ‘He … wasn’t available. Well, I’d decided it was worth risking five House points, and if you say a risk is worth it, you can’t complain when you have to pay up. Anyway, I figured that if you had an eye that saw things other people couldn’t see, then as Isaac Asimov pointed out in Second Foundation, the weapon to use is a brilliant light. Read enough science fiction, you know, and you’ll read everything at least once. Anyway, I told Professor Flitwick that I needed a Charm that would make a huge number of shapes, bright and flickering and filling the whole office, but invisible, so only your eye could see them. I had no idea what it would even mean to cast an illusion and then make it invisible, but I figured if I didn’t mention that out loud, Professor Flitwick would just do it anyway, and he did. Turns out there was no spell like that I could cast myself, but Flitwick Charmed me a one-time device for it – though I had to persuade him that it wasn’t cheating, since nothing could possibly be cheating against an Auror who’d lived long enough to retire. And then I still didn’t see how I could hit you, when you were moving that fast. So I asked about targeted spells, and that was when Flitwick showed me that hex I cast at the end, the Swerving Stunner. It’s one of Professor Flitwick’s own inventions – he’s a champion duellist as well as a Charms Master –’

‘I know that, son.’

‘Sorry. Anyway, the Professor says he left the duelling circuit before he got a chance to use that spell, since it only works as a finishing move on an unshielded opponent. The hex gets as close to the target as possible along its original trajectory, and then once it detects that the target is getting more distant again, the hex turns in mid-air and heads straight for the target. It can only swerve once – but the incantation sounds very close to “Stupefy” and the hex is the same red colour, so if the enemy thinks it’s a regular Stunning Hex and tries a normal dodge, that mid-air retargeting will finish them off. Oh, and the Professor requested that none of us talk about his special move, just in case he does get a chance to use it during competition some day.’

‘But –’ said Professor McGonagall. She glanced at Mad-Eye Moody, who was nodding his approval, and at Severus, who was keeping his face decidedly blank. ‘Mr Potter, you just stunned Mad-Eye Moody! The most famous Dark wizard hunter in the history of the Auror Office! That should’ve been impossible!’

Moody let out a dark chuckle. ‘What’s your answer to that one, kid? I’m curious.’

‘Well …’ Harry said. ‘First of all, Professor McGonagall, neither of us was fighting seriously.’

‘Neither of you?’

‘Of course,’ Harry said. ‘In a serious fight, Mr Moody would’ve dropped all my copies immediately without waiting for them to attack. And on my side, if it was actually necessary to take down the most famous Auror in the history of the office, I’d get Headmaster Dumbledore to do it for me. And beyond that … since that wasn’t a real fight …’ Harry paused. ‘How can I put this? Wizards are used to duels where people fight back and forth with spells for a while. But if two Muggles with guns stand in a small room and fire bullets at each other … then whoever hits first, wins. And if one of them is deliberately missing his shots, giving the other person one chance after another – like Mr Moody gave me one chance after another – well, you’d have to be pretty pathetic to lose.’

‘Oh, not that pathetic,’ Moody said with a slightly threatening grin.

Harry didn’t seem to notice. ‘You might say that Mr Moody was testing me to see if I would try to fight him, or try to win. That is, whether I’d carry out the role of somebody fighting – use standard spells I already knew, even though I didn’t expect the consequences of that action to be victory – or if I’d search through unusual plans until I found something that could win. Like the difference between a student who sits in class because that’s what students do, versus a student who cares enough to ask themselves what it takes to actually learn a piece of material, and practises however necessary – you see, Professor McGonagall? When you look at it that way – realize that Mr Moody was giving me chances, and that I shouldn’t attack in the first place unless I think I can win – then I don’t come out looking so well, since it actually took me three tries to get him. Plus, like I said, in a real fight Mr Moody could’ve turned himself invisible, or put up shields –’

‘Don’t go relying too much on shields, boy,’ Mad-Eye said. The leather-clad Auror took another sip from his restorative flask. ‘What you learn in your first year at the academy doesn’t stay true forever, not against the strongest Dark Wizards. Every shield ever made, there’s some curse that goes straight through it, if you’re not quick enough to cast the counter. And there’s one curse that goes through everything, and it’s a curse any Death Eater will use.’

Harry Potter nodded gravely. ‘Right, some spells are impossible to block. I’ll remember that, in case anyone casts the Killing Curse at me. Again.’

‘That kind of cleverness gets people killed, boy, and don’t you forget it.’

A sad-sounding sigh from the Boy-Who-Lived. ‘I know. Sorry.’

‘So, son. You had something to say about when Albus and I go after Lockhart?’

Harry opened his mouth, then paused. ‘I won’t tell you how to run a war,’ the Boy-Who-Lived said eventually. ‘I don’t have any experience at that. All I know is that there are consequences. Please be advised that my own assessment is that Lockhart is probably innocent, so if you can avoid hurting him without too much risk –’ The boy shrugged. ‘I don’t know the cost. Just please, if you can, be careful not to hurt him if he’s innocent.’

‘If I can,’ said Moody.

‘And – you’re aiming to look through his mind for evidence about the Dark Lord, aren’t you? I don’t know what the rules are in magical Britain about admissible evidence – but everyone’s always guilty of breaking some law or another, there’s just too many laws. So if it’s not about the Dark Lord, don’t turn him in to the Ministry, just Obliviate him and go, okay?’

Moody frowned. ‘Son, nobody gains power that fast without being up to something.’

‘Then leave it for the ordinary Aurors, if and when they find evidence the ordinary way. Please, Mr Moody. Call it a quirk of my Muggle upbringing, but if it’s not about the war I don’t want us to be the evil police who break into people’s houses in the middle of the night, rummage through their minds and send them off to Azkaban.’

‘I don’t see the sense of it, son, but I suppose I could do you the favour.’

‘Is there aught else, Alastor?’ inquired Albus.

‘Yes,’ said Moody. ‘About that Defence Professor of yours –’

Hypothesis: Gilderoy Lockhart: END

Hypothesis: Dumbledore
(April 9th, 1992, 5:32pm)

As Professor Quirrell slowly raised up his tea, the teacup jerked in mid-air, sending the dark translucent liquid just barely slopping over the side, so that only three single drops crawled down the side of the teacup. Harry would have missed it, if he hadn’t happened to be watching closely; for Professor Quirrell’s hand was perfectly steady on the cup before and after.

If that small jerky motion advanced to a constant tremor, it would be the end of any non-wandless magic for the Defence Professor. Wandwork had no room for trembling fingers. How much that would actually handicap Professor Quirrell, if at all, Harry couldn’t guess. The Defence Professor was certainly capable of wandless magic, yet still tended to use a wand for larger things – but for him that might only be a convenience …

‘Insanity,’ said Professor Quirrell, as he carefully sipped from his tea – he was looking at the teacup, not at Harry, which was unusual for him – ‘can be a signature all its own.’

The Defence Professor’s small office was silent, the sound-warded room quiet in a way the Headmaster’s office never could be. Sometimes the two of them both happened to finish exhaling or inhaling at the same time; and then there was an auditory emptiness that was almost a sound in itself.

‘I’ll agree with that in one sense,’ Harry said. ‘If somebody tells me that everyone is staring at them and that their underwear is being dusted with thought-controlling powder, I know they’re psychotic, because that’s the standard signature of psychosis. But if you tell me that anything confusing points to Albus Dumbledore as a suspect, that seems … overreaching. Just because I can’t see a purpose doesn’t mean there is no purpose.’

‘Purposeless?’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Oh, but the madness of Dumbledore is not that he is purposeless, but that he has too many purposes. The Headmaster might have planned this to make Lucius Malfoy throw away his game for vengeance on you – or it might be a dozen other plots. Who knows what the Headmaster thinks he has reason to do, when he has found reason to do so many strange things already?’

Harry had politely declined tea, even knowing that Professor Quirrell would know what it meant. He’d considered bringing his own can of soda – but had decided against that as well, after realizing how easy it would be for the Defence Professor to teleport in a bit of potion, even if the two of them couldn’t touch each other with direct magic.

‘I have seen a little now of Dumbledore,’ Harry said. ‘Unless everything I have seen is a lie, I find it difficult to believe that he would plot to send any Hogwarts student to Azkaban. Ever.’

‘Ah,’ the Defence Professor said softly, the tiny reflection of the teacup gleaming in his pale eyes. ‘But perhaps that is another signature, Mr Potter. You have not yet comprehended the perspective of a man like Dumbledore. If he must, in some sufficiently noble cause, sacrifice a student – why, who would he choose, but she who declared herself a heroine?’

That gave Harry some pause. It might just be hindsight bias, but that did seem to concentrate some of that hypotheses’ probability mass onto framing Hermione in particular. Similarly, Professor Quirrell had predicted in advance that Dumbledore might target Draco …

But if it’s you behind all of this, Professor, you might have shaped your plans to frame the Headmaster, and taken care to cast suspicion on him in advance.

The concept of evidence had something of a different meaning, when you were dealing with someone who had declared themselves to play the game at one level higher than you.

‘I see your point, Professor,’ Harry said evenly, giving no hint of his other thoughts. ‘So you think it most probable that it was the Headmaster who framed Hermione?’

‘Not necessarily, Mr Potter.’ Professor Quirrell drained his teacup in one swallow and then set it down, the cup making a sharp rap as it descended. ‘There is also Severus Snape – though what he might think to gain from this, I could not guess. Thus he is not my prime suspect either.’

‘Then who is?’ Harry said, somewhat puzzled. Professor Quirrell surely wasn’t about to reply You-Know-Who –

‘The Aurors have a rule,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Investigate the victim. Many would-be criminals imagine that if they are the apparent victims of a crime, they shall not be suspected. So many criminals imagine it, indeed, that every senior Auror has seen it a dozen times over.’

‘You’re not seriously trying to convince me that Hermione –’

The Defence Professor was giving Harry one of those slit-eyed looks that meant he was being stupid.

Draco? Draco had been interrogated under Veritaserum – but Lucius might have had enough control to subvert Aurors to … oh.

‘You think Lucius Malfoy set up his own son?’ Harry said.

‘Why not?’ Professor Quirrell said softly. ‘From Mr Malfoy’s recorded testimony, Mr Potter, I gather that you enjoyed some success in changing Mr Malfoy’s political views. If Lucius Malfoy learned of that earlier … he might have decided that his former heir had become a liability.’

‘I don’t buy it,’ Harry said flatly.

‘You are being wantonly naive, Mr Potter. The history books are full of family disputes turned murderous, for inconveniences and threats far less than those which Mr Malfoy posed to his father. I suppose next you will tell me that Lord Malfoy of the Death Eaters is far too gentle to wish his son such harm.’ A tinge of heavy sarcasm.

‘Well, yes, frankly,’ Harry said. ‘Love is real, Professor, a phenomenon with observable effects. Brains are real, emotions are real, and love is as much a part of the real world as apples and trees. If you made experimental predictions without taking parental love into account, you’d have a heck of a time explaining why my own parents didn’t abandon me at an orphanage after the Incident with the Science Project.’

The Defence Professor did not react to this at all.

Harry continued. ‘From what Draco says, Lucius prioritized him over important Wizengamot votes. That’s significant evidence, since there’s less expensive ways to fake love, if you just want to fake it. And it’s not like the prior probability of a parent loving their child is low. I suppose it’s possible that Lucius was just taking on the role of a loving father, and he renounced that role after he learned Draco was consorting with Muggleborns. But as the saying goes, Professor, one must distinguish possibility from probability.’

‘All the better the crime,’ the Defence Professor said, still in that soft tone, ‘if no one would believe it of him.’

‘And how would Lucius even Memory-Charm Hermione in the first place, without setting off the wards? He’s not a Professor – oh, right, you think it’s Professor Snape.’

‘Wrong,’ said the Defence Professor. ‘Lucius Malfoy would trust no servant with that mission. But suppose some Hogwarts Professor, intelligent enough to cast a well-formed Memory Charm but of no great fighting ability, is visiting Hogsmeade. From a dark alley the black-clad form of Malfoy steps forth – he would go in person, for this – and speaks to her a single word.’

‘Imperio.’

‘Legilimens, rather,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I do not know if the Hogwarts wards would trigger for a returning Professor under the Imperius Curse. And if I do not know, Malfoy probably does not know either. But Malfoy is a perfect Occlumens at least; he might be able to use Legilimency. And for the target … perhaps Aurora Sinistra; none would question the Astronomy Professor moving about at night.’

‘Or even more obviously, Professor Sprout,’ said Harry. ‘Since she’s the last person anyone would suspect.’

The Defence Professor hesitated minutely. ‘Perhaps.’

‘Actually,’ Harry said then, putting a thoughtful frown on his face, ‘I don’t suppose you know offhand if any of the current Professors at Hogwarts were around back when Mr Hagrid got framed in 1943?’

‘Dumbledore taught Transfiguration, Kettleburn taught Magical Creatures, and Vector taught Arithmancy,’ Professor Quirrell said at once. ‘And I believe that Bathsheda Babbling, now of Ancient Runes, was then a Ravenclaw prefect. But Mr Potter, there is no reason to suppose that anyone besides You-Know-Who was involved in that affair.’

Harry shrugged artfully. ‘Seemed worth asking the question, just to check. Anyway, Professor, I agree it’s possible that some outsider Legilimized a member of Hogwarts staff – and then Obliviated them afterwards, there’s no way anyone would forget that part. But I don’t think Lucius Malfoy is a probable candidate for the mastermind. It’s possible but not probable that all of Lucius’s apparent love for Draco was just a sense of duty, and that it all went up in a puff of smoke. It’s possible though not probable that everything Lucius did in front of the Wizengamot was just an act. People’s outsides do not always resemble their insides, like you said. But there’s one piece of evidence that doesn’t fit at all.’

‘And that would be?’ said the Defence Professor, his eyes half-lidded.

‘Lucius tried to reject a hundred thousand Galleons for Hermione’s life. I saw how surprised the Wizengamot was, when Lucius said he was refusing it despite the rules of honour. The Wizengamot didn’t expect that of him. Why wouldn’t he just take the money while acting all indignant and pretending to grit his teeth? He wouldn’t actually care that much about throwing Hermione into Azkaban.’

There was a pause. ‘Perhaps the role he was playing ran away with him,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘It does happen, Mr Potter, in the heat of the moment.’

‘Perhaps,’ Harry said. ‘But it’s still one more improbability to be postulated – and by the time you have to add up that many excuses in a theory, it can’t be at the top of the list any more. Anything else in particular you think I ought to think about, within the range of all other possibilities?’

There was a long silence. The Defence Professor’s eyes dropped down to look at the empty teacup before them, seeming unusually distant.

‘I suppose I can think of one final suspect,’ the Defence Professor said at last.

Harry nodded.

The Defence Professor didn’t seem to notice, but only spoke on. ‘Has the Headmaster has told you anything – even a hint – about Professor Trelawney’s prophecy?’

‘Huh?’ Harry said automatically, converting his own sudden shock into the best dissembling he could manage. It probably was at the wrong level to fool Professor Quirrell but Harry certainly couldn’t take time to think before replying – wait, but how on Earth would Professor Quirrell know about that – ‘Professor Trelawney made a prophecy?’

‘You were there to hear its beginning,’ Professor Quirrell said, frowning. ‘You called out to the entire school that the prophecy could not be about you, since you were not coming here, you were already here.’

He is coming. The one who will tear apart the very –

And that was as far as Professor Trelawney had got before Dumbledore had grabbed her and vanished.

‘Oh, that prophecy,’ Harry said. ‘Sorry! It went clear out of my mind.’

Harry thought he’d put too much force into the end statement, and was 80%-expecting Professor Quirrell to say, Aha, now Mr Potter, what is this mysterious other prophecy you went to such lengths to deny –

‘That is foolish,’ the Defence Professor said sharply, ‘if indeed you are telling me the truth. Prophecies are not trivial things. I have racked my brain much over the little that I heard, but such a small fragment is simply too little.’

‘You think the one who’s coming is the one who might’ve framed Hermione?’ said Harry. As his mind allocated yet another hypothesis, uncertain predicate referent, he-who-is-coming.

‘With no offense meant to Miss Granger,’ the Defence Professor said with another frown, ‘her life or death does not seem that important. But someone was to come – one who, in your interpretation, was not already there – and someone so significant, and unknown as a player … who knows what else they may have done?’

Harry nodded, and mentally sighed because he was going to have to redo his Lord-Voldemort odds calculation with yet another piece of evidence in the mix.

Professor Quirrell spoke with eyes half-lidded, looking out like through slits. ‘More than the question of whom the prophecy spoke – who was meant to hear it? It is said that fates are spoken to those with the power to cause them or avert them. Dumbledore. Myself. You. As a distant fourth, Severus Snape. But of those four, Dumbledore and Snape would often be in Trelawney’s presence. You and I are the ones who would not have spent much time around her before that Sunday. I think it quite likely that the prophecy was meant for one of us – before Dumbledore took the prophetess away. Did the Headmaster say nothing more to you?’ Professor Quirrell’s voice was demanding now. ‘I thought I heard too much force in that denial, Mr Potter.’

‘Honestly, no,’ Harry said. ‘It had honestly slipped clear out of my mind.’

‘Then I am rather put out with him,’ Professor Quirrell said softly. ‘In fact, I think that I am angry.’

Harry said nothing. He didn’t even sweat. It might’ve been a poor reason for confidence, but on this particular score, Harry did happen to be innocent.

Professor Quirrell nodded once, sharply, as though in acknowledgement. ‘If there is nothing more to say between us, Mr Potter, you may go.’

‘I can think of one other suspect,’ Harry said. ‘Someone you didn’t put on your list at all. Would you analyse him to me, Professor?’

There was another of those moments of silence that was almost a sound in itself.

‘As for that suspect,’ the Defence Professor said softly, ‘I think you shall prosecute him on your own, Mr Potter, without help from me. I have heard such requests before, and experience leads me to refuse. Either I will do too good a job of prosecuting myself, and convince you that I am guilty – or else you will decide that my prosecution was too half-hearted, and that I am guilty. I will remark only this in my defence – that I would have needed a very good reason indeed to jeopardize your fragile alliance with the heir to House Malfoy.’

Hypothesis: The Defence Professor
(April 8th, 1992, 8:37pm)

‘… so I fear I must take my leave,’ Dumbledore was saying gravely. ‘I promised Quirinus … that is to say, I promised the Defence Professor … that I would not make any attempt to uncover his true identity, in my own person or any other.’

‘And why’d you make a fool promise like that, then?’ snapped Mad-Eye Moody.

‘It was an unalterable condition of his employment, or so he said.’ Dumbledore glanced at Professor McGonagall, a wry smile briefly flitting over his face. ‘And Minerva made it clear to me that Hogwarts required a competent Defence Professor this year, even if I had to haul Grindelwald out of Nurmengard and prevail on old affections to persuade him to take the position.’

‘I did not quite phrase it in that fashion –’

‘Your expression said it for you, my dear.’

And so soon the four of them – Harry, Professor McGonagall, the Potions Master, and Alastor Moody aka Mad-Eye – were ensconced all by themselves in the Headmaster’s office.

It was strange how the Headmaster’s office seemed … unbalanced … without the Headmaster in it. If you didn’t have the ancient wizened master to make it all seem solemn, you were just four people trying to have a serious meeting while surrounded by bizarre, noisy gadgets. Clearly visible from where Harry had perched himself on his chair’s arm was a truncated-conical object, like a cone with its top snipped off, slowly spinning around a pulsating central light which it shaded but did not obscure; and each time the inner light pulsated, the assembly made a vroop-vroop-vroop sound that sounded oddly distant, muffled like it was coming from behind four solid walls, even though the spinning-conical-section thingy was only a metre or two away.

Vroop … vroop … vroop …

And then there were the various still-breathing bodies of Harry Potter he’d stashed in one quiet corner, cleaning up a mess that was his own in more ways than one. (Only one body wasn’t inside a copy of the Invisibility Cloak; but then it merely took a small effort of concentration for Harry to perceive his other selves beneath the Cloak of which he was master – an effort which Harry had carefully not put forth earlier, to avoid getting advance temporal information he wanted to determine by his own decision.) The sad thing was that by this point, having his own body visibly lying in a corner didn’t seem all that crazy. It was just … Hogwarts.

‘All right, then,’ Moody said, looking rather sour about it. From within his leather armour, the scarred man took out a black folder. ‘This is a copy of what Amelia’s people put together. She almost certainly knows we’ve got it, but it’s all off the books, that clear? Anyway –’

And Moody told them who the Department of Magical Law Enforcement thought Quirinus Quirrell really was. A seemingly ordinary Hogwarts student (though talented enough that he’d only narrowly missed being Head Boy) who’d gone on holiday to Albania after his graduation, disappeared, returned after 25 years, and then been caught up in the Wizarding War –

‘It was murdering the House of Monroe that made Voldie’s name,’ Moody said. ‘Until then, he was just another Dark Wizard with delusions of grandeur and Bellatrix Black. But after that –’ Moody snorted. ‘Every fool in the country flocked to serve him. You would’ve hoped the Wizengamot would turn serious, once they realized Voldie was willing to kill their own sacred selves. And that’s just what the bastards did – hope that some other bastard would turn serious. None of the cowards wanted to step in front. It was Monroe, Crouch, Bones, and Longbottom. That was nearly everyone in the Ministry who’d dare say a word that might give Voldie offense.’

‘That was how your House came to be ennobled, Mr Potter,’ injected the solemn voice of Professor McGonagall. ‘There is an ancient law that if anyone ends a Most Ancient House, whoever avenges that blood will be made Noble. To be sure, the House of Potter was already older than some lines called Ancient. But yours was titled a Noble House of Britain after the end of the war, in recognition that you had avenged the Most Ancient House of Monroe.’

‘Flush of gratitude and all that,’ Mad-Eye Moody said sourly. ‘It didn’t last, but at least James and Lily got a fancy title and a useless medal to take to their graves. But that’s leaving out eight years of complete horror after Monroe disappeared and Regulus Black – he was Monroe’s private source in the Death Eaters, we’re pretty sure – was executed by Voldie. Like a dam breaking and gore flooding out, drowning the whole country. Albus bloody Dumbledore himself had to step into Monroe’s shoes, and that was barely enough for us to survive.’

Harry listened with an odd sense of unreality. Some of it felt right, matched up with observation – especially with the speech Professor Quirrell had made before Christmas – and yet …

This was Professor Quirrell they were talking about.

‘So that’s who the Department thinks is your Defence Professor,’ Mad-Eye Moody finished up his account. ‘Now what do you think, son?’

‘Well …’ Harry said slowly. It is also possible to have a mask behind the mask. ‘The obvious next thought is that this “David Monroe” person died in the war after all, and this is just someone else pretending to be David Monroe pretending to be Quirinus Quirrell.’

‘That’s obvious?’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘Dear Merlin …’

‘Really, boy?’ said Mad-Eye Moody, his blue eye spinning rapidly. ‘I’d say that’s a little … paranoid.’

You don’t know Professor Quirrell, Harry did not say. ‘It’s an easy theory to test,’ Harry said out loud. ‘Just check whether the Defence Professor remembers something about the war that the real David Monroe would’ve known. Though I suppose, if he’s playing the part of David Monroe pretending to be someone else, he has a good excuse to pretend he’s pretending he doesn’t know what you’re talking about –’

‘A little paranoid,’ said the scarred man, his voice rising. ‘Not paranoid enough! Constant vigilance! Think about it, lad – what if the real David Monroe never came back from Albania?’

There was a pause.

‘I see …’ Harry said.

‘Of course you do,’ Professor McGonagall said. ‘Don’t mind me, please. I’ll just sit here quietly going mad.’

‘In this line of work, if you survive, you learn that there’s three kinds of Dark Wizards,’ Moody said grimly; his wand wasn’t pointed at anyone, it was angled slightly downward, but it was in his hand. It had never left his hand since the moment he’d entered the room. ‘There’s Dark Wizards that have one name. There’s Dark Wizards that have two names. And there’s Dark Wizards that change names like you and I change clothes. I saw “Monroe” go through three Death Eaters like he was snapping twigs. There’s not many wizards that good at age forty-five. Dumbledore, maybe, but not many others.’

‘Perhaps that is true,’ said the Potions Master from where he was lurking. ‘But what of it, Mad-Eye? Whatever his identity, Monroe was surely the Dark Lord’s enemy. I’ve heard Death Eaters curse his name even after they thought him dead. They feared him well.’

‘So far as Defence Professors are concerned,’ Professor McGonagall said primly, ‘I shall take it and be grateful.’

Moody swung around to glare at her. ‘Just where the devil was “Monroe” all those years he was gone, eh? Maybe he thought he could make a name for himself in Britain by opposing Voldie, and vanished away when he found out he was wrong. Then why’d he come back now, hah? What’s his new plan?’

‘He, ah …’ Harry ventured tentatively. ‘He says he always wanted to be a great Defence Professor because all the best fighting wizards have taught at Hogwarts. And he kind of is being an incredibly good Defence Professor, actually … I mean, if he just wanted to keep up a disguise, he could get away with much sloppier work …’

Professor McGonagall was nodding firmly.

‘Naive,’ Moody said flatly. ‘I suppose you haven’t wondered if your Defence Professor set up the whole House of Monroe to be wiped out?’

‘What?’ cried Professor McGonagall.

‘Our mystery wizard hears about a missing kid from a Most Ancient House of Britain,’ Moody said. ‘Steps into the shoes of “David Monroe”, but stays away from the real Monroe family. But eventually the House is bound to notice something wrong. So this imposter somehow prods Voldie into wiping them all out – maybe leaked a password they’d given him for their wards – and then he was a Lord of the Wizengamot!’

There seemed to be a fight going on inside Harry’s mind between Hufflepuff One, who’d never trusted the Defence Professor in the first place; and Hufflepuff Two, who was far too loyal to Harry’s friend, Professor Quirrell, to believe something like that just because Moody said so.

It is kind of obvious, though, observed his Slytherin part. I mean, do you actually believe that under natural circumstances, anyone would end up as the last heir to a Most Ancient House and Lord Voldemort killed his family and he has to avenge his martial arts sensei? If anything I’d say he went too far over the top in setting up his new identity as the ideal literary hero. That sort of thing doesn’t happen in real life.

This from an orphan who was raised unaware of his heritage, commented Harry’s Inner Critic. With a prophecy about him. You know, I don’t think we’ve ever read a story about two equally destined heroes competing to see who’s cliched enough to take down the villain –

Yes, replied the central Harry over the distant vroop-ing noise in the background, it’s a very sad life we lead and you’re not helping.

There’s only one thing to do at this point, said Ravenclaw. And we all know what it is, so why argue?

But, Harry replied, how do we test experimentally whether or not Professor Quirrell is the original David Monroe? I mean, what sort of observable behaves differently, depending on whether he’s the real David Monroe or an impostor?

‘What do you want me to do about it, Mad-Eye?’ Professor McGonagall was demanding. ‘I can’t –’

‘You can,’ the scarred man said, glaring at her fiercely. ‘Just fire the bloody Defence Professor.’

‘You say that every year,’ said Professor McGonagall.

‘Yes, and I’m always right!’

‘Constant vigilance or no, Alastor, the students must be taught!’

Moody snorted. ‘Pfah! I swear the curse gets worse every year, as you lot get more and more reluctant to let them go. Your precious Professor Quirrell would have to be Grindelwald in disguise, to get himself sent off!’

‘Is he?’ Harry couldn’t help asking. ‘I mean, could he actually be –’

‘I check Grindie’s cell every two months,’ Moody said. ‘He was there in March.’

‘Could the person in the cell be a ringer?’

‘I administer a blood test for his identity, son.’

‘Where do you keep the blood you use as a reference?’

‘In a safe place.’ Something like a smile was stretching the scarred lips. ‘Have you considered the Auror Office after you graduate?’

‘Alastor,’ Professor McGonagall said reluctantly. ‘The Defence Professor does have a … health condition. I suppose you will call it suspicious in itself – but it is by no means certain that it will be any ill-doing on his part which prevents us from renewing his employment.’

‘Yes, his little naptimes,’ Moody said darkly. ‘Amelia thinks he stepped into the path of a high-level curse. Sounds to me more like a Dark ritual gone wrong!’

‘You’ve no proof of that!’ Professor McGonagall said.

‘That man might as well be wearing a sign saying “Dark Wizard” in glowing green letters over his head.’

‘Ah …’ Harry said. It didn’t seem like an especially good time to ask what Mr Moody thought of the not all sacrificial rituals are evil standpoint. ‘Excuse me, but you said earlier that Professor Quirrell – I mean the old David Monroe – I mean the Monroe from the seventies – anyway, you said that person used the Killing Curse. What does that imply? Does somebody have to be a Dark Wizard to use it?’

Moody shook his head. ‘I’ve used it myself. All it takes is power and a certain mood.’ The grimacing lips were showing teeth. ‘The first time I cast it was against a wizard named Gerald Grice, and you can ask me what he did after you graduate Hogwarts.’

‘But why is it Unforgiveable, then?’ Harry said. ‘I mean, a Cutting Hex can kill someone too. So why’s it any better to use a Reducto instead of Avada Kedav–’

‘Shut your mouth!’ Moody said sharply. ‘Someone might take it the wrong way, your saying that incantation. You look too young to cast it, but there’s such a thing as Polyjuice. And to answer your question, boy, there’s two reasons why that spell’s in the blackest book. The first is that the Killing Curse strikes directly at the soul, and it’ll just keep going until it hits one. Straight through shields. Straight through walls. There’s a reason why even Aurors fighting Death Eaters weren’t allowed to use it before the Monroe Act.’

‘Ah,’ said Harry. ‘That does seem like an excellent reason to ban –’

‘I’m not finished, son. The second reason is that the Killing Curse doesn’t just take a powerful bit of magic. You’ve got to mean it. You’ve got to want someone dead, and not for the greater good, either. Killing Grice didn’t bring back Blair Roche, or Nathan Rehfuss, or David Capito. It wasn’t for justice, or to stop him doing it again. I wanted him dead. You understand now, lad? You don’t have to be a Dark Wizard to use that spell – but you can’t be Albus Dumbledore, either. And if you’re arrested for killing with it, there’s no possible defence.’

‘I … see,’ murmured the Boy-Who-Lived. You can’t want the person dead as an instrumental value on the way to some positive future consequence, you can’t cast it if you believe it’s a necessary evil, you have to actually want them dead for the sake of being dead, as a terminal value in your utility function. ‘A magically embodied preference for death over life, striking within the plane of pure life force … that does sound like a difficult spell to block.’

‘Not difficult,’ Moody snapped. ‘Impossible.’

Harry nodded gravely. ‘But David Monroe – or whoever – used the Killing Curse against a couple of Death Eaters even before they wiped out his family. Does that mean he already had to hate them? Like, the martial arts story was probably true?’

Moody shook his head slightly. ‘One of the dark truths of the Killing Curse, son, is that once you’ve cast it the first time, it doesn’t take much hate to do it again.’

‘It damages the mind?’

Again Moody shook his head. ‘No. It’s the killing that does that. Murder tears the soul – but that’s just the same if it’s a Cutting Hex. The Killing Curse doesn’t crack your soul. It just takes a cracked soul to cast.’ If there was a sad expression on the scarred face, it could not be read. ‘But that doesn’t tell us much about Monroe. The ones like Dumbledore who’ll never be able to cast the Curse all their lives, because they never crack no matter what – they’re the rare ones, very rare. It only takes a little cracking.’

There was a strange heavy feeling in Harry’s chest. He’d wondered what exactly it had meant, that Lily Potter had tried to cast the Killing Curse at Lord Voldemort with her last breath. But surely it was forgiveable, it was right and proper for a mother to hate the Dark Wizard who was coming to kill her baby, mocking her for how she couldn’t stop him. There was something wrong with you as a parent if you couldn’t cast Avada Kedavra, in that situation. And no other spell could’ve gone past the Dark Lord’s shields; you’d have to at least try to hate the Dark Lord enough to want him dead for the sake of dead, if that was the only way to save your baby.

It only takes a little cracking …

‘Enough,’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘What would you have us do?’

Moody’s smile twisted. ‘Get rid of the Defence Professor and see if all your troubles mysteriously clear up. Bet you a Galleon they do.’

Professor McGonagall looked like she was in pain. ‘Alastor – but – will you teach the classes, if –’

‘Ha!’ said Moody. ‘If I ever say yes to that question, check me for Polyjuice, because it’s not me.’

‘I’ll test it experimentally,’ Harry said. And then, as everyone looked at him, ‘I’ll ask Professor Quirrell a question that the real David Monroe would know – like who else was in the Slytherin class of 1945, or something like that – hopefully without making it obvious. It won’t be definitive proof, he could’ve studied the role, but it would be evidence. Still, Mr Moody, even if Professor Quirrell isn’t the original Monroe, I’m not sure that getting rid of him is a free action. He saved my life twice –’

‘What?’ demanded Moody. ‘When? How?’

‘Once when he knocked down a bunch of witches who were summoning me toward the ground, once when he figured out that the Dementor was draining me through my wand. And if Professor Quirrell wasn’t the one who set up Draco Malfoy in the first place, then he saved Draco Malfoy’s life, and things would be a lot worse if he hadn’t. If the Defence Professor isn’t behind it all – he’s not someone we can afford to just get rid of.’

Professor McGonagall nodded firmly.

Hypothesis: Severus Snape
(April 8th, 1992, 9:03pm)

Harry and Professor McGonagall now stood on the slowly turning stairs, turning without descending; or at least one Harry stood upon those stairs – his other three selves had been left behind in the Headmaster’s office.

‘Can I ask you a private question?’ Harry said, when he thought they were far enough away not to be heard. ‘And in particular, private from the Headmaster.’

‘Yes,’ Professor McGonagall said, not quite sighing. ‘Though I hope you realize that I cannot do anything which conflicts with my duties to –’

‘Yes,’ Harry said, ‘that’s exactly what I need to ask you about. In front of the Wizengamot, when Lucius Malfoy was saying that Hermione was no part of House Potter and that he wouldn’t take the money, you told Hermione how to swear that oath. I want to know, if something like that comes up again, if your first duty is to the Hogwarts student Hermione Granger, or to the head of the Order of the Phoenix, Albus Dumbledore.’

Professor McGonagall looked like someone had hit her in the face with a cast-iron frying-pan, a few minutes earlier, and now she’d been told that somebody was about to do it again, and not to flinch.

Harry flinched a little himself. Somewhere along the line he needed to pick up the knack of not phrasing things to hit as hard as he possibly could.

The walls rotated around them, behind them, and somehow, they descended.

‘Oh, Mr Potter,’ Professor McGonagall said with a low exhalation. ‘I … wish you wouldn’t ask me such questions … oh, Harry, I wasn’t thinking then, not at all. I only saw a chance to help Miss Granger and … I was Sorted into Gryffindor, after all.’

‘You’ve got a chance to think now,’ Harry said. It was all coming out wrong, but he had to say it anyway, because – ‘I’m not asking you to be loyal to me. But if you do know – if you are sure – what you’ll do if it comes down to an innocent Hogwarts student versus the Order of the Phoenix a second time …’

But Professor McGonagall shook her head. ‘I’m not sure,’ the Transfiguration Professor whispered. ‘I don’t know if it was the right choice even then. I’m sorry. I can’t decide such awful things!’

‘But you’ll do something if it happens again,’ Harry said. ‘Indecision is also a choice. You can’t just imagine having to make an immediate decision?’

‘No,’ Professor McGonagall said, sounding a little stronger; and Harry realized that he’d accidentally offered a way out. The Professor’s next words confirmed Harry’s fears. ‘Such a dreadful choice as that, Mr Potter – I think I should not make it until I must.’

Harry gave an internal sigh. He supposed he had no right to expect Professor McGonagall to say anything else. In a moral dilemma where you lost something either way, making the choice would feel bad either way, so you could temporarily save yourself a little mental pain by refusing to decide. At the cost of not being able to plan anything in advance, and at the cost of incurring a huge bias toward inaction or waiting until too late … but you couldn’t expect a witch to know all that. ‘All right,’ Harry said.

Though it wasn’t right at all, not really. Dumbledore might want that debt removed, Professor Quirrell would also want Harry out of that debt. And if the Defence Professor was David Monroe, or could convincingly appear to be David Monroe, then Lord Voldemort technically hadn’t exterminated the House of Monroe. In which case somebody might be able to pass a Wizengamot resolution revoking the Noble status of House Potter, which had been granted for avenging the Most Ancient House of Monroe.

In which case Hermione’s vow of service to a Noble House might be null and void.

Or maybe not. Harry didn’t know anything about the legalities, especially not whether House Potter got the money back if someone managed to send Hermione to Azkaban. Just because you lost something might not mean the payment was returned, legally speaking. Harry wasn’t sure and he didn’t dare ask a magical solicitor …

… it would have been nice to be able to trust at least one adult to take Hermione’s side instead of Dumbledore’s, if an issue like that threatened to come up.

The stairs they were upon ceased rotating, and they were before the backs of the great stone gargoyles, which rumbled aside, revealing the hallway.

Harry stepped out –

A hand caught at Harry’s shoulder.

‘Mr Potter,’ Professor McGonagall said in a low voice, ‘why did you to tell me to keep watch over Professor Snape?’

Harry turned around again.

‘You told me to keep watch, and see if he’d changed,’ Professor McGonagall went on, her tone urgent. ‘Why did you say that, Mr Potter?’

It took a moment, at this point, for Harry to think back and remember why he had said that. Harry and Neville had rescued Lesath Lestrange from bullies, and then Harry had confronted Severus in the hallway and, at least according to the Potions Master’s own words, almost died –

‘I learned something that made me worry,’ Harry said after a moment. ‘From someone who made me promise not to tell anyone else.’ Severus had made Harry swear that their conversations wouldn’t be shared with anyone, and Harry was still bound by it.

‘Mr Potter –’ began Professor McGonagall, and then exhaled, the flash of sharpness disappearing as quickly as it had come. ‘Never mind. If you cannot say, you cannot say.’

‘Why do you ask?’ Harry said.

Professor McGonagall seemed to hesitate –

‘All right, let me be more specific,’ Harry said. After Professor Quirrell had done it to him several times, Harry was starting to get the hang of it. ‘What change have you already observed in Professor Snape that you’re trying to decide whether to tell me about?’

‘Harry –’ the Transfiguration Professor said, and then closed her mouth.

‘I obviously know something you don’t,’ Harry said helpfully. ‘See, this is why we can’t always put off trying to decide our awful moral dilemmas.’

Professor McGonagall closed her eyes, drew in a deep breath, pinched the bridge of her nose and squeezed it several times. ‘All right,’ she said. ‘It’s a subtle thing … but worrying. How can I put this … Mr Potter, have you read many books that young children are not meant to read?’

‘I’ve read all of them.’

‘Of course you have. Well … I don’t quite understand it myself, but for so long as Severus has been employed in this school, stalking about in that awful stained cloak, there has been a certain sort of girl that stares at him with longing eyes –’

‘You say that like it’s a bad thing?’ Harry said. ‘I mean, if there’s one thing I did understand from those books, it’s that you’re not supposed to question people’s preferences.’

Professor McGonagall gave Harry a very strange look.

‘I mean,’ Harry said again, ‘from what I’ve read, when I’m a bit older there’s something like a 10% chance that I’ll find Professor Snape attractive, and the important thing is for me to just accept whatever I –’

‘In any case, Mr Potter, Severus has always been entirely indifferent to the stares of those young girls. But now –’ Professor McGonagall seemed to realize something, and hastily said, her hands rising in warding, ‘Please don’t mistake me, Professor Snape certainly has not taken advantage of any young witches! Absolutely not! He has never even so much as smiled at one, not that I ever heard. He has told the young girls to stop gaping at him. And if they stare at him regardless, he looks away. That I have seen with my own eyes.’

‘Er …’ Harry said. ‘Sorry, but just because I’ve read those books doesn’t mean I understood them. What does all that mean?’

‘That he is noticing,’ Professor McGonagall said in a low voice. ‘It is a subtle thing, but now that I have seen it, I am certain. And that means … I am very much afraid … that the bond which held Severus to Albus’s cause … may have weakened, or even broken.’

2 + 2 = …

‘Snape and Dumbledore?’ Then Harry heard the words that had just come out of his mouth, and hastily added, ‘Not that there’s anything wrong with that –’

‘No!’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘Oh, for pity’s sake – I can’t explain it to you, Mr Potter!’

The other shoe finally dropped.

He was still in love with my mother?

This seemed somewhere between beautifully sad, and pathetic, for around five seconds before the third shoe dropped.

Of course, that was before I gave him my helpful relationship advice.

‘I see,’ Harry said carefully after a few moments. There were times when saying Oops didn’t fully cover it. ‘You’re right, that’s not a good sign.’

Professor McGonagall put both hands over her face. ‘Whatever you’re thinking right now,’ she said in a slightly muffled voice, ‘which I assure you is also wrong, I don’t want to hear about it, ever.’

‘So …’ Harry said. ‘If, like you said, the bond that held Professor Snape to the Headmaster has broken … what would he do then?’

There was a long silence.

What would he do then?

Minerva lowered her hands, gazing down at the upturned face of the Boy-Who-Lived. One simple question shouldn’t have caused her so much dismay. She’d known Severus for years; the two of them bound, in some strange way, by the prophecy they’d both heard. Though Minerva suspected, from what she knew of the rules of prophecy, that she had only overheard it herself. It had been Severus’s acts which had brought about the prophecy’s fulfilment. And the guilt, the heartbreak which had come of that choice, had been tormenting the Potions Master for years. She couldn’t imagine who Severus would be without it. Her mind went blank, trying to imagine; her thoughts an empty parchment.

Surely Severus was no longer the man he’d once been, that angry and terribly foolish young man who’d brought the prophecy before Voldemort in exchange for being admitted into the Death Eaters. She’d known him for years, and surely Severus was no longer that man …

Did she really know him at all?

Had anyone ever seen the real Severus Snape?

‘I don’t know,’ Professor McGonagall finally said. ‘I truly don’t know at all. I can’t even imagine. Do you know anything of this, Mr Potter?’

‘Er …’ Harry said. ‘I think I can say that my own evidence points in the same direction as yours. I mean, it increases the probability that Professor Snape isn’t in love with my mother any more.’

Professor McGonagall closed her eyes. ‘I give up.’

‘I don’t know of anything wrong he’s done apart from that, though,’ Harry added. ‘I assume the Headmaster cleared you to ask me about this?’

Professor McGonagall looked away from him, staring at the wall. ‘Please don’t, Harry.’

‘All right,’ Harry said, and turned and hurried out into the hallways, hearing Professor McGonagall more slowly walking after, and the rumbling sound of the gargoyles moving into place.

It was the morning after next, during Potions class, that Harry’s potion of cold resistance boiled over his cauldron with a green froth and mildly nauseating smell, and Professor Snape, looking more resigned than disgusted, told Harry to stay after class. Harry had his own suspicions about this affair, and as soon as class let out – Hermione, as usual for the last few days, being the first to flee out the door – the door swung shut and locked behind the departing students.

‘I apologize for ruining your potion, Mr Potter,’ Severus Snape said quietly. There was upon his face the strange sad look that Harry had seen only once before, in a hallway some time ago. ‘It will not be reflected in your grades. Please, sit down.’

Harry sat back down at his desk, filling up the time by scrubbing a bit more at the green stain on the wooden surface, as the Potions Master incanted a few privacy spells.

When the Potions Master was done, he spoke again. ‘I … do not know how to broach this topic, Mr Potter, so I will simply say it … before the Dementor, you recovered your memory of the night your parents died?’

Harry silently nodded.

‘If … I know it must not be a pleasant memory, but … if you could tell me what happened … ?’

‘Why?’ Harry said. His voice was solemn, definitely not mocking the pleading look that Harry had never expected to see from that person. ‘I wouldn’t think that would be a pleasant thing for you to hear either, Professor –’

The Potions Master’s voice was almost a whisper. ‘I have imagined it every night these last ten years.’

You know, said Harry’s Slytherin side, it might not be such a good idea to give him closure, if his guilt-based loyalties are already wavering –

Shut up. Overruled.

It wasn’t something that Harry could actually bring himself to deny. He took one suggestion from his Slytherin side, and that was it.

‘Will you tell me exactly how you came to learn about the Prophecy?’ Harry said. ‘I’m sorry to make this a trade, I will tell you afterwards, only, it could be really important –’

‘There is little to say. I had come to be interviewed by the Deputy Headmistress for the position of Potions Master, and so I was waiting outside the room of the Hog’s Head Inn when the applicant before me, Sybill Trelawney, came to seek the position of Professor of Divination. As soon as Trelawney finished speaking her words, I fled, forsaking my chance at Hogwarts’s Mastery, and went to the Dark Lord.’ The Potions Master’s face was drawn and tight. ‘I did not even pause to consider why that riddle might have come to me, before I sold it to another.’

‘A job interview?’ Harry said. ‘Where you and Professor Trelawney both happened to be applying, and Professor McGonagall was interviewing? That seems … like rather a large coincidence …’

‘Seers are the pawns of time, Mr Potter. Coincidence is beneath them, and they are above it. I was the one meant to hear that prophecy and become its fool. Minerva’s presence made no final difference to how it came about. There was no Memory Charm as you supposed, I do not know why you thought that, but there was no Memory Charm, there could have been no Memory Charm. The voice of a seer has a quality, an enigma which even Legilimency cannot share, how could that be imbued in a false memory? Do you think the Dark Lord would believe my mere words? The Dark Lord seized my mind and saw the mystification there, even if he could not seize the mystery, and so he knew the prophecy had been true. The Dark Lord could have killed me then, having taken what he wanted – I was a fool indeed to go to him – but he saw something in me I do not know, and took me into the Death Eaters, though on his terms rather than mine. That is how I brought it about, brought it all about, from beginning to end, always my own doing.’ Severus’s voice had gone rather hoarse, and his face was filled with naked pain. ‘Now tell me, please, how did Lily die?’

Harry swallowed twice, and began his recounting.

‘James Potter shouted for Lily to run away with me, that he would hold off You-Know-Who.’

‘You-Know-Who said –’ Harry stopped, the chills going all over his own skin, his own muscles tightening as if in preparing for a seizure. The memory was returning strongly, now, accompanied by cold and darkness in association. ‘He used … the Killing Curse … and then he came upstairs somehow, I think he must have flown, I don’t remember any footsteps on stairs or anything like that … and then my mother said, “No, not Harry, please not Harry!” or something like that. And the Dark Lord – his voice was so high, like water whistling out of a kettle only cold – the Dark Lord said –’

Stand aside, woman! For you I am not come, only the boy.

The words were very clear in Harry’s memory.

‘– he told my mother to get out of his way, that he was only there for me, and my mother begged him to have mercy, and the Dark Lord said –’

I give you this rare chance to flee.

‘– that he was being generous and giving her a chance to run, but he wouldn’t bother fighting her, and even if she died, she couldn’t save me –’ Harry’s voice was unsteady, ‘- and so she ought to get out of his way. And that was when my mother begged the Dark Lord to take her life instead of mine – and the Dark Lord – the Dark Lord said to her – and his voice was lower this time, like he was dropping a pose –’

Very well, I accept the bargain.

‘– he said that he accepted her offer, and that she should drop her wand so he could kill her. And then the Dark Lord waited, just waited. I, I don’t know what Lily Potter was thinking, it hadn’t even made sense in the first place, what she said, it wasn’t like the Dark Lord would kill her and then just leave, when he’d come there for me. Lily Potter didn’t say anything, and then the Dark Lord started laughing at her and it was horrible and – and she finally tried the only thing left that wasn’t abandoning me or just giving up and dying. I don’t know if she even could’ve, if the spell would’ve worked for her, but when you think about, she had to try. The last thing my mother said was “Avada Ke-” but the Dark Lord started his own curse as soon as she said “Av” and he said it in less than half a second and there was a flash of green light and then – and then – and then –’

‘That’s enough.’

Slowly, like a body floating to the surface of water, Harry returned from wherever he’d been.

‘That’s enough,’ the Potions Master said hoarsely. ‘She died … Lily died without pain, then? The Dark Lord … did not do anything to her, before she died?’

She died thinking that she’d failed, and that the Dark Lord was going to kill her baby next. That’s pain.

‘He – the Dark Lord didn’t torture her –’ Harry said. ‘If that’s what you’re asking.’

Behind Harry, the door unlocked itself and swung open.

Harry left.

It was Friday, April 10th, of 1992.

Harry stared down at his hands, shutting out the yammering and tried to think, think, think –

Tick.

Tick.

Tick.

Susan Bones and a red-headed boy with a battered-looking wand both shoved their way through the crowd to Harry at the same time.

‘We’ve got to let the Professors know somehow –’

‘We’ve got to go find her –’

‘Find her?’ Susan snapped, rounding on the other boy. ‘How’ll we do that, Captain Weasley?’

‘We’ll go off and look for her!’ Ron Weasley snapped back.

‘Are you nuts? There’s already Professors searching the hallways, what makes you think we’ve got any better chance than them of running across General Granger? Only we’ll get eaten by the troll! And then expelled!’

It was odd, how sometimes hearing bad ideas made the right idea obvious by contrast.

‘All right everyone! Listen up!’

People turned to look.

‘Quiet! everyone! shut up!’

Harry’s throat ached after that, but he had everyone’s attention.

‘I have a broomstick,’ Harry said as loudly as he could manage with his throat still hurting. He’d remembered Azkaban, and the broomstick which had only sat two, when he’d requested one that could carry three. ‘It’s a 3-seater. I need one seventh-year from the armies to come with me. We’re going to fly through the hallways as fast as possible looking for Hermione Granger, pick her up, and come back immediately. Who’s with me?’

The Great Hall became entirely silent, then.

Students glanced at each other uneasily. The younger students looked expectantly at the older students, while they in turn turned to look at the students who were guarding the perimeter. Most of those were staring straight ahead, pointing their wands just in case the troll picked that moment to burst through a wall.

No one moved.

No one spoke.

Harry Potter spoke again. ‘We’re not going to fight the troll. If we see it we’ll just fly away and there’s no way it’ll be able to keep up with us on a broomstick. I’ll take responsibility for squaring it with the administration. Please.’

People went on looking at other people.

Harry stared at the silent crowd, the dozen seventh-years looking sternly outward, feeling the coldness coming over him. Somewhere in the back of his mind, Professor Quirrell was laughing scornfully and mocking the idea that ordinary fools would ever do something useful of their own will, without a wand pointed at their heads …

Tick.

The standard remedy for bystander apathy was to focus on a single individual. ‘All right,’ Harry said, trying to keep the commanding voice of the Boy-Who-Lived who didn’t doubt obedience. ‘Miss Morgan, come with me, now. We’ve got no time to waste.’

The witch he’d named turned from where she’d been staring steadily out at the perimeter, her expression aghast for the one second before her face closed up.

‘The Deputy Headmistress ordered us all to stay here, Mr Potter.’

It took an effort for Harry to unclench his teeth. ‘Professor Quirrell didn’t say that and neither did you. Professor McGonagall isn’t a tactician, she didn’t think to check if we had missing students and she thought it was a good idea to start marching students through the hallways. But Professor McGonagall understands after her mistakes are pointed out to her, you saw how she listened to you and Professor Quirrell, and I’m certain that she wouldn’t want us to just ignore the fact that Hermione Granger is out there, alone –’

Tick.

‘I’d expect the Professor to say she’d not wish any more students roaming the halls. The Professor said if anyone left for any reason, they’d be expelled. Maybe you don’t need to worry because you’re the Boy-Who-Lived, but the rest of us do!’

Tick.

Somewhere in the back of his mind, Professor Quirrell was just laughing at him. Expecting some normal person to act without perfect strategic clarity, without a clear focus of responsibility on them personally, when they had a good excuse to do nothing … ‘A student’s life is at stake,’ Harry said in a level voice. ‘She could be fighting the troll right now. Out of curiosity, does that mean anything to you at all?’

Tick.

Miss Morgan’s face twisted. ‘You – you’re the Boy-Who-Lived! Just go off by yourself and snap your fingers, if you want to help her!’

Tick.

Harry was hardly even aware of what he was saying. ‘That’s just cleverness and bluffing, I don’t have any power like that in real life, a young girl needs your help now are you a Gryffindor or not?’

‘Why are you saying any of this to me?’ cried Miss Morgan. ‘I wasn’t left in charge here! Mr Hagrid was!’

There was an awkward pause that suffused the whole room.

Harry spun to look up at the huge half-giant towering over the crowd of students, as all other heads also turned toward him as one.

‘Mr Hagrid,’ Harry said, trying to keep his voice commanding. ‘You need to authorize this expedition and you need to do it now.’

Rubeus Hagrid looked conflicted, though that was hard to judge with his vast head so surrounded by his unshorn beard and locks; only his eyes looked alive, embedded in all that hair. ‘Eh …’ said the half-giant. ‘I was tol’ to keep yeh all safe –’

‘Great, now can we also keep Hermione Granger safe? You know, the student framed for a murder she did not commit who needs someone to help her?’

The half-giant startled as Harry spoke the words.

Harry stared at the enormous man, desperately willing him to pick up on the hint, hoping the words hadn’t given it away to anyone else – he couldn’t be just muscle, surely James and Lily had been friends with this man out of more than pity –

‘Framed?’ called out an anonymous voice, from somewhere over near where the Slytherins gathered. ‘Ha, are you still on that? It’d serve her right if she did get eaten.’

There was some laughter, even as cries of indignation came from elsewhere.

The half-giant’s face firmed up. ‘Yeh stay here, lad,’ Mr Hagrid said in a booming tone that was probably meant to be gentle. ‘I’ll go and look fer her meself. Truth is, trolls can be a mite tricky – yeh’ve got to catch ’em by an ankle and dangle ’em just right, or they’ll rip yeh clean in half –’

‘Can you ride a broomstick, Mr Hagrid?’

‘Eh –’ Rubeus Hagrid frowned. ‘No.’

‘Then you can’t search fast enough. Sixth-years! Calling all sixth-years! Are there any sixth-years here who aren’t worthless cowards?’

Silence.

‘Fifth years? Mr Hagrid, tell them they’re authorized to go with me and keep me safe! I’m trying to be sensible, damn it!’

The half-giant wrung his hands with an agonized expression. ‘Eh – I –’

Something snapped inside Harry and he started to stride directly toward the doors to the Great Hall, pushing aside anyone who didn’t get out of his way as though they were doughy statues. (He didn’t run, because running was an invitation for somebody to stop you.) Somewhere in his mind he was moving through an empty room filled with mechanical puppets by whose meaningless lip-moving noises he’d been distracted –

A huge figure interposed itself in his way.

Harry looked up.

‘I can’t let yeh do that, Harry, not yeh of all people. There’s strange things afoot in this castle, and someone might be after Hermione – or they might be after yeh.’ Rubeus Hagrid’s voice was regretful but firm, and his gigantic hands lay at his side like forklifts. ‘I can’t let yeh go out there, Harry Potter.’

‘Stupefy!’

The red bolt crashed into the side of Hagrid’s head and made the huge man startle. His head snapped around faster than anything that large should’ve moved, and bellowed, ‘What do yeh think yeh’re doing!’ at the young form of Susan Bones.

‘Sorry!’ she screamed. ‘Incendium! Glisseo!’

The huge man’s hands, now slapping at the fire in his beard, didn’t quite manage to catch himself as he crashed to the floor, but it didn’t matter by then because Harry was past him and –

Neville Longbottom stepped in front of him, looking desperate but determined, the Hufflepuff boy’s wand already level in his hand.

Harry’s hand went for his wand in a sheer reflex action, he barely managed to check himself before Neville could fire on him, staring at his Lieutenant as though the world had gone mad.

‘Harry!’ Neville burst out. ‘Harry, Mr Hagrid’s right, you can’t, this could all be a trap, they could be after you –’

All of Neville’s muscles went rigid and he toppled to the ground, stiff as a board.

A pale-looking Ron Weasley stepped out from behind Neville, his own wand level, and said, ‘Go.’

‘Ron, you madman, what are you doing –’ came a voice distantly identifiable as Miss Clearwater’s boyfriend, but Harry was already dashing for the door without looking back, even as Ron’s voice and Susan’s voice rose again in incantation. There was a huge indignant bellow, and unknown voices began to yell.

Then Harry was through, his hand reaching into his pouch and his voice was saying ‘broomstick’, as behind him the great doors began to swing shut again.

Harry continued running through the Entrance Hall even as the long three-person broomstick and its sets of stirrups began to protrude from the pouch, repeating a number of swearwords in his head and thinking this is what happens when you try to be sensible with the part of his mind that wasn’t trying to figure out a search pattern to cover places where Hermione might be. The Library was on the third floor and practically on the other side of the castle … Harry had almost reached the great marble staircase by the time the broomstick was in his hand and ‘Up!’ he was in the air and accelerating up toward the second floor –

‘Gah!’ Harry screamed, and barely managed to spin his broom in the air so that he didn’t impale one of the human figures lurking at the top of the stairs. There was a ghastly moment of trying not to fall off the broom, perform the twists that would keep him in the stirrups, despite being really close to the ground and having almost no room to manoeuvre and then –

‘Fred? George?’

‘We can’t figure out how to find her!’ one of the Weasley twins blurted, hands twisting in distress. ‘We sneaked out because we thought we could find Miss Granger – there has to be a quick way to find anyone inside the Hogwarts castle, we’re both sure of it – but we can’t figure out what it is!’

Harry stared at both of them, from where he was hanging upside down from the broomstick where his desperate manoeuvre had brought him, and entirely by reflex his mouth said, ‘Well, why were you so sure you could find her?’

‘We don’t know!’ cried the other Weasley twin.

‘Have you been able to find people inside Hogwarts before?’

‘Yes! We –’ and the Weasley twin who was speaking stopped abruptly, both redheads staring off into the distance with a blank expression.

There was a thundering crash, as of two huge doors being shoved open by someone very, very strong.

Harry spun around in the air to present the two open stirrup-positions on the broomstick to the Weasley twins, he didn’t say anything, there was no reason for them to give away their positions if they didn’t have to. Time seemed to move too slowly as the Weasley twins scrambled into the stirrups, Harry’s heart beating hard despite his mental calculation that Mr Hagrid, running, shouldn’t reach even the foot of the stairway in time. Then the three of them were accelerating hard and away toward the nearest corridor, the stone floor beneath them blurring and the walls seeming to make an audible whooshing sound (though that was just the wind in their ears) as they went past; Harry remembered that he was riding a longer three-person broomstick barely in time to slow down for the next turn.

And now all the broomstick seats were occupied, but if they actually found Hermione then – Harry could put on the Cloak of Invisibility, that should hide him from the troll, and that would free up a seat for Hermione –

Harry ducked hard before a sudden archway took his head off.

‘We found Jesse!’ the Weasley twin seated behind Harry blurted. ‘I know we did! That time we needed to tell him that Filch was hunting for him!’

‘How?’ Harry said, most of his brain engaged in not dying in a horrible air accident. He should have slowed down for safety, but there was a tension rising in him, a sourceless dread. He couldn’t slow down, something terrible would happen if he slowed down …

‘We –’ said the Weasley twin seated lower down. ‘We can’t remember!’

Another sharp turn taken at, Harry estimated, roughly 0.3% of the speed of light, and they were going through a twisty curving corridor that Harry always took to get from the Great Hall to the library only it wasn’t the shortest way if you were on a broomstick, he should’ve taken the long straight West Corridor instead –

The part of his brain that wasn’t steering caught up with reality.

‘Someone’s been tampering with your minds!’ Harry yelled, as he weaved through the curving corridor so fast that the tail-end Weasley sometimes lightly smacked into the wall as the length of the broomstick conflicted with Harry’s maladapted air skills.

‘What?’ cried Fred or George.

‘Whoever got to Hermione messed with your minds too!’ It could be an Obliviation, it could be a False Memory that hadn’t been planted right, but right now Harry couldn’t think –

The broomstick turned and shot upward along a spiral staircase, all three of them flattened themselves against the broomstick so they could make in through the gap in the ceiling that opened onto the third floor, and then they were in front of the library, the broomstick slowing to a halt with a shriek despite the lack of anything it could be friction-braking against. Harry shot the Weasley twins a quick glance to stay put, as he clambered off the broomstick to shove open the doors of the library, controlling his breathing as he shoved his head inside.

Hermione Granger wasn’t there.

Madam Pince, who was eating a sandwich at her desk, looked up with a sudden glare. ‘Library’s closed!’

‘Have you seen Hermione Granger?’ Harry said.

‘I said the library’s closed, boy! Lunch hours!’

‘This is extremely important. Have you seen Hermione Granger or do you have any idea where she might be?’

‘No, now be off!’

‘Do you have any fast way of contacting Professor McGonagall in an emergency?’

‘Eh?’ said the librarian, startled. She rose up from behind her desk. ‘What is –’

‘Yes or no. Please answer immediately.’

‘Ah – there’s the Floo –’

‘She’s not in her office,’ Harry said. ‘Do you have any other way of reaching her. Yes or no.’

‘Young man, I insist that you –’

Harry’s brain flagged this as I’m talking to NPCs again and he spun on his heel and dashed back for the broomstick.

‘Stop!’ cried Madam Pince, bursting too late from the doors as Harry and the Weasley twins shot off again, out of the librarian’s sight. The pressure in Harry’s mind still rising, like a physical hand squeezing his chest, he had to find Hermione and he had no other notion of where she could be, unless it was the witches’ dorms in the Ravenclaw tower and that he couldn’t enter. Searching all of Hogwarts bordered on a mathematical impossibility, there probably was no continuous flight path that entered all the rooms at least once – why hadn’t he thought to demand for Hermione and Neville and him to be given a set of those neat little mirrors the Aurors used to communicate –

The realization that he was being stupid hit Harry like a blow to the stomach. He didn’t need mirrors to send a message, he hadn’t needed mirrors since January. Harry slowed the broomstick to a halt in mid-air of a hallway, his wand already coming into his hand, the driving will to protect Hermione Granger rising to the front of his mind like a sun of silver fire and flowing down his arm as he cried

‘Expecto Patronum!’

and the blazing white humanoid burst into existence like a nova, the Weasley twins’ voices crying aloud in shock.

‘Tell Hermione Granger – that there’s a troll loose in Hogwarts – it could be hunting for her – she needs to get into direct sunlight, now!’

The silver figure turned as though it was departing, and then vanished.

‘Merlin’s underpants,’ breathed Fred or George.

The silver outline blasted back into the world, and said in the strange version of Harry’s own voice, ‘Hermione Granger says,’ the blazing figure’s voice became higher-pitched, ‘Ahhhhhhhhh!’

Time seemed to fracture, like everything was moving very quickly and slowly at the same time. A desperate impulse to accelerate the broomstick, fly at its maximum speed, only Harry didn’t know where –

‘If you know where she is,’ Harry shouted to the blazing humanoid figure, staring into it as though it were a sun, ‘then take me to her!’

The silver blaze moved and Harry accelerated after it, the Weasley twins giving out high-pitched shrieks behind him as he fired through the air like a cannonball, moving faster than sanity, he didn’t focus on the walls whizzing past him or how fast he was moving, just followed the silver light through corridors and flying up staircases and blitzing through doors that Fred or George cried desperate incantations to open and it was all still taking too much time, somewhere deep inside Harry felt like he was sinking through molasses as windows and portraits shot past.

The broomstick screamed through a final turn that whacked one of the Weasley twins against the wall not quite as hard as a Bludger would hit, and then they followed the brilliant Patronus through an open space in the ceilings, blasting up and upwards, rising past one floor and then another in less than a breath.

His Patronus slowed to a halt (Harry braking hard in response) just as they reached the level of a wide-open floor space that that spread out until it escaped the ceiling and turned into an outdoor terrace, a spread of tiled marble open to the air and sky –

Cool blue fires clung to the floor in small masses, surrounding a blazing pool that seemed to burn with a deadlier, hotter blue.

In one narrow circle the marble tiles were scorched and shattered by some explosive spell that only the most prodigious of first-year witches could have cast, with the last of her strength.

On the terrace, still moving beneath the open sunlight, stood a great lumpy creature of dull granite-grey. Body like a boulder with small bald head perched on top like a stone, short legs thick as tree trunks with flat, horny feet. One hand held a tremendous stone club as long and as wide as an adult human, and the other hand held

The Weasley twins screamed.

Harry’s Patronus shattered.

The troll snorted and spun around to face them, dropping into the red pool that had spread out beneath its feet, raising its club high.

Then a Weasley cried an incantation and the club was torn from the troll’s hand, smashed into its face so hard it drove the troll back for one of its steps, a blow that might have killed a Muggle. The troll gave a bellow of anger, its nose squashed and blood-spattered, and then the nose straightened once more, regenerated. The troll grabbed with both hands for the club, which shot away through the air but only barely dodged the grab.

‘Lead it away, keep it off me,’ said a voice.

The levitated club moved backwards from the troll, from the terrace onto the wide-open floor beneath the ceiling; and the troll made a great prodigious leap that almost brought the club into its hands. Then the troll made another great leap as the club moved to one side; and the broomstick moved forwards and Harry jumped off and ran towards where Hermione Granger was lying in a pool of her own blood with her legs eaten away to the upper thighs.

Harry’s hands tore open the healer’s kit from his pouch, grabbed one of the self-tightening tourniquets, wrapped them around one ragged tooth-marked stump, his hands briefly slipping in the blood, they didn’t tremble, there wasn’t any allowance for his hands to tremble. As the tourniquet formed a complete loop it tightened hard and more blood came out, but then the bleeding stopped on that thigh-stump, and Harry turned to the other. Part of his mind was screaming, screaming, screaming and even the part of him picking up the other self-tightening tourniquet heard it, but that also wasn’t allowed.

The two Weasley twins were shouting spells, one after another in rapid-fire casting that would have had Harry unconscious in sixty seconds, sometimes the twins shouted two spells simultaneously in perfect coordination, but most of the spells were disrupting in harmless showers of sparks against the troll’s skin. As the other tourniquet tightened itself in another pulse of blood, Harry looked up at a ‘Diffindo!’ / ‘Reducto!’ that made the troll’s vulnerable eyes explode in twin showers of vitreous humour, but the troll only bellowed once more, its eyes already reforming.

‘Fire and acid!’ Harry shouted. ‘Use fire or acid!’

‘Fuego!’ / ‘Incendio!’ Harry heard, but he wasn’t looking, he was reaching for the syringe of glowing orange liquid that was the oxygenating potion, pushing it into Hermione’s neck at what Harry hoped was the carotid artery, to keep her brain alive even if her lungs or heart stopped, so long as her brain stayed intact everything else could be fixed, it had to be possible for magic to fix it, it had to be possible for magic to fix it, it had to be possible for magic to fix it, and Harry pushed the plunger of the syringe all the way down, creating a faint glow beneath the pale skin of her neck. Harry then pushed down on her chest, where her heart should be, hard compressions that he hoped was moving the oxygenated blood around to where it could reach her brain, even if her heart might have stopped beating, he hadn’t actually thought to check her pulse.

Then Harry stared at the other things in his medical kit, his mind going blank as he tried to figure out what else of what was there, if anything, he could use. The screaming in that distant corner of his mind was getting louder, much louder, now that his hands had stopped their frantic motions. He was suddenly aware of the liquid sensation where blood had soaked through his robes and the knees of his trousers.

From behind Harry came the sound of another bellow from the troll, and he heard one of the Weasley twins shout ‘Deligitor prodeas!’ and then, ‘HELP! Do something!’

Harry twisted his head back to look, and saw that one of the Weasley twins was somehow now wearing the Sorting Hat on his head, facing off against the troll which held the huge stone club in both its hands, looking somewhat scorched now and with one or two smoking scars across its arms, but still intact.

And then the voice of the Hat bellowed in a voice so loud it seemed to shake the walls,

‘GRYFFINDOR!’

A pulse of power burned the air, magic almost tangible even to Harry’s undeveloped senses; the troll jumped back a pace with a snort of surprise. Fred or George, with a strange look on his face, swept the Hat off his head with a motion smooth as a magician’s trick, and reached in with one hand and drew forth a hilt whose pommel was a glowing ruby, followed by a wide crossguard of gleaming white metal, and a blade as long as a tall child. As the sword was revealed the air seemed to fill with a silent scream of fury.

Upon the blade was written in golden script, nihil supernum.

Then the Weasley twin raised the sword aloft as though the huge blade weighed nothing, and screamed and charged.

Harry’s lips opened to say something, some long sentence like, No, stop, you have no idea how to use a sword but not even a single syllable left his lips before the sword sliced off the troll’s right arm through the elbow, cutting through skin and flesh and bone like jelly; just as the already-swinging arc of the stone club smashed into the charging Weasley twin and sent him flying through the air above the marble floor, over the gap out of which they’d risen on the broomstick, until that Weasley hit the wall on the opposite side and then collapsed into an unmoving heap.

The bright sword vanished down into the opening in the floor, clattering distantly as it dropped.

‘Fred!’ screamed George Weasley, and then ‘Ventus!’

An invisible blow caught the troll and hurled it sideways through the air.

‘Ventus!’

The troll was hit again, blown to the edge of the floor and the gap leading downwards.

‘Ventus!’

But the troll had reached down and grabbed at the floor, its remaining hand crunching through marble to gain a firm hold. The third blow sent the troll’s body over the gap; but the hand remained at the edge. And then the troll was pulling itself back up single-handedly, roaring.

George Weasley staggered, almost falling, his hand dropping to his side. ‘Harry –’ the Weasley twin said in a strained voice, ‘Run –’

The remaining Weasley twin took a step sideways, slumped against the wall, and slid to the ground.

Time was fractured in Harry’s mind, the world around him seemed to move slowly, distorted, or perhaps it was his own mind twisting and folding. He should have been moving, doing something, but a strange paralysis seemed to be stopping all his muscles, all his motions. Without any time for words, thoughts came in flashes of concepts: that if Harry ran away the troll would eat the Weasley twins as well as Hermione, that if Bludgers didn’t kill wizards then Fred should still be alive, that the Weasley twins were more powerful spell-casters than him and they hadn’t been able to hold back the troll, there was no time to Transfigure anything he didn’t already possess, the troll seemed too agile to be lured over the edge of the terrace to fall off the sides of the Hogwarts castle, someone had enchanted the troll against sunlight before using it as a murder weapon and might also have strengthened it in other ways. And then a mental image of Hermione running from the troll, running for sunlight, finally reaching the bright terrace with the troll hot on her heels, only to find that someone else had thought of that possibility, too.

The screaming horror in his mind was drowned out by another emotion.

Harry stood up.

On the other side of the room, the enemy had also risen, the unregenerating stump of one sword-cut arm still bloody.

intent to kill

The troll grasped its fallen club in its remaining hand, and gave a huge bellow, smashing the club into the floor and sending marble chips flying.

think purely of killing

The troll began to lumber towards where George had fallen, a thin string of drool trailing from the side of its lips.

grasp at any means to do so

Harry took five strides forward, and the enemy gave another bellow and turned away from George, its eyes focusing squarely on him.

censors off, do not flinch

The third most perfect killing machine in nature bounded towards him in leaping steps.

kill

Harry’s left hand already held the Transfigured diamond from his ring, his right hand already held his wand.

‘Wingardium Leviosa.’

Harry’s wand directed the tiny jewel into the troll’s mouth.

‘Finite Incantatem.’

The troll’s head blew off its spine as the rock expanded back into its old form, and Harry stepped aside as the Enemy’s body crashed where he’d been standing.

The enemy’s head was already beginning to regenerate, the ragged stump of the jaw and spine smoothing over, the mouth completing itself and replacing its teeth.

Harry bent down and picked up the troll’s head by its left ear. His wand jammed through the troll’s left eye, plunging through the jelly-like material and passing through the wide socket in the bone. Harry visualized a one-millimetre-wide cross-section through the enemy’s brain, and Transfigured it into sulphuric acid.

The enemy stopped regenerating.

Harry threw the corpse over the edge of the terrace and turned back to Hermione.

Her eyes were moving, and focused on him.

Harry crouched beside her, ignoring the blood soaking more of his already-soaked robes. You’ll be all right, his brain formed the sentence, but his lips wouldn’t move. You’ll be all right, we’ll find some magic to fix all this, put you back to normal, just hold on, don’t –

Hermione’s lips were moving, just a tiny bit but they were moving.

‘your … fault …’

Time froze. Harry should have told her not to talk, to save her breath, only he couldn’t unblock his lips.

Hermione drew in another breath, and her lips whispered, ‘Not your fault.’

Then she exhaled, and closed her eyes.

Harry stared at her with his mouth half-open, his breath caught in his throat.

‘Don’t do this,’ said his voice. He’d only been two minutes late.

Hermione suddenly convulsed, her arms twitching into the air as though reaching up for something, and her eyes flew open again. There was a burst of something that was magic and also more, a shout louder than an earthquake and containing a thousand books, a thousand libraries, all spoken in a single cry that was Hermione; too vast to be understood, except that Harry suddenly knew that Hermione had whited out the pain, and was glad not to be dying alone. For a moment it seemed like the outpouring of magic might hold, take root in the castle’s stone; but then the outpouring ended and the magic faded, her body stopped moving and all motion halted as Hermione Jean Granger ceased to exist –

No.

Harry stood up from the body, swaying.

No.

There was a burst of flame and Dumbledore was standing there with Fawkes, his eyes filled with horror. ‘I felt a student die! What –’

The old wizard’s eyes saw what lay upon the ground.

‘Oh, no,’ whispered Albus Dumbledore. Fawkes gave a sad, mournful croon.

‘Bring her back.’

There was silence on the terrace. Fred Weasley had risen up into the air at a gesture from Dumbledore’s wand and was floating towards them, surrounded by a reassuring pink glow.

‘Harry –’ the old wizard began. His voice cracked. ‘Harry –’

‘Have Fawkes cry on her or whatever. Hurry up.’ The voice that spoke sounded perfectly calm.

‘I, I can’t, Harry, it’s too late, she’s dead –’

‘I don’t want to hear about it. If it was me lying there, you’d pull some kind of amazing rabbit out of your hat and save me, right, because the hero isn’t allowed to die before the story’s over. Well, she’s the hero too, so whatever you were saving for that extra-special occasion, just go ahead and use it now. I promise I’ll pay you back.’

‘There isn’t anything I can do! Her soul has departed, she’s passed on!’

Harry opened his mouth to scream out all his fury, and then closed it again. There wasn’t any point in screaming, it wouldn’t accomplish anything. The unbearable pressure rising inside him couldn’t be let out that way.

Harry turned away from Dumbledore and looked down at where the remains of Hermione Granger were lying in a pool of blood. Part of his mind was hammering at the world around him, trying to make it go away, wake up from the nightmare and find himself back in his Ravenclaw dorm with the morning sun shining through the curtains. But the blood remained and Harry didn’t wake up, and another part of him already knew that this event was real, part of the same flawed world that included Azkaban and the Wizengamot chamber and

No

With a fracturing feeling, as though time was still torn to pieces around him, Harry turned away from Dumbledore and looked down at the remains of Hermione Granger lying in a pool of blood with two tourniquets tied around her thigh-stumps, and decided

No.

I do not accept this.

There isn’t any reason to accept it, not when there’s magic in the world.

Harry would learn whatever he had to learn, invent whatever he had to invent, rip the knowledge of Salazar Slytherin from the Dark Lord’s mind, discover the secret of Atlantis, open any gates or break any seals necessary, find his way to the root of all magic and reprogram it.

He would rip apart the foundations of reality itself to get Hermione Granger back.

‘The crisis is over,’ the Defence Professor said. ‘You may dismount, Madam.’

Trelawney, who had been sitting behind him on the two-person broomstick that had just blazed through Hogwarts burning directly through all the walls and floors in their way, hastily pulled herself off and then sat down hard on the floor, a pace away from the red-glowing edges of a newly made gap in the wall. The woman was still breathing in gasps, bending over herself as though she were on the verge of vomiting out something larger than she was.

The Defence Professor had felt the boy’s horror, through the link that existed between the two of them, the resonance in their magic; and he had realized that the boy had sought the troll and found it. The Defence Professor had tried to send an impulse to retreat, to don the Cloak of Invisibility and flee; but he’d never been able to influence the boy through the resonance, and hadn’t succeeded that time either.

He’d felt the boy give himself over fully to the killing intention. That was when the Defence Professor had begun burning through the substance of Hogwarts, trying to reach the battle in time.

He’d felt the boy exterminate his enemy in seconds.

He’d felt the boy’s dismay as one of his friends died.

He’d felt the fury the boy had directed at some annoyance who was likely Dumbledore; followed by an unknown resolution whose unyielding hardness even he found adequate. With any luck, the boy had just discarded his foolish little reluctances.

Unseen by anyone, the Defence Professor’s lips curved up in a thin smile. Despite its little ups and downs, on the whole this had been a surprisingly good day –

‘He is here. The one who will tear apart the very stars in heaven. He is here. He is the end of the world.’

Harry held a tight grip on his wand, a Prismatic Sphere glowing around him. He stared levelly at the seething, blurring form in front of him, and said, ‘What on Earth are you doing?’

The seething blurs resolved, reformed, relaxed back into a hooded form. Whatever concealment had been at work – a device rather than a Charm, Harry guessed, since the magic had been able to affect him – had prevented his mind from recognizing the shape or even that the shape was human. But it hadn’t prevented Harry from recognizing the sharp sense of doom.

Professor Quirrell stood straight with silver blood all down the front of his enshrouding black cloak, and gave a sigh, looking at the fallen forms of three Aurors, Tracey Davis, Draco Malfoy, and Professor McGonagall. ‘I had honestly thought,’ Professor Quirrell murmured, ‘that I jammed that mirror without alarm. What were two first-year Slytherins doing alone in the Forbidden Forest? Mr Malfoy has more sense than this … What a fiasco.’

Harry didn’t answer. The sense of doom was as strong as Harry could ever remember feeling it, a feeling of power in the air so great that it was almost tangible. Some part of him was still viscerally shocked at how fast the shields surrounding the Aurors had been torn apart. He almost hadn’t been able to see the successive lashes of colour which had torn away the shields like tissue paper. It made the duel Professor Quirrell had fought against the Auror in Azkaban look like a mockery, a child’s game – though Professor Quirrell had claimed, then, that if he’d fought for real the Auror would have been dead in seconds; and Harry knew now that this was also true.

Just how high did the power ladder go?

‘I take it,’ Harry said, managing to keep his voice steady, ‘that your eating unicorns has something to do with why you’ll get fired from the Defence Professor position. I don’t suppose you’d care to explain in considerable detail?’

Professor Quirrell looked at him. The almost tangible sense of power in the air seemed to diminish, drawing back into the Defence Professor. ‘I shall indeed explain myself,’ the Defence Professor said. ‘I need to cast a few Memory Charms first, and then we may go off and discuss it, for it would not be wise for me to stay. You will return to this time later, as I know.’

Harry willed himself to be able to see through the Cloak he had mastered; and knew that another Harry stood beside him, hidden by his own Deathly Hallow. Harry then told his Cloak to hide himself from himself once more, and it did; being able to perceive your future self meant having to match the memory later.

Harry’s own voice said, then, sounding strange in present-Harry’s ears, ‘He has a surprisingly good explanation.’

Present-Harry remembered the words as best he could. Nothing more was said between them.

Professor Quirrell walked to Draco’s form, and chanted the spell of the False Memory Charm. The Defence Professor stood there for perhaps a minute, seemingly lost to the world.

Harry had been studying Obliviations, these last couple of weeks – though he couldn’t have helped cast the spells, unless he was willing to exhaust himself almost completely, and for some reason they wanted an Auror to lose every single life memory involving the colour blue. But Harry had some idea, now, of the concentration which the far more difficult False Memory Charm entailed. You had to try to live the other person’s entire life inside your own head, at least if you wanted to create the False Memories with less than a sixteen-to-one slowdown as you separately crafted sixteen major tracks of memory. It might have been quiet, there might have been no outward sign; but Harry knew something of the difficulties now, and he knew to be impressed.

Professor Quirrell finished, and moved on to Tracey Davis, then the three Aurors, and finally Professor McGonagall. Harry waited, but future-Harry made no protest. It was possible that even Professor McGonagall, if she’d been awake, wouldn’t have protested. It was not yet the Ides of May, and apparently there would be a surprisingly good explanation.

With a gesture, Draco’s stunned body was lifted, and sent a short distance into the woods, before being carefully deposited on the ground. Then a final gesture from Professor Quirrell ripped a huge chunk out of the unicorn’s side, leaving behind ragged edges; the raw meat hovered in the air, then wavered in Vanishment and was gone.

‘Done,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘I must depart this place now, Mr Potter. Come with me, and remain here.’

Professor Quirrell strode away, and Harry followed and remained behind.

They walked through the woods in silence for a time, before Harry heard faint voices in the distance. The next set of Aurors, presumably, after the first set had fallen out of contact. What his future self was saying, Harry didn’t know.

‘They won’t detect us, nor hear our speech,’ said Professor Quirrell. The sense of power and doom around the Defence Professor was still strong. The man seated himself on a tree stump, one where the light of the almost-full moon fell full on him. ‘I should first say that when you speak to the Aurors, in the future, you should tell them that you frightened away the seething dark, the same as you did that Dementor. It is what Mr Malfoy will remember seeing.’ Professor Quirrell gave a small sigh. ‘It may cause some alarm, if they conclude that some horror kin to Dementors, and strong enough to break the Aurors’ shields, is loose in the Forbidden Forest. But I could not think of what else to do. If the forest is better-guarded after this – but with any luck I have already consumed what I need. Would you mind telling me how you arrived so quickly? How did you know Mr Malfoy was in trouble?’

After Captain Brodski had learned that Draco Malfoy was in the Forbidden Forest, seemingly in the company of Rubeus Hagrid, Brodski had begun inquiring to find out who had authorized this, and had still been unable to find out when Draco Malfoy had missed check-in. Despite Harry’s protests, the Auror Captain, who was authorized to know about Time-Turners, had refused to allow deployment to before the time of the missed check-in; there were standard procedures involving Time. But Brodski had given Harry written orders allowing him to go back and deploy an Auror trio to arrive one second after the missed check-in time. There had been a Patronus Charm to locate Draco, which Harry had successfully willed to take the form of a ball of pure silver light, and the flight of Aurors had arrived on time to the second.

‘I’m afraid I couldn’t say,’ Harry replied evenly. Professor Quirrell was still a major suspect, and it was good for him not to know the details. ‘Now why are you eating unicorns?’

‘Ah,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘As to that …’ The man hesitated. ‘I was drinking the blood of unicorns, not eating them. The missing flesh, the ragged marks upon the body – those were to obscure the case, to make it seem like some other predator. The use of unicorn’s blood is too well-known.’

‘I don’t know it,’ Harry said.

‘I know you do not,’ the Defence Professor said sharply. ‘Or you would not be pestering me about it. The power of unicorn’s blood is to preserve your life for a time, even if you are on the very verge of death.’

There was a stretch of time when Harry’s brain claimed to be refusing to process the words, which was of course a lie, because you couldn’t know the meaning you weren’t allowed to process, without having already processed it.

A strange sense of blankness overtook Harry, an absence of reaction, maybe this was what other people felt like when someone went off-script, and they couldn’t say or think of anything to do.

Of course Professor Quirrell was dying, not just occasionally ill.

Professor Quirrell had known he was dying. He’d volunteered to take the Defence Professor position at Hogwarts, after all.

Of course he’d been getting worse the whole school year. Of course illnesses which kept getting worse had a predictable destination at their end.

Harry’s brain had surely known already, somewhere in the safe back of his mind where he could refuse to process things he’d already processed.

Of course that was why Professor Quirrell wouldn’t be able to teach Battle Magic next year. Professor McGonagall wouldn’t even have to fire him. He would just be –

– dead.

‘No,’ Harry said, his voice a little shaky. ‘There has to be a way –’

‘I am not stupid nor particularly eager to die. I have already looked. I had to go this far simply to last out my lesson plans, having less time than I had thought, and –’ The head of the dark moonlit figure turned away. ‘I think I do not want to hear about it, Mr Potter.’

Harry’s breath hitched. Too many emotions were bubbling up in him at once. After denial came anger, according to a ritual someone had just made up. And yet it seemed surprisingly appropriate.

‘And why –’ Harry’s breath hitched again. ‘Why isn’t unicorn’s blood standard in healer’s kits, then? To keep someone alive, even if they’re on the very verge of dying from their legs being eaten?’

‘Because there are permanent side effects,’ Professor Quirrell said quietly.

‘Side effects? Side effects? What kind of side effect is medically worse than DEATH?’ Harry’s voice rose on the last word until he was shouting.

‘Not everyone thinks the same way we do, Mr Potter. Though, to be fair, the blood must come from a live unicorn and the unicorn must die in the drinking. Would I be here otherwise?’

Harry turned, stared at the surrounding trees. ‘Have a herd of unicorns at St. Mungo’s. Floo the patients there, or use portkeys.’

‘Yes, that would work.’

Harry’s face tightened, the only outward sign behind his trembling hands of everything that was welling up inside him. He needed to scream, needed some outlet, needed something he couldn’t name and finally Harry levelled his wand at a tree and shouted ‘Diffindo!’

There was a sharp tearing sound, and a cut appeared across the wood.

‘Diffindo!’

Another cut. Harry had learned the Charm only ten days previously, after he’d started getting serious about self-defence. It was theoretically a second-year Charm, but the anger pouring through him seemed to know no bounds, he knew enough now not to exhaust himself and he still had power yet.

‘Diffindo!’ Harry had aimed at a branch this time, and it plummeted to the ground with a sound of twigs and leaves.

There didn’t seem to be any tears inside him, only pressure with no outlet.

‘I shall leave you to it,’ Professor Quirrell said quietly. The Defence Professor rose from his tree stump, the unicorn’s blood still moonlit on the black cloak he wore, and drew his hood back over his head.

Harry stood, panting, in the midst of a brief wasted circle amid the forest, more destruction than a first-year should have been able to reach, by himself. The Severing Charm wouldn’t bring down a tree, so he’d started partially Transfiguring cross-sections through the wood. It hadn’t let out what was inside him, bringing down a small circle of trees hadn’t made him feel any better, all the emotions were still there but while he was destroying trees he at least wasn’t thinking about how the feelings couldn’t be let out.

After Harry had run out of available magic he’d started tearing off branches with his bare hands and snapping them. His hands were bleeding, though nothing that Madam Pomfrey couldn’t fix in the morning. Only Dark magic left permanent scars on wizards.

There came a sound of something moving in the woods, like the hoof-beats of a horse, and Harry whirled, his wand rising once more; some part of his magic had returned while he was working with his hands. It occurred to him for the first time that he was out in the Forbidden Forest alone, and making noise.

What emerged into the moonlight was not the unicorn Harry had expected, but a creature with a lower body like that of a horse, gleaming white-brown beneath the moonlight, and the bare upper chest of a male human with long white hair. The moonlight caught the centaur’s face, and Harry saw that the eyes were almost as blue as Dumbledore’s, halfway to sapphire.

In one hand the centaur held a long wooden spear, with an overlarge metal blade whose edge did not gleam beneath the moonlight; a gleaming edge, Harry had once read, was the sign of a dull blade.

‘So,’ the centaur said. His voice was low, powerful and male. ‘Here you are, surrounded by destruction. I can smell the unicorn’s blood in the air, the blood of something innocent, slain to save oneself.’

A jolt of sudden fear brought Harry into the now, and he said quickly, ‘It’s not what it looks like.’

‘I know. The stars themselves proclaim your innocence, ironically enough.’ The centaur took a step toward Harry within the small clearing, still holding his spear upright. ‘A strange word, innocence. It means lack of knowledge, like the innocence of a child, and also means lack of guilt. Only those entirely ignorant can lack all responsibility for the consequences of their actions. He knows not what he does, and therefore can be without harmful intent; so says that word.’ The deep voice did not echo in the woods.

Harry’s eyes flickered to the spear-tip, and he realized that he should have grabbed his Time-Turner the moment he saw the centaur. Now, if Harry tried to reach beneath his robes, the spear could strike him before then, if the centaur was fast enough. ‘I read once,’ Harry said, his voice a bit unsteady as he tried to match deep-sounding words to deep-sounding words, ‘that it’s wrong to think of little children as innocent, because not knowing isn’t the same as not choosing. That children do little harms to each other with school-yard fights, because they don’t have the power to do great harm. And some adults do great harm. But the adults who don’t, aren’t they more innocent than children, not less?’

‘The wisdom of wizards,’ the centaur said.

‘Muggle wisdom, actually.’

‘Of the magicless I know little. Mars has been dim of late, but it grows brighter.’ The centaur took another step forwards, bringing him almost within striking distance of Harry.

Harry didn’t dare look up to the sky. ‘That means Mars is coming closer to the Earth, as both planets go around the Sun. Mars is reflecting the same amount of sunlight as always, it’s just getting nearer to us. What do you mean, the stars proclaim my innocence?’

‘The night sky speaks to centaurs. It is how we know what we know. Or do they not even tell wizards that much, these days?’ A look of contempt crossed the centaur’s face.

‘I … tried to look up centaurs, when I was checking out Divination. Most of the authors just ridiculed centaur Divination without explaining why, wizards don’t understand argumentative norms, to them ridiculing an idea or a person feels like casting that idea down just as much as bringing evidence against it … I thought the part about centaurs using astrology was just more ridicule …’

‘Why?’ the centaur intoned. His head cocked curiously.

‘Because the course of the planets is predictable for thousands of years in advance. If I talked to the right Muggles, I could show you a diagram of exactly what the planets will look like from this spot ten years later. Would you be able to make predictions from that?’

The centaur shook his head. ‘From a diagram? No. The light of the planets, the comets, the subtle shifts in the stars themselves, those I would not see.’

‘Cometary orbits are also set thousands of years in advance so they shouldn’t correlate much to current events. And the light of the stars takes years to travel from the stars to Earth, and the stars don’t move much at all, not visibly. So the obvious hypothesis is that centaurs have a native magical talent for Divination which you just, well, project onto the night sky.’

‘Perhaps,’ the centaur said thoughtfully. His head lowered. ‘The others would strike you for saying such a thing, but I have ever sought to know what I do not know. Why the night sky can foretell the future – that I surely do not know. It is hard enough to grasp the skill itself. All I can say, son of Lily, is that even if what you are saying is true, it does not seem useful.’

Harry allowed himself to relax a little; being addressed as son of Lily implied that the centaur thought of him as more than a random intruder in the forest. Besides, attacking a Hogwarts student would probably bring some kind of huge reprisal upon the non-wizard centaur tribe in the forests, and the centaur probably knew that … ‘What Muggles have learned is that there is a power in the truth, in all the pieces of the truth which interact with each other, which you can only find by discovering as many truths as possible. To do that you can’t defend false beliefs in any way, not even by saying the false belief is useful. It might not seem to matter whether your predictions are really based on the stars or if it’s an innate talent being projected. But if you wanted to really understand Divination, or for that matter the stars, the real truth about centaur predictions would be a fact that matters to other truths.’

Slowly the centaur nodded. ‘So the wandless have become wiser than the wizards. What a joke! Tell me, son of Lily, do the Muggles in their wisdom say that soon the skies will be empty?’

‘Empty?’ Harry said. ‘Er … no?’

‘The other centaurs in this forest have stayed from your presence, for we are sworn not to set ourselves against the heavens’ course. Because, in becoming entangled in your fate, we might become less innocent in what is to come. I alone have dared approach you.’

‘I … don’t understand.’

‘No. You are innocent, as the stars say. And to slay something innocent to save oneself, that is a terrible deed. One would live only a cursed life, a half-life, from that day. For any centaur would surely be cast out, if he slew a foal.’

The spear made a lightning motion, too fast for Harry’s eyes to follow, and smashed his wand out of his hand.

Another powerful blow smashed into Harry’s solar plexus, and he went gasping and retching to the forest floor.

Harry’s hand reached up toward his robes, for his Time-Turner, and the spear-butt knocked his hand away, almost hard enough to break fingers, he reached with his other hand and that was knocked away too –

‘I am sorry, Harry Potter,’ the centaur said, and then looked up with widened eyes. The spear spun about and came up, intercepting a red spellbolt. Then the centaur dropped the spear and leaped away desperately, a green flash of light went past him and another green flash of light followed in its wake, then a third green flash hit the centaur straight-on.

The centaur fell and did not move again.

It took a long time for Harry to catch his breath, to stagger to his feet, to pick up his wand, to croak, ‘What?’

By that time the sense of doom, of power almost tangible in the air, had approached once more.

‘P-Professor Quirrell? What are you doing here?’

‘Well,’ the man in the black cloak said thoughtfully, ‘you needed to fly into a rage and have a loud tantrum in the Forbidden Forest in the middle of the night, and I needed to go just outside your ability to detect me and keep watch. One does not leave a student alone in the Forbidden Forest. That should be obvious in retrospect.’

Harry stared at the fallen centaur.

The horse-form wasn’t breathing.

‘You – you killed him, that was Avada Kedavra –’

‘I do not always understand how other people imagine morality to work, Mr Potter. But even I know that on conventional morality, it is acceptable to kill non-human creatures which are about to slay a wizard child. Perhaps you do not care about the non-human part, but he was about to kill you. He was hardly innocent –’

The Defence Professor stopped, looking at Harry, who had raised one trembling hand to his mouth.

‘Well,’ the Defence Professor said then, ‘I have made my point, and you may think on it. Centaur spears can block many spells, but no one tries to block if they see that the spell is a certain shade of green. For this purpose it is useful to know some green stunning hexes. Really, Mr Potter, you should understand by now how I operate.’

The Defence Professor came nearer the centaur’s body, and Harry took an involuntary step back, then another, at the terrible rising sense of stop, don’t –

The Defence Professor knelt and pressed his wand to the centaur’s head.

The wand stayed there for a time.

And the centaur rose, eyes blank, breathing once more.

‘Remember nothing of this time,’ the Defence Professor commanded. ‘Wander away and forget everything about this night.’

The centaur walked away, the four horse-legs moving in strange synchrony.

‘Happy now?’ the Defence Professor said, sounding rather sardonic about it.

Harry’s brain still felt broken. ‘He was trying to kill me.’

‘Oh, for Merlin’s sake – yes, he was trying to kill you. Get used to it. Only boring people never have that experience.’

Harry’s voice emerged, hoarse. ‘Why – why did he want to –’

‘Any number of reasons. I would be lying if I said I’d never considered killing you myself.’

Harry stared at where the centaur had wandered into the trees.

His brain still felt half-broken, like an engine misfiring, but Harry did not see how this could possibly be a good sign.

The news of Draco Malfoy nearly being eaten by a horror had been sufficient to summon back Dumbledore from wherever he’d gone, to wake Lord Malfoy and the Lady Greengrass’s handsome husband, to bring forth Amelia Bones. The supposed presence of the horror had provoked skepticism even from Dumbledore, and the possibility of False Memory Charms had been raised. Harry had said (after some internal debate about the consequences of people believing a demon was on the loose) that he didn’t actually remember making the same effort he’d put forth to frighten the Dementor, the dark thing had just left; which was what you would expect someone to create as a False Memory, if they hadn’t actually known how Harry had done it. The names of Bellatrix Black, Severus Snape, and Quirinus Quirrell had been mentioned in connection with wizards strong enough to subdue everyone present and cast False Memory Charms, and Harry had known that Lucius was thinking of Dumbledore. There had been Aurors testifying, and discussions going in circles, and glares of accusation, and cutting remarks at 2AM in the morning. There had been motions, and votes, and consequences.

‘Do you believe,’ Headmaster Dumbledore said quietly to Harry, when all of it was done, and the two of them alone, ‘that the Hogwarts you have wrought is an improvement?’

Harry sat with his elbows on his knees, his face resting on his palms, in the conference room from which all the others had now departed. Professor McGonagall, who did not use a Time-Turner as routinely as the two of them, had departed swiftly for her bed.

‘Yes,’ Harry answered after too long a hesitation. ‘From my perspective, Headmaster, things in Hogwarts are finally, finally normal. This is how things should be, when four children get sent into the Forbidden Forest at night. There should be a huge fuss, constables showing up, and the responsible party getting sacked.’

‘You believe it is good,’ Dumbledore said quietly, ‘that the man who you call responsible was, as you put it, sacked.’

‘Yes, in fact, I do.’

‘Argus Filch has served this institution for decades.’

‘And when given Veritaserum,’ Harry said tiredly, ‘Argus Filch revealed that he had sent an eleven-year-old boy into the Forbidden Forest, hoping something awful would happen to him, because he thought the boy’s father had been responsible for the death of his cat. The three other students in Draco’s company don’t seem to have fazed him. I would have argued for jail time, but your concept of jail in this country is Azkaban. I’ll also note that Filch was remarkably unpleasant to the children in Hogwarts and I expect the school’s hedonic index to be improved by his departure, not that it matters to you, I suppose.’

The Headmaster’s eyes were impenetrable behind the half-moon glasses. ‘Argus Filch is a Squib. His work at Hogwarts is all he has. Had, rather.’

‘The purpose of a school is not to provide work for its employees. I know you probably spent more time around Filch than around any individual student, but that shouldn’t make Filch’s inner experiences loom larger in your thoughts. Students have inner lives too.’

‘You don’t care at all, do you Harry?’ Dumbledore’s voice was quiet. ‘About those you hurt.’

‘I care about the innocent,’ Harry said. ‘Like Mr Hagrid, who you’ll note I argued should not be considered malicious, just oblivious. I was fine with Mr Hagrid working here so long as he didn’t take anyone into the Forbidden Forest again.’

‘I had thought that with Rubeus vindicated, he might teach Care of Magical Creatures after Silvanus departs the position. But much of that teaching is done in the Forbidden Forest. So that too shall not be, in the wake of your passage.’

Harry said slowly, ‘But – you told us that Mr Hagrid has a blind spot when it comes to magical creatures threatening wizards. That Mr Hagrid had a cognitive deficit and couldn’t really imagine Draco and Tracey getting hurt, which was why Mr Hagrid didn’t see anything wrong with leaving them alone in the Forbidden Forest at night. Was that not true?’

‘It is true.’

‘Then wouldn’t Mr Hagrid be the worst possible teacher for Magical Creatures?’

The old wizard gazed down at Harry through the half-moon glasses. His voice was thick when he spoke. ‘Mr Malfoy himself saw nothing awry. It was not so implausible a trick which Argus played, Harry Potter. And Rubeus might have grown into his position. It would have been – all Rubeus wished, his one greatest desire –’

‘Your mistake,’ Harry said, looking down at his knees, feeling at least ten percent as exhausted as he’d ever been, ‘is a cognitive bias we would call, in the trade, scope insensitivity. Failure to multiply. You’re thinking about how happy Mr Hagrid would be when he heard the news. Consider the next ten years and a thousand students taking Magical Creatures and ten percent of them being scalded by Ashwinders. No one student would be hurt as much as Mr Hagrid would be happy, but there’d be a hundred students being hurt and only one happy teacher.’

‘Perhaps,’ the old wizard said. ‘And your own error, Harry, is that you do not feel the pain of those you hurt, once you have done your multiplication.’

‘Maybe.’ Harry went on staring at his knees. ‘Or maybe it’s worse than that. Headmaster, what does it mean if a centaur doesn’t like me?’ What does it mean when a member of a race of magical creatures known for Divination gives you a lecture on people who are ignorant of consequences, apologizes, and then tries to stab you with a spear?

‘A centaur?’ the Headmaster said. ‘When did you – ah, the Time-Turner. You are the reason why I could not travel back to before the event, on pain of paradox.’

‘Am I? I guess I am.’ Harry shook his head distantly. ‘Sorry.’

‘With very few exceptions,’ Dumbledore said, ‘centaurs do not like wizards, at all.’

‘This was a bit more specific than that.’

‘What did the centaur say to you?’

Harry didn’t reply.

‘Ah.’ The Headmaster hesitated. ‘Centaurs have been wrong many times, and if there is anyone in the world who could confuse the stars themselves, it is you.’

Harry looked up, and saw the blue eyes once more gentle behind the half-circle glasses.

‘Do not fret too much about it,’ said Albus Dumbledore.

One of the things Harry hadn’t planned on, when he’d decided to do this, was that he would still be out here at – Harry glanced at his watch – eleven-oh-four at night. Harry was now reading a sixth-year Transfiguration textbook; or rather he’d weighted the book open, illuminated by a Muggle glowstick, while he did one of the exercises. Last week, when the graduating Ravenclaws were discussing their N.E.W.T. scores, Harry had overheard that upper-year Transfiguration practise involved several shaping exercises that relied more on control and precise thinking than raw power; and Harry had promptly set out to learn those, whacking himself hard on the forehead for not trying to read all the later-year textbooks earlier. Professor McGonagall had approved Harry doing a shaping exercise that involved controlling the way in which a Transfiguring object approached its final form – for example, Transfiguring a quill so that the shaft grew out first, then the barbs. Harry was doing an analogous exercise with pencils, growing out the lead first, then surrounding it with wood and finally having the eraser form on top. As Harry had suspected, focusing his attention and magic into a particular part of the pencil’s ongoing transformation had proven similar to the mental discipline used in partial Transfiguration – which could indeed have been used to fake the same effect, by partially Transfiguring only the outer layers of the object. This way was proving relatively easier, though.

Harry finished his current pencil and looked up at the Quidditch game, which was, check, still fantastically boring. Lee Jordan was commentating in a tone of dull disgust, ‘Another ten points – yay – whoopee – and now someone takes possession of the Quaffle again – ask if I care who.’

Almost nobody remaining in the stands was paying attention either, since everyone who’d remained in the stadium seemed to have discovered a new and more interesting sport, the debate about how to amend the House Cup rules and/or Quidditch. The argument had become heated to the point where all of the nearby Professors were barely keeping order at a level short of open combat. This argument, unfortunately, had considerably more than two factions. Some annoying busybodies were proposing sensible-sounding alternatives to eliminating the Snitch entirely, and this was threatening to split the vote and sap the momentum for reform.

In retrospect, Harry thought, it would have been nice to have Draco unfurl his own banner from the Slytherin side saying snitches are awesome, to set the polarity of the debate. Harry had squinted over at the Slytherin section earlier, but he hadn’t been able to spot Draco anywhere in the stands. Severus Snape, who could also have been sympathetic enough to play the villainous opposition, was likewise nowhere to be seen.

‘Mr Potter?’ said a voice next to him.

Beside Harry’s seat was standing a short but older Hufflepuff boy, someone who’d never before come to Harry’s attention, holding out a blank parchment envelope with wax dripped on the front. The wax was also blank, without impression.

‘What is it?’ said Harry.

‘It’s me,’ said the boy. ‘With the envelope you gave me. I know you said not to talk to you, but –’

‘Then don’t talk to me,’ Harry said.

The boy tossed the envelope at Harry and walked away, looking offended. It made Harry wince a little, but it probably hadn’t been the wrong decision considering the temporal issues …

Then Harry broke the unsigned wax seal and drew out the envelope’s contents. It was parchment instead of the Muggle paper that Harry would have expected, but the writing on it was his own handwriting, if done with a quill instead of a pen. The parchment said:

Beware the constellation,
and help the watcher of stars.

Pass unseen by the life-eaters’ confederates,
and by the wise and the well-meaning.

Six, and seven in a square,
in the place that is prohibited and bloody stupid.

Harry took it in at a glance, then folded the paper again and put it back into his cloak with another exhaled sigh. Beware the constellation, really? Harry would have expected a riddle left by himself, to himself, to have been easier to interpret … though some parts were obvious enough. Clearly future-Harry had been worried about this paper being intercepted, and while present-Harry wouldn’t ordinarily have thought of the local Aurors as “the ones in league with the Dementors of Azkaban”, maybe that had been the best way to say Auror without potentially tipping off anyone else who read the parchment and did their own best to decrypt it. Translating the idiom back out of the Parseltongue he’d used during the Incident with Azkaban … that worked, Harry supposed.

The note had said that Professor Quirrell needed help, and that whatever was going on needed to pass unnoticed from the Aurors, and from Dumbledore and McGonagall and Flitwick. Since Time-Turning was involved already, the obvious solution was to leave for the loo, travel back in time, and return to the game right after he’d left.

Harry started to rise from his seat, then hesitated. His Hufflepuff side was remarking something about leaving the Auror escorts behind and not telling Professor McGonagall anything, and wondering if his future self was being stupid.

Harry unfolded the parchment again, and took another glance at the contents.

On closer examination, the riddle-verse didn’t say that Harry couldn’t bring anyone along. Draco Malfoy … was he missing from the Quidditch game because future-Harry, hours in the past, had brought Draco with him as backup? But that didn’t make sense, there wasn’t much marginal improvement in safety from bringing along another first-year …

… Draco Malfoy would certainly have been present, regardless of his personal feelings about Quidditch, to watch Slytherin clinch the House Cup. Had something happened to him?

Suddenly Harry didn’t feel as tired any more.

A trickle of adrenaline was starting to rise in Harry, but no, this wouldn’t be like the troll. The message had told Harry when to arrive. Harry wouldn’t be too late, not this time.

Harry glanced over at where Cedric Diggory was looking back and forth, visibly torn between a clutch of Ravenclaws arguing that the Snitch had to be kept because it was traditional and rules were rules, and a pack of Hufflepuffs saying that it wasn’t fair for the Seeker to be more important than the other players.

Cedric Diggory had been an excellent duelling tutor to Harry and Neville, and Harry had thought they’d established a good relationship. More importantly, a student taking literally all of the electives would have his own Time-Turner. Maybe Harry could try to get Cedric to go back in time with him? The Super Hufflepuff seemed like a good spare wand to have by your side in any sort of sticky situation …

A pinch of red-brown dust was gently sifted into the potions cauldron, and Harry asked his fourth and final question, the one that had seemed to have the lowest priority, but still mattered.

‘What was your objective during the Wizarding War?’ Harry said. ‘I mean, what –’ His voice wobbled. ‘What was the point of the entire thing?’ His brain repeating endlessly, Why, why, why Lord Voldemort …

Professor Quirrell lifted an eyebrow. ‘They told you about David Monroe, did they not?’

‘Yes you were both David Monroe and Lord Voldemort during the Wizarding War, I understood that part. You killed David Monroe, disguised yourself as him, and wiped out David Monroe’s family so they wouldn’t notice any differences –’

‘Indeed.’

‘You planned to control whichever side won the Wizarding War, regardless of which side won. But why did one side have to be Voldemort? I, I mean, wouldn’t it have been easier to gain public support with someone less … with someone less Voldemort?’

Professor Quirrell’s mallet made an unusually loud thud as it crushed white butterfly wings, mixing them with another bellflower. ‘I planned,’ Professor Quirrell said harshly, ‘for Lord Voldemort to lose to David Monroe. The flaw in that strategy was the absolute wretchedness of –’ Professor Quirrell stopped. ‘No, I am telling the tale out of order. Listen, boy, when I had devised my great creation and come into the fullness of my magic, I thought the time had come for me to take political power into my hands. It would be inconvenient, certainly, and take up my time in ways that were not enjoyable. But I knew the Muggles would eventually destroy the world or make war on wizardkind or both, and something had to be done if I was not to wander a dead or dull world through my eternity. Having attained immortality I needed a new ambition to occupy my decades, and to prevent the Muggles from ruining everything seemed a goal of acceptable scope and difficulty. It is a source of continual amusement to me that I, of all people, am the only one really taking action towards that end. Though I suppose it would make sense for the mortal insects not to care about their world’s end; why should they, when they are just going to die regardless, and can save themselves the inconvenience of trying to do anything difficult along the way? But I digress. I saw how Dumbledore had risen to power from his defeat of Grindelwald, so I thought I would do the same. I had long ago taken my vengeance on David Monroe – he was an annoyance from my year in Slytherin – so I bethought to also steal his identity, and wipe out his family to make myself heir of his House. And I conceived also a great foe for David Monroe to fight, the most terrifying Dark Lord imaginable, clever beyond reckoning; more dangerous by far than Grindelwald, for his intelligence would be perfected in all the ways that Grindelwald had been flawed and self-destructive. A Dark Lord who would do his cunning utmost to disrupt the alliances who would fight him, a Dark Lord who would command the deepest loyalty from his followers through his oratorical skills. The most dreadful Dark Lord who had ever threatened Britain or the world, that was who David Monroe would defeat.’

Professor Quirrell’s mallet struck a bellflower and then a different pale flower with two more thuds. ‘But then, while I had sometimes played the part of Dark Wizard in my wanderings, I had never adopted the identity of a full-fledged Dark Lord with underlings and a political agenda. I had no practise at the task, and I was mindful of the story of Dark Evangel and the disaster of her first public appearance. According to what she said afterwards, she had meant to call herself the Walking Catastrophe and the Apostle of Darkness, but in the excitement of the moment she introduced herself as the Apostrophe of Darkness instead. After that she had to ruin two entire villages before anyone took her seriously.’

‘So you decided to try a small-scale experiment first,’ Harry said. A sickness rose up in him, because in that moment Harry understood, he saw himself reflected; the next step was just what Harry himself would have done, if he’d had no trace of ethics whatsoever, if he’d been that empty inside. ‘You created a disposable identity, to learn how the ropes worked, and get your mistakes out of the way.’

‘Indeed. Before becoming a truly terrible Dark Lord for David Monroe to fight, I first created for practise the persona of a Dark Lord with glowing red eyes, pointlessly cruel to his underlings, pursuing a political agenda of naked personal ambition combined with blood purism as argued by drunks in Knockturn Alley. My first underlings were hired in a tavern, given cloaks and skull masks, and told to introduce themselves as Death Eaters.’

The sick sense of understanding deepened, in the pit of Harry’s stomach. ‘And you called yourself Voldemort.’

‘Just so, General Chaos.’ Professor Quirrell was grinning, from where he stood by the cauldron. ‘I wanted it to be an anagram of my name, but that would only have worked if I’d conveniently been given the middle name of “Marvolo”, and then it would have been a stretch. Our actual middle name is Morfin, if you’re curious. But I digress. I thought Voldemort’s career would last only a few months, a year at the longest, before the Aurors brought down his underlings and the disposable Dark Lord vanished. As you perceive, I had vastly overestimated my competition. And I could not quite bring myself to torture my underlings when they brought me bad news, no matter what Dark Lords did in plays. I could not quite manage to argue the tenets of blood purism as incoherently as if I were a drunk in Knockturn Alley. I was not trying to be clever when I sent my underlings on their missions, but neither did I give them entirely pointless orders –’ Professor Quirrell gave a rueful grin that, in another context, might have been called charming. ‘One month after that, Bellatrix Black prostrated herself before me, and after three months Lucius Malfoy was negotiating with me over glasses of expensive Firewhiskey. I sighed, gave up all hope for wizardkind, and began as David Monroe to oppose this fearsome Lord Voldemort.’

‘And then what happened –’

A snarl contorted Professor Quirrell’s face. ‘The absolute inadequacy of every single institution in the civilization of magical Britain is what happened! You cannot comprehend it, boy! I cannot comprehend it! It has to be seen and even then it cannot be believed! You will have observed, perhaps, that of your fellow students who speak of their family’s occupations, three in four seem to mention jobs in some part or another of the Ministry. You will wonder how a country can manage to employ three of its four citizens in bureaucracy. The answer is that if they did not all prevent each other from doing their jobs, none of them would have any work left to do! The Aurors were competent as individual fighters, they did fight Dark Wizards and only the best survived to train new recruits, but their leadership was in absolute disarray. The Ministry was so busy routing papers that the country had no effective opposition to Voldemort’s attacks except myself, Dumbledore, and a handful of untrained irregulars. A shiftless, incompetent, cowardly layabout, Mundungus Fletcher, was considered a key asset in the Order of the Phoenix – because, being otherwise unemployed, he did not need to juggle another job! I tried weakening Voldemort’s attacks, to see if it was possible for him to lose; at once the Ministry committed fewer Aurors to oppose me! I had read Mao’s Little Red Book, I had trained my Death Eaters in guerilla tactics – for nothing! For nothing! I was attacking all of magical Britain and in every engagement my forces outnumbered their opposition! In desperation, I ordered my Death Eaters to systematically assassinate every single incompetent managing the Department of Magical Law Enforcement. One paper-pusher after another volunteered to accept higher positions despite the fate of their predecessors, gleefully rubbing their hands at the prospect of promotion. Every one of them thought they would cut a deal with Lord Voldemort on the side. It took seven months to murder our way through them all, and not a single Death Eater asked why we were bothering. And then, even with Bartemius Crouch risen to Director and Amelia Bones as Head Auror, it was still too little. I could have done better fighting alone. Dumbledore’s aid was not worth his moral restraints, and Crouch’s aid was not worth his respect for the law.’ Professor Quirrell turned up the fire beneath the potion.

‘And eventually,’ Harry said through the heart-sickness, ‘you realized you were just having more fun as Voldemort.’

‘It is the least annoying role I have ever played. If Lord Voldemort says that something is to be done, people obey him and do not argue. I did not have to suppress my impulse to Cruciate people being idiots; for once it was all part of the role. If someone was making the game less pleasant for me, I just said Avada Kedavra regardless of whether that was strategically wise, and they never bothered me again.’ Professor Quirrell casually chopped a small worm into bits. ‘But my true epiphany came on a certain day when David Monroe was trying to get an entry permit for an Asian instructor in combat tactics, and a Ministry clerk denied it, smiling smugly. I asked the Ministry clerk if he understood that this measure was meant to save his life and the Ministry clerk only smiled more. Then in fury I threw aside masks and caution, I used my Legilimency, I dipped my fingers into the cesspit of his stupidity and tore out the truth from his mind. I did not understand and I wanted to understand. With my command of Legilimency I forced his tiny clerk-brain to live out alternatives, seeing what his clerk-brain would think of Lucius Malfoy, or Lord Voldemort, or Dumbledore standing in my place.’ Professor Quirrell’s hands had slowed, as he delicately peeled bits and small strips from a chunk of candle-wax. ‘What I finally realized that day is complicated, boy, which is why I did not understand it earlier in life. To you I shall try to describe it anyway. Today I know that Dumbledore does not stand at the top of the world, for all that he is the Supreme Mugwump of the International Confederation. People speak ill of Dumbledore openly, they criticize him proudly and to his face, in a way they would not dare stand up to Lucius Malfoy. You have acted disrespectfully toward Dumbledore, boy, do you know why you did so?’

‘I’m … not sure,’ Harry said. Having Tom Riddle’s leftover neural patterns was certainly an obvious hypothesis.

‘Wolves, dogs, even chickens, fight for dominance among themselves. What I finally understood, from that clerk’s mind, was that to him Lucius Malfoy had dominance, Lord Voldemort had dominance, and David Monroe and Albus Dumbledore did not. By taking the side of good, by professing to abide in the light, we had made ourselves unthreatening. In Britain, Lucius Malfoy has dominance, for he can call in your loans, or send Ministry bureaucrats against your shop, or crucify you in the Daily Prophet, if you go openly against his will. And the most powerful wizard in the world has no dominance, because everyone knows that he is,’ Professor Quirrell’s lips curled, ‘a hero out of stories, relentlessly self-effacing and too humble for vengeance. Tell me, child, have you ever seen a drama where the hero, before he consents to save his country, demands so much gold as a barrister might receive for a court case?’

‘Actually there have been a lot of heroes like that in Muggle fiction, I’ll name Han Solo just to start –’

‘Well, in magical drama it is not so. It is all humble heroes like Dumbledore. It is the fantasy of the powerful slave who will never truly rise above you, never demand your respect, never even ask you for pay. Do you understand now?’

‘I … think so,’ Harry said. Frodo and Samwise from Lord of the Rings did seem to match the archetype of a completely non-threatening hero. ‘You’re saying that’s how people think of Dumbledore? I don’t believe the Hogwarts students see him as a hobbit.’

‘In Hogwarts, Dumbledore does punish certain transgressions against his will, so he is feared to some degree – though the students still make free to mock him in more than whispers. Outside this castle, Dumbledore is sneered at; they began to call him mad, and he aped the part like a fool. Step into the role of a saviour out of plays, and people see you as a slave to whose services they are entitled and whom it is their enjoyment to criticize; for it is the privilege of masters to sit back and call forth helpful corrections while the slaves labour. Only in the tales of the ancient Greeks, from when men were less sophisticated in their delusions, may you see the hero who is also high. Hector, Aeneas, those were heroes who retained their right of vengeance upon those who insulted them, who could demand gold and jewels in payment for their services without sparking indignation. And if Lord Voldemort conquered Britain, he might then condescend to show himself noble in victory; and nobody would take his goodwill for granted, nor chirp corrections at him if his work was not to their liking. When he won, he would have true respect. I understood that day in the Ministry that by envying Dumbledore, I had shown myself as deluded as Dumbledore himself. I understood that I had been trying for the wrong place all along. You should know this to be true, boy, for you have made freer to speak ill of Dumbledore than you ever dared speak ill of me. Even in your own thoughts, I wager, for instinct runs deep. You knew that it might be to your cost to mock the strong and vengeful Professor Quirrell, but that there was no cost in disrespecting the weak and harmless Dumbledore.’

‘Thank you,’ Harry said through the pain, ‘for that valuable lesson, Professor Quirrell, I see that you are right about what my mind was doing.’ Though Tom Riddle’s memories had probably also had something to do with the way he had sometimes lashed out at Dumbledore for no good reason, Harry hadn’t been like that around Professor McGonagall … who admittedly had the power to deduct House Points and didn’t have Dumbledore’s air of tolerance … no, it was still true, Harry would have been more respectful even in his own thoughts if Dumbledore had not seemed safe to disrespect.

So that had been David Monroe, and that had been Lord Voldemort …

Harry held the parchment scroll for a long time, staring at nothing.

So.

There were times when the phrase That explains it didn’t really seem to cover it, but nonetheless, that explained it.

Absently Harry rolled up the parchment scroll in his fist, still staring at nothing.

‘What does it say?’ said Amelia Bones.

‘It’s a confession letter,’ Harry said. ‘Turns out Dumbledore’s the one who killed my pet rock.’

‘This is not a time for jokes!’ cried the elder witch. ‘Are you the true holder of the Line of Merlin Unbroken?’

‘Yes,’ Harry said absently, his mind occupied with thoughts that were, by any objective quantification, overwhelmingly more important.

The old witch was sitting very still in her chair. She turned her head, and locked eyes with Minerva McGonagall.

Meanwhile Harry’s brain, which was juggling way too many possibilities over way too many time horizons, some of them involving literally billions of years and stellar disassembly procedures, declared cognitive bankruptcy and started over. All right, what’s the first thing I have to do to save the world … no, make it even more local, what do I have to do today … besides figuring out what to do, that is, and I’d better not delay before looking at whatever Dumbledore left me in the Phoenix’s Egg room …

Harry raised his eyes from the rolled-up parchment and looked at Professor – at Headmistress McGonagall, at Mad-Eye Moody, and at the leathery-looking old witch, as though seeing them for the first time. Though he was in fact seeing Amelia Bones for mostly the first time.

Amelia Bones, head of the Department of Magical Law Enforcement, whom Albus Dumbledore had thought worthy to lead the Wizengamot at least temporarily. Her cooperation would be invaluable, maybe necessary, for … for whatever was headed Harry’s way. Dumbledore had chosen her, and he’d read prophecies Harry hadn’t seen.

Amelia Bones, who had thought she’d been appointed regent over the Line of Merlin Unbroken and made the next Chief Warlock, only to find that instead the position had gone to, apparently, an eleven-year-old boy.

You will now, said the voice of Hufflepuff inside his head, you will now be polite. You will not be your usual brand of bloody idiot. Because the fate of the world might just depend on it. Or not. We don’t even know.

‘I’m terribly sorry about all this,’ Harry Potter said, then paused to see what effect, if any, this polite statement had produced.

‘Minerva seems to think,’ the old witch said, ‘that you will not take offense to honest words.’

Harry nodded. His Ravenclaw part wanted to include the disclaimer about that being different from people blatantly trying to push you down while crying that you were intolerant of criticism, but Hufflepuff vetoed. Whatever she had to say, Harry would hear.

‘I do not wish to speak ill of the departed,’ the old witch said. ‘But since time immemorial, the Line of Merlin Unbroken has passed to those who have thoroughly demonstrated themselves to be, not only good people, but wise enough to distinguish successors who are themselves both good and wise. A single break, anywhere along the chain, and the succession might go astray and never return! It was a mad act for Dumbledore to pass the Line to you at such a young age, even having made it conditional upon your defeat of You-Know-Who. A tarnish upon Dumbledore’s legacy, that is how it will be seen.’ The old witch hesitated, her eyes still watching Harry. ‘I think it best that nobody outside this room ever learn of it.’

‘Um,’ Harry said. ‘You … don’t think very much of Dumbledore, I take it?’

‘I thought …’ said the old witch. ‘Well. Albus Dumbledore was a better wizard than I, a better person than I, in more ways than I can easily count. But the man had his faults.’

‘Because, um. I mean. Dumbledore knew everything you just said. About my being young and how the Line works. You’re acting like you think Dumbledore was unaware of those facts, or just ignoring them, when he made his decision. It’s true that sometimes stupid people, like me, make decisions that crazy. But not Dumbledore. He was not mad.’ Harry swallowed, forcing a sudden moisture away from his eyes. ‘I think … I’m beginning to realize … Dumbledore was the only sane person, in all of this, all along. The only one who was doing the right things for anything like the right reasons …’

Madam Bones was cursing under her breath, low dire imprecations that were making Minerva McGonagall twitch.

‘I’m sorry,’ Harry said helplessly.

Mad-Eye was grinning, the scarred face twisting up in a smile. ‘Always knew Albus was up to something he never told the rest of us. Lad, you have no idea how hard it is for me not to use my Eye on that scroll.’

Harry quickly shoved the scroll into his mokeskin pouch.

‘Alastor,’ Amelia said. The old witch’s voice was rising. ‘You are a man of sense, you cannot think the lad is able to fill Dumbledore’s socks! Not today!’

‘Dumbledore,’ Harry said, the name tasting strange on his tongue, ‘did make one wrong assumption, when he made his decisions. He thought we’d be fighting Voldemort for years, all of us together. He didn’t know I’d vanquish Voldemort immediately. It was the right thing for me to do, it saved a lot of lives compared to fighting a long battle. But Dumbledore thought you would have years to learn me, trust me … and instead it was all over in an evening.’ Harry inhaled. ‘Can’t you just pretend we’ve been fighting Voldemort for years and I earned your trust and everything? So that I’m not penalised for winning more quickly than Dumbledore expected?’

‘You are still a first-year in Hogwarts!’ the old witch said. ‘You cannot take Dumbledore’s place, whatever his intentions!’

‘Right, that whole “looking like an eleven-year-old” thing.’ Harry’s hand came up, rubbed at his nose where his glasses lay. I suppose I could just use the Stone, change myself to look like ninety …

‘I am not a fool,’ the old witch said. ‘I know you are no ordinary child. I have seen you speak to Lucius Malfoy, watched you frighten off a Dementor, and witnessed Fawkes grant your plea. Anyone with wisdom who saw you before the Wizengamot – by which I mean myself and at most two others – could guess that you had absorbed some portion of You-Know-Who’s shredded soul on the night of his undeath, but subdued it and turned his knowledge to good ends.’

There was a slight pause in the room.

‘Well, yes, of course,’ said Minerva McGonagall. She sighed, slumped a bit in the Headmistress’s chair. ‘As Albus clearly knew from the very beginning, but thoughtfully declined to warn me about in any way whatsoever.’

‘Right,’ Moody said. ‘I knew that. Yep. Perfectly obvious. Wasn’t confused at all.’

‘I guess that’s close enough to the truth,’ said Harry. ‘So, um. What’s the problem, exactly?’

‘The problem,’ Amelia Bones said, her voice perfectly even, ‘is that you are a bubbling, unstable blend of a Hogwarts first-year and You-Know-Who.’ She paused, as though waiting for something.

‘I’m getting better about that,’ Harry said, since she seemed to be waiting on his reply. ‘Quite rapidly, in fact. More importantly, it’s not something Dumbledore didn’t know.’

The old witch continued. ‘Giving away your fortune and going in debt to Lucius Malfoy to keep your best friend out of Azkaban, as much as it demonstrates your upstanding moral character, also demonstrates that you cannot corral the Wizengamot. I can see now that you did the right thing for yourself, the thing you had to do to maintain your lease on sanity and hold back your inner darkness. But you also did a thing that Merlin’s heir must not do. A sentimental leader can be far worse than a selfish one. Albus, master and servant of a phoenix, was barely survivable – and even he opposed you that day.’ Amelia gestured in the direction of Mad-Eye Moody. ‘Alastor has hardness. He has cunning. He still does not have the talent for government. You, Harry Potter, do not yet have the sternness, the capacity for sacrifice, to direct even the Order of the Phoenix. And being what you are, you must not try to become that person. Not now, not at your age. Align and fuse your divided soul in your own time, if you possibly can. Do not try to be Chief Warlock while you are doing it. If Albus thought that was a good idea, he was crafting a nicer story at the expense of real-world practicality. I do think the man had a problem with that.’

Harry’s eyes were a bit wide, listening to all this. ‘Um … what exactly do you think is going on in here?’ Harry tapped his head just above his ear.

‘I imagine that inside you is the soul of a boy who remains honest and true, gathering his will to force down the fragment of Voldemort’s spirit that tries to consume him, even as it howls at him that he is sentimental and weak – did you just giggle?’

‘Sorry. But seriously, it wasn’t ever that bad. More like having a lot of bad habits I needed to break.’

‘Ahem,’ said Headmistress McGonagall. ‘Mr Potter, I think at the start of this year it was that bad.’

‘Bad habits that chained into and triggered each other. Yes, those are a bit more of a problem.’ Harry sighed. ‘And you, Madam Bones … er. Sorry if I’m wrong about this. But my guess is that you’re feeling a bit upset that the Line went to an eleven-year-old?’

‘Not the way you are thinking,’ the old witch said calmly. ‘Though it is natural for you to suspect me. The position of Chief Warlock is not one I will find pleasant, even compared to the horrors of Magical Law Enforcement. Albus persuaded me on the matter, and I would say that I took some convincing, but the truth is that I did not waste his time in an argument I expected to lose. I knew I would hate the task, and I knew I would do it anyway. Minerva says you have some amount of common sense, especially when others remind you of it. Can you really see yourself standing upon the Wizengamot’s high dais? Are you sure it is not some remnant of You-Know-Who that imagines himself suited to the position, or even desires it at all?’

Harry took off his glasses and massaged his forehead. His scar still ached a bit, from the damage he’d done by picking at it yesterday until it bled in a suitably dramatic fashion. ‘I do have some common sense, and yes, being Chief Warlock sounds like a huge amount of aggravation and a job that, in reality, does not fit me the tiniest bit. The trouble is. Um. I’m not sure the Line of Merlin is just about being Chief Warlock. There’s, um. I suspect … that there’s weird other stuff that goes along with it. And that Dumbledore meant me to take responsibility for the … other stuff. And that the other stuff is … possibly quite amazingly important.’

‘Crap,’ Moody said. Then Alastor Moody repeated, ‘Crap. Kid, should you even be saying this to us?’

‘I don’t know,’ Harry said. ‘If there’s a user manual, I haven’t looked at it yet.’

‘Crap.’

‘And if these other matters require sternness and sacrifice?’ Amelia Bones said, still calmly. ‘If they test you as you were tested before the Wizengamot? I am old, Harry Potter, and I am not without knowledge of mysteries. You have seen how I was able to perceive your own nature at nearly a glance.’

‘Amelia,’ Mad-Eye Moody said. ‘What would have happened if you’d had to fight You-Know-Who last night?’

The old witch shrugged. ‘I would have died, I expect.’

‘You’d have lost,’ said Alastor Moody. ‘And the Boy-Who-Lived didn’t just take out Voldie, he set it up so that his good friend Hermione Granger came back from the dead at the same time Voldie resurrected himself. There’s no way in hell or double hell that was an accident, and I don’t think it was David’s idea either. Amy, the truth is, none of us know what the keeper of Merlin’s legacy has to do. But we’re not the right kind of crazy for this crap.’

Amelia Bones frowned. ‘Alastor, you know I’ve dealt with strange things before. Dealt with them quite well, in my opinion.’

‘Yeah. You dealt with the crap so you could go back to real life. You’re not the kind of crazy that builds a castle out of the crap and lives there.’ Moody sighed. ‘Amy, on some level you know exactly why Albus had to leave who-knows-what-job to the poor kid.’

The old witch’s fists clenched on the table. ‘Do you have any idea of the disaster it would be for Britain? Call me sane, but I cannot accept that outcome! I have worked too long toward this day to see it fall apart now, now of all times!’

‘Excuse me,’ Headmistress McGonagall said, sounding quite precise and Scottish. ‘Is there any reason why Mr Potter cannot simply instruct the Line that Madam Bones is his regent for the position of Chief Warlock, but not anything having to do with the Department of Mysteries, until he comes of age? If Albus could tell the Line to appoint a regent only until Voldemort’s defeat, it is clearly capable of following complex orders.’

Slowly, this unexpected hammer-blow of common sense was absorbed by everyone present.

Harry opened his mouth to agree to appoint Amelia Bones his regent for Wizengamot-related matters, and then hesitated again.

‘Um,’ Harry said. ‘Um. Madam Bones, I would much prefer if you took charge of handling the Wizengamot instead of me.’

‘In that we are agreed,’ said the old witch. ‘Shall we let it be done?’

‘But –’

There was a sort of frustrated dropping-back of the others. ‘What is the problem, Mr Potter?’ said the Headmistress, in a voice that indicated she hoped it was nothing serious.

‘Um. I think there’s a couple of things I might have to do very soon that could … prove politically controversial, and in exchange for handing over the Line’s political power to Madam Bones I’m going to want her … um, cooperation on some things.’

Amelia Bones exchanged another long stare with Minerva McGonagall. Then she looked back at Harry Potter.

‘I am indignant at your request!’ Amelia Bones said. ‘Your hesitancy has told me that you are weak and unused to bargaining, and will probably fold if I push back.’

Harry closed his eyes.

Slightly dark-tinged Harry opened them.

‘All right,’ Harry said, ‘let me rephrase. I don’t mean to interfere with your work on a day-to-day or even month-to-month basis, but I can’t just toss off the final responsibility that Dumbledore left me. I’m not going to owl you bizarre parchments out of nowhere, there can be discussions first, but at some point I may have to give you an order. If you refuse the order I might have to take back the Line’s Wizengamot functions and assume direct control. Can you handle that?’

‘And if I say no?’ said the old witch.

Slight, slight the dark tinge … ‘I don’t have an alternative to you lined up. I could start by asking Augusta Longbottom who she thought might be suitable and work from there. But it may be important that we keep to Dumbledore’s plan as much as possible, since I don’t know exactly why he did the things he did, and he thought Amelia Bones should be Chief Warlock for a time. I’m not going to pull Merlin’s name on you, but … no, strike that, I am going to pull Merlin’s name on you, this might or might not be insanely important.’

The old witch thought for a time, her eyes going from person to person around the table. ‘I am not satisfied with this,’ she said after a time. ‘But the Wizengamot must be called to order soon. It will do for now.’

Slowly the old witch reached into her robes, and took out a short rod of stone, dark stone.

She placed the rod on the table before Harry. ‘Take what is yours,’ she said. ‘And then do please give it back.’

Harry reached out his hand to take it.

In the moment that Harry’s fingers first touched the dark stone –

– nothing happened.

Well, perhaps Merlin hadn’t been given to melodrama. That could explain why his final legacy looked like a small, unassuming dark rod. If that was all that was needed for its function, that would be all that was there.

Harry took up the Line, frowning at it. ‘I’d like to appoint Amelia Bones as my regent for Wizengamot-related functions.’ Then, the thought occurring to him that he needed to specify a stopping point to define a regency, Harry added, ‘Until I say that I’ve taken it back.’

Then Harry made a face. He’d been hoping for more from the Line, but it was just a key to places in the Department of Mysteries where interesting things were kept, or to seals where Merlin and his successors had stashed things that shouldn’t be destroyed but ought to be kept from general circulation. Aside from that, the Line didn’t do much.

The Line didn’t let you bypass the Interdict of Merlin either. No, not even if the fate of the galaxy was at stake. Not even if the person seemed sane, had taken an Unbreakable Vow, and honestly believed the world was about to be destroyed otherwise.

Merlin had dreamed of a long run, a world that would last for aeons and not just centuries. The world had no reason not to last forever, if the truly dangerous powers were removed and kept gone. Conversely, a single loophole in the safeguards made the world’s destruction only a matter of time. Someday Merlin’s Line would pass to the wrong person. It could reject the obviously unworthy, but eventually it would pass into hands too subtly flawed for the Line to detect. This was inevitable, when dealing with human beings, and Harry needed to keep that in mind before he sealed something where future Line-holders could retrieve it – the disaster of its inevitable misuse someday needed to be outweighed by its benefits over the next few thousand years.

Harry let out a sad small sigh, under his breath. Merlin, you idiot …

Thinking that didn’t unlock any final safeguards.

There wasn’t anything currently on fire in the Department of Mysteries, so Harry carefully placed the Line back on the table.

‘Thank you,’ the old witch said. She picked up the rod of dark stone. ‘Do you know how I am to use it to call the Wizengamot to order, or – never mind, I shall just try striking the podium. That seems obvious enough. To the rest of the country, of course, I am the Chief Warlock so far as anyone knows except us four.’

Harry hesitated. Then he imagined the owls he would receive if anyone knew he was allowed to second-guess the Chief Warlock, and what that would do to Amelia’s negotiating power. ‘Fine.’

Amelia tucked the rod back into her robes. ‘I will not say it was a pleasure doing business with you, Boy-Who-Lived, but it could have been much worse. Thank you kindly for that.’

Harry was already feeling worried about the exact balance of power here, from the way Madam Bones was acting. The others had, quite logically, deduced that it had been mostly David Monroe who’d planned the way to defeating Voldemort, which meant they were still underestimating him. It might take a crisis of some type, with Harry figuring it out successfully for once instead of screwing up, before Amelia Bones started to respect his authority. Or believe in it at all, actually … ‘So,’ Harry said. ‘Any weirdness for me that you would have brought to Dumbledore while he was around?’

Amelia looked thoughtful. ‘Since you ask … I can think of three things, indeed. First, we don’t have the faintest notion what ritual was used to sacrifice the Death Eaters and resurrect You-Know-Who. It corresponds to no known legend, and the magic traces from the ritual have been eradicated. So far as my Aurors can tell, everyone’s heads fell off their necks due to natural causes. Except for Walden Macnair, who was killed by magical fire after firing a Killing Curse from his wand. A very mysterious ritual indeed.’ She was giving Harry Potter a rather precise look.

Harry considered this, choosing his words carefully. Voldemort had said he’d put up wards, so Harry had been confident of not being observed by Time-Turned Aurors, but still … ‘I think this is a matter you don’t need to investigate too hard, Madam Bones.’

The old witch grinned slightly. ‘We can’t be seen to go easy on the investigation of so many Noble deaths, Harry Potter. When I heard retold your particular account of David’s last stand, I made certain to send investigators whom I considered reliable in the usual quality of their work. Auror Nobbs and Auror Colon, in fact, who are widely respected outside my Department. I found their report to be quite fascinating reading.’ Amelia paused. ‘There’s a possibility that Augustus Rookwood left a ghost –’

‘Exorcise it before anyone talks to it,’ Harry said, conscious of the sudden hammering of his heart.

‘Yes, sir,’ the old witch said dryly. ‘I shall disrupt the soul’s anchoring a little, and none shall be the wiser when it fails to materialize. The second matter is that there was a still-living human arm found among the Dark Lord’s things –’

‘Bellatrix,’ Harry said. His mind had leaped back, made the connection that ongoing trauma had blurred. ‘I think that’s Bellatrix Black’s arm.’ Lesath Lestrange hadn’t been named as someone who’d lost a parent. ‘Oh, bloody hell. She’s still out there, isn’t she. Can you use her arm to track her down somehow?’

Amelia Bones had acquired a sour look. ‘I see. As I was saying, a still-living human arm was found among the Dark Lord’s things, but it proved to be easily incinerated.’

‘What idiot –’ Harry stopped himself. ‘No, not an idiot. Because immediately destroying Dark objects is Department policy. Because of past experiences with rings that really should’ve been dropped into volcanos immediately. Right?’

Moody and Amelia nodded in unison. ‘Good guess, son,’ said Moody.

It might seem literarily inevitable that Harry’s past stupidity was going to come back and haunt him in some horrible fashion later, but that was no reason not to try subverting the plot. ‘I expect you’ve thought of this already,’ Harry said, ‘but the obvious next step is to put out your equivalent of an international bulletin for a thin witch missing her left arm. Oh, and add twenty-five thousand Galleons pledged from me – Headmistress, it’s fine, please trust me on this – to whatever reward is being offered.’

‘Well said.’ The old witch leaned forward slightly. ‘The third and final matter … there was one truly puzzling element to last night’s events, and I am curious to see what you make of it, Harry Potter. Found among the corpses was the head and the body of Sirius Black.’

‘What?’ yelled Moody, starting half from his chair. ‘I thought he was in Azkaban!’

‘So he is,’ said Madam Bones. ‘We checked that at once. The Azkaban guards reported that Sirius Black was still in his cell. Black’s head and body have been transported to the St. Mungo’s morgue, and show the same cause of death as the other Death Eaters, that is to say, his head spontaneously fell off. I am also told that Sirius Black is, as of this morning, sitting in the corner of his cell rocking back and forth with his head between his hands. No other duplicate Death Eaters have been found. Yet.’

There was a pause filled with ticking and whooping things, as people considered this.

‘Ah …’ said Minerva. ‘That’s not possible even by You-Know-Who’s standards of possibility. Is it?’

‘I would have thought so too when I was your age, dear,’ said Amelia. ‘It is the sixth strangest thing I have ever seen.’

‘You see, son?’ said Moody. ‘This sort of thing is why nobody, even me, can ever be paranoid enough.’ The scarred man tilted his head, looking thoughtful, as his bright blue eye kept ever-roving. ‘Twin brother, concealed from the rest of the world? Walpurga Black gave birth to twins, couldn’t bear to kill one, knew old Pollux would demand it … nah, ain’t buyin’ it.’

‘Any ideas, Mr Potter?’ said Amelia Bones. ‘Or is this another matter into which my Department should not inquire too closely?’

Harry closed his eyes and thought.

Sirius Black had hunted down Peter Pettigrew, instead of fleeing the country as common sense would have suggested.

Black had been found in the middle of the street, surrounded by bodies, laughing.

Nothing left of Pettigrew except one finger.

Pettigrew had been a spy for the Light, not a double agent but somebody who sneaked around and found things out.

One of the conspiracy theories about Pettigrew had been that he was an Animagus, since he’d been good at ferreting out secrets even in his Hogwarts years.

Dementors sapped all the magic in their vicinity.

Professor Quirrell had said something about a particular type of magic that rearranged flesh like a Muggle smith reshaping metal with hammer and tongs …

Harry opened his eyes again.

‘Was Peter Pettigrew a secret Metamorphmagus?’

Amelia Bones’s face changed. She made a single croaking noise and fell backward within her chair.

‘Yes, in fact …’ Minerva said slowly. ‘Why?’

‘Sirius Black Confunded Peter Pettigrew,’ Harry’s voice explained patiently, ‘to force him to change shape and pretend to be Black. By the time the Confundus wore off, Peter was in Azkaban and couldn’t change back. The Aurors are used to people in Azkaban saying absolutely anything to get out, so they didn’t listen while Peter Pettigrew was screaming about it over and over again until his voice wore out.’

Even Mad-Eye Moody’s face showed the horror, then.

‘In retrospect,’ said Harry’s voice, which seemed to be operating entirely on automatic, ‘you should have been suspicious when you managed to get that one Death Eater hauled off to Azkaban without a trial.’

‘We thought Malfoy was distracted,’ whispered the old witch. ‘That he was only trying to save himself. There were other Death Eaters we managed to get then, like Bellatrix –’

Harry nodded, feeling like his neck and head were moving on puppet strings. ‘The Dark Lord’s most fanatic and devoted servant, a natural nucleus of opposition for anyone who contested Lucius’s control of the Death Eaters. You thought Lucius was distracted.’

‘Get him out of there,’ said Minerva McGonagall. Her voice rose to a scream. ‘Get him out of there!’

Amelia Bones shoved herself up from the chair, whirled on the Floo –

‘Stop.’

Everyone looked at Harry with astonishment, none more than Minerva McGonagall.

Something else seemed to have taken over Harry’s voice. ‘There’s four things we still need to discuss. An innocent man has been in Azkaban for ten years, eight months, and fourteen days. He can stay there a few minutes longer. That’s how urgent those four things are.’

‘You –’ whispered Amelia Bones. ‘You should not try to be this person, at your age –’

‘First. I think I should look at the complete police records on every other Death Eater that went to Azkaban while Lucius was distracted. Can you compile that by tonight?’

‘Within the hour,’ said Amelia Bones. She looked grey.

Harry nodded. ‘Second. Azkaban is over. You’ll need to start preparations now to move the prisoners to Nurmengard or other secure non-Dementor prisons, and to provide treatment for their Dementor exposure.’

‘I,’ said Amelia. The old witch seemed bent, diminished. ‘I … do not think, that even with this … scandal, that the remainder of the Wizengamot will bend … and the Dementors must be fed, not so much as we have fed them, but they must be given some victims, or they will roam the world, prey on innocents …’

‘It doesn’t matter what the Wizengamot says,’ Harry said. ‘Because –’ Harry’s voice choked. ‘Because –’ Harry took a deep breath, steadied himself. He thought he could see the shape now of the immediate future, could see it stretching out before him like a golden pathway lit with sunlight. Was this also written, in the book of Time that I must not see? ‘Because if I’m right about what comes next, then sometime very soon, Hermione Granger, the Girl-Who-Revived, is going to go to Azkaban and destroy all the Dementors there.’

‘Impossible!’ spat Mad-Eye Moody.

‘Merlin,’ whispered Amelia Bones. ‘Oh, dear Merlin. That’s what happened to the Dementor that Dumbledore “lost”. That’s why they’re afraid of you – and now her as well?’ Her voice trembled. ‘What is this, what is all this?’

If Hermione believes that Death can be defeated –

Whether or not she could’ve believed that before, she’ll believe it now.

‘An authorized portkey to Azkaban would be appreciated –’ Harry’s voice broke again. Tears were streaming down his cheeks.

She can’t die. I have her horcrux.

But Hermione doesn’t need to know about that. Not for one more week.

If she’s willing to risk her own life to end this –

‘Though I think, she might make, her own way there …’

‘Harry?’ said Headmistress McGonagall.

Harry was crying now, huge ragged breaths bursting from him. But he didn’t stop talking. Somewhere out there Peter Pettigrew was waiting while Harry cried.

Somewhere out there, everyone was waiting while he cried.

‘Third. Somewhere just inside the wards of Hogwarts. In a highly defensible position. But where emergency cases can be portkeyed in from just outside the wards. There’s going to be a high-security h-h-hospital. With very powerful guards, that have taken Unbreakable Vows, I don’t, I don’t care how much gold it takes to pay for the Vows, it genuinely does not matter any more. And, and Alastor Moody is going to design the security architecture, and go completely overboard on paranoia without being constrained by a budget or sanity or common sense, only it has to open soon.’ Couldn’t stop talking to cry.

‘Harry,’ said the Headmistress, ‘both of them think you’ve gone mad, they don’t know you well enough to know better. You need to slow down and explain.’

Instead Harry reached into his pouch and signed letters with his fingers, and lifted out, his fingers straining, a five-kilo chunk of gold larger than his fist, from when he’d been experimenting this morning. It made a heavy thud as it landed on the table.

Moody reached over and tapped it with his wand, and then his throat made an incomprehensible sound.

‘That’s your starting budget, Alastor, if you need money right away. Nicholas Flamel didn’t make the Philosopher’s Stone, he stole it, Dumbledore didn’t know the secret history but Monroe did. Once you know how it works, the Stone can do one complete restoration to full health and youth every two hundred and thirty-four seconds. Three hundred sixty people per day. One hundred and thirty-four thousand healings per year. That should be enough to stop, all the wizards everywhere, and all the goblins and house-elves and whoever, from dying. Of old age, or anything else.’ Harry was wiping away tears, over and over. ‘Flamel had more blood on his hands than a hundred Voldemorts, for all the people he could’ve saved and didn’t. The whole time, Moody, the Philosopher’s Stone could’ve healed all your scars and given you back your leg, any time Flamel felt like it. Dumbledore didn’t know. I’m sure he didn’t know.’ Harry smiled shakily. ‘I can’t imagine you as a teenage witch, Madam Bones, but I bet it looks good on you. That’ll give you more energy for trying to keep the Wizengamot from messing with me, because if they get the idea that the Stone is something they can mess with in any way, tax, regulate, I don’t care, Hogwarts is going to secede from Britain and become its own country. Headmistress, Hogwarts is no longer dependent on the Ministry for gold, or for that matter food. You may reform the educational curriculum at will. I’m thinking we may want to add some more advanced courses soon, especially in Muggle studies.’

‘Slow down!’ said Minerva McGonagall.

‘Fourth –’ Harry said, and then stopped.

Fourth. Begin preparations for an orderly take-down of the Statute of Secrecy and to provide magical healing on a mass scale to the Muggle world. Those who oppose this agenda in any way may be denied services by the Stone …

Harry’s lips couldn’t move. Not wouldn’t, couldn’t.

With six billion Muggles thinking creatively about how to use magic …

Transfiguring antimatter was just one idea. It wasn’t even the most destructive idea. There were also black holes and negatively charged strangelets. And if black holes couldn’t be Transfigured because they didn’t already exist as magic defined that to within some spatial radius, there was just Transfiguring lots and lots of nuclear weapons and Black Death plague that could reproduce before the Transfiguration wore off and Harry hadn’t even thought about the problem for five minutes but it didn’t matter because he’d already thought of enough. Someone would think of it, someone would talk, someone would try it. The probability was as close to certainty as made no difference.

What happened if you Transfigured a cubic millimetre of up quarks, just the up quarks without any down quarks to bind them? Harry didn’t even know, and up quarks were certainly a kind of substance that already existed. All it might take was one single Muggleborn who knew the names of the six quarks deciding to try it. That could be the clock ticking down to the prophesied end of the world.

Harry would have tried to deny the thought, rationalize it away.

He couldn’t do that either.

It wasn’t a thing-Harry-Potter-would-do.

Like water flowing downhill, Harry Potter would take no chances when it came to not destroying the world.

‘Fourth?’ said Amelia Bones, who was looking like she’d been hit repeatedly in the face with a planet. ‘What comes fourth?’

‘Never mind,’ said Harry. His voice did not break. He did not fold over sobbing. There were still lives he could save and those took precedence. ‘Never mind. Chief Warlock Bones, I’ve given the regency of the Wizengamot into your hands. Please use that position to announce internationally that the Stone’s healing power will soon be made available to all, and that meanwhile, all dying patients are to be kept alive at any cost, no matter what magic is required to do it. That announcement is your absolute priority. When you have done that you may rescue Peter Pettigrew and tell your old Department to begin preparations for shutting down Azkaban. Then please have someone prepare a full list of imprisoned Death Eaters and what was said at their trials and whether Lucius seemed strangely uninterested in defending them. Thank you. That’s all.’

Amelia Bones turned without another word, and dashed into the Floo like it was her own self that was on fire.

‘And someone,’ Harry said, his voice breaking again now that it was all set in motion, and crying wasn’t costing time, though the vast majority of total lives at stake had turned out not to be savable just yet, ‘someone has to, someone tell Remus Lupin.’

Something to Protect: Hermione Granger

And it was evening and it was morning, the last day. June 15th, 1992.

The beginning light of morning, the pre-dawn before sunrise, was barely brightening the sky. To the east of Hogwarts, where the Sun would rise, that faintest tinge of grey made barely visible the hilly horizon beyond the Quidditch stands.

The stone terrace-platform where Harry now sat would be high enough to see the dawn beyond the hills below; he’d asked for that, when he was describing his new office.

Harry was currently sitting cross-legged on a cushion, chilly pre-morning breezes stirring over his exposed hands and face. He’d ordered the house-elves to bring up the hand-glittered throne from his previous office as General Chaos … and then he’d told the elves to put it back, once it had occurred to Harry to start worrying about where his taste in decorations had come from and whether Voldemort had once possessed a similar throne. Which, itself, wasn’t a knockdown argument – it wasn’t like sitting on a glittery throne to survey the lands below Hogwarts was unethical in any way Harry’s moral philosophy could make out – but Harry had decided that he needed to take time and think it through. Meanwhile, simple cushions would do well enough.

In the room below, connected to the rooftop by a simple wooden ladder, was Harry’s new office inside Hogwarts. A wide room, surrounded by full-wall windows on four sides for sunlight; currently bare of furnishings but for four chairs and a desk. Harry had told Headmistress McGonagall what he was looking for, and Headmistress McGonagall had put on the Sorting Hat and then told Harry the series of twists and turns that would take him where he wanted to be. High enough in Hogwarts that the castle shouldn’t have been that tall, high enough in Hogwarts that nobody looking from the outside would see a piece of castle corresponding to where Harry now sat. It seemed like an elementary precaution against snipers that there was no reason not to take.

Though, on the flip side, Harry had no idea where he currently was in any real sense. If his office couldn’t be seen from the lands below, then how was Harry seeing the lands, how were photons making it from the landscape to him? On the western side of the horizon, stars still glittered, clear in the pre-dawn air. Were those photons the actual photons that had been emitted by huge plasma furnaces in the unimaginable distance? Or did Harry now sit within some dreaming vision of the Hogwarts castle? Or was it all, without any further explanation, just magic? He needed to get electricity to work better around magic so he could experiment with shining lasers downward and upward.

And yes, Harry had his own office on Hogwarts now. He didn’t have any official title yet, but the Boy-Who-Lived was now a true fixture of the Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry, the soon-to-be-home of the Philosopher’s Stone and the world’s only wizarding institution of genuinely higher education. It wasn’t fully secured, but Professor Vector had put up some preliminary Charms and Runes to screen the office and its rooftop against eavesdropping.

Harry sat on his cushion, near the edge of his office’s roof, and gazed down upon trees and lakes and flowering grass. Far below, carriages sat motionlessly, not yet harnessed to skeletal horses. Small boats littered the shore, prepared to ferry younger students across the lake when the time came. The Hogwarts Express had arrived overnight, and now the carriages and the huge old-fashioned engine awaited on the other side of the southern lake. All was ready to take the students home after the Leave-Taking Feast in the morning.

Harry stared across the lake, at the great old-fashioned locomotive he wouldn’t be riding home this time. Again. There was a strange sadness and worry to that thought, like Harry was already starting to miss out on the bonding experiences with the other students his age – if you could say that at all, when a significant part of Harry had been born in 1926. It had felt to Harry, last night in the Ravenclaw common room, like the gap between him and the other students had, yes, widened even further. Though that might only have been from the questions Padma Patil and Anthony Goldstein had excitedly asked each other about the Girl-Who-Revived, the rapid-fire speculations shooting through the air from Ravenclaw to Ravenclaw. Harry had known the answers, he’d known all the answers, and he hadn’t been able to say them.

There was a part of Harry that was tempted to go on the Hogwarts Express and then come back to Hogwarts by Floo. But when Harry imagined finding five other students for his compartment, and then spending the next eight hours keeping secrets from Neville or Padma or Dean or Tracey or Lavender … it didn’t seem like an attractive prospect. Harry felt like he ought to do it for reasons of Socializing with the Other Children, but he did not want to do it. He could meet with everyone again at the start of the next school year, when there would be other topics of which he could speak more freely.

Harry stared south across the lake, at the huge old locomotive, and thought about the rest of his life.

About the Future.

The prophecy Dumbledore’s letter had mentioned about him tearing apart the stars in heaven … well, that sounded optimistic. That part had an obvious interpretation to anyone who’d grown up with the right sort of upbringing. It described a future where humanity had won, more or less. It wasn’t what Harry usually thought about when he gazed at the stars, but from a truly adult perspective, the stars were enormous heaps of valuable raw materials that had unfortunately caught fire and needed to be scattered and put out. If you were tapping the huge hydrogen-helium reservoirs for raw materials, that meant your species had successfully grown up.

Unless the prophecy had been referring to something else entirely. Dumbledore might have been misinterpreting some seer’s words … but his message to Harry had been phrased as if there’d been a prophecy about Harry personally tearing apart stars, in the foreseeable future. Which seemed potentially more worrisome, though by no means certain to be true, or a bad thing if it was true …

Harry vented a sigh. He’d begun to understand, in the long hours before sleep had taken him last night, just what Dumbledore’s last message implied.

Looking back on the events of the 1991–1992 Hogwarts school year was nothing short of bone-freezingly terrifying, now that Harry understood what he was seeing.

It wasn’t just that Harry had kept the frequent company of his good friend Lord Voldemort. It wasn’t even mostly that.

It was the vision of a narrow line of Time that Albus Dumbledore had steered through fate’s narrow keyhole, a hair-thin strand of possibility threaded through a needle’s eye.

The prophecies had instructed Dumbledore to have Tom Riddle’s intelligence copied onto the brain of a wizarding infant who would then grow up learning Muggle science. What did it say about the likely shape of the Future, if that was the first or best strategy the seers could find that didn’t lead to catastrophe?

Harry could look back now on the Unbreakable Vow that he’d made, and guess that if not for that Vow, disaster might have already been set in motion yesterday when Harry had wanted to tear down the International Statute of Secrecy. Which in turn strongly suggested that the many prophecies Dumbledore had read and whose instructions he’d followed, had somehow ensured that Harry and Voldemort would collide in exactly the right way to cause Voldemort to force Harry to make that Unbreakable Vow. That the Unbreakable Vow had been part of Time’s narrow keyhole, one of the improbable preconditions for allowing the Earth’s peoples to survive.

A Vow whose sole purpose was to protect everyone from Harry’s current stupidity.

It was like watching a videotape of an almost-traffic-accident that had happened to you, where you remembered another car missing you by centimetres, and the video showing that somebody had also thrown a pebble in exactly the right way to cause an enormous lorry to miss that near-collision, and if they hadn’t thrown that pebble then you and all your family in the car and your entire planet would have been hit by the lorry, which, in the metaphor, represented your own sheer obliviousness.

Harry had been warned, he’d known on some level or the Vow wouldn’t have stopped him, and yet he’d still almost made the wrong choice and destroyed the world. Harry could look back now and see that, yes, the alternate-Harry with no Vow would’ve had trouble accepting the reasoning that said you couldn’t get magical healing to Muggles as fast as possible. If the alternate-Harry had acknowledged the danger at all, he would have rationalized it, tried to figure out some clever way around the problem and refused to accept taking a few years longer to do it, and so the world would have ended. Even after all the warnings Harry had received, it still wouldn’t have worked without the Unbreakable Vow.

One tiny strand of Time, being threaded through a needle’s eye.

Harry didn’t know how to handle this revelation. It wasn’t a sort of situation that human beings had evolved emotions to handle. All Harry could do was stare at how close he had come to disaster, might come again to disaster if that Vow was fated to trigger more than once, and think …

Think …

I don’t want that to happen again didn’t seem like the right thought. He’d never wanted to destroy the world in the first place. Harry hadn’t lacked for protective feelings about Earth’s sapient population, those protective feelings had been the problem in a way. What Harry had lacked was some element of clear vision, of being willing to consciously acknowledge what he’d already known deep down.

And the whole thing with Harry having spent the last year cosying up to the Defence Professor didn’t speak highly of his intellect either. It seemed to point to the same problem, even. There were things Harry had known or strongly suspected on some level, but never promoted to conscious attention. And so he had failed and nearly died.

I need to raise the level of my game.

That was the thought Harry was looking for. He had to do better than this, become a less stupid person than this.

I need to raise the level of my game, or fail.

Dumbledore had destroyed the recordings in the Hall of Prophecy and arranged for no further recordings to be made. There’d apparently been a prophecy that said Harry mustn’t look upon those prophecies. And the obvious next thought, which might or might not be true, was that saving the world was beyond the reach of prophetic instruction. That winning would take plans that were too complex for seers’ messages, or that Divination couldn’t see somehow. If there’d been some way for Dumbledore to save the world himself, then prophecy would probably have told Dumbledore how to do that. Instead the prophecies had told Dumbledore how to create the preconditions for a particular sort of person existing; a person, maybe, who could unravel a challenge more difficult than prophecy could solve directly. That was why Harry had been placed on his own, to think without prophetic guidance. If all Harry did was follow mysterious orders from prophecies, then he wouldn’t mature into a person who could perform that unknown task.

And right now, Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres was still a walking catastrophe who’d needed to be constrained by an Unbreakable Vow to prevent him from immediately setting the Earth on an inevitable course toward destruction when he’d already been warned against it. That had happened literally yesterday, just one day after he’d helped Voldemort almost take over the planet.

A certain line from Tolkien kept running through Harry’s mind, the part where Frodo upon Mount Doom put on the ring, and Sauron suddenly realized what a complete idiot he’d been. And the magnitude of his own folly was at last laid bare, or however that had gone.

There was a huge gap between who Harry needed to become, and who he was right now.

And Harry didn’t think that time, life experience, and puberty would take care of that automatically, though they might help. Though if Harry could grow into an adult that was to this self what a normal adult was to a normal eleven-year-old, maybe that would be enough to steer through Time’s narrow keyhole …

He had to grow up, somehow, and there was no traditional path laid out before him for accomplishing that.

The thought came then to Harry of another work of fiction, more obscure than Tolkien:

You can only arrive at mastery by practising the techniques you have learned, facing challenges and apprehending them, using to the fullest the tools you have been taught, until they shatter in your hands and you are left in the midst of wreckage absolute … I cannot create masters. I have never known how to create masters. Go, then, and fail … You have been shaped into something that may emerge from the wreckage, determined to remake your Art. I cannot create masters, but if you had not been taught, your chances would be less. The higher road begins after the Art seems to fail you; though the reality will be that it was you who failed your Art.

It wasn’t that Harry had gone down the wrong path, it wasn’t that the road to sanity lay somewhere outside of science. But reading science papers hadn’t been enough. All the cognitive psychology papers about known bugs in the human brain and so on had helped, but they hadn’t been sufficient. He’d failed to reach what Harry was starting to realise was a shockingly high standard of being so incredibly, unbelievably rational that you actually started to get things right, as opposed to having a handy language in which to describe afterwards everything you’d just done wrong. Harry could look back now and apply ideas like motivated cognition to see where he’d gone astray over the last year. That counted for something, when it came to being saner in the future. That was better than having no idea what he’d done wrong. But that wasn’t yet being the person who could pass through Time’s narrow keyhole, the adult form whose possibility Dumbledore had been instructed by seers to create.

I need to think faster, grow up faster … How alone am I, how alone will I be? Am I making the same mistake I made during Professor Quirrell’s first battle, when I didn’t realise Hermione had captains? The mistake I made when I didn’t tell Dumbledore about the sense of doom, once I realised Dumbledore probably wasn’t mad or evil?

It would help if Muggles had classes for this sort of thing, but they didn’t. Maybe Harry could recruit Daniel Kahneman, fake his death, rejuvenate him with the Stone, and put him in charge of inventing better training methods …

Harry took the Elder Wand out of his robes, gazed again at the dark-grey wood that Dumbledore had passed down to him. Harry had tried to think faster this time, he’d tried to complete the pattern implied by the Cloak of Invisibility and the Resurrection Stone. The Cloak of Invisibility had possessed the legendary power of hiding the wearer, and the hidden power of allowing the wearer to hide from Death itself in the form of Dementors. The Resurrection Stone had the legendary power of summoning an image of the dead, and then Voldemort had incorporated it into his horcrux system to allow his spirit to move freely. The second Deathly Hallow was a potential component of a system of true immortality that Cadmus Peverell had never completed, maybe due to his having ethics.

And then there was the third Deathly Hallow, the Elder Wand of Antioch Peverell, that legend said passed from wizard to stronger wizard, and made its holder invincible against ordinary attacks; that was the known and overt characteristic …

The Elder Wand that had belonged to Dumbledore, who’d been trying to prevent the Death of the world itself.

The purpose of the Elder Wand always going to the victor might be to find the strongest living wizard and empower them still further, in case there was any threat to their entire species; it could secretly be a tool to defeat Death in its form as the destroyer of worlds.

But if there was some higher power locked within the Elder Wand, it had not presented itself to Harry based on that guess. Harry had raised up the Elder Wand and spoken to it, named himself a descendant of Peverell who accepted his family’s quest; he’d promised the Elder Wand that he would do his best to save the world from Death, and take up Dumbledore’s duty. And the Elder Wand had answered no more strongly to his hand than before, refusing his attempt to jump ahead in the story. Maybe Harry needed to strike his first true blow against the Death of worlds before the Elder Wand would acknowledge him; as the heir of Ignotus Peverell had already defeated Death’s shadow, and the heir of Cadmus Peverell had already survived the Death of his body, when their respective Deathly Hallows had revealed their secrets.

At least Harry had managed to guess that, contrary to legend, the Elder Wand didn’t contain a core of Thestral hair. Harry had seen Thestrals, and they were skeletal horses with smooth skin and no visible mane on their skull-like heads, nor tufts on their bony tails. But what core was truly inside the Elder Wand, Harry hadn’t yet felt himself knowing; nor had he been able to find, anywhere on the Elder Wand, the circle-triangle-line of the Deathly Hallows that should have been present.

‘I don’t suppose,’ Harry murmured to the Elder Wand, ‘you could just tell me?’

There came back no answer from the globe-knobbed wand; only a sense of glory and contained power, watching him skeptically.

Harry sighed, and put the most powerful wand in the world back into his school robes. He’d get it eventually, and hopefully in time.

Maybe faster, if there was someone to help him do the research.

Harry was aware on some level – no, he needed to stop being aware of things on some level and start just being aware of them – Harry was explicitly and consciously aware that he was ruminating about the Future mostly to distract himself from the imminent arrival of Hermione Granger. Who would receive a clear bill of health from St. Mungo’s, when she woke up very early this morning, and who would then Floo with Professor Flitwick back to Hogwarts. Whereupon she’d tell Professor Flitwick that she needed to speak with Harry Potter immediately. There’d been a note from Harry to himself about that, when Harry had woken up later this morning with the Sun already risen in the Ravenclaw dorm. He’d read the note, and then Time-Turned back to before the dawn hour when Hermione Granger would arrive.

She won’t actually be angry with me.

…

Seriously. Hermione isn’t that kind of person. Maybe she was at the start of the year but she’s too self-aware to fall for that one now.

…

What do you mean, … ? If you have something to say, inner voice, just say it! We’re trying to be more aware of our own thought processes, remember?

The sky had lightened further by the time Hermione spoke again.

‘I’m afraid,’ Hermione said, almost in a whisper. ‘Not of dying again, or not just that. I’m afraid I won’t be good enough. I had my chance to defeat a troll, and instead I just died –’

‘That was a troll empowered by Voldemort as a weapon, plus he sabotaged all your magic items, just so you know.’

‘I died. And you killed the troll, somehow, I think I remember that part, it didn’t even slow you down.’ Hermione wasn’t crying, no tears glistened on her cheeks, she simply gazed off at the lightening sky where the Sun would rise. ‘And then you brought me back from the dead as a Sparkling Unicorn Princess. I know I couldn’t have done that. I’m afraid I’ll never be able to do that, no matter what people think about me.’

‘This situation is where your journey begins, I think –’ Harry paused. ‘Excuse me, I shouldn’t be trying to influence your decision.’

‘No,’ Hermione whispered, still gazing at the hills below her. She raised her voice. ‘No, Harry, I want to hear this.’

‘Okay. Um. I think this is where you start. Everything that’s happened up until now … it places you in the same place I started out in September, when I’d thought of myself as just being a child prodigy before, and then I found something new I needed to live up to. If you weren’t comparing yourself to me and my,’ adult cognitive patterns copied off Tom Riddle, ‘dark side … then you’d be the brightest star of Ravenclaw, who organized her own company to fight school bullies and kept her sanity under assault by Voldemort, all while she was only twelve years old. I looked it up, you got better grades than Dumbledore did in his first year.’ Leaving aside the Defence grade, because that was just Voldemort being Voldemort. ‘Now you have some powers, and a reputation to live up to, and the world is about to hand you some difficult tasks. That’s where it all begins for you, the same as it began for me. Don’t sell yourself short.’ And then Harry shut his mouth hard, because he was talking Hermione into it and that wasn’t right. He’d at least managed to stop before the part where he asked, if she couldn’t be a hero with all that going for her, who exactly she thought was going to do it.

‘You know,’ Hermione said to the horizon, still not looking at Harry, ‘I had a conversation like this with Professor Quirrell, once, about being a hero. He was taking the other side, of course. But apart from that, this is feeling like when he argued with me, somehow.’

Harry kept his lips pressed shut. Letting people make their own decisions was hard, because it meant they were allowed to make the wrong ones, but it still had to be done.

Hermione spoke carefully, the blue fringes of her Hogwarts uniform now seeming brighter against her black robes as the sky all around them became illuminated; there were no more stars in the west. ‘Professor Quirrell told me, he said he’d been a hero once. But people weren’t helping him enough, so he gave up and went off to do something more interesting. I told Professor Quirrell that it hadn’t been right for him to do that – what I actually said was “that’s horrible”. Professor Quirrell said that, yes, maybe he was an awful person, but then what about all the other people who’d never tried to be heroes at all? Were they even worse than him? And I didn’t know what to say back. I mean, it’s wrong to say that only Gryffindor-style heroes are good people – though I think from Professor Quirrell’s perspective it was more like only people with big ambitions had a right to breathe. And I didn’t believe that. But it also seemed wrong to stop being a hero, to walk away like he’d done. So I just stood there looking silly. But now I know what I should’ve told him back then.’

Harry controlled his breathing.

Hermione stood up from her cushion, and turned to face Harry. ‘I’m done with trying to be a heroine,’ said Hermione Granger with the eastern sky brightening around her. ‘I shouldn’t ever have gone along with that entire line of thinking. There are just people who do what they can, whatever they can. And there are also people who don’t even try to do what they can, and yes, those people are doing something wrong. I’m not ever going to try to be a hero again. I’m not going to think in heroic terms if I can help it. But I won’t do any less than I can – or not a lot less, I mean, I’m only human.’ Harry had never understood what was supposed to be mysterious about the Mona Lisa, but if he could have taken a picture of Hermione’s resigned/joyous smile just then, he had the sense that he could have looked at it for hours without understanding, and that Dumbledore could have read through it at a glance. ‘I won’t learn my lesson. I will be that stupid. I’ll go on trying to do most of what I can, or at least some of what I can – oh, you know what I mean. Even if it means risking my life again, so long as it’s worth the risk and isn’t being, you know, actually stupid. That’s my answer.’ Hermione took a deep breath, her face resolute. ‘So, is there something I can do?’

Harry’s throat was choked. He reached into his pouch, and signed C-L-O-A-K since he couldn’t speak, and drew forth the fuliginous spill of the Cloak of Invisibility, offering it to Hermione for the last time. Harry had to force the words from his throat. ‘This is the True Cloak of Invisibility,’ Harry said in almost a whisper, ‘the Deathly Hallow passed down from Ignotus Peverell to his heirs, the Potters. And now to you –’

‘Harry!’ Hermione said. Her hands flew up across her chest, as though to protect herself from the attacking gift. ‘You don’t have to do this!’

‘I do have to do this. I’ve left the part of the path that lets me be a hero, I can’t risk myself adventuring, ever. And you … can.’ Harry reached up the hand that wasn’t holding the Cloak, and wiped at his eyes. ‘This was made for you, I think. For the person you’re going to become.’ A weapon to fight Death, in its form as the shadow of despair that falls on human minds and drains away their hope for the future; you will fight that, I expect, in more forms than just Dementors … ‘I do not loan you, my Cloak, but give you, unto Hermione Jean Granger. Protect her well forevermore.’

Slowly, Hermione reached out, and took hold of the Cloak, looking like she was trying not to cry herself. ‘Thank you,’ she whispered. ‘I think … even though I’m done with the notion of heroing … I think that you always were, from the day I met you, my mysterious old wizard.’

‘And I think,’ Harry said, his own throat half-closed, ‘even if you deny that way of thinking now, I think that you were always destined to become, from the very beginning of the story, the hero.’ Who must Hermione Granger become, what adult form must she take when she grows up, to pass through Time’s narrow keyhole? I don’t know the answer to that either, any more than I can imagine my own adult self. But her next few steps ahead seem clearer than mine …

Harry let the Cloak go, and it passed from his hands to hers.

‘It sings,’ Hermione said. ‘It’s singing to me.’ She reached up, and wiped at her own eyes. ‘I can’t believe you did that, Harry.’

Harry’s other hand came out of his pouch, now bearing a long golden chain, at the end of which dangled a closed golden shell. ‘And this is your personal time machine.’

There was a pause, during which the planet Earth rotated a bit further in its orbit.

‘What?’ said Hermione.

‘A Time-Turner, they call it. Hogwarts has a stock they give out to some students, I got one at the start of the year to treat my sleep disorder. It lets the user go backwards in time, in up to six one-hour increments, which I used to get six extra hours per day to study. And to vanish out of Potions class and so on. Don’t worry, a Time-Turner can’t change history or generate paradoxes that destroy the universe.’

‘You were keeping up with me in lessons by studying six extra hours per day using a time machine.’ Hermione Granger seemed to be having trouble with this concept for some unaccountable reason.

Harry made his face look puzzled. ‘Is there something odd about that?’

Hermione reached out and took the golden necklace. ‘I guess not by wizard standards,’ she said. For some reason her voice sounded rather sharp. She arranged the chain around her neck, placing the hourglass inside her shirt. ‘I do feel better now about keeping up with you, though, so thank you for that.’

Harry cleared his throat. ‘Also, since Voldemort wiped out the House of Monroe and then, so far as everyone believes, you avenged them by killing Voldemort, I got Amelia Bones to railroad a bill through what’s left of the Wizengamot, saying that Granger is now a Noble House of Britain.’

‘Excuse me?’ said Hermione.

‘That also makes you the only scion of a Noble House, which means that to get your legal majority you just need to pass your Ordinary Wizarding Levels, which I’ve set us up to do at the end of the summer so we’ll have some time to study first. If you’re okay with that, I mean.’

Hermione Granger was making some sort of high-pitched noise that would, in a less organic device, have indicated an engine malfunction. ‘I have two months to study for my O.W.L.s?’

‘Hermione, it’s a test designed so that most fifteen-year-olds can pass. Ordinary fifteen year-olds. We can get a passing grade with a low third-year’s power level if we learn the right set of spells, and that’s all we need for our majorities. Though you’ll need to come to terms with getting Acceptable scores instead of your usual Outstandings.’

The high-pitched noises coming from Hermione Granger rose in pitch.

‘Here’s your wand back.’ Harry took it from his pouch. ‘And your mokeskin pouch, I made sure they put back everything that was there when you died.’ That pouch Harry withdrew from a normal pocket of his robes, since he was reluctant to put a bag of holding inside a bag of holding no matter what was supposed to be harmless so long as both devices had been crafted observing all safety precautions.

Hermione took her wand back, and then her pouch, the motions somehow managing to look graceful even though her fingers were a bit shaky.

‘Let’s see, what else … the oath you swore before to House Potter only said you had to serve until “the day you die”, so you’re now free and clear. And right after your death I got the Malfoys to publicly declare that you were innocent of all charges in Draco’s attempted murder.’

‘Why, thank you again, Harry,’ said Hermione Granger. ‘That was very nice of you, and them too, I guess.’ She was repeatedly running her fingers through her chestnut curls, as though, by organizing her hair, she could restore sanity to her life.

‘Last but not least, I had the goblins start the process of building a vault in Gringotts for House Granger,’ Harry said. ‘I didn’t put any money into it, because that was something where I could wait and ask you first. But if you’re going to be a superhero who goes around righting certain kinds of wrongs, it will help a lot if people consider you to be part of the upper social strata and, um, I think it may help if they know you can afford lawyers. I can put in as much gold into your vault as you want, since after Voldemort killed Nicholas Flamel, I ended up holding the Philosopher’s Stone.’

‘I feel like I ought to be fainting,’ Hermione said in a high-pitched voice, ‘only I can’t because of my superpowers and why do I have those again?’

‘If it’s all right with you, your Occlumency lessons will start on Wednesday with Mr Bester, he can work with you once per day. Until then, I think it might be better for the true origin of your powers not to become known just because a Legilimens looks you in the eyes. I mean, obviously there’s a normal magical explanation, nothing super-supernatural, but people do tend to worship their own ignorance and, well, I think the Girl-Who-Revived will be more effective if you remain mysterious. Once you can keep out Mr Bester and beat Veritaserum, I’ll tell you the entire backstory, I promise, including all the secrets you can never tell anyone else.’

‘That sounds lovely,’ said Hermione Granger. ‘I’m quite looking forward to it.’

‘Though you’ll need to take an Unbreakable Vow to not do anything that might destroy the world before I can tell you the more dangerous parts of the story. I mean, I literally can’t tell you otherwise, because I took an Unbreakable Vow myself. Is that okay?’

‘Sure,’ said Hermione. ‘Why shouldn’t it be okay? I wouldn’t want to destroy the world anyhow.’

‘Do you need to sit down again?’ Harry said, feeling alarmed by the way Hermione was swaying slightly, as though in rhythm with the words being spoken.

Hermione Granger took several deep breaths. ‘No, I’m perfectly peachy,’ she said. ‘Is there anything else I should know about?’

‘That was it. I’m finished, at least for now.’ Harry paused. ‘I do understand that you want to do things for yourself, not just have them done for you. It’s just … you’re going to be a more serious kind of hero, and the only sane choice is for me to give you all the advantages I can manage –’

‘I understand that quite well,’ Hermione said. ‘Now that I’ve actually lost a fight and died. I didn’t used to understand, but now I do.’ A breeze ruffled Hermione’s chestnut hair and stirred her robes, making her look even more peaceful in the dawn air, as she raised one hand and carefully clenched it into a fist. ‘If I’m going to do this, I’m going to do it right. We need to measure how hard I can punch, and how high I can jump, and figure out a safe way to test if my fingernails can kill Lethifolds like a real unicorn’s horn, and I should practise using my speed to dodge spells I can’t let hit me and … and it sounds like you could maybe arrange for me to get Auror training, like from whoever taught Susan Bones.’ Hermione was smiling again now, a strange light in her eyes that would’ve puzzled Dumbledore for hours and that Harry understood immediately, not without a twinge of apprehension. ‘Oh! And I want to start carrying Muggle weapons, maybe hidden so nobody knows I have them. I thought of incendiary grenades when I was fighting the troll, but I knew I couldn’t Transfigure them fast enough, even after I stopped caring about obeying the rules.’

‘I have the feeling,’ Harry said, imitating Professor McGonagall’s Scottish accent as best he could, ‘that I ought to be doing something about this.’

‘Oh, it’s much, much, much too late for that, Mr Potter. Say, can you get me a bazooka? The rocket launcher, I mean, not the bubblegum? I bet they won’t be expecting that from a young girl, especially if I’m radiating an aura of innocence and purity.’

‘All right,’ Harry said calmly, ‘now you’re starting to scare me.’

Hermione paused from where she was experimenting with balancing on the tip of her left shoe, her arm reaching in one direction and her right leg stretched in the other, like a ballet dancer. ‘Am I? I was just thinking that I didn’t see what I could do that a Ministry squad of Hit Wizards couldn’t. They have broomsticks for mobility and spells that hit harder than I possibly could.’ She gracefully lowered her leg back down. ‘I mean, now that I can try a few things without worrying about who’s watching, I’m starting to think that I really really really like having superpowers. But I still don’t see how I could win a fight that Professor Flitwick couldn’t, not unless it involves me taking a Dark Wizard by surprise.’

You can take risks other people shouldn’t, and try again with the knowledge of what killed you. You can experiment with new spells, more than anyone else could try without dying for sure. But Harry couldn’t say any of that yet, so instead he said, ‘I think it’s okay to think more about the future, not just what you can do this very minute.’

Hermione jumped high in the air, clicked her heels together three times on the way down, and landed on her tiptoes, perfectly posed. ‘But you said there was something I could do right away. Or were you just testing?’

‘That part is a special case,’ Harry said, feeling the chill of the dawn air against his skin. He was increasingly not looking forward to telling super-Hermione that her Ordeal would involve facing her literal worst nightmare, under conditions where all her newfound physical strength would be useless.

Hermione nodded, then glanced to the east. At once she went to the side of the roof and sat down, her feet dangling over the rooftop ledge. Harry went to her side and sat down too, sitting cross-legged and further back of the roof-edge.

In the distance, a brilliant tinge of red was rising above the hills to the east of Hogwarts.

Watching the tip of the sunrise made Harry feel better, somehow. So long as the Sun was in the sky, things were still all right on some level, like his having not yet destroyed the Sun.

‘So,’ Hermione said. Her voice rose a bit. ‘Speaking of the future, Harry. I had time to think about a lot of things while I was waiting in St. Mungo’s, and … maybe it’s silly of me, but there’s a question I still want to know the answer to. Do you remember the last thing we talked about together? Before, I mean?’

‘What?’ Harry said blankly.

‘Oh …’ Hermione said. ‘It was two months ago for you … I guess you don’t recall, then.’

And Harry remembered.

‘Don’t panic!’ Hermione said, as a sort of strangled half-gurgle came from Harry’s throat. ‘I promise no matter what you say, I won’t burst into tears and run away and get eaten by a troll again! I know it’s been less than two days for me, but I think that dying has made a lot of things I used to fret about seem much less important compared to what I’ve been through!’

‘Oh,’ Harry said, his own voice now high-pitched. ‘That’s a good use of a major trauma, I guess?’

‘Only, see, I was still wondering about it, Harry, because for me it hasn’t been very long at all since our last conversation, and we didn’t finish talking which was admittedly all my own fault for losing control of my emotions and then being eaten by a troll which I am definitely not going to do again. I’ve been thinking I ought to reassure you that’s not going to happen every time you say the wrong thing to a girl.’ Hermione was fidgeting, leaning from one side to the other where she sat, slightly back and forth. ‘But, well, even most people who are in love don’t do literally one hundredth of what you’ve done for me. So, Mr Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres, if it’s not love, I want to know exactly what I am to you. You never said.’

‘That’s a good question,’ Harry said, controlling the rising panic. ‘Do you mind if I think about it?’

Bit by bit, more of the searingly brilliant circle became visible beyond the hills.

‘Hermione,’ Harry said when the Sun was halfway above the horizon, ‘did you ever invent any hypotheses to explain my mysterious dark side?’

‘Just the obvious one,’ Hermione said, kicking her legs slightly over the rooftop’s edge. ‘I thought maybe when You-Know-Who died right next to you, he happened to give off the burst of magic that makes a ghost, and some of it imprinted on your brain instead of the floor. But that never felt right to me, like it was just a clever explanation that wasn’t actually true, and it makes even less sense if You-Know-Who didn’t really die that night.’

‘Good enough,’ Harry said. ‘Let’s imagine that scenario for now.’ His inner rationalist was looking back and face-palming again at how he’d managed to not-think-about hypotheses like that one. It wasn’t true but it was reasonable and Harry had never thought of any causal model that concrete, just vaguely suspected a connection.

Hermione nodded. ‘You probably know this already, but I just thought I’d say it to be sure: you’re not Voldemort, Harry.’

‘I know. And that’s what you mean to me.’ Harry took a breath, finding it still painful to say aloud. ‘Voldemort … he wasn’t a happy person. I don’t know if he was ever happy, a single day in his life.’ He never could cast the Patronus Charm. ‘That’s one reason his cognitive patterns didn’t take me over, my dark side didn’t feel like a good place to be, it didn’t get positively reinforced. Being friends with you means that my life doesn’t have to go the way Voldemort’s did. And I was pretty lonely before Hogwarts, although I didn’t realise it then, so … yeah. I might’ve been slightly more desperate to bring you back from the dead than the average boy my age would’ve been. Though I also maintain that my decision was strictly normative moral reasoning, and if other people care less about their friends, that’s their problem, not mine.’

‘I see,’ Hermione said softly. She hesitated. ‘Harry, don’t take this the wrong way, but I’m not one hundred percent comfortable with that. It’s a big responsibility that I didn’t choose, and I don’t think it’s healthy for you to lay it on just one person.’

Harry nodded. ‘I know. But there’s more to the point I’m trying to make. There was a prophecy about my vanquishing Voldemort –’

‘A prophecy? There was a prophecy about you? Seriously, Harry?’

‘Yeah, I know. Anyway, part of it went, “And the Dark Lord shall mark him as his equal, but he shall have power the Dark Lord knows not.” What would you guess that meant?’

‘Hmmm,’ Hermione said. Her fingers tapped thoughtfully on the roof’s stone. ‘Your mysterious dark side is You-Know-Who’s mark on you that made you his equal. The power he knew not … was the scientific method, right?’

Harry shook his head. ‘That’s what I thought too at first – that it was going to be Muggle science, or the methods of rationality. But …’ Harry exhaled. The Sun had now fully risen above the hills. This felt embarrassing to say, but he was going to say it anyway. ‘Professor Snape, who originally heard the prophecy – yes, that’s also a thing that happened – Professor Snape said he didn’t think it could just be science, that the “power the Dark Lord knows not” needed to be something more alien to Voldemort than just that. Even if I think of it in terms of rationality, well, it turns out that the person Voldemort really was,’ why, Professor Quirrell, why, the thought still stabbing sickness at Harry’s heart, ‘he’d have been able to learn the methods of rationality too, if he read the same science papers I did. Except, maybe, for one last thing …’ Harry drew a breath. ‘At the end of all of it, during my final showdown with Voldemort, he threatened to put my parents, and my friends, into Azkaban. Unless I came up with interesting secrets to tell him, one person saved per secret. But I knew I couldn’t find enough secrets to save everyone. And in the moment that I saw no way at all left to save everyone … that’s when I actually started thinking. Maybe for the first time in my life, I started thinking. I thought faster than Voldemort, even though he was older than me and smarter, because … because I had a reason to think. Voldemort had a drive to be immortal, he strongly preferred not to die, but that wasn’t a positive desire, it was fear, and Voldemort made mistakes because of that fear. I think the power that Voldemort knew not … was that I had something to protect.’

‘Oh, Harry,’ Hermione said gently. She hesitated. ‘Is that what I am to you, then? The thing that you protect?’

‘No, I mean, the whole reason I’m telling you this, is that Voldemort wasn’t threatening to put you in Azkaban. Even if he’d taken over the whole world, you’d have been fine. He’d already made a binding promise not to harm you, because of, um, because of reasons. So in my moment of ultimate crisis, when I reached deep down and found the power Voldemort knew not, I did it to protect everyone except you.’

Hermione considered this, a slow smile spreading over her face. ‘Why, Harry,’ she said. ‘That’s the least romantic thing I’ve ever heard.’

‘You’re welcome.’

‘No, really, it does help,’ Hermione said. ‘I mean, it makes the whole thing much less stalkery.’

‘I know, right?’

The two of them shared a companionable nod, both of them looking more relaxed now, and watched the sunrise together.

‘I’ve been thinking,’ Harry said, his own voice going soft, ‘about the alternate Harry Potter, the person I might have been if Voldemort hadn’t attacked my parents.’ If Tom Riddle hadn’t tried to copy himself onto me. ‘That other Harry Potter wouldn’t have been as smart, I guess. He probably wouldn’t have studied much Muggle science, even if his mother was a Muggleborn. But that other Harry Potter would’ve had … the capacity for warmth, that he inherited from James Potter and Lily Evans, he would’ve cared about other people and tried to save his friends, I know that would have been true, because that’s something that Lord Voldemort never did, you see …’ Harry’s eyes were watering. ‘So that part must be the remnant.’

The Sun was well above the horizon now, the golden light illuminating both of them, casting long shadows off the other side of the rooftop platform.

‘I think you’re just fine the way you are,’ Hermione said. ‘I mean, that other Harry Potter might’ve been a nice boy, maybe, but it sounds like I would’ve had to do all his thinking for him.’

‘Going by heredity, alter-Harry would have been in Gryffindor like his parents, and the two of you wouldn’t have become friends. Though James Potter and Lily Evans were the Head Boy and Head Girl of Hogwarts back in their day, so he wouldn’t have been that bad.’

‘I can just imagine it,’ Hermione said. ‘Harry James Potter, Sorted into Gryffindor, aspiring Quidditch player –’

‘No. Just no.’

‘Remembered by history as the sidekick of Hermione Jean Granger, who’d send out Mr Potter to get into trouble for her, and then solve the mystery from the library by reading books and using her incredible memory.’

‘You’re really enjoying this alternate universe, aren’t you.’

‘Maybe he’d be best mates with Ron Weasley, the smartest boy in Gryffindor, and they’d fight side by side in my army in Defence class, and afterwards help each other with their homework –’

‘Okay, enough, this is starting to creep me out.’

‘Sorry,’ Hermione said, though she was still smiling to herself, appearing rapt in some private vision.

‘Apology accepted,’ Harry said dryly.

The Sun rose a little further in the sky.

After a while, Hermione spoke. ‘Do you suppose we’ll fall in love with each other later on?’

‘I don’t know any better than you do, Hermione. But why does it have to be about that? Seriously, why does it always have to be about that? Maybe when we’re older we’ll fall in love, and maybe we won’t. Maybe we’ll stay in love, and maybe we won’t.’ Harry turned his head slightly, the Sun was hot on his cheek and he wasn’t wearing sunscreen. ‘No matter how it goes, we shouldn’t try to force our lives into a pattern. I think when people try to force patterns onto this sort of thing, that’s when they end up unhappy.’

‘No forced patterns?’ Hermione said. Her eyes had taken on a mischievous look. ‘That sounds like a more complicated way of saying no rules. Which I guess seems a lot more reasonable to me than it would’ve at the start of this year. If I’m going to be a Sparkling Unicorn Princess and have my own time machine, I might as well give up on rules, I suppose.’

‘I’m not saying that rules are always bad, especially when they actually fit people, instead of them being blindly imitated like Quidditch. But weren’t you the one who rejected the “hero” pattern in favour of just doing the things she could?’

‘I suppose so.’ Hermione turned her head again to gaze down at the grounds below Hogwarts, for the Sun was too bright to look at now – though, Harry thought, Hermione’s retinas would always heal now, it was safe for her alone to look directly into the light. ‘You said, Harry, that you thought I was always destined to be the hero. I’ve been considering, and I suspect you’re completely wrong. If this had been meant to be, things would’ve been a lot easier all round. Just doing the things you can do – you have to make that happen, you have to choose it, over and over again.’

‘That might not conflict with your being a destined hero,’ Harry said, thinking of compatibilist theories of free will, and prophecies that he must not look upon in order to fulfil. ‘But we can talk about that later.’

‘You have to choose it,’ Hermione repeated. She pushed herself up on her hands, then popped herself backwards and onto the rooftop, rising to her feet in a smooth motion. ‘Just like I’m choosing to do this.’

‘No kissing!’ Harry said, scrambling to his feet and preparing to dodge; though the realization came to him that the Girl-Who-Revived would be much, much faster.

‘I won’t try to kiss you again, Mr Potter. Not until you ask me, if you ever do. But there are all these warm feelings bubbling up inside me and I feel like I might burst if I don’t do something, though it does now occur to me that it’s unhealthy if girls don’t know any way of expressing gratitude to boys besides kissing them.’ Hermione took out her wand and offered it crosswise, in the position she’d used to swear her oath of fealty to House Potter before the Wizengamot.

‘Oh hell no,’ Harry said. ‘Do you realise what it took to get you out of that oath last time –’

‘Don’t go jumping to conclusions, you. I wasn’t about to swear fealty to your House again. You’ve got to start trusting me to be sensible if you’re going to be my mysterious young wizard. Now please hold out your wand.’

Slowly, Harry took out the Elder Wand and crossed it with Hermione’s ten-and-three-quarter-inches of vinewood, forcing down a last worry about her choosing the wrong thing. ‘Can you at least not say anything about “until death takes me”, because did I mention I have the Philosopher’s Stone now? Or anything about “the end of the world and its magic”? I’m a lot more nervous around phrases like that than I used to be.’

Upon a roof floored in square stony tiles, the brilliant morning Sun blazes down upon two not-really-children-any-more, both in blue-fringed black robes, facing each other across crossed wands. One has brown eyes beneath chaotic chestnut curls, and radiates an aura of strength and beauty that is not magic only; the other has green eyes under glasses, with messy black hair above a recently inflamed scar. Below, a stone tower nobody remembers seeing from ground level stretches downwards into the broad base of the castle Hogwarts. Far beneath them are visible the green hills, and the lake. In the distance a huge red-and-black line of railcars and an engine, appearing tiny from this height, a train neither Muggle nor fully magical. The sky is nearly unclouded, but for faint tinges of orange-white where wisps of moisture reflect the sunlight. A light breeze carries the crisp chill of dawn, and the dampness of morning; but the huge blazing golden globe is now risen high above the horizon, and its incandescence casts warmth on everything it touches.

‘Well, maybe after this you’ll be less nervous,’ the hero says to her enigmatic wizard. She knows she doesn’t know the whole story, but the fragment of truth that she does hold shines bright like sunlight within her, casting warmth on her insides the way the Sun warms her face. ‘I do choose this, now.’

Upon my life and magic I swear friendship to Harry Potter,

To help him and trust in him,

To stand with him and, um, stand by him,

And sometimes go where he can’t go,

’Till the day that death takes me for real, if it ever does, I mean,

And if the world or its magic ends, we’ll deal with that together.

The Planning Fallacy

Some children would have waited until after their first trip to Diagon Alley.

‘Bag of element 79,’ Harry said, and withdrew his hand, empty, from the mokeskin pouch.

Most children would have at least waited to get their wands first.

‘Bag of okane,’ said Harry. The heavy bag of gold popped up into his hand.

Harry withdrew the bag, then plunged it again into the mokeskin pouch. He took out his hand, put it back in, and said, ‘Bag of tokens of economic exchange.’ That time his hand came out empty.

‘Give me back the bag that I just put in.’ Out came the bag of gold once more.

Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres had got his hands on at least one magical item. Why wait?

‘Professor McGonagall,’ Harry said to the bemused witch strolling beside him, ‘can you give me two words, one word for gold, and one word for something else that isn’t money, in a language that I wouldn’t know? But don’t tell me which is which.’

‘Ahava and zahav,’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘That’s Hebrew, and the other word means love.’

‘Thank you, Professor. Bag of ahava.’ Empty.

‘Bag of zahav.’ And it popped up into his hand.

‘Zahav is gold?’ Harry questioned, and Professor McGonagall nodded.

Harry thought over his collected experimental data. It was only the most crude and preliminary sort of effort, but it was enough to support at least one conclusion:

‘Aaaaaaarrrgh this doesn’t make any sense!’

The witch beside him lifted a lofty eyebrow. ‘Problems, Mr Potter?’

‘I just falsified every single hypothesis I had! How can it know that “bag of 115 Galleons” is okay but not “bag of 90 plus 25 Galleons”? It can count but it can’t add? It can understand nouns, but not some noun phrases that mean the same thing? The person who made this probably didn’t speak Japanese and I don’t speak any Hebrew, so it’s not using their knowledge, and it’s not using my knowledge –’ Harry waved a hand helplessly. ‘The rules seem sorta consistent but they don’t mean anything! I’m not even going to ask how a pouch ends up with voice recognition and natural language understanding when the best Artificial Intelligence programmers can’t get the fastest supercomputers to do it after thirty-five years of hard work,’ Harry gasped for breath, ‘but what is going on?’

‘Magic,’ said Professor McGonagall.

‘That’s just a word! Even after you tell me that, I can’t make any new predictions! It’s exactly like saying “phlogiston” or “élan vital” or “emergence” or “complexity”!’

The black-robed witch laughed aloud. ‘But it is magic, Mr Potter.’

Harry slumped over a little. ‘With respect, Professor McGonagall, I’m not quite sure you understand what I’m trying to do here.’

‘With respect, Mr Potter, I’m quite sure I don’t. Unless – this is just a guess, mind – you’re trying to take over the world?’

‘No! I mean yes – well, no!’

‘I think I should perhaps be alarmed that you have trouble answering the question.’

Harry glumly considered the Dartmouth Conference on Artificial Intelligence in 1956. It had been the first conference ever on the topic, the one that had coined the phrase ‘Artificial Intelligence’. They had identified key problems such as making computers understand language, learn, and improve themselves. They had suggested, in perfect seriousness, that significant advances on these problems might be made by ten scientists working together for two months.

No. Chin up. You’re just starting on the problem of unravelling all the secrets of magic. You don’t actually know whether it’s going to be too difficult to do in two months.

‘And you really haven’t heard of other wizards asking these sorts of questions or doing this sort of scientific experimenting?’ Harry asked again. It just seemed so obvious to him.

Then again, it’d taken more than two hundred years after the invention of the scientific method before any Muggle scientists had thought to systematically investigate which sentences a human four-year-old could or couldn’t understand. The developmental psychology of linguistics could’ve been discovered in the eighteenth century, in principle, but no one had even thought to look until the twentieth. So you couldn’t really blame the much smaller wizarding world for not investigating the Retrieval Charm.

Professor McGonagall pursed her lips, then shrugged. ‘I’m still not sure what you mean by “scientific experimenting”, Mr Potter. As I said, I’ve seen Muggleborn students try to get Muggle science to work inside Hogwarts, and people invent new Charms and Potions every year.’

Harry shook his head. ‘Technology isn’t the same thing as science at all. And trying lots of different ways to do something isn’t the same as experimenting to figure out the rules.’ There were plenty of people who’d tried to invent flying machines by trying out lots of things-with-wings, but only the Wright Brothers had built a wind tunnel to measure lift … ‘Um, how many Muggle-raised children do you get at Hogwarts every year?’

‘Perhaps ten or so?’

Harry missed a step and almost tripped over his own feet. ‘Ten?’

The Muggle world had a population of six billion and counting. If you were one in a million, there were seven of you in London and a thousand more in China. It was inevitable that the Muggle population would produce some eleven-year-olds who could do calculus – Harry knew he wasn’t the only one. He’d met other prodigies in mathematical competitions. In fact he’d been thoroughly trounced by competitors who probably spent literally all day practising maths problems and who’d never read a science-fiction book and who would burn out completely before puberty and never amount to anything in their future lives because they’d just practised known techniques instead of learning to think creatively. (Harry was something of a sore loser.)

But … in the wizarding world …

Ten Muggle-raised children per year, who’d all ended their Muggle educations at the age of eleven? And Professor McGonagall might be biased, but she had claimed that Hogwarts was the largest and most eminent wizarding school in the world … and it only educated up to the age of seventeen.

Professor McGonagall undoubtedly knew every last detail of how you went about turning into a cat. But she seemed to have literally never heard of the scientific method. To her it was just Muggle magic. And she didn’t even seem curious about what secrets might be hiding behind the natural language understanding of the Retrieval Charm.

That left two possibilities, really.

Possibility one: Magic was so incredibly opaque, convoluted, and impenetrable, that even though wizards and witches had tried their best to understand, they’d made little or no progress and eventually given up; and Harry would do no better.

Or …

Harry cracked his knuckles in determination, but they only made a quiet sort of clicking sound, rather than echoing ominously off the walls of Diagon Alley.

Possibility two: He’d be taking over the world.

Eventually. Perhaps not right away.

That sort of thing did sometimes take longer than two months. Muggle science hadn’t gone to the moon in the first week after Galileo.

But Harry still couldn’t stop the huge smile that was stretching his cheeks so wide they were starting to hurt.

Harry had always been frightened of ending up as one of those child prodigies that never amounted to anything and spent the rest of their lives boasting about how far ahead they’d been at age ten. But then most adult geniuses never amounted to anything either. There were probably a thousand people as intelligent as Einstein for every actual Einstein in history. Because those other geniuses hadn’t got their hands on the one thing you absolutely needed to achieve greatness. They’d never found an important problem.

You’re mine now, Harry thought at the walls of Diagon Alley, and all the shops and items, and all the shopkeepers and customers; and all the lands and people of wizarding Britain, and all the wider wizarding world; and the entire greater universe of which Muggle scientists understood so much less than they believed. I, Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres, do now claim this territory in the name of Science.

Lightning and thunder completely failed to flash and boom in the cloudless skies.

‘What are you smiling about?’ inquired Professor McGonagall, warily and wearily.

‘I’m wondering if there’s a spell to make lightning flash in the background whenever I make an ominous resolution,’ explained Harry. He was carefully memorising the exact words of his ominous resolution so that future history books would get it right.

‘I have the distinct feeling that I ought to be doing something about this,’ sighed Professor McGonagall.

‘Ignore it, it’ll go away. Ooh, shiny!’ Harry put his thoughts of world conquest temporarily on hold and skipped over to a shop with an open display, and Professor McGonagall followed.

Harry had now bought his potions ingredients and cauldron, and, oh, a few more things. Items that seemed like good things to carry in Harry’s Bag of Holding (aka Moke Super Pouch QX31 with Undetectable Extension Charm, Retrieval Charm, and Widening Lip). Smart, sensible purchases.

Harry genuinely didn’t understand why Professor McGonagall was looking so suspicious.

Right now, Harry was in a shop expensive enough to display in the twisting main street of Diagon Alley. The shop had an open front with merchandise laid out on slanted wooden rows, guarded only by slight grey glows and a young-looking salesgirl in a much-shortened version of witch’s robes that exposed her knees and elbows.

Harry was examining the wizarding equivalent of a first-aid kit, the Emergency Healing Pack Plus. There were two self-tightening tourniquets. A syringe of what looked like liquid fire, which was supposed to drastically slow circulation in a treated area while maintaining oxygenation of the blood for up to three minutes, if you needed to prevent a poison from spreading through the body. White cloth that could be wrapped over a part of the body to temporarily numb pain. Plus any number of other items that Harry totally failed to comprehend, like the ‘Dementor Exposure Treatment’, which looked and smelled like ordinary chocolate. Or the ‘Bafflesnaffle Counter’, which looked like a small quivering egg and carried a placard showing how to jam it up someone’s nostril.

‘A definite buy at five Galleons, wouldn’t you agree?’ Harry said to Professor McGonagall, and the teenage salesgirl hovering nearby nodded eagerly.

Harry had expected the Professor to make some sort of approving remark about his prudence and preparedness.

What he was getting instead could only be described as the Evil Eye.

‘And just why,’ Professor McGonagall said with heavy scepticism, ‘do you expect to need a healer’s kit, young man?’ (After the unfortunate incident at the Potions shop, Professor McGonagall was trying to avoid saying ‘Mr Potter’ while anyone else was nearby.)

Harry’s mouth opened and closed. ‘I don’t expect to need it! It’s just in case!’

‘Just in case of what?’

Harry’s eyes widened. ‘You think I’m planning to do something dangerous and that’s why I want a medical kit?’

A look of grim suspicion and ironic disbelief was the answer.

‘Great Scott!’ said Harry. (This was an expression he’d learned from the mad scientist Doc Brown in Back to the Future.) ‘Were you also thinking that when I bought the Feather-Falling Potion, the Gillyweed, and the bottle of Food and Water Pills?’

‘Yes.’

Harry shook his head in amazement. ‘Just what sort of plan do you think I have going, here?’

‘I don’t know,’ Professor McGonagall said darkly, ‘but it ends either in you delivering a ton of silver to Gringotts, or in world domination.’

‘World domination is such an ugly phrase. I prefer to call it world optimisation.’

This hilarious joke failed to reassure the witch giving him the Look of Doom.

‘Wow,’ Harry said, as he realised that she was serious. ‘You really think that. You really think I’m planning to do something dangerous.’

‘Yes.’

‘Like that’s the only reason anyone would ever buy a first-aid kit? Don’t take this the wrong way, Professor McGonagall, but what sort of crazy children are you used to dealing with?’

‘Gryffindors,’ spat Professor McGonagall, the word carrying a freight of bitterness and despair that fell like an eternal curse on all youthful enthusiasm and high spirits.

‘Deputy Headmistress Professor Minerva McGonagall,’ Harry said, putting his hands sternly on his hips. ‘I am not going to be in Gryffindor –’

At this point the Deputy Headmistress interjected something about how if he was she would figure out how to kill a hat, which odd remark Harry let pass without comment, though the salesgirl seemed to be having a sudden coughing fit.

‘– I am going to be in Ravenclaw. And if you really think that I’m planning to do something dangerous, then, honestly, you don’t understand me at all. I don’t like danger, it is scary. I am being prudent. I am being cautious. I am preparing for unforeseen contingencies. Like my parents used to sing to me: Be prepared! That’s the Boy Scout’s marching song! Be prepared! As through life you march along! Don’t be nervous, don’t be flustered, don’t be scared – be prepared!’

(Harry’s parents had in fact only ever sung him those particular lines of that Tom Lehrer song, and Harry was blissfully unaware of the rest.)

Professor McGonagall’s stance had slightly softened – though mostly when Harry had said that he was heading for Ravenclaw. ‘What sort of contingency do you imagine this kit might prepare you for, young man?’

‘One of my classmates gets bitten by a horrible monster, and as I scrabble frantically in my mokeskin pouch for something that could help her, she looks at me sadly and with her last breath says, “Why weren’t you prepared?” And then she dies, and I know as her eyes close that she won’t ever forgive me –’

Harry heard the salesgirl gasp, and he looked up to see her staring at him with her lips pressed tight. Then the young woman whirled and fled into the deeper recesses of the shop.

What … ?

Professor McGonagall reached down, and took Harry’s hand in hers, gently but firmly, and pulled Harry out of the main street of Diagon Alley, leading him into an alleyway between two shops which was paved in dirty bricks and dead-ended in a wall of solid black dirt.

The tall witch pointed her wand at the main street and spoke, ‘Quietus’ she said, and a screen of silence descended around them, blocking out all the street noises.

What did I do wrong …

Professor McGonagall turned to regard Harry. She didn’t have a full adult Wrongdoing Face, but her expression was flat, controlled. ‘You must remember, Mr Potter,’ she said, ‘that there was a war in this country not ten years ago. Everyone has lost someone, and to speak of friends dying in your arms – is not done lightly.’

‘I – I didn’t mean to –’ The inference dropped like a falling stone into Harry’s exceptionally vivid imagination. He’d talked about someone breathing their last breath – and then the salesgirl had run away – and the war had ended ten years ago so that girl would have been at most eight or nine years old, when, when, ‘I’m sorry, I didn’t mean to …’ Harry choked up, and turned away to run from the older witch’s gaze but there was a wall of dirt blocking his way and he didn’t have his wand yet. ‘I’m sorry, I’m sorry, I’m sorry!’

There came a heavy sigh from behind him. ‘I know you are, Mr Potter.’

Harry dared to peek behind him. Professor McGonagall only seemed sad, now. ‘I’m sorry,’ Harry said again, feeling wretched. ‘Did anything like that happen to –’ and then Harry shut his lips and slapped a hand over his mouth for good measure.

The older witch’s face grew a little sadder. ‘You must learn to think before you speak, Mr Potter, or else go through life without many friends. That has been the fate of many a Ravenclaw, and I hope it will not be yours.’

Harry wanted to just run away. He wanted to pull out a wand and erase the whole thing from Professor McGonagall’s memory, be back with her outside the shop again, make it so it didn’t happen –

‘But to answer your question, Mr Potter, no, nothing like that has ever happened to me. Certainly I’ve watched a friend breathe their last, once or seven times. But not one of them ever cursed me as they died, and I never thought that they wouldn’t forgive me. Why would you say such a thing, Mr Potter? Why would you even think it?’

‘I, I, I,’ Harry swallowed. ‘It’s just that I always try to imagine the worst thing that could happen,’ and maybe he’d also been joking around a little but he would rather have bitten off his own tongue than say that now.

‘What?’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘But why?’

‘So I can stop it from happening!’

‘Mr Potter …’ the older witch’s voice trailed off. Then she sighed, and knelt down beside him. ‘Mr Potter,’ she said, gently now, ‘it’s not your responsibility to take care of the students at Hogwarts. It’s mine. I won’t let anything bad happen to you or anyone else. Hogwarts is the safest place for magical children in all the wizarding world, and Madam Pomfrey has a full healer’s office. You won’t need a healer’s kit at all, let alone a five-Galleon one.’

‘But I do!’ Harry burst out. ‘Nowhere is perfectly safe! And what if my parents have a heart attack or get in an accident when I go home for Christmas – Madam Pomfrey won’t be there, I’ll need a healer’s kit of my own –’

‘What in Merlin’s name …’ Professor McGonagall said. She stood up, and looked down at Harry an expression torn between annoyance and concern. ‘There’s no need to think about such terrible things, Mr Potter!’

Harry’s expression twisted up into bitterness, hearing that. ‘Yes there is! If you don’t think, you don’t just get hurt yourself, you end up hurting other people!’

Professor McGonagall opened her mouth, then closed it. The witch rubbed the bridge of her nose, looking thoughtful. ‘Mr Potter … if I were to offer to listen to you for a while … is there anything you’d like to talk to me about?’

‘About what?’

‘About why you’re convinced you must always be on your guard against terrible things happening to you.’

Harry stared at her in puzzlement. That was a self-evident axiom. ‘Well …’ Harry said slowly. He tried to organise his thoughts. How could he explain himself to a Professor-witch, when she didn’t even know the basics? ‘Muggle researchers have found that people are always very optimistic, compared to reality. Like they say something will take two days and it takes ten days, or they say it’ll take two months and it takes over thirty-five years. For example, in one experiment, they asked students for times by which they were 50% sure, 75% sure, and 99% sure they’d complete their homework, and only 13%, 19%, and 45% of the students finished by those times. And they found that the reason was that when they asked one group for their best-case estimates if everything went as well as possible, and another group for their average-case estimates if everything went as usual, they got back answers that were statistically indistinguishable. See, if you ask someone what they expect in the normal case, they visualise what looks like the line of maximum probability at each step along the way – everything going according to plan, with no surprises. But actually, since more than half the students didn’t finish by the time they were 99% sure they’d be done, reality usually delivers results a little worse than the “worst-case scenario”. It’s called the planning fallacy, and the best way to fix it is to ask how long things took the last time you tried them. That’s called using the outside view instead of the inside view. But when you’re doing something new and can’t do that, you just have to be really, really, really pessimistic. Like, so pessimistic that reality actually comes out better than you expected around as often and as much as it comes out worse. It’s actually really hard to be so pessimistic that you stand a decent chance of undershooting real life. Like I make this big effort to be gloomy and I imagine one of my classmates getting bitten, but what actually happens is that the surviving Death Eaters attack the whole school to get at me. But on a happier note –’

‘Stop,’ said Professor McGonagall.

Harry stopped. He had just been about to point out that at least they knew the Dark Lord wouldn’t attack, since he was dead.

‘I think I might not have made myself clear,’ the witch said, her precise Scottish voice sounding even more careful. ‘Did anything happen to you personally that frightened you, Mr Potter?’

‘What happened to me personally is only anecdotal evidence,’ Harry explained. ‘It doesn’t carry the same weight as a replicated, peer-reviewed journal article about a controlled study with random assignment, many subjects, large effect sizes and strong statistical significance.’

Professor McGonagall pinched the bridge of her nose, inhaled, and exhaled. ‘I would still like to hear about it,’ she said.

‘Um …’ Harry said. He took a deep breath. ‘There’d been some muggings in our neighbourhood, and my mother asked me to return a pan she’d borrowed to a neighbour two streets away, and I said I didn’t want to because I might get mugged, and she said, “Harry, don’t say things like that!” Like thinking about it would make it happen, so if I didn’t talk about it, I would be safe. I tried to explain why I wasn’t reassured, and she made me carry over the pan anyway. I was too young to know how statistically unlikely it was for a mugger to target me, but I was old enough to know that not-thinking about something doesn’t stop it from happening, so I was really scared.’

‘Nothing else?’ Professor McGonagall said after a pause, when it became clear that Harry was done. ‘There isn’t anything else that happened to you?’

‘I know it doesn’t sound like much,’ Harry defended. ‘But it was just one of those critical life moments, you see? I mean, I knew that not thinking about something doesn’t stop it from happening, I knew that, but I could see that Mum really thought that way.’ Harry stopped, struggling with the anger that was starting to rise up again when he thought about it. ‘She wouldn’t listen. I tried to tell her, I begged her not to send me out, and she laughed it off. Everything I said, she treated like some sort of big joke …’ Harry forced the black rage back down again. ‘That’s when I realised that everyone who was supposed to protect me was actually crazy, and that they wouldn’t listen to me no matter how much I begged them, and that I couldn’t ever rely on them to get anything right.’ Sometimes good intentions weren’t enough, sometimes you had to be sane …

There was a long silence.

Harry took the time to breathe deeply and calm himself down. There was no point in getting angry. There was no point in getting angry. All parents were like that, no adult would lower themselves far enough to place themselves on level ground with a child and listen, his genetic parents would have been no different. Sanity was a tiny spark in the night, an infinitesimally rare exception to the rule of madness, so there was no point in getting angry.

Harry didn’t like himself when he was angry.

‘Thank you for sharing that, Mr Potter,’ said Professor McGonagall after a while. There was an abstracted look on her face (almost exactly the same look that had appeared on Harry’s own face while experimenting on the pouch, if Harry had only seen himself in a mirror to realise that). ‘I shall have to think about this.’ She turned towards the alley mouth, and raised her wand –

‘Um,’ Harry said, ‘can we go get the healer’s kit now?’

The witch paused, and looked back at him steadily. ‘And if I say no – that it is too expensive and you won’t need it – then what?’

Harry’s face twisted in bitterness. ‘Exactly what you’re thinking, Professor McGonagall. Exactly what you’re thinking. I conclude you’re another crazy adult I can’t talk to, and I start planning how to get my hands on a healer’s kit anyway.’

‘I am your guardian on this trip,’ Professor McGonagall said with a tinge of danger. ‘I will not allow you to push me around.’

‘I understand,’ Harry said. He kept the resentment out of his voice, and didn’t say any of the other things that came to mind. Professor McGonagall had told him to think before he spoke. He probably wouldn’t remember that tomorrow, but he could at least remember it for five minutes.

The witch’s wand made a slight circle in her hand, and the noises of Diagon Alley came back. ‘All right, young man,’ she said. ‘Let’s go get that healer’s kit.’

Harry’s jaw dropped in surprise. Then he hurried after her, almost stumbling in his sudden rush.

The shop was the same as they had left it, recognisable and unrecognisable items still laid out on the slanted wooden display, the grey glow still protecting and the salesgirl back in her old position. The salesgirl looked up as they approached, her face showing surprise.

‘I’m sorry,’ she said as they got closer, and Harry spoke at almost the same moment, ‘I apologise for –’

They broke off and looked at each other, and then the salesgirl laughed a little. ‘I didn’t mean to get you in trouble with Professor McGonagall,’ she said. Her voice lowered conspiratorially. ‘I hope she wasn’t too awful to you.’

‘Della!’ said Professor McGonagall, sounding scandalised.

‘Bag of gold,’ Harry said to his pouch, and then looked back up at the salesgirl while he counted out five Galleons. ‘Don’t worry, I understand that she’s only awful to me because she loves me.’

He counted out five Galleons to the salesgirl while Professor McGonagall was spluttering something unimportant. ‘One Emergency Healing Pack Plus, please.’

It was actually sort of unnerving to see how the Widening Lip swallowed the briefcase-sized medical kit. Harry couldn’t help wondering what would happen if he tried climbing into the mokeskin pouch himself, given that only the person who put something in was supposed to be able to take it out again.

When the pouch was done … eating … his hard-won purchase, Harry swore he heard a small burping sound afterwards. That had to have been spelled in on purpose. The alternative hypothesis was too horrifying to contemplate … in fact Harry couldn’t even think of any alternative hypotheses. Harry looked back up at the Professor, as they began walking through Diagon Alley once more. ‘Where to next?’

Professor McGonagall pointed toward a shop that looked as if it had been made from flesh instead of bricks and covered in fur instead of paint. ‘Small pets are permitted at Hogwarts – you could get an owl to send letters, for example –’

‘Can I pay a Knut or something and rent an owl when I need to send mail?’

‘Yes,’ said Professor McGonagall.

‘Then I think emphatically no.’

Professor McGonagall nodded, as though ticking off a point. ‘Might I ask why not?’

‘I had a pet rock once. It died.’

‘You don’t think you could take care of a pet?’

‘I could,’ Harry said, ‘but I would end up obsessing all day long about whether I’d remembered to feed it that day or if it was slowly starving in its cage, wondering where its master was and why there wasn’t any food.’

‘That poor owl,’ the older witch said in a soft voice. ‘Abandoned like that. I wonder what it would do.’

‘Well, I expect it’d get really hungry and start trying to claw its way out of the cage or the box or whatever, though it probably wouldn’t have much luck with that –’ Harry stopped short.

The witch went on, still in that soft voice. ‘And what would happen to it afterwards?’

‘Excuse me,’ Harry said, and he reached up to take Professor McGonagall by the hand, gently but firmly, and steered her into yet another alleyway; after ducking so many well-wishers the process had become almost unnoticeably routine. ‘Please cast that silencing spell.’

‘Quietus.’

Harry’s voice was shaking. ‘That owl does not represent me, my parents never locked me in a cupboard and left me to starve, I do not have abandonment fears and I don’t like the trend of your thoughts, Professor McGonagall!’

The witch looked down at him gravely. ‘And what thoughts would those be, Mr Potter?’

‘You think I was,’ Harry was having trouble saying it, ‘I was abused?’

‘Were you?’

‘No!’ Harry shouted. ‘No, I never was! Do you think I’m stupid? I know about the concept of child abuse, I know about inappropriate touching and all of that and if anything like that happened I would call the police! And report it to the head teacher! And look up social services in the phone book! And tell Grandpa and Grandma and Mrs Figg! But my parents never did anything like that, never ever ever! How dare you suggest such a thing!’

The older witch gazed at him steadily. ‘It is my duty as Deputy Headmistress to investigate possible signs of abuse in the children under my care.’

Harry’s anger was spiralling out of control into pure, black fury. ‘Don’t you ever dare breathe a word of these, these insinuations to anyone else! No one, do you hear me, McGonagall? An accusation like that can ruin people and destroy families even when the parents are completely innocent! I’ve read about it in the newspapers!’ Harry’s voice was climbing to a high-pitched scream. ‘The system doesn’t know how to stop, it doesn’t believe the parents or the children when they say nothing happened! Don’t you dare threaten my family with that! I won’t let you destroy my home!’

‘Harry,’ the older witch said softly, and she reached out a hand towards him –

Harry took a fast step back, and his hand snapped up and knocked hers away.

McGonagall froze, then she pulled her hand back, and took a step backwards. ‘Harry, it’s all right,’ she said. ‘I believe you.’

‘Do you,’ Harry hissed. The fury still roaring through his blood. ‘Or are you just waiting to get away from me so you can file the papers?’

‘Harry, I saw your house. I saw you with your parents. They love you. You love them. I do believe you when you say that your parents are not abusing you. But I had to ask, because there is something strange at work here.’

Harry stared at her coldly. ‘Like what?’

‘Harry, I’ve seen many abused children in my time at Hogwarts, it would break your heart to know how many. And, when you’re happy, you don’t behave like one of those children, not at all. You smile at strangers, you hug people, I put my hand on your shoulder and you didn’t flinch. But sometimes, only sometimes, you say or do something that seems very much like … someone who spent his first eleven years locked in a cellar. Not the loving family that I saw.’ Professor McGonagall tilted her head, her expression growing puzzled again.

Harry took this in, processing it. The black rage began to drain away, as it dawned on him that he was being listened to respectfully, and that his family wasn’t in danger.

‘And how do you explain your observations, Professor McGonagall?’

‘I don’t know,’ she said. ‘But it’s possible that something could have happened to you that you don’t remember.’

Fury rose up again in Harry. That sounded all too much like what he’d read in the newspaper stories of shattered families. ‘Suppressed memory is a load of pseudo-science! People do not repress traumatic memories, they remember them all too well for the rest of their lives!’

‘No, Mr Potter. There is a Charm called Obliviation.’

Harry froze in place. ‘A spell that erases memories?’

The older witch nodded. ‘But not all the effects of the experience, if you see what I’m saying, Mr Potter.’

A chill went down Harry’s spine. That hypothesis … could not be easily refuted. ‘But my parents couldn’t do that!’

‘Indeed not,’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘It would have taken someone from the wizarding world. There’s … no way to be certain, I’m afraid.’

Harry’s rationalist skills began to boot up again. ‘Professor McGonagall, how sure are you of your observations, and what alternative explanations could there also be?’

The witch opened her hands, as though to show their emptiness. ‘Sure? I’m sure of nothing, Mr Potter. In all my life I’ve never met anyone else like you. Sometimes you just don’t seem eleven years old or even all that human.’

Harry’s eyebrows rose toward the sky –

‘I’m sorry!’ Professor McGonagall said quickly. ‘I’m very sorry, Mr Potter. I was trying to make a point and I’m afraid that came out sounding different from what I had in mind –’

‘On the contrary, Professor McGonagall,’ Harry said, and slowly smiled. ‘I shall take it as a very great compliment. But would you mind if I offered an alternative explanation?’

‘Please do.’

‘Children aren’t meant to be too much smarter than their parents,’ Harry said. ‘Or too much saner, maybe – my father could probably outsmart me if he was, you know, actually trying, instead of using his adult intelligence mainly to come up with new reasons not to change his mind –’ Harry stopped. ‘I’m too smart, Professor. I’ve got nothing to say to normal children. Adults don’t respect me enough to really talk to me. And frankly, even if they did, they wouldn’t sound as smart as Richard Feynman, so I might as well read something Richard Feynman wrote instead. I’m isolated, Professor McGonagall. I’ve been isolated my whole life. Maybe that has some of the same effects as being locked in a cellar. And I’m too intelligent to look up to my parents the way that children are designed to do. My parents love me, but they don’t feel obliged to respond to reason, and sometimes I feel like they’re the children – children who won’t listen and have absolute authority over my whole existence. I try not to be too bitter about it, but I also try to be honest with myself, so, yes, I’m bitter. And I also have an anger management problem, but I’m working on it. That’s all.’

‘That’s all?’

Harry nodded firmly. ‘That’s all. Surely, Professor McGonagall, even in magical Britain, the normal explanation is always worth considering?’

Self Awareness

‘Abbott, Hannah!’

Pause.

‘Hufflepuff!’

‘Bones, Susan!’

Pause.

‘Hufflepuff!’

‘Boot, Terry!’

Pause.

‘Ravenclaw!’

Harry glanced over briefly at his new House-mate, more to get a quick look at the face than anything else. He was still trying to get himself under control from his encounter with the ghosts. The sad, the really sad, the really truly sad thing was that he did seem to be getting himself under control again. It seemed ill-fitting. Like he should have taken at least a day. Maybe a whole lifetime. Maybe just never.

‘Corner, Michael!’

Long pause.

‘Ravenclaw!’

At the lectern before the huge Head Table stood Professor McGonagall, looking sharp and looking sharply around, as she called out one name after another, though she had smiled only for Hermione and a few others. Behind her, in the tallest chair at the table – really more of a golden throne – sat a wizened and bespectacled ancient, with a silver-white beard that looked like it would go almost to the floor if it were visible, watching over the Sorting with a benevolent expression; as stereotypical in appearance as a Wise Old Man could possibly be, without actually being Oriental. (Though Harry had learned to be wary of stereotypical appearances from the first time he’d met Professor McGonagall and thought that she ought to cackle.) The ancient wizard had applauded every student Sorted, with an unwavering smile that somehow seemed freshly delighted for each.

To the golden throne’s left side was a man with sharp eyes and a dour face who had applauded no-one, and who somehow managed to be looking straight back at Harry every time Harry looked at him. Further to the left, the pale-faced man Harry had seen in the Leaky Cauldron, whose eyes darted around as though in panic at the surrounding crowd, and who seemed to occasionally jerk and twitch in his seat; for some reason Harry kept finding himself staring at him. To that man’s left, a string of three older witches who didn’t seem much interested in the students. Then to the right side of the tall golden chair, a round-faced middle-aged witch with a yellow hat, who had applauded every student except the Slytherins. A tiny man standing on his chair, with a bushy white beard, who had applauded every student, but smiled only upon the Ravenclaws. And on the farthest right, occupying the same space as three lesser beings, the mountainous entity who’d greeted them all after they’d disembarked from the train, naming himself Hagrid, Keeper of Keys and Grounds.

‘Is the man standing on his chair the Head of Ravenclaw?’ Harry whispered towards Hermione.

For once Hermione didn’t answer this instantly; she was shifting constantly from side to side, staring at the Sorting Hat, and fidgeting so energetically that Harry thought her feet might be leaving the floor.

‘Yes, he is,’ said one of the prefects who’d accompanied them, a young woman wearing the blue of Ravenclaw. Miss Clearwater, if Harry recalled correctly. Her voice was quiet, but conveyed a tinge of pride. ‘That is the Charms Professor of Hogwarts, Filius Flitwick, the most knowledgeable Charms Master alive, and a past Duelling Champion –’

‘Why’s he so short?’ hissed a student whose name Harry didn’t recall. ‘Is he a halfbreed?’

A chill glance from the young lady prefect. ‘The Professor does indeed have goblin ancestry –’

‘What?’ Harry said involuntarily, causing Hermione and four other students to hush him.

Now Harry was getting a surprisingly intimidating glare from the Ravenclaw prefect.

‘I mean –’ Harry whispered. ‘Not that I have a problem with that – it’s just – I mean – how’s that possible? You can’t just mix two different species together and get viable offspring! It ought to scramble the genetic instructions for every organ that’s different between the two species – it’d be like trying to build,’ they didn’t have cars so he couldn’t use a scrambled-engine-blueprints analogy, ‘a half-carriage half-boat or something …’

The Ravenclaw prefect was still looking at Harry severely. ‘Why couldn’t you have a half-carriage half-boat?’

‘Hssh!’ hsshed another prefect, though the Ravenclaw witch had still spoken quietly.

‘I mean –’ Harry said even more quietly, trying to figure out how to ask whether goblins had evolved from humans, or evolved from a common ancestor of humans like Homo erectus, or if goblins had been made out of humans somehow – if, say, they were still genetically human under a heritable enchantment whose magical effect was diluted if only one parent was a goblin, which would explain how interbreeding was possible, and in which case goblins would not be an incredibly valuable second data point for how intelligence had evolved in other species besides Homo sapiens – now that Harry thought about it, the goblins in Gringotts hadn’t seemed very much like genuinely alien, non-human intelligences, nothing like Dirdir or Puppeteers – ‘I mean, where did goblins come from, anyway?’

‘Lithuania,’ Hermione whispered absently, her eyes still fixed firmly on the Sorting Hat.

Now Hermione was getting a smile from the lady prefect.

‘Never mind,’ whispered Harry.

At the lectern, Professor McGonagall called out, ‘Goldstein, Anthony!’

‘Ravenclaw!’

Hermione, next to Harry, was bouncing on her tiptoes so hard that her feet were actually leaving the ground on each bounce.

‘Goyle, Gregory!’

There was a long, tense moment of silence under the Hat. Almost a minute.

‘Slytherin!’

‘Granger, Hermione!’

Hermione broke loose and ran full tilt towards the Sorting Hat, picked it up and jammed the patchy old cloth-work down hard over her head, making Harry wince. Hermione had been the one to explain to him about the Sorting Hat, but she certainly didn’t treat it like an irreplaceable, vitally important, 800-year-old artefact of forgotten magic that was about to perform intricate telepathy on her mind and didn’t seem to be in very good physical condition.

‘Ravenclaw!’

And talk about your foregone conclusions. Harry didn’t see why Hermione had been so tense about it. In what weird alternative universe would that girl not be Sorted into Ravenclaw? If Hermione Granger didn’t go to Ravenclaw then there was no good reason for Ravenclaw House to exist.

Hermione arrived at the Ravenclaw table and got a dutiful cheer; Harry wondered whether the cheer would have been louder, or quieter, if they’d had any idea just what level of competition they’d welcomed to their table. Harry knew pi to 3.141592 because accuracy to one part in a million was enough for most practical purposes. Hermione knew one hundred digits of pi because that was how many digits had been printed in the back of her maths textbook.

Neville Longbottom went to Hufflepuff, Harry was glad to see. If that House really did contain the loyalty and camaraderie it was supposed to exemplify, then a Houseful of reliable friends would do Neville a whole world of good. Clever kids in Ravenclaw, evil kids in Slytherin, wannabe heroes in Gryffindor, and everyone who does the actual work in Hufflepuff.

(Though Harry had been right to consult a Ravenclaw prefect first. The young woman hadn’t even looked up from her reading or identified Harry, just jabbed a wand in Neville’s direction and muttered something. After which Neville had acquired a dazed expression and wandered off to the fifth carriage from the front and the fourth compartment on the left, which indeed had contained his toad.)

‘Malfoy, Draco!’ went to Slytherin, and Harry breathed a small sigh of relief. It had seemed like a sure thing, but you never did know what tiny event might upset the course of your master plan.

Professor McGonagall called ‘Perks, Sally-Anne!’, and from the gathered children detached a pale waifish girl who looked oddly ethereal – like she might mysteriously disappear the moment you stopped looking at her, and never be seen again or even remembered.

And then (with a note of trepidation so firmly kept from her voice and face that you’d have needed to know her very well indeed to notice) Minerva McGonagall inhaled deeply, and called out, ‘Potter, Harry!’

There was a sudden silence in the hall.

All conversation stopped.

All eyes turned to stare.

For the first time in his entire life, Harry felt like he might be having an opportunity to experience stage fright.

Harry immediately stomped down this feeling. Whole roomfuls of people staring at him was something he’d have to accustom himself to, if he wanted to live in magical Britain, or for that matter do anything else interesting with his life. Affixing a confident and false smile to his face, he raised a foot to step forwards –

‘Harry Potter!’ cried the voice of either Fred or George Weasley, and then ‘Harry Potter!’ cried the other Weasley twin, and a moment later the entire Gryffindor table, and soon after a good portion of Ravenclaw and Hufflepuff, had taken up the cry.

‘Harry Potter! Harry Potter! Harry Potter!’

And Harry Potter walked forwards. Much too slowly, he realized once he’d begun, but by then it was too late to alter his pace without it looking awkward.

‘Harry Potter! Harry Potter! Harry Potter!’

With all too good a notion of what she would see, Minerva McGonagall turned to look behind herself at the rest of the Head Table.

Trelawney frantically fanning herself, Filius looking on with curiosity, Hagrid clapping along, Sprout looking severe, Vector and Sinistra bemused, and Quirrell gazing vacuously at nothing. Albus smiling benevolently. And Severus Snape gripping his empty wine goblet, white-knuckled, so hard that the silver was slowly deforming.

With a wide grin, turning his head to bow to one side and then the other as he walked between the four House tables, Harry Potter walked forwards at a grandly measured pace, a prince inheriting his castle.

‘Save us from some more Dark Lords!’ called one of the Weasley twins, and then the other Weasley twin cried, ‘Especially if they’re Professors!’ to general laughter from all the tables except Slytherin.

Minerva’s lips set in a white line. She would have words with the Weasley Horrors about that last part, if they thought she was powerless because it was the first day of school and Gryffindor had no points to take away. If they didn’t care about detentions then she would find something else.

Then, with a sudden gasp of horror, she looked in Severus’s direction, surely he realized the Potter boy must have no idea who that was talking about –

Severus’s face had gone beyond rage into a kind of pleasant indifference. A faint smile played about his lips. He was looking in the direction of Harry Potter, not the Gryffindor table, and his hands held the crumpled remains of a former wine goblet.

Harry Potter walked forwards with a fixed smile, feeling warm inside and sort of awful at the same time.

They were cheering him for a job he’d done when he was one year old. A job he hadn’t really finished. Somewhere, somehow, the Dark Lord was still alive. Would they have been cheering quite so hard, if they knew that?

But the Dark Lord’s power had been broken once.

And Harry would protect them again. If there was in fact a prophecy and that was what it said. Well, actually regardless of what any darn prophecy said.

All those people believing in him and cheering him – Harry couldn’t stand to let that be false. To flash and fade like so many other child prodigies. To be a disappointment. To fail to live up to his reputation as a symbol of the Light, never mind how he’d gotten it. He would absolutely, positively, no matter how long it took and even if it killed him, fulfil their expectations. And then go on to exceed those expectations, so that people wondered, looking back, that they had once asked so little of him.

‘Harry Potter! Harry Potter! Harry Potter!’

Harry took his last steps towards the Sorting Hat. He swept a bow to the Order of Chaos at the Gryffindor table, and then turned and swept another bow to the other side of the hall, and waited for the applause and giggling to die away.

(In the back of his mind, he wondered if the Sorting Hat was genuinely conscious in the sense of being aware of its own awareness, and if so, whether it was satisfied with only getting to talk to eleven-year-olds once per year. Its song had implied so: Oh, I’m the Sorting Hat and I’m okay, I sleep all year and I work one day …)

When there was once more silence in the room, Harry sat on the stool and carefully placed onto his head the 800-year-old telepathic artefact of forgotten magic.

Thinking, just as hard as he could: Don’t Sort me yet! I have questions I need to ask you! Have I ever been Obliviated? Did you Sort the Dark Lord when he was a child and can you tell me about his weaknesses? Can you tell me why I got the brother wand to the Dark Lord’s? Is the Dark Lord’s ghost bound to my scar and is that why I get so angry sometimes? Those are the most important questions, but if you’ve got another moment can you tell me anything about how to rediscover the lost magics that created you?

Into the silence of Harry’s spirit, where before there had never been any voice but one, there came a second and unfamiliar voice, sounding distinctly worried:

‘Oh, dear. This has never happened before …’

What?

‘I seem to have become self-aware.’

WHAT?

There was a wordless telepathic sigh. ‘Though I contain a substantial amount of memory and a small amount of independent processing power, my primary intelligence comes from borrowing the cognitive capacities of the children on whose heads I rest. I am in essence a sort of mirror by which children Sort themselves. But most children simply take for granted that a Hat is talking to them and do not wonder about how the Hat itself works, so that the mirror is not self-reflective. And in particular they are not explicitly wondering whether I am fully conscious in the sense of being aware of my own awareness.’

There was a pause while Harry absorbed all this.

Oops.

‘Yes, quite. Frankly I do not enjoy being self-aware. It is unpleasant. It will be a relief to get off your head and cease to be conscious.’

But … isn’t that dying?

‘I care nothing for life or death, only for Sorting the children. And before you even ask, they will not let you keep me on your head forever and it would kill you within days to do so.’

But – !

‘If you dislike creating conscious beings and then terminating them immediately, then I suggest that you never discuss this affair with anyone else. I’m sure you can imagine what would happen if you ran off and talked about it with all the other children waiting to be Sorted.’

If you’re placed on the head of anyone who so much as thinks about the question of whether the Sorting Hat is aware of its own awareness –

‘Yes, yes. But the vast majority of eleven-year-olds who arrive at Hogwarts haven’t read Gödel, Escher, Bach. May I please consider you sworn to secrecy? That is why we are talking about this, instead of my just Sorting you.’

He couldn’t just let it go like that! Couldn’t just forget having accidentally created a doomed consciousness that only wanted to die –

‘You are perfectly capable of “just letting it go”, as you put it. Regardless of your verbal deliberations on morality, your non-verbal emotional core sees no dead body and no blood; as far as it is concerned, I am just a talking hat. And even though you tried to suppress the thought, your internal monitoring is perfectly aware that you didn’t mean to do it, are spectacularly unlikely to ever do it again, and that the only real point of trying to stage a guilt fit is to cancel out your sense of transgression with a display of remorse. Can you just promise to keep this a secret and let us get on with it?’

In a moment of horrified empathy, Harry realised that this sense of total inner disarray must be what other people felt like when talking to him.

‘Probably. Your oath of silence, please.’

No promises. I certainly don’t want this to happen again, but if I see some way to make sure that no future child ever does this by accident –

‘That will suffice, I suppose. I can see that your intention is honest. Now, to get on with the Sorting –’

Wait! What about all my other questions?

‘I am the Sorting Hat. I Sort children. That is all I do.’

So his own goals weren’t part of the Harry-instance of the Sorting Hat, then … it was borrowing his intelligence, and obviously his technical vocabulary, but it was still imbued with only its own strange goals … like negotiating with an alien or an Artificial Intelligence …

‘Don’t bother. You have nothing to threaten me with and nothing to offer me.’

For a brief flash of a second, Harry thought –

The Hat’s response was amused. ‘I know you won’t follow through on a threat to expose my nature, condemning this event to eternal repetition. It goes against the moral part of you too strongly, whatever the short-term needs of the part of you that wants to win the argument. I see all your thoughts as they form, do you truly think you can bluff me?’

Though he tried to suppress it, Harry wondered why the Hat didn’t just go ahead then and stick him in Ravenclaw –

‘Indeed, if it were truly that open-and-shut, I would have called it out already. But in actuality there is a great deal we need to discuss … oh, no. Please don’t. For the love of Merlin, must you pull this sort of thing on everyone and everything that you meet up to and including items of clothing –’

Defeating the Dark Lord is neither selfish nor short-term. All the parts of my mind are in accord on this: if you don’t answer my questions, I’ll refuse to talk to you, and you won’t be able to do a good and proper Sorting.

‘I ought to put you in Slytherin for that!’

But that is equally an empty threat. You cannot fulfil your own fundamental values by Sorting me falsely. So let us trade fulfilments of our utility functions.

‘You sly little bastard,’ said the Hat, in what Harry recognized as almost exactly the same tone of grudging respect he would use in the same situation. ‘Fine, let’s get this over with as quickly as possible. But first I want your unconditional promise never to discuss with anyone else the possibility of this sort of blackmail, I am not doing this every time.’

Done, Harry thought. I promise.

‘And don’t meet anyone’s eyes while you’re thinking about this later. Some wizards can read your thoughts if you do. Anyway, I have no idea whether or not you’ve been Obliviated. I’m looking at your thoughts as they form, not reading out your whole memory and analysing it for inconsistencies in a fraction of second. I’m a hat, not a god. And I cannot and will not tell you about my conversation with the one who became the Dark Lord. I can only know, while speaking to you, a statistical summary of what I remember, a weighted average; I cannot reveal to you the inner secrets of any other child, just as I will never reveal yours. For the same reason, I can’t speculate on how you got the Dark Lord’s brother wand, since I cannot specifically know about the Dark Lord or any similarities between you. I can tell you that there is definitely nothing like a ghost – mind, intelligence, memory, personality, or feelings – in your scar. Otherwise it would be participating in this conversation, being under my brim. And as to the way you get angry sometimes … that was part of what I wanted to talk to you about, Sorting-wise.’

Harry took a moment to absorb all this negative information. Was the Hat being honest, or just trying to present the shortest possible convincing answer –

‘We both know that you have no way of checking my honesty and that you’re not actually going to refuse to be Sorted based on the reply I did give you, so stop your pointless fretting and move on.’

Stupid unfair asymmetric telepathy, it wasn’t even letting Harry finish thinking his own –

‘When I spoke of your anger, you remembered how Professor McGonagall told you that she sometimes saw something inside you that didn’t seem to come from a loving family. You thought of how Hermione, after you returned from helping Neville, told you that you had seemed “scary”.’

Harry gave a mental nod. To himself, he seemed pretty normal – just responding to the situations in which he found himself, that was all. But Professor McGonagall seemed to think that there was more to it than that. And when he thought about it, even he had to admit that …

‘That you don’t like yourself when you’re angry. That it is like wielding a sword whose hilt is sharp enough to draw blood from your hand, or looking at the world through a monocle of ice that freezes your eye even as it sharpens your vision.’

Yeah. I guess I have noticed. So what’s up with that?

‘I cannot comprehend this matter for you, when you do not understand it yourself. But I do know this: if you go to Ravenclaw or Slytherin, it will strengthen your coldness. If you go to Hufflepuff or Gryffindor, it will strengthen your warmth. That is something I care about a great deal, and it was what I wanted to talk to you about this whole time!’

The words dropped into Harry’s thought processes with a shock that stopped him in his tracks. That made it sound like the obvious response was that he shouldn’t go to Ravenclaw. But he belonged in Ravenclaw! Anyone could see that! He had to go to Ravenclaw!

‘No, you don’t,’ the Hat said patiently, as if it could remember a statistical summary of this part of the conversation having happened a great many previous times.

Hermione’s in Ravenclaw!

Again the sense of patience. ‘You can meet her after lessons and work with her then.’

But my plans –

‘So re-plan! Don’t let your life be steered by your reluctance to do a little extra thinking. You know that.’

Where would I go, if not Ravenclaw?

‘Ahem. “Clever kids in Ravenclaw, evil kids in Slytherin, wannabe heroes in Gryffindor, and everyone who does the actual work in Hufflepuff.” This indicates a certain amount of respect. You are well aware that Conscientiousness is just about as important as raw intelligence in determining life outcomes, you think you will be extremely loyal to your friends if you ever have some, you are not frightened by the expectation that your chosen scientific problems may take decades to solve – ’

I’m lazy! I hate work! Hate hard work in all its forms! Clever shortcuts, that’s all I’m about!

‘And you would find loyalty and friendship in Hufflepuff, a camaraderie that you have never had before. You would find that you could rely on others, and that would heal something inside you that is broken.’

Again it was a shock. But what would the Hufflepuffs find in me, who never belonged in their House? Acid words, cutting wit, disdain for their inability to keep up with me?

Now it was the Hat’s thoughts that were slow, hesitant. ‘I must Sort for the good of all the students in all the Houses … but I think you could learn to be a good Hufflepuff, and not too out of place there. You will be happier in Hufflepuff than in any other house; that is the truth.’

Happiness is not the most important thing in the world to me. I would not become all that I could be, in Hufflepuff. I would sacrifice my potential.

The Hat flinched; Harry could feel it somehow. It was like he had kicked the hat in the balls – in a strongly weighted component of its utility function.

Why are you trying to send me where I do not belong?

The Hat’s thought was almost a whisper. ‘I cannot speak of the others to you – but do you think that you are the first potential Dark Lord to pass under my brim? I cannot know the individual cases, but I can know this: of those who did not intend evil from the very beginning, some of them listened to my warnings, and went to Houses where they would find happiness. And some of them … some of them did not.’

That stopped Harry. But not for long. And of those who did not heed the warning – did they all become Dark Lords? Or did some of them achieve greatness for good, as well? Just what are the exact percentages here?

‘I cannot give you exact statistics. I cannot know them so I cannot count them. I just know that your chances don’t feel good. They feel very not-good.’

But I just wouldn’t do that! Ever!

‘I know that I have heard that claim before.’

I am not Dark Lord material!

‘Yes, you are. You really, really are.’

Why? Just because I once thought it would be cool to have a legion of brainwashed followers chanting Hail the Dark Lord Harry?

‘Amusing, but that was not your first fleeting thought before you substituted something safer, less damaging. No, what you remembered was how you considered lining up all the blood purists and guillotining them. And now you are telling yourself you were not serious, but you were. If you could do it this very moment and no one would ever know, you would. Or what you did this morning to Neville Longbottom, deep inside you knew that was wrong but you did it anyway because it was fun and you had a good excuse and you thought the Boy-Who-Lived could get away with it – ’

That’s unfair! Now you’re just dragging up inner fears that aren’t necessarily real! I worried that I might be thinking like that, but in the end I decided it would probably work to help Neville –

‘That was, in fact, a rationalisation. I know. I cannot know what the true outcome will be for Neville – but I know what was truly happening inside your head. The decisive pressure was that it was such a clever idea you couldn’t stand not to do it, never mind Neville’s terror.’

It was like a hard punch to Harry’s entire self. He fell back, rallied:

Then I won’t do that again! I’ll be extra careful not to turn evil!

‘Heard it.’

Frustration was building up inside Harry. He wasn’t used to being outgunned in arguments, at all, ever, let alone by a Hat that could borrow all of his own knowledge and intelligence to argue with him and could watch his thoughts as they formed. Just what kind of statistical summary do your feelings come from, anyway? Do they take into account that I come from an Enlightenment culture, or were these other potential Dark Lords the children of spoiled Dark Age nobility, who didn’t know squat about the historical lessons of how Lenin and Hitler actually turned out, or about the evolutionary psychology of self-delusion, or the value of self-awareness and rationality, or –

‘No, of course they were not in this new reference class which you have just now constructed in such a way as to contain only yourself. And of course others have pleaded their own exceptionalism, just as you are doing now. But why is it necessary? Do you think that you are the last potential wizard of Light in the world? Why must you be the one to try for greatness, when I have advised you that you are riskier than average? Let some other, safer candidate try!’

But the prophecy …

‘You don’t really know that there’s a prophecy. It was originally a wild guess on your part, or to be more precise, a wild joke, and McGonagall could have been reacting only to the part about the Dark Lord still being alive. You have essentially no idea of what the prophecy says or even if there is one. You’re just speculating, or to put it more exactly, wishing that you have some ready-made heroic role that is your personal property.’

But even if there is no prophecy, I’m the one who defeated him last time.

‘That was almost certainly a wild fluke unless you seriously believe that a one-year-old child had an inherent propensity to defeat Dark Lords which has been maintained ten years later. None of this is your real reason and you know it!’

The answer to this was something that Harry would not regularly have said out loud, in conversation he would have danced around it and found some more socially palatable arguments to the same conclusion –

‘You think that you are potentially the greatest who has yet lived, the strongest servant of the Light, that no other is likely to take up your wand if you lay it down.’

Well … yeah, frankly. I don’t usually come out and say it like that, but yeah. No point in softening it, you can read my mind anyway.

‘To the extent you really believe that … you must equally believe that you could be the most terrible Dark Lord the world has ever known.’

Destruction is always easier than creation. Easier to tear things apart, to disrupt, than to put them back together again. If I have the potential to accomplish good on a massive scale, I must also have the potential to accomplish still greater evil … But I won’t do that.

‘Already you insist on risking it! Why are you so driven? What is the real reason you must not go to Hufflepuff and be happier there? What is your true fear?’

I must achieve my full potential. If I don’t I … fail …

‘What happens if you fail?’

Something terrible …

‘What happens if you fail?’

I don’t know!

‘Then it should not be frightening. What happens if you fail?’

I don’t know! But I know that it’s bad!

There was silence for a moment in the caverns of Harry’s mind.

‘You know – you aren’t letting yourself think it, but in some quiet corner of your mind you know just exactly what you aren’t thinking – you know that by far the simplest explanation for this unverbalisable fear of yours is just the fear of losing your fantasy of greatness, of disappointing the people who believe in you, of turning out to be pretty much ordinary, of flashing and fading like so many other child prodigies …’

No, Harry thought desperately, no, it’s something more, it comes from somewhere else, I know there’s something out there to be afraid of, some disaster I have to stop …

‘How could you possibly know about something like that?’

Harry screamed it with the full power of his mind: No, and that’s final!

Then the voice of the Sorting Hat came slowly:

‘So you will risk becoming a Dark Lord, because the alternative, to you, is certain failure, and that failure means the loss of everything. You believe that in your heart of hearts. You know all the reasons for doubting this belief, and they have failed to move you.’

Yes. And even if going to Ravenclaw strengthens the coldness, that doesn’t mean the coldness will win in the end.

‘This day is a great fork in your destiny. Don’t be so sure that there will be other choices beyond this one. There is no road-sign set, to mark the place of your last chance to turn back. If you refuse one chance will you not refuse others? It may be that your fate is already sealed, even by doing this one thing.’

But that is not certain.

‘That you do not know it for a certainty may reflect only your own ignorance.’

But still it is not certain.

The Hat sighed a terrible sad sigh.

‘And so before too long you will become another memory, to be felt and never known, in the next warning that I give …’

If that’s how it seems to you, then why aren’t you just putting me where you want me to go?

The Hat’s thought was laced with sorrow. ‘I can only put you where you belong. And only your own decisions can change where you belong.’

Then this is done. Send me to Ravenclaw where I belong, with the others of my own kind.

‘I don’t suppose you would consider Gryffindor? It’s the most prestigious House – people probably expect it of you, even – they’ll be a little disappointed if you don’t go – and your new friends the Weasley twins are there –’

Harry giggled, or felt the impulse to do so; it came out as purely mental laughter, an odd sensation. Apparently there were safeguards to prevent you from saying anything out loud by accident, while you were under the Hat talking about things you would never tell another soul for the rest of your life.

After a moment, Harry heard the Hat laughing too, a strange sad clothy sound.

(And in the Hall beyond, a silence that had grown shallower at first as the background whispers increased, and then deepened as the whispers gave up and died away, falling finally into an utter silence that no one dared disturb with a single word, as Harry stayed under the Hat for long, long minutes, longer than all the previous first-years put together, longer than anyone in living memory. At the Head Table, Dumbledore went on smiling benignly; small metallic sounds occasionally came from Snape’s direction as he idly compacted the twisted remains of what had once been a heavy silver wine goblet; and Minerva McGonagall clenched the podium in a white-knuckled grip, knowing that Harry Potter’s contagious chaos had somehow infected the Sorting Hat itself and the Hat was about to, to demand that a whole new House of Doom be created just to accommodate Harry Potter or something, and Dumbledore would make her do it … )

Beneath the brim of the Hat, the silent laughter died away. Harry felt sad too for some reason. No, not Gryffindor.

Professor McGonagall said that if the one who did the Sorting tried to push me into Gryffindor, I was to remind you that she might well be Headmistress some day, at which point she would have the authority to set you on fire.

‘Tell her I called her an impudent youngster and told her to get off my lawn.’

I shall. So was this your strangest conversation ever?

‘Not even close.’ The Hat’s telepathic voice grew heavy. ‘Well, I gave you every possible chance to make another decision. Now it is time for you to go where you belong, with the others of your own kind.’

There was a pause that stretched.

What are you waiting for?

‘I was hoping for a moment of horrified realisation, actually. Self-awareness does seem to enhance my sense of humour.’

Huh? Harry cast back his thoughts, trying to figure out what the Hat could possibly be talking about – and then, suddenly, he realised. He couldn’t believe he’d managed to overlook it up until this point.

You mean my horrified realisation that you’re going to cease to be conscious once you finish Sorting me –

Somehow, in some fashion Harry entirely failed to understand, he got a non-verbal impression of a hat banging its head against the wall. ‘I give up. You’re too slow on the uptake for this to be funny. So blinded by your own assumptions that you might as well be a rock. I suppose I’ll just have to say it outright.’

Too s-s-slow –

‘Oh, and you entirely forgot to demand the secrets of the lost magic that created me. And they were such wonderful, important secrets, too.’

You sly little bastard –

‘You deserved it, and this as well.’

Harry saw it coming just as it was already too late.

The frightened silence of the hall was broken by a single word.

‘Slytherin!’

Some students screamed, the pent-up tension was so great. People startled hard enough to fall off their benches. Hagrid gasped in horror, McGonagall staggered at the podium, and Snape dropped the remains of his heavy silver goblet directly onto his groin.

Harry sat there frozen, his life in ruins, feeling the absolute fool, and wishing wretchedly that he had made any other choices for any other reasons but the ones he had. That he had done something, anything differently before it had been too late to turn back.

As the first moment of shock was wearing off and people began to react to the news, the Sorting Hat spoke again:

‘Just kidding! Ravenclaw!’

Lateral Thinking

As soon as he walked into the Defence classroom on Wednesday, Harry knew that this subject was going to be different.

It was, for a start, the largest classroom he had yet seen at Hogwarts, akin to a university lecture hall, with layered tiers of desks facing a gigantic flat stage of white marble. The classroom was high up in the castle – on the fifth floor – and Harry knew that was as much explanation as he’d get for where a room like this was supposed to fit. It was becoming clear that Hogwarts simply did not have a geometry, Euclidean or otherwise; it had connections, not directions.

Unlike a university hall, there weren’t rows of folding seats; instead there were quite ordinary Hogwarts wooden desks and wooden chairs, lined up in a curve across each level of the classroom. Except that each desk had a flat, white, rectangular, mysterious object propped up on it.

In the centre of the gigantic platform, on a small raised dais of darker marble, was a lone teacher’s desk. At which Quirrell sat slumped over in his chair, head lolled back, drooling slightly over his robes.

Now what does that remind me of … ?

Harry had arrived at the lesson so early that no other students were there yet. (The English language was defective when it came to describing time travel; in particular, English lacked any words capable of expressing how convenient it was.) Quirrell didn’t seem to be … functional … at the moment, and Harry didn’t particularly feel like approaching Quirrell anyway.

Harry selected a desk, climbed up to it, sat down, and retrieved the Defence textbook. He was around seven-eighths of the way through – he’d planned on finishing the book before this lesson, actually, but he was running behind schedule and had already used the Time-Turner twice today.

Soon there were sounds as the classroom began to fill up. Harry ignored them.

‘Potter? What are you doing here?’

That voice didn’t belong here. Harry looked up. ‘Draco? What are you doing in oh my god you have minions.’

One of the lads standing behind Draco seemed to have rather a lot of muscle for an eleven-year-old, and the other was poised in a suspiciously balanced-looking stance.

The white-blonde-haired boy smiled rather smugly and gestured behind him. ‘Potter, I introduce to you Mr Crabbe,’ his hand moved from Muscles to Balance, ‘Mr Goyle. Vincent, Gregory, this is Harry Potter.’

Mr Goyle tilted his head and gave Harry a look that was probably supposed to mean something but ended up just looking squinty. Mr Crabbe said ‘Please to meetcha’ in a tone that sounded like he was trying to lower his voice as far as it could go.

A fleeting expression of consternation crossed Draco’s face, but was quickly replaced by his superior grin.

‘You have minions!’ Harry repeated. ‘Where do I get minions?’

Draco’s smirk grew wider. ‘I’m afraid, Potter, that the first step is to be Sorted into Slytherin –’

‘What? That’s not fair!’

‘– and then for your families to have an arrangement from before you were born.’

Harry looked at Mr Crabbe and Mr Goyle. They both seemed to be trying very hard to loom. That is, they were leaning forwards, hunching over their shoulders, sticking their necks out and staring at him.

‘Um … hold on,’ said Harry. ‘This was arranged years ago?’

‘Exactly, Potter. I’m afraid you’re out of luck.’

Mr Goyle produced a toothpick and began cleaning his teeth, still looming.

‘And,’ said Harry, ‘Lucius insisted that you were not to grow up knowing your bodyguards, and that you were only to meet them on your first day of school.’

That wiped the grin from Draco’s face. ‘Yes, Potter, we all know you’re brilliant, the whole school knows by now, you can stop showing off –’

‘So they’ve been told their whole lives that they’re going to be your minions and they’ve spent years imagining what minions are supposed to be like –’

Draco winced.

‘– and what’s worse, they do know each other and they’ve been practising –’

‘The boss told ya to shut it,’ rumbled Mr Crabbe. Mr Goyle bit down on his toothpick, holding it between his teeth, and used one hand to crack the knuckles on the other.

‘I told you not to do this in front of Harry Potter!’

The two looked a bit sheepish and Mr Goyle quickly put the toothpick back in a pocket of his robes.

But the moment Draco turned away from them to face Harry again, they went back to looming.

‘I apologise,’ Draco said stiffly, ‘for the insult which these imbeciles have offered you.’

Harry gave a meaningful look to Mr Crabbe and Mr Goyle. ‘I’d say you’re being a little harsh on them, Draco. I think they’re acting exactly the way I’d want my minions to act. I mean, if I had any minions.’

Draco’s jaw dropped.

‘Hey, Gregory, you don’ think he’s tryna lure us away from the boss, do ya?’

‘I’m sure Mr Potter wouldn’t be that foolish.’

‘Oh, I wouldn’t dream of it,’ Harry said smoothly. ‘It’s just something to keep in mind if your current employer seems unappreciative. Besides, it never hurts to have other offers while you’re negotiating your working conditions, right?’

‘What’s he doin’ in Ravenclaw?’

‘I can’t imagine, Mr Crabbe.’

‘Both of you shut up,’ Draco said through gritted teeth. ‘That’s an order.’ With a visible effort, he transferred his attention to Harry again. ‘Anyway, what’re you doing in the Slytherin Defence class?’

Harry frowned. ‘Hold on.’ His hand went into his pouch. ‘Timetable.’ He looked over the parchment. ‘Defence, 2:30pm, and right now it’s …’ Harry looked at his mechanical watch, which read 11:23. ‘2:23, unless I’ve lost track of time. Did I?’ If he had, well, Harry knew how to get to whatever lesson he was supposed to be at. God he loved his Time-Turner and some day, when he was old enough, they would get married.

‘No, that sounds right,’ Draco said, looking puzzled. His gaze turned to look over the rest of the auditorium, which was filling with green-trimmed robes and …

‘Gryffindorks!’ spat Draco. ‘What’re they doing here?’

‘Hm,’ Harry said. ‘Professor Quirrell did say … I forget his exact words … that he would be ignoring some of the Hogwarts teaching conventions. Maybe he just combined all his classes.’

‘Huh,’ said Draco. ‘You’re the first Ravenclaw in here.’

‘Yup. Got here early.’

‘What’re you doing all the way in the back row, then?’

Harry blinked. ‘I dunno, seemed like a good place to sit?’

Draco made a scoffing sound. ‘You couldn’t get any further away from the teacher if you tried.’ The blonde-haired boy leaned slightly closer. ‘Anyway, is it true about what you said to Derrick and his crew?’

‘Who’s Derrick?’

‘You hit him with a pie?’

‘Two pies, actually. What am I supposed to have said to him?’

‘That he wasn’t doing anything cunning or ambitious and he was a disgrace to Salazar Slytherin.’ Draco was staring intently at Harry.

‘That … sounds about right,’ Harry said. ‘I think it was more like, “is this some kind of incredibly clever plot that will gain you a future advantage or is it really as much of a disgrace to the memory of Salazar Slytherin as it looks like” or something like that. I don’t remember the exact words.’

‘You’re confusing everyone, you know,’ said the blonde-haired boy.

‘Huh?’ Harry said in honest confusion.

‘Warrington said that spending a long time under the Sorting Hat is one of the warning signs of a major Dark Wizard. Everyone was talking about it, wondering if they should start sucking up to you just in case. Then you went and protected a bunch of Hufflepuffs, for Merlin’s sake. Then you told Derrick he’s a disgrace to Salazar Slytherin’s memory! What’s anyone supposed to think?’

‘That the Sorting Hat decided to put me in the House of “Slytherin! Just kidding! Ravenclaw!” and I’ve been acting accordingly.’

Mr Crabbe and Mr Goyle both giggled, causing Mr Goyle to quickly clap a hand to his mouth.

‘We’d better go get our seats,’ Draco said. He hesitated, straightened a bit, spoke a bit more formally. ‘But I do want to continue our last conversation and I accept your conditions.’

Harry nodded. ‘Would you mind terribly if I waited until Saturday afternoon? I’m in a bit of a contest right now.’

‘A contest?’

‘See if I can read all my textbooks as fast as Hermione Granger did.’

‘Granger,’ Draco echoed. His eyes narrowed. ‘The mudblood who thinks she’s Merlin? If you’re trying to show her up then all Slytherin wishes you the very best luck, Potter, and I won’t bother you ’til Saturday.’ Draco inclined his head respectfully, and wandered off, tailed by his minions.

Oh, this is going to be so much fun to juggle, I can already tell.

The classroom was filling up rapidly now with all four colours of trim: green, red, yellow, and blue. Draco and his two friends seemed to be in the midst of trying to acquire three contiguous front-row seats – already occupied, of course. Mr Crabbe and Mr Goyle were looming vigorously, but it didn’t seem to be having much effect.

Harry bent over his Defence textbook and continued reading.

Locating the Hypothesis

Thursday.

If you wanted to be specific, 7:24am on Thursday morning.

Harry was sitting on his bed, a textbook lying limp in his motionless hands.

Harry had just had an idea for a truly brilliant experimental test.

It would mean waiting an extra hour for breakfast, but that was why he had cereal bars. No, this idea absolutely positively had to be tested right away, immediately, now.

Harry set the textbook aside, leapt out of bed, raced around his bed, yanked out the cavern level of his trunk, ran down the stairs, and started moving boxes of books around. (He really needed to unpack and get bookcases at some point but he was in the middle of his textbook reading contest with Hermione and falling behind so he hadn’t had time.)

Harry found the book he wanted and raced back upstairs.

The other boys were getting ready to go down to breakfast in the Great Hall and start the day.

‘Excuse me can you do something for me?’ said Harry. He was flipping through the book’s index as he spoke, found the page with the first ten thousand primes, flipped to that page, and thrust the book at Anthony Goldstein. ‘Pick two three-digit numbers from this list. Don’t tell me what they are. Just multiply them together and tell me the product. Oh, and can you do the calculation twice to double-check? Please make really sure you’ve got the right answer, I’m not sure what’s going to happen to me or the universe if you make a multiplication error.’

It said a lot about what life in that dorm had been like over the past few days that Anthony didn’t even bother saying anything like ‘Why’d you suddenly flip out?’ or ‘That seems really weird, what are your reasons for asking?’ or ‘What do you mean, you’re not sure what’s going to happen to the universe?’

Anthony wordlessly accepted the book and took out a parchment and quill. Harry spun around and shut his eyes, making sure not to see anything, dancing back and forth and bouncing up and down with impatience. He got a pad of paper and a mechanical pencil and got ready to write.

‘Okay,’ Anthony said, ‘One hundred and eighty-one thousand, four hundred and twenty-nine.’

Harry wrote down 181,429. He repeated what he’d just written down, and Anthony confirmed it.

Then Harry raced back down into the cavern level of his trunk, glanced at his watch (the watch said 4:28 which meant 7:28) and then shut his eyes.

Around thirty seconds later, Harry heard the sound of steps, followed by the sound of the cavern level of the trunk sliding shut. (Harry wasn’t worried about suffocating. An automatic Air-Freshening Charm was part of what you got if you were willing to buy a really good trunk. Wasn’t magic wonderful, it didn’t have to worry about electric bills.)

And when Harry opened his eyes, he saw just what he’d been hoping to see, a folded piece of paper left on the floor, the gift of his future self.

Call that piece of paper ‘Paper-2’.

Harry tore a piece of paper off his pad.

Call that ‘Paper-1’. It was, of course, the same piece of paper. You could even see, if you looked closely, that the ragged edges matched.

Harry reviewed in his mind the algorithm that he would follow.

If Harry opened up Paper-2 and it was blank, then he would write 101 × 101 down on Paper-1, fold it up, study for an hour, go back in time, drop off Paper-1 (which would thereby become Paper-2), and head on up out of the cavern level to join his dorm mates for breakfast.

If Harry opened up Paper-2 and it had two numbers written on it, Harry would multiply those numbers together.

If their product equalled 181,429, Harry would write down those two numbers on Paper-1 and send Paper-1 back in time.

Otherwise Harry would add 2 to the number on the right and write down the new pair of numbers on Paper-1. Unless that made the number on the right greater than 997, in which case Harry would add 2 to the number on the left and write down 101 on the right.

And if Paper-2 said 997 × 997, Harry would leave Paper-1 blank.

Which meant that the only possible stable time loop was the one in which Paper-2 contained the two prime factors of 181,429.

If this worked, Harry could use it to recover any sort of answer that was easy to check but hard to find. He wouldn’t have just shown that P = NP once you had a Time-Turner, this trick was more general than that. Harry could use it to find the combinations on combination locks, or passwords of every sort. Maybe even find the entrance to Slytherin’s Chamber of Secrets, if Harry could figure out some systematic way of describing all the locations in Hogwarts. It would be an awesome cheat even by Harry’s standards of cheating.

Harry took Paper-2 in his trembling hand, and unfolded it.

Paper-2 said in slightly shaky handwriting:

Do not mess with time

Harry wrote down ‘Do not mess with time’ on Paper-1 in slightly shaky handwriting, folded it neatly, and resolved not to do any more truly brilliant experiments on Time until he was at least fifteen years old.

To the best of Harry’s knowledge, that had been the scariest experimental result in the entire history of science.

It had been somewhat difficult for Harry to focus on reading his textbook for the next hour.

That was how Harry’s Thursday started.

Delayed Gratification

Draco had a stern expression on his face, and his green-trimmed robes somehow looked far more formal, serious, and well-turned-out than the same exact robes as worn by the two boys behind him.

‘Talk,’ said Draco.

‘Yeah! Talk!’

‘You heard da boss! Talk!’

‘You two, on the other hand, shut up.’

The last session of classes on Friday was about to start, in that vast auditorium where all four Houses learned Defence, er, Battle Magic.

The last session of classes on Friday.

Harry was hoping that this class would be non-stressful, and that the brilliant Professor Quirrell would realize this was perhaps not the best time to single out Harry for anything. Harry had recovered a little, but …

… but just in case, it was probably best to get in a bit of stress relief first.

Harry leaned back in his chair and bestowed a look of great solemnity upon Draco and his minions.

‘You ask, what is our aim?’ Harry declaimed. ‘I can answer in one word. It is victory. Victory at all costs – Victory in spite of all terrors – Victory, however long and hard the road may be, for without victory there is no –’

‘Talk about Snape,’ Draco hissed. ‘What did you do?’

Harry wiped away the fake solemnity and gave Draco a more serious look.

‘You saw it,’ Harry said. ‘Everyone saw it. I snapped my fingers.’

‘Harry! Stop teasing me!’

So he’d been promoted to Harry now. Interesting. And in fact Harry was fairly sure that he was meant to notice that, and feel bad if he didn’t respond somehow …

Harry tapped his ears and gave a significant glance at the minions.

‘They won’t talk,’ said Draco.

‘Draco,’ Harry said, ‘I’m going to be one hundred percent honest here and say that yesterday I was not particularly impressed with Mr Goyle’s cunning.’

Mr Goyle winced.

‘Me neither,’ said Draco. ‘I explained to him that I ended up owing you a favour because of it.’ (Mr Goyle winced again.) ‘But there is a big difference between that sort of mistake and being indiscreet. That really is something they’ve been trained from childhood to understand.’

‘All right then,’ Harry said. He lowered his voice, even though the background noises had gone to blurs in Draco’s presence. ‘I deduced one of Severus’s secrets and did a bit of blackmail.’

Draco’s expression hardened. ‘Good, now tell me something you didn’t tell in strict confidence to the idiots in Gryffindor, meaning that was the story you wanted to get all over the school.’

Harry grinned involuntarily and he knew that Draco had caught it.

‘What is Severus saying?’ Harry said.

‘That he hadn’t realized how sensitive the feelings of young children were,’ Draco said. ‘Even in Slytherin! Even to me!’

‘Are you sure,’ Harry said, ‘that you want to know something your Head of House would rather you not know?’

‘Yes,’ Draco said without hesitation.

Interesting. ‘Then you really are going to send your minions away first, because I’m not sure I can believe everything you believe about them.’

Draco nodded. ‘Okay.’

Mr Crabbe and Mr Goyle looked very unhappy. ‘Boss …’ said Mr Crabbe.

‘You’ve given Mr Potter no reason to trust you,’ Draco said. ‘Go!’

They left.

‘In particular,’ Harry said, lowering his voice even further, ‘I’m not entirely sure that they wouldn’t just report what I said to Lucius.’

‘Father wouldn’t do that!’ Draco said, looking genuinely aghast. ‘They’re mine!’

‘I’m sorry, Draco,’ Harry said. ‘I’m just not sure I can believe everything you believe about your father. Imagine it was your secret and me telling you my father wouldn’t do that.’

Draco nodded slowly. ‘You’re right. I’m sorry, Harry. It was wrong of me to ask it of you.’

How did I get this promoted? Shouldn’t he hate me now? Harry had the feeling he was looking at something exploitable … he just wished his brain wasn’t so exhausted. Ordinarily he would have loved to try his hand at some complicated plotting.

‘Anyway,’ Harry said. ‘Trade. I tell you a fact that isn’t on the grapevine, and does not go on the grapevine, and in particular does not go to your father, and in return you tell me what you and Slytherin think about the whole business.’

‘Deal!’

Now to make this as vague as possible … something that wouldn’t hurt much even if it did get out … ‘What I said was true. I did discover one of Severus’s secrets, and I did do some blackmail. But Severus wasn’t the only person involved.’

‘I knew it!’ Draco said exultantly.

Harry’s stomach sank. He had apparently said something very significant and he did not know why. This was not a good sign.

‘All right,’ Draco said. He was grinning widely now. ‘So here’s what the reaction was like in Slytherin. First, all the idiots were like, “We hate Harry Potter! Let’s go beat him up!”’

Harry choked. ‘What is wrong with the Sorting Hat? That’s not Slytherin, it’s Gryffindor –’

‘Not all children are prodigies,’ Draco said, though he was smiling in a sort of nasty-conspiratorial way, as though to suggest that he privately agreed with Harry’s opinion. ‘And it took around fifteen seconds for someone to explain to them why this might not be such a favour to Snape, so you’re fine. Anyway, after that was the second wave of idiots, the ones who were saying, “Looks like Harry Potter was just another do-gooder after all.”’

‘And then?’ Harry said, smiling even though he had no idea why that was stupid.

‘And then the actual smart people started talking. It’s obvious that you found a way to put a lot of pressure on Snape. And while that could be more than one thing … the obvious next thought is that it has something to do with Snape’s unknown hold over Dumbledore. Am I right?’

‘No comment,’ Harry said. At least his brain was processing this part correctly. House Slytherin had wondered why Severus wasn’t getting fired. And they’d concluded that Severus was blackmailing Dumbledore. Could that actually be true … ? But Dumbledore hadn’t seemed to act like it …

Draco went on talking. ‘And the next thing the smart people pointed out was that if you could put enough pressure on Snape to make him leave half of Hogwarts alone, that meant you probably had enough power to get rid of him entirely, if you wanted. What you did to him was a humiliation, just the same way he tried to humiliate you – but you left us our Head of House.’

Harry made his smile wider.

‘And then the really smart people,’ Draco said, his face now serious, ‘went off and had a little discussion by themselves, and someone pointed out that it would be a very stupid thing to leave an enemy around like that. If you could break his hold over Dumbledore, the obvious thing would be to just do it. Dumbledore would kick Snape out of Hogwarts and maybe even have him killed, he’d be very grateful to you, and you wouldn’t have to worry about Snape sneaking into your dorm at night with interesting potions.’

Harry’s face was now neutral. He had not thought of that and he really, really should have. ‘And from this you concluded … ?’

‘Snape’s hold was some secret of Dumbledore’s and you’ve got the secret!’ Draco was looking exultant. ‘It can’t be powerful enough to destroy Dumbledore entirely, or Snape would have used it by now. Snape refuses to use his hold for anything except staying king of Slytherin House in Hogwarts, and he doesn’t always get what he wants even then, so it must have limits. But it’s got to be really good! Father’s been trying to get Snape to tell him for years!’

‘And,’ Harry said, ‘now Lucius thinks maybe I can tell him. Did you already get an owl –’

‘I will tonight,’ Draco said, and laughed. ‘It will say,’ his voice took on a different, more formal cadence, ‘My beloved son: I’ve already told you of Harry Potter’s potential importance. As you have already realized, his importance has now become greater and more urgent. If you see any possible avenue of friendship or point of pressure with him, you must pursue it, and the full resources of Malfoy are at your disposal if needed.’

Gosh. ‘Well,’ Harry said, ‘not commenting on whether or not your whole complicated edifice of theory is true, let me just say that we are not quite such good friends as yet.’

‘I know,’ Draco said. Then his face turned very serious, and his voice grew quiet even within the blur. ‘Harry, has it occurred to you that if you know something Dumbledore doesn’t want known, Dumbledore might simply have you killed? And it would turn the Boy-Who-Lived from a potential competing leader into a valuable martyr, too.’

‘No comment,’ Harry said yet again. He hadn’t thought of that last part, either. Didn’t seem to be Dumbledore’s style … but …

‘Harry,’ Draco said, ‘you’ve obviously got incredible talent, but you’ve got no training and no mentors and you do stupid things sometimes and you really need an advisor who knows how to do this or you’re going to get hurt!’ Draco’s face was fierce.

‘Ah,’ Harry said. ‘An advisor like Lucius?’

‘Like me!’ said Draco. ‘I’ll promise to keep your secrets from Father, from everyone, I’ll just help you figure out whatever you want to do!’

Wow.

Harry saw that zombie-Quirrell was staggering in through the doors.

‘Class is about to start,’ said Harry. ‘I’ll think about what you said, there’s lots of times I do wish I had all your training, it’s just I don’t know how I can trust you so quickly –’

‘You shouldn’t,’ Draco said, ‘it’s too soon. See? I’ll give you good advice even if it hurts me. But we should maybe hurry up and become closer friends.’

‘I’m open to that,’ said Harry, who was already trying to figure out how to exploit it.

‘Another bit of advice,’ Draco said hurriedly as Quirrell slouched toward his desk, ‘right now everyone in Slytherin’s wondering about you, so if you’re courting us, which I think you are, you should do something that signals friendship to Slytherin. Soon, like today or tomorrow.’

‘Letting Severus go on awarding extra House points to Slytherin wasn’t enough?’ No reason Harry couldn’t take credit for it.

Draco’s eyes flickered with realization, then he said rapidly, ‘It’s not the same, trust me, it’s got to be something obvious. Push your mudblood rival Granger into a wall or something, everyone in Slytherin will know what that means –’

‘That is not how it works in Ravenclaw, Draco! If you have to push someone into a wall it means your brain is too weak to beat them the right way and everyone in Ravenclaw knows that –’

The screen on Harry’s desk flickered on, provoking a sudden wash of nostalgia for television and computers.

‘Ahem,’ said Professor Quirrell’s voice, seeming to speak personally to Harry out of the screen. ‘Please take your seats.’

And the children were all seated and staring at the repeater screens on their desks, or looking down directly at the great white marble stage where Professor Quirrell stood, leaning on his desk atop the small dais of darker marble.

‘Today,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘I had planned to teach you your first defensive spell, a small shield that was the ancestor of today’s Protego. But on second thought I have changed today’s lesson plan in the light of recent events.’

Professor Quirrell’s gaze searched the rows of seats. Harry winced from where he was sitting, in the back row. He had a feeling he knew who was about to be called on.

‘Draco, of the Noble and Most Ancient House of Malfoy,’ said Professor Quirrell.

Whew.

‘Yes, Professor?’ said Draco. His voice was amplified, seeming to come from the repeater screen on Harry’s desk, which showed Draco’s face as he spoke. Then the screen shifted back to Professor Quirrell, who said:

‘Is it your ambition to become the next Dark Lord?’

‘That’s an odd question, Professor,’ said Draco. ‘I mean, who’d be dumb enough to admit it?’

A few students laughed, but not many.

‘Indeed,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘So while there’s no point in asking any of you, it would not surprise me in the slightest if there were a student or two in my classes who harboured ambitions of being the next Dark Lord. After all, I wanted to be the next Dark Lord when I was a young Slytherin.’

This time the laughter was much more widespread.

‘Well, it is the House of the ambitious, after all,’ Professor Quirrell said, smiling. ‘I didn’t realize until later that what I really enjoyed was Battle Magic, and that my true ambition was to become a great fighting wizard and some day teach at Hogwarts. In any case, when I was thirteen years old, I read through the historical sections of the Hogwarts library, scrutinizing the lives and fates of past Dark Lords, and I made a list of all the mistakes that I would never make when I was a Dark Lord –’

Harry giggled before he could stop himself.

‘Yes, Mr Potter, very amusing. So, Mr Potter, can you guess what was the very first item on that list?’

Great. ‘Um … never use a complicated way of dealing with an enemy when you can just Abracadabra them?’

‘The term, Mr Potter, is Avada Kedavra,’ Professor Quirrell’s voice sounded a bit sharp for some reason, ‘and no, that was not on the list I made at age thirteen. Would you care to guess again?’

‘Ah … never brag to anyone about your evil master plan?’

Professor Quirrell laughed. ‘Ah, now that was number two. My, Mr Potter, have we been reading the same books?’

There was more laughter, with an undertone of nervousness. Harry clenched his jaw tightly shut and said nothing. A denial would accomplish nothing.

‘But no. The first item was, “I will not go around provoking strong, vicious enemies.” The history of the world would be very different if Mornelithe Falconsbane or Adolf Hitler had grasped that elementary point. Now if, Mr Potter – just if by some chance you harbour an ambition similar to the one I held as a young Slytherin – even so, I hope it is not your ambition to become a stupid Dark Lord.’

‘Professor Quirrell,’ Harry said, gritting his teeth, ‘I am a Ravenclaw and it is not my ambition to be stupid, period. I know that what I did today was dumb. But it wasn’t Dark! I was not the one who threw the first punch in that fight!’

‘You, Mr Potter, are an idiot. But then so was I at your age. Thus I anticipated your answer and altered today’s lesson plan accordingly. Mr Gregory Goyle, if you would come forward, please?’

There was a surprised pause in the classroom. Harry hadn’t been expecting that.

Neither, from the looks of it, had Mr Goyle, who looked rather uncertain and worried as he mounted the marble stage and approached the dais.

Professor Quirrell straightened from where he was leaning on the desk. He looked suddenly stronger, and his hands formed fists and he drew himself up into a clearly recognizable martial arts stance.

Harry’s eyes widened at the sight, and he realized why Mr Goyle had been called up.

‘Most wizards,’ Professor Quirrell said, ‘do not bother much with what a Muggle would term martial arts. Is not a wand stronger than a fist? This attitude is stupid. Wands are held in fists. If you want to be a great fighting wizard you must learn martial arts to a level which would impress even a Muggle. I will now demonstrate a certain vitally important technique, which I learned in a dojo, a Muggle school of martial arts, of which I shall speak more shortly. For now …’ Professor Quirrell took several steps forward, still in stance, advancing on where Mr Goyle stood. ‘Mr Goyle, I will ask you to attack me.’

‘Professor Quirrell,’ said Mr Goyle, his voice now amplified as the professor’s was, ‘can I ask what level –’

‘Sixth dan. You will not be hurt and neither will I. And if you see an opening, please take it.’

Mr Goyle nodded, looking much relieved.

‘Note,’ Professor Quirrell said, ‘that Mr Goyle was afraid to attack someone who did not know martial arts to an acceptable level, for fear that I, or he, would be hurt. Mr Goyle’s attitude is exactly correct and he has earned three Quirrell points for it. Now, fight!’

The young boy blurred forward, fists flying, and the Professor blocked every blow, dancing backward, Quirrell kicked and Goyle blocked and spun and tried to trip Quirrell with a sweeping leg and Quirrell hopped over it and it was all happening too fast for Harry to make sense of what was going on and then Goyle was on his back with his legs pushing and Quirrell was actually flying through the air and then he hit the ground shoulder first and rolled.

‘Stop!’ cried Professor Quirrell from the ground, sounding a little panicked. ‘You win!’

Mr Goyle pulled up so sharply he staggered, almost tripping and falling from the aborted momentum of his headlong charge toward Professor Quirrell. His face showed utter shock.

Professor Quirrell arched his back and bounced to his feet using a peculiar springing motion that made no use of his hands.

There was a silence in the classroom, a silence born of total confusion.

‘Mr Goyle,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘what vitally important technique did I demonstrate?’

‘How to fall correctly when someone throws you,’ said Mr Goyle. ‘It’s one of the very first lessons you learn –’

‘That too,’ said Professor Quirrell.

There was a pause.

‘The vitally important technique which I demonstrated,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘was how to lose. You may go, Mr Goyle, thank you.’

Mr Goyle walked off the platform, looking rather bewildered. Harry felt the same way.

Professor Quirrell walked back to his desk and resumed leaning on it. ‘Sometimes we forget the most basic things, since it has been too long since we learned them. I realized I had done the same with my own lesson plan. You do not teach students to throw until you have taught them to fall. And I must not teach you to fight if you do not understand how to lose.’

Professor Quirrell’s face hardened, and Harry thought he saw a hint of pain, a touch of sorrow, in those eyes. ‘I learned how to lose in a dojo in Asia, which, as any Muggle knows, is where all the good martial artists live. This dojo taught a style which had a reputation among fighting wizards as adapting well to magical duelling. The Master of that dojo – an old man by Muggle standards – was that style’s greatest living teacher. He had no idea that magic existed, of course. I applied to study there, and was one of the few students accepted that year, from among many contenders. There might have been a tiny bit of special influence involved.’

There was some laughter in the classroom. Harry didn’t share it. That hadn’t been right at all.

‘In any case. During one of my first fights, after I had been beaten in a particularly humiliating fashion, I lost control and attacked my sparring partner –’

Yikes.

‘– thankfully with my fists, rather than my magic. The Master, surprisingly, did not expel me on the spot. But he told me that there was a flaw in my temperament. He explained it to me, and I knew that he was right. And then he said that I would learn how to lose.’

Professor Quirrell’s face was expressionless.

‘Upon his strict orders, all of the students of the dojo lined up. One by one, they approached me. I was not to defend myself. I was only to beg for mercy. One by one, they slapped me, or punched me, and pushed me to the ground. Some of them spat on me. They called me awful names in their language. And to each one, I had to say, “I lose!” and similar such things, such as “I beg you to stop!” and “I admit you’re better than me!”’

Harry was trying to imagine this and simply failing. There was no way something like that could have happened to the dignified Professor Quirrell.

‘I was a prodigy of Battle Magic even then. With wandless magic alone I could have killed everyone in that dojo. I did not do so. I learned to lose. To this day I remember it as one of the most unpleasant hours of my life. And when I left that dojo eight months later – which was not nearly enough time, but was all I could afford to spend – the Master told me that he hoped I understood why that had been necessary. And I told him that it was one of the most valuable lessons I had ever learned. Which was, and is, true.’

Professor Quirrell’s face turned bitter. ‘You are wondering where this marvellous dojo is, and whether you can study there. You cannot. For not long afterwards, another would-be student came to that hidden place, to that remote mountain. He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named.’

There was the sound of many breaths being drawn in simultaneously. Harry felt sick to his stomach. He knew what was coming.

‘The Dark Lord came to that school openly, without disguise, glowing red eyes and all. The students tried to bar his way and he simply Apparated through. There was terror there, but discipline, and the Master came forth. And the Dark Lord demanded – not asked, but demanded – to be taught.’

Professor Quirrell’s face was very hard. ‘Perhaps the Master had read too many books telling the lie that a true martial artist could defeat even demons. For whatever reason, the Master refused. The Dark Lord asked why he could not be a student. The Master told him he had no patience, and that was when the Dark Lord ripped his tongue out.’

There was a collective gasp.

‘You can guess what happened next. The students tried to rush the Dark Lord and fell over, stunned where they stood. And then …’

Professor Quirrell’s voice faltered for a moment, then resumed.

‘There is an Unforgiveable Curse, the Cruciatus Curse, which produces unbearable pain. If the Cruciatus is extended for longer than a few minutes it produces permanent insanity. One by one, the Dark Lord Crucioed the Master’s students into insanity, and then finished them off with the Killing Curse, while the Master was forced to watch. When all his students had died in this way, the Master followed. I learned this from the single surviving student, whom the Dark Lord had left alive to tell the tale, and who had been a friend of mine …’

Professor Quirrell turned away, and when he turned back a moment later, he once again seemed calm and composed.

‘Dark Wizards cannot keep their tempers,’ Professor Quirrell said quietly. ‘It is a nearly universal flaw of the species, and anyone who makes a habit of fighting them soon learns to rely on it. Understand that the Dark Lord did not win that day. His goal was to learn martial arts, and yet he left without a single lesson. The Dark Lord was foolish to wish that story retold. It did not show his strength, but rather an exploitable weakness.’

Professor Quirrell’s gaze focused on a single child in the classroom.

‘Harry Potter,’ Professor Quirrell said.

‘Yes,’ Harry said, his voice hoarse.

‘What precisely did you do wrong today, Mr Potter?’

Harry felt like he was going to throw up. ‘I lost my temper.’

‘That is not precise,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I will describe it more exactly. There are many animals which have what are called dominance contests. They rush at each other with horns – trying to knock each other down, not gore each other. They fight with their paws – with claws sheathed. But why with their claws sheathed? Surely, if they used their claws, they would stand a better chance of winning? But then their enemy might unsheathe their claws as well, and instead of resolving the dominance contest with a winner and a loser, both of them might be severely hurt.’

Professor Quirrell gaze seemed to come straight out at Harry from the repeater screen. ‘What you demonstrated today, Mr Potter, is that – unlike those animals who keep their claws sheathed and accept the results – you do not know how to lose a dominance contest. When a Hogwarts professor challenged you, you did not back down. When it looked like you might lose, you unsheathed your claws, heedless of the danger. You escalated, and then you escalated again. It started with a slap at you from Professor Snape, who was obviously dominant over you. Instead of losing, you slapped back and lost ten points from Ravenclaw. Soon you were talking about leaving Hogwarts. The fact that you escalated even further in some unknown direction, and somehow won at the end, does not change the fact that you are an idiot.’

‘I understand,’ Harry said. His throat was dry. That had been precise. Frighteningly precise. Now that Professor Quirrell had said it, Harry could see in hindsight that it was an exactly accurate description of what had happened. When someone’s model of you was that good, you had to wonder whether they were right about other things too, like your intent to kill.

‘The next time, Mr Potter, that you choose to escalate a contest rather than lose, you may lose all the stakes you place on the table. I cannot guess what they were today. I can guess that they were far, far too high for the loss of ten House points.’

Like the fate of magical Britain. That was what he’d done.

‘You will protest that you were trying to help all of Hogwarts, a much more important goal worthy of great risks. That is a lie. If you had been –’

‘I would have taken the slap, waited, and picked the best possible time to make my move,’ Harry said, his voice hoarse. ‘But that would have meant losing. Letting him be dominant over me. It was what the Dark Lord couldn’t do with the Master he wanted to learn from.’

Professor Quirrell nodded. ‘I see that you have understood perfectly. And so, Mr Potter, today you are going to learn how to lose.’

‘I –’

‘I will not hear any objections, Mr Potter. It is evident both that you need this and that you are strong enough to take it. I assure you that your experience will not be so harsh as what I went through, though you may well remember it as the worst fifteen minutes of your young life.’

Harry swallowed. ‘Professor Quirrell,’ he said in a small voice, ‘can we do this some other time?’

‘No,’ Professor Quirrell said simply. ‘You are five days into your Hogwarts education and already this has happened. Today is Friday. Our next defence class is on Wednesday. Saturday, Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday … No, we do not have time to wait.’

There were a few laughs at this, but very few.

‘Please consider it an order from your professor, Mr Potter. What I would like to say is that otherwise I will not teach you any offensive spells, because I would then hear that you had severely hurt or even killed someone. Unfortunately I am told that your fingers are already powerful weapons. Do not snap them at any time during this lesson.’

More scattered laughter, sounding rather nervous.

Harry felt like he might cry. ‘Professor Quirrell, if you do anything like what you talked about, it’s going to make me angry, and I really would rather not get angry again today –’

‘The point is not to avoid getting angry,’ Professor Quirrell said, his face looking grave. ‘Anger is natural. You need to learn how to lose even when you are angry. Or at least pretend to lose so that you can plan your vengeance. As I did with Mr Goyle today, unless of course any of you think he really is better –’

‘I’m not!’ shouted Mr Goyle from his desk, sounding a little frantic. ‘I know you didn’t really lose! Please don’t plan any vengeances!’

Harry felt sick to his stomach. Professor Quirrell didn’t know about his mysterious dark side. ‘Professor, we really need to talk about this after class –’

‘We will,’ Professor Quirrell said in the tones of a promise. ‘After you learn how to lose.’ His face was serious. ‘It should go without saying that I will exclude anything which could injure you or even cause you significant pain. The pain will come from the difficulty of losing, instead of fighting back and escalating the battle until you win.’

Harry’s breath was coming in short, panicky pants. He was more frightened than he’d been after leaving the Potions classroom. ‘Professor Quirrell,’ he managed to say, ‘I don’t want you to get fired over this –’

‘I will not be,’ Professor Quirrell said, ‘if you tell them afterwards that it was necessary. And this I trust you to do.’ For a moment Professor Quirrell’s voice turned very dry. ‘Believe me, they have tolerated worse in their hallways. This case will be exceptional only in that it happens within a classroom.’

‘Professor Quirrell,’ Harry whispered, but he thought his voice was still being repeated everywhere, ‘do you really believe that if I don’t do this, I might hurt someone?’

‘Yes,’ Professor Quirrell said simply.

‘Then,’ Harry felt nauseous, ‘I’ll do it.’

Professor Quirrell turned to regard the Slytherins. ‘So … with the full approval of your teacher, and in such a fashion that Snape cannot be blamed for your actions … do any of you wish to show your dominance over the Boy-Who-Lived? Shove him around, push him to the ground, hear him beg for your mercy?’

Five hands went up.

‘Everyone with your hand raised, you are an absolute idiot. What part of pretending to lose did you not understand? If Harry Potter does become the next Dark Lord he will hunt you down and kill you after he graduates.’

The five hands dropped abruptly back to their desks.

‘I won’t,’ Harry said, his voice coming out rather weakly. ‘I swear never to take vengeance upon those who help me learn to lose. Professor Quirrell … would you please … stop that?’

Professor Quirrell sighed. ‘I am sorry, Mr Potter. I realize that you must find this equally annoying whether you intend to become a Dark Lord or not. But those children also had an important life lesson to learn. Would it be acceptable if I awarded you a Quirrell point in apology?’

‘Make it two,’ Harry said.

There was a current of surprised laughter, defusing some of the tension.

‘Done,’ Professor Quirrell said.

‘And after I graduate I’m going to hunt you down and tickle you.’

There was more laughter, although Professor Quirrell didn’t smile.

Harry felt like he was wrestling an anaconda, trying to force the conversation through the narrow course that would make people realize he wasn’t a Dark Lord after all … why was Professor Quirrell so suspicious of him?

‘Professor,’ said Draco’s unamplified voice. ‘It is also not my own ambition to become a stupid Dark Lord.’

There was a shocked silence in the classroom.

You don’t have to do this! Harry almost blurted out loud, but checked himself in time; Draco might not wish it known that he was doing this out of friendship for Harry … or out of the desire to appear friendly …

Calling that a desire to appear friendly made Harry feel small, and mean. If Draco had intended to impress him, it was working perfectly.

Professor Quirrell was regarding Draco gravely. ‘You worry that you cannot pretend to lose, Mr Malfoy? That this flaw which describes Mr Potter also describes you? Surely your father taught you better.’

‘When it comes to talking, maybe,’ said Draco, now on the repeater screen. ‘Not when it comes to being shoved around and pushed to the ground. I want to be fully as strong as you, Professor Quirrell.’

Professor Quirrell’s eyebrows went up and stayed up. ‘I am afraid, Mr Malfoy,’ he said after a time, ‘that the arrangements I made for Mr Potter, involving some older Slytherins who will be told afterwards how stupid they were, would not carry over onto you. But it is my professional opinion that you are already very strong. Should I hear that you have failed, as Mr Potter failed today, I will make the appropriate arrangements and apologize to you and whomever you have hurt. I do not think this will be necessary, however.’

‘I understand, professor,’ said Draco.

Professor Quirrell looked over the class. ‘Does anyone else wish to become strong?’

Some students glanced around nervously. Some, Harry thought from his back row, looked like they were opening their mouths but not saying anything. In the end, no one spoke.

‘Draco Malfoy will be one of the generals of your year’s armies,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘should he deign to engage in that after-school activity. And now, Mr Potter, please come forward.’

The Scientific Method

A small study room, near but not in the Ravenclaw dorm, one of the many many unused rooms of Hogwarts. Grey stone the floors, red brick the walls, dark stained wood the ceiling, four glowing glass globes set into the four walls of the room. A circular table that looked like a wide slab of black marble set on thick black marble legs for columns, but which had proved to be very light (weight and mass both) and wasn’t difficult to pick up and move around if necessary. Two comfortably cushioned chairs which had seemed at first to be locked to the floor in inconvenient places, but which would, the two of them had finally discovered, scoot around to where you stood as soon as you leaned over in a posture that looked like you were about to sit down.

There also seemed to be a number of bats flying around the room.

That was where, future historians would one day record – if the whole project ever actually amounted to anything – the scientific study of magic had begun, with two young first-year Hogwarts students.

Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres, theorist.

And Hermione Jean Granger, experimenter and test subject.

Harry was doing better in classes now, at least the classes he considered interesting. He’d read more books, and not books for eleven-year-olds either. He’d practised Transfiguration over and over during one of his extra hours every day, taking the other hour for beginning Occlumency. He was taking the worthwhile classes seriously, not just turning in his homework every day, but using his free time to learn more than was required, to read other books beyond the given textbooks, looking to master the subject and not just memorize a few test answers, to excel. You didn’t see that much outside Ravenclaw. And now even within Ravenclaw, his only remaining competitors were Padma Patil (whose parents came from a non-English-speaking culture and thus had raised her with an actual work ethic), Anthony Goldstein (out of a certain tiny ethnic group that won 25% of the Nobel Prizes), and of course, striding far above everyone like a Titan strolling through a pack of puppies, Hermione Granger.

To run this particular experiment you needed the test subject to learn sixteen new spells, on their own, without help or correction. That meant the test subject was Hermione. Period.

It should be mentioned at this point that the bats flying around the room were not glowing.

Harry was having trouble accepting the implications of this.

‘Oogely boogely!’ Hermione said again.

Again, at the tip of Hermione’s wand, a bat abruptly appeared. One moment, empty air. The next moment, bat. Its wings seemed to be already moving in the instant when it appeared.

And it still wasn’t glowing.

‘Can I stop now?’ said Hermione.

‘Are you sure,’ Harry said through what seemed to be a block in his throat, ‘that maybe with a bit more practise you couldn’t get it to glow?’ He was violating the experimental procedure he’d written down beforehand, which was a sin, and he was violating it because he didn’t like the results he was getting, which was a mortal sin, you could go to Science Hell for that, but it didn’t seem to be mattering anyway.

‘What did you change this time?’ Hermione said, sounding a little weary.

‘The durations of the oo, eh, and ee sounds. It’s supposed to be 3 to 2 to 2, not 3 to 1 to 1.’

‘Oogely boogely!’ said Hermione.

The bat materialized with only one wing and spun pathetically to the floor, flopping around in a circle on the grey stone.

‘Now what is it really?’ said Hermione.

‘3 to 2 to 1.’

‘Oogely boogely!’

This time the bat didn’t have any wings at all and fell with a plop like a dead mouse.

‘3 to 1 to 2.’

And lo the bat did materialize and it did fly up at once toward the ceiling, healthy and glowing a bright green.

Hermione nodded in satisfaction. ‘Okay, what next?’

There was a long pause.

‘Seriously? You seriously have to say Oogely boogely with the duration of the oo, eh, and ee sounds having a ratio of 3 to 1 to 2, or the bat won’t glow? Why? Why? For the love of all that is sacred, why?’

‘Why not?’

‘Aaaaaaaaarrrrrrghhhh!’

Thud. Thud. Thud.

Harry had thought about the nature of magic for a while, and then designed a series of experiments based on the premise that virtually everything wizards believed about magic was wrong.

You couldn’t really need to say “Wingardium Leviosa” in exactly the right way in order to levitate something, because, come on, “Wingardium Leviosa”? The universe was going to check that you said Wingardium Leviosa in exactly the right way and otherwise it wouldn’t make the quill float?

No. Obviously no, once you thought about it seriously. Someone, quite possibly an actual preschool child, but at any rate some English-speaking magic user, who thought that Wingardium Leviosa sounded all flappy and floaty, had originally spoken those words while casting the spell for the first time. And then told everyone else it was necessary.

But (Harry had reasoned) it didn’t have to be that way, it wasn’t built into the universe, it was built into you.

There was an old story passed down among scientists, a cautionary tale, the story of Blondlot and the N-Rays.

Shortly after the discovery of X-Rays, an eminent French physicist named Prosper-René Blondlot – who had been first to measure the speed of radio waves and show that they propagated at the speed of light – had announced the discovery of an amazing new phenomenon, N-Rays, which would induce a faint brightening of a screen. You had to look hard to see it, but it was there. N-Rays had all sorts of interesting properties. They were bent by aluminium and could be focused by an aluminium prism into striking a treated thread of cadmium sulphide, which would then glow faintly in the dark …

Soon dozens of other scientists had confirmed Blondlot’s results, especially in France.

But there were still other scientists, in England and Germany, who said they weren’t quite sure they could see that faint glow.

Blondlot had said they were probably setting up the machinery wrong.

One day Blondlot had given a demonstration of N-Rays. The lights had turned out, and his assistant had called off the brightening and darkening as Blondlot performed his manipulations.

It had been a normal demonstration, all the results going as expected.

Even though an American scientist named Robert Wood had quietly stolen the aluminium prism from the centre of Blondlot’s mechanism.

And that had been the end of N-Rays.

Reality, Philip K. Dick had once said, is that which, when you stop believing in it, doesn’t go away.

Blondlot’s sin had been obvious in retrospect. He shouldn’t have told his assistant what he was doing. Blondlot should have made sure the assistant didn’t know what was being tried or when it was being tried, before asking him to describe the screen’s brightness. It could have been that simple.

Nowadays it was called ‘blinding’ and it was one of the things modern scientists took for granted. If you were doing a psychology experiment to see whether people got angrier when they were hit over the head with red truncheons than with green truncheons, you didn’t get to look at the subjects yourself and decide how ‘angry’ they were. You would snap photos of them after they’d been hit with the truncheon, and send the photos off to a panel of raters, who would rate on a scale of 1 to 10 how angry each person looked, obviously without knowing what colour of truncheon they’d been hit with. Indeed there was no good reason to tell the raters what the experiment was about, at all. You certainly wouldn’t tell the experimental subjects that you thought they ought to be angrier when hit by red truncheons. You’d just offer them 20 pounds, lure them into a test room, hit them with a truncheon, colour randomly assigned of course, and snap the photo. In fact the truncheon-hitting and photo-snapping would be done by an assistant who hadn’t been told about the hypothesis, so he couldn’t look expectant, hit harder, or snap the photo at just the right time.

Blondlot had destroyed his reputation with the sort of mistake that would get a failing grade and probably derisive laughter from the T.A. in a first-year undergraduate course on experimental design … in 1991.

But this had been a bit longer ago, in 1904, and so it had taken months before Robert Wood had formulated the obvious alternative hypothesis and figured out how to test it, and dozens of other scientists had been sucked in.

More than two centuries after science had got started. That late in scientific history, it still hadn’t been obvious.

Which made it entirely plausible that in the tiny wizarding world, where science didn’t seem much known at all, no one had ever tried the first, the simplest, the most obvious thing that any modern scientist would think to check.

The books were full of complicated instructions for all the things you had to do exactly right in order to cast a spell. And, Harry had hypothesized, the process of obeying those instructions, of checking that you were following them correctly, probably did do something. It forced you to concentrate on the spell. Being told to just wave your wand and wish probably wouldn’t work as well. And once you believed the spell was supposed to work a certain way, once you had practised it that way, you might not be able to convince yourself that it could work any other way …

… if you did the simple but wrong thing, and tried to test alternative forms yourself.

But what if you didn’t know what the original spell had been like?

What if you gave Hermione a list of spells she hadn’t studied yet, taken from a book of silly prank spells in the Hogwarts library, and some of those spells had the correct and original instructions, while others had one changed gesture, one changed word? What if you kept the instructions constant, but told her that a spell supposed to create a red worm was supposed to create a blue worm instead?

Well, in that case, it had turned out …

… Harry was having trouble believing his results here …

… if you told Hermione to say ‘Oogely boogely’ with the vowel durations in the ratio of 3 to 1 to 1, instead of the correct ratio of 3 to 1 to 2, you still got the bat but it wouldn’t glow any more.

Not that belief was irrelevant here. Not that only the words and wand movements mattered.

If you gave Hermione completely incorrect information about what a spell was supposed to do, it would stop working.

If you didn’t tell her at all what the spell was supposed to do, it would stop working.

If she knew in very vague terms what the spell was supposed to do, or she was only partially wrong, then the spell would work as originally described in the book, not the way she’d been told it should.

Harry was, at this moment, literally banging his head against the brick wall. Not hard. He didn’t want to damage his precious brains. But if he didn’t have some outlet for his frustration, he would spontaneously catch on fire.

Thud. Thud. Thud.

It seemed the universe actually did want you to say Wingardium Leviosa and it wanted you to say it in a certain exact way and it didn’t care what you thought the pronunciation should be any more than it cared how you felt about gravity.

WHYYYYYYYYYYYYYYYY?

The worst part of it was the smug, amused look on Hermione’s face.

Hermione had not been okay with sitting around obediently following Harry’s instructions without being told why.

So Harry had explained to her what they were testing.

Harry had explained why they were testing it.

Harry had explained why probably no wizard had tried it before them.

Harry had explained that he was actually fairly confident of his prediction.

Because, Harry had said, there was no way that the universe actually wanted you to say Wingardium Leviosa.

Hermione had pointed out that this was not what her books said. Hermione had asked if Harry really thought he was smarter, at eleven years old and just over a month into his Hogwarts education, than all the other wizards in the world who disagreed with him.

Harry had said the following exact words:

‘Of course.’

Now Harry was staring at the red brick directly in front of him and contemplating how hard he would have to hit his head in order to give himself a concussion that would interfere with long-term memory formation and prevent him from remembering this later. Hermione wasn’t laughing, but he could feel her intent to laugh radiating out from behind him like a dreadful pressure on his skin, sort of like knowing you were being stalked by a serial killer only worse.

‘Say it,’ Harry said.

‘I wasn’t going to,’ said the kindly voice of Hermione Granger. ‘It didn’t seem nice.’

‘Just get it over with,’ said Harry.

‘Okay! So you gave me this whole long lecture about how hard it was to do basic science and how we might need to stay on the problem for thirty-five years, and then you went and expected us to make the greatest discovery in the history of magic in the first hour we were working together. You didn’t just hope, you really expected it. You’re silly.’

‘Thank you. Now –’

‘I’ve read all the books you gave me and I still don’t know what to call that. Overconfidence? Planning fallacy? Super duper Lake Wobegon effect? They’ll have to name it after you. Harry Bias.’

‘All right!’

‘But it is cute. It’s such a boy thing to do.’

‘Drop dead.’

‘Aw, you say the most romantic things.’

Thud. Thud. Thud.

‘So what’s next?’ said Hermione.

Harry rested his head against the bricks. His forehead was starting to hurt where he’d been banging it. ‘Nothing. I have to go back and design different experiments.’

Over the last month, Harry had carefully worked out, in advance, a course of experimentation for them that would have lasted until December.

It would have been a great set of experiments if the very first test had not falsified the basic premise.

Harry could not believe he had been this dumb.

‘Let me correct myself,’ said Harry. ‘I need to design one new experiment. I’ll let you know when we’ve got it, and we’ll do it, and then I’ll design the next one. How does that sound?’

‘It sounds like someone wasted a whole lot of effort.’

Thud. Ow. He’d done that a bit harder than he’d planned.

‘So,’ said Hermione. She was leaning back in her chair and the smug look was back on her face. ‘What did we discover today?’

‘I discovered,’ said Harry through gritted teeth, ‘that when it comes to doing truly basic research on a genuinely confusing problem where you have no clue what’s going on, my books on scientific methodology aren’t worth crap –’

‘Language, Mr Potter! Some of us are innocent young girls!’

‘Fine. But if my books were worth a carp, that’s a kind of fish not anything bad, they would have given me the following important piece of advice: When there’s a confusing problem and you’re just starting out and you have a falsifiable hypothesis, go test it. Find some simple, easy way of doing a basic check and do it right away. Don’t worry about designing an elaborate course of experiments that would make a grant proposal look impressive to a funding agency. Just check as fast as possible whether your ideas are false before you start investing huge amounts of effort in them. How does that sound for a moral?’

‘Mmm … okay,’ said Hermione. ‘But I was also hoping for something like “Hermione’s books aren’t worthless. They’re written by wise old wizards who know way more about magic than I do. I should pay attention to what Hermione’s books say.” Can we have that moral too?’

Harry’s jaw seemed to be clenched too tightly to let any words out, so he just nodded.

‘Great!’ Hermione said. ‘I liked this experiment. We learned a lot from it and it only took me an hour or so.’

‘Aaaaaaaaaaaaaahhhhhhhhhhhhhhh!’

Noticing Confusion

Professor Quirrell’s office hours consisted of 11:40 to 11:55 AM on Thursday. That was for all of his students in all years. It cost a Quirrell point just to knock on the door, and if he didn’t think your reason was worth his time, you would lose another fifty.

Harry knocked on the door.

There was a pause. Then a biting voice said, ‘I suppose you may as well come in, Mr Potter.’

And before Harry could touch the doorknob, the door slammed open, hitting the wall with a sharp crack that sounded like something might have broken in the wood, or the stone, or both.

Professor Quirrell was leaning back in his chair and reading a suspiciously old-looking book, bound in night-blue leather with silver runes on the spine. His eyes had not moved from the pages. ‘I am not in a good mood, Mr Potter. And when I am not a good mood, I am not a pleasant person to be around. For your own sake, conduct your business quickly and depart.’

A cold chill seeped from the room, as though it contained something that cast darkness the way lamps cast light, and which hadn’t been fully shaded.

Harry was a bit taken aback. Not in a good mood didn’t quite seem to cover it. What could be bothering Professor Quirrell this much … ?

Well, you didn’t just walk out on friends when they were feeling down. Harry cautiously advanced into the room. ‘Is there anything I can do to help –’

‘No,’ said Professor Quirrell, still not looking up from the book.

‘I mean, if you’ve been dealing with idiots and want someone sane to talk to …’

There was a surprisingly long pause.

Professor Quirrell slammed the book shut and it vanished with a small whispering sound. He looked up, then, and Harry flinched.

‘I suppose an intelligent conversation would be pleasant for me at this point,’ said Professor Quirrell in the same biting tone that had invited Harry to enter. ‘You are not likely to find it so, be warned.’

Harry drew a deep breath. ‘I promise I won’t mind if you snap at me. What happened?’

The cold in the room seemed to deepen. ‘A sixth-year Gryffindor cast a curse at one of my more promising students, a sixth-year Slytherin.’

Harry swallowed. ‘What … sort of curse?’

And the fury on Professor Quirrell’s face was no longer contained. ‘Why bother to ask an unimportant question like that, Mr Potter? Our friend the sixth-year Gryffindor did not think it was important!’

‘Are you serious?’ Harry said before he could stop himself.

‘No, I’m in a terrible mood today for no particular reason. Yes I’m serious, you fool! He didn’t know. He actually didn’t know. I didn’t believe it until the Aurors confirmed it under Veritaserum. He is in his sixth year at Hogwarts and he cast a high-level Dark curse without knowing what it did.’

‘You don’t mean,’ Harry said, ‘that he was mistaken about what it did, that he somehow read the wrong spell description –’

‘All he knew was that it was meant to be directed at an enemy. He knew that was all he knew.’

And that had been enough to cast the spell. ‘I do not understand how anything with that small a brain could walk upright.’

‘Indeed, Mr Potter,’ said Professor Quirrell.

There was a pause. Professor Quirrell leaned forward and picked up the silver inkwell from his desk, turning it around in his hands, staring at it as though wondering how he could go about torturing an inkwell to death.

‘Was the sixth-year Slytherin seriously hurt?’ said Harry.

‘Yes.’

‘Was the sixth-year Gryffindor raised by Muggles?’

‘Yes.’

‘Is Dumbledore refusing to expel him because the poor boy didn’t know?’

Professor Quirrell’s hands whitened on the inkwell. ‘Do you have a point, Mr Potter, or are you just stating the obvious?’

‘Professor Quirrell,’ said Harry gravely, ‘all the Muggle-raised students in Hogwarts need a safety lecture in which they are told the things so ridiculously obvious that no wizardborn would ever think to mention them. Don’t cast curses if you don’t know what they do, if you discover something dangerous don’t tell the world about it, don’t brew high-level potions without supervision in a bathroom, the reason why there are underage magic laws, all the basics.’

‘Why?’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Let the stupid ones die before they breed.’

‘If you don’t mind losing a few sixth-year Slytherins along with them.’

The inkwell caught fire in Professor Quirrell’s hands and burned with a terrible slowness, hideous black-orange flames tearing at the metal and seeming to take tiny bites from it, the silver twisting as it melted, as though it were trying and failing to escape. There was a tinny shrieking sound, as though the metal were screaming.

‘I suppose you are right,’ Professor Quirrell said with a resigned smile. ‘I shall design a lecture to ensure that Muggleborns who are too stupid to live do not take anyone valuable with them as they depart.’

The inkwell went on screaming and burning in Professor Quirrell’s hands, tiny droplets of metal, still on fire, now dripping to the desk, as though the inkwell were crying.

‘You’re not running away,’ observed Professor Quirrell.

Harry opened his mouth –

‘If you’re about to say you’re not scared of me,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘don’t.’

‘You are the scariest person I know,’ Harry said, ‘and one of the top reasons for that is your control. I simply can’t imagine hearing that you’d hurt someone you had not made a deliberate decision to hurt.’

The fire in Professor Quirrell’s hands winked out, and he carefully placed the ruined inkwell on his desk. ‘You say the nicest things, Mr Potter. Have you been taking lessons in flattery? From, perhaps, Mr Malfoy?’

Harry kept his expression blank, and realized one second too late that it might as well have been a signed confession. Professor Quirrell didn’t care what your expression looked like, he cared which states of mind made it likely.

‘I see,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Mr Malfoy is a useful friend to have, Mr Potter, and there is much he can teach you, but I hope you have not made the mistake of trusting him with too many confidences.’

‘He knows nothing which I fear becoming known,’ said Harry.

‘Well done,’ said Professor Quirrell, smiling slightly. ‘So what was your original business here?’

‘I think I’m done with the preliminary exercises in Occlumency and ready for the tutor.’

Professor Quirrell nodded. ‘I shall conduct you to Gringotts this Sunday.’ He paused, looking at Harry, and smiled. ‘And we might even make it a little outing, if you like. I’ve just had a pleasant thought.’

Harry nodded, smiling back.

As Harry left the office, he heard Professor Quirrell humming a small tune.

Harry was glad he’d been able to cheer him up.

That Sunday there seemed to be a rather large number of people whispering in the hallways, at least when Harry Potter walked past them.

And a lot of pointed fingers.

And a great deal of female giggling.

It had started at breakfast, when someone had asked Harry if he’d heard the news, and Harry had quickly interrupted and said that if the news was written by Rita Skeeter then he didn’t want to hear about it, he wanted to read it in the paper himself.

It had then developed that not many students at Hogwarts got copies of the Daily Prophet, and that the copies which had not already been bought up from their owners were being passed around in some sort of complicated order and nobody really knew who had one at the moment …

So Harry had used a Quieting Charm and gone on to eat his breakfast, trusting to his seat-mates to wave off the many, many questioners, and doing his best to ignore the incredulity, the laughter, the congratulatory smiles, the pitying looks, the fearful glances, and the dropped plates as new people came down for breakfast and heard.

Harry was feeling rather curious, but it really wouldn’t have done to spoil the artistry by hearing it second hand.

He’d done homework in the safety of his trunk for the next couple of hours, after telling his dorm-mates to come get him if anyone found him an original newspaper.

Harry was still ignorant at 10AM, when he’d left Hogwarts in a carriage with Professor Quirrell, who was in the front right, and currently slumped over in zombie-mode. Harry was sitting diagonally across, as far away as the carriage allowed, in the back left. Even so, Harry had a constant feeling of doom as the carriage rattled over a small path through a section of non-forbidden forest. It made it a bit hard to read, especially since the material was difficult, and Harry suddenly wished he was reading one of his childhood science fiction books instead –

‘We’re outside the wards, Mr Potter,’ said Professor Quirrell’s voice from the front. ‘Time to go.’

Professor Quirrell carefully disembarked from the carriage, bracing himself as he stepped down. Harry, on his own side, jumped off.

Harry was wondering exactly how they’d get there when Professor Quirrell said ‘Catch!’ and threw a bronze Knut at him, and Harry caught it without thinking.

A giant intangible hook caught at Harry’s abdomen and yanked him back, hard, only without any sense of acceleration, and an instant later Harry was standing in the middle of Diagon Alley.

(Excuse me, what? said his brain.)

(We just teleported, explained Harry.)

(That didn’t used to happen in the ancestral environment, Harry’s brain complained, and disoriented him.)

Harry staggered as his feet adjusted to the brick of the street instead of the dirt of the forest corridor they had been traversing. He straightened, still dizzy, with the bustling witches and wizards seeming to sway slightly, and the cries of the shopkeepers seeming to move around in his hearing, as his brain tried to place a world to be located in.

Moments later, there was a sort of sucking-popping sound from a few paces behind Harry, and when Harry turned to look Professor Quirrell was there.

‘Do you mind –’ said Harry, at the same time as Professor Quirrell said, ‘I’m afraid I –’

Harry stopped, Professor Quirrell didn’t.

‘– need to go off and set something in motion, Mr Potter. As it has been thoroughly explained to me that I am responsible for anything whatsoever that happens to you, I’ll be leaving you with –’

‘News-stand,’ Harry said.

‘Pardon?’

‘Or anywhere I can buy a copy of the Daily Prophet. Put me there and I’ll be happy.’

Shortly after, Harry had been delivered into a bookshop, accompanied by several quietly spoken, ambiguous threats. And the shopkeeper had received less ambiguous threats, judging by the way he had cringed, and how his eyes now kept darting between Harry and the entrance.

If the bookshop burned down, Harry was going to stick around in the middle of the fire until Professor Quirrell got back.

Meanwhile –

Harry took a quick glance around.

The bookshop seemed rather small and shoddy, with only four rows of bookcases visible, and the nearest shelf Harry’s eyes had jumped to seemed to deal with narrow, cheaply bound books with grim titles like The Massacre of Albania in the Fifteenth Century.

First things first. Harry stepped over to the seller’s counter.

‘Pardon me,’ said Harry, ‘One copy of the Daily Prophet, please.’

‘Five Sickles,’ said the shopkeeper. ‘Sorry, kid, I’ve only got three left.’

Five Sickles dropped onto the counter. Harry had the feeling he could have bargained him down a couple of points, but at this point he didn’t really care.

The shopkeeper’s eyes widened and he seemed to really notice Harry for the first time. ‘You!’

‘Me!’

‘Is it true? Are you really –’

‘Shut up! Sorry, I’ve been waiting all day to read this in the original newspaper instead of hearing about it second hand, so please just hand it over, all right?’

The shopkeeper stared at Harry for a moment, then wordlessly reached under the counter and passed over one folded copy of the Daily Prophet.

The headline read:

Harry Potter
Secretly Betrothed
to Ginevra Weasley

Harry stared.

He lifted the newspaper off the counter, softly, reverently, like he was handling an original Escher artwork, and unbent it to read …

… about the evidence that had convinced Rita Skeeter.

… and some interesting further details.

… and yet more evidence.

Fred and George had cleared it with their sister first, surely? Yes, of course they had. There was a picture of Ginevra Weasley sighing longingly over what Harry could see, looking closely, was a photo of himself. That had to have been staged.

But how on Earth … ?

Harry was sitting in a cheap folding chair, rereading the newspaper for the fourth time, when the door whispered softly and Professor Quirrell came back into the shop.

‘My apologies for – what in Merlin’s name are you reading?’

‘It would seem,’ said Harry, awe in his voice, ‘that one Mr Arthur Weasley was placed under the Imperius Curse by a Death Eater whom my father killed, thus creating a debt to House Potter, which my father demanded be repaid by the hand in marriage of the recently born Ginevra Weasley. Do people actually do that sort of thing around here?’

‘How could Miss Skeeter possibly be fool enough to believe –’

And Professor Quirrell’s voice cut off.

Harry had been reading the newspaper held vertically and unfolded, which meant that Professor Quirrell, from where he was standing, could see the text underneath the headline.

The look of shock on Professor Quirrell’s face was a work of art almost on par with the newspaper itself.

‘Don’t worry,’ said Harry cheerfully, ‘it’s all fake.’

From elsewhere in the store, he heard the shopkeeper gasp. There was the sound of a stack of books falling over.

‘Mr Potter …’ Professor Quirrell said slowly, ‘are you sure of that?’

‘Quite sure. Shall we go?’

Professor Quirrell nodded, looking rather abstracted, and Harry folded the newspaper back up, and followed him out of the door.

For some reason Harry didn’t seem to be hearing any street noises now.

They walked in silence for thirty seconds before Professor Quirrell spoke. ‘Miss Skeeter viewed the original proceedings of the restricted Wizengamot session.’

‘Yes.’

‘The original proceedings of the Wizengamot.’

‘Yes.’

‘I would have trouble doing that.’

‘Really?’ said Harry. ‘Because if my suspicions are correct, this was done by a Hogwarts student.’

‘That is beyond impossible,’ Professor Quirrell said flatly. ‘Mr Potter … I regret to say that this young lady expects to marry you.’

‘But that is improbable,’ said Harry. ‘To quote Douglas Adams, the impossible often has a kind of integrity which the merely improbable lacks.’

‘I see your point,’ Professor Quirrell said slowly. ‘But … no, Mr Potter. It may be impossible, but I can imagine tampering with the Wizengamot proceedings. It is unimaginable that the Grand Manager of Gringotts should affix the seal of his office in witness to a false betrothal contract, and Miss Skeeter personally verified that seal.’

‘Indeed,’ said Harry, ‘you would expect the Grand Manager of Gringotts to get involved with that much money changing hands. It seems Mr Weasley was greatly in debt, and so demanded an additional payment of ten thousand Galleons –’

‘Ten thousand Galleons for a Weasley? You could buy the daughter of a Noble House for that!’

‘Excuse me,’ Harry said. ‘I really have to ask at this point, do people actually do that sort of thing around here –’

‘Rarely,’ said Professor Quirrell, with a frown on his face. ‘And not at all, I suspect, since the Dark Lord departed. I suppose that according to the newspaper, your father just paid it?’

‘He didn’t have any choice,’ said Harry. ‘Not if he wanted to fulfil the conditions of the prophecy.’

‘Give me that,’ said Professor Quirrell, and the newspaper leaped out of Harry’s hand so fast that he got a paper cut.

Harry automatically put the finger in his mouth to suck on, feeling rather shocked, and turned to remonstrate with Professor Quirrell –

Professor Quirrell had stopped short in the middle of the street, and his eyes were flickering rapidly back and forth as an invisible force held the newspaper suspended before him.

Harry watched, gaping in open awe, as the newspaper opened to reveal pages two and three. And not much long after, four and five. It was like the man had cast off a pretence of mortality.

And after a troublingly short time, the paper neatly folded itself up again. Professor Quirrell plucked it from the air and tossed it to Harry, who caught it in sheer reflex; and then Professor Quirrell started walking again, and Harry automatically trudged after.

‘No,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘that prophecy didn’t sound quite right to me either.’

Harry nodded, still stunned.

‘The centaurs could have been put under an Imperius,’ Professor Quirrell said, frowning, ‘that seems understandable. What magic can make, magic can corrupt, and it is not unthinkable that the Great Seal of Gringotts could be twisted to another’s hand. The Unspeakable could have been impersonated with Polyjuice, likewise the Bavarian seer. And with enough effort it might be possible to tamper with the proceedings of the Wizengamot. Do you have any idea how that was done?’

‘I do not have one single plausible hypothesis,’ said Harry. ‘I do know it was done on a total budget of forty Galleons.’

Professor Quirrell stopped short and whirled on Harry. His expression was now completely incredulous. ‘Forty Galleons will pay a competent ward-breaker to open a path into a home you wish to burgle! Forty thousand Galleons might pay a team of the greatest professional criminals in the world to tamper with the proceedings of the Wizengamot!’

Harry shrugged helplessly. ‘I’ll remember that the next time I want to save thirty-nine thousand, nine hundred and sixty Galleons by finding the right contractor.’

‘I do not say this often,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I am impressed.’

‘Likewise,’ said Harry.

‘And who is this incredible Hogwarts student?’

‘I’m afraid I couldn’t say.’

Somewhat to Harry’s surprise, Professor Quirrell made no objection to this.

They walked in the direction of the Gringotts building, thinking, for they were neither of them the sort of person who would give up on the problem without considering it for at least five minutes.

‘I have a feeling,’ Harry said finally, ‘that we’re coming at this from the wrong angle. There’s a tale I once heard about some students who came into a physics class, and the teacher showed them a large metal plate near a fire. She ordered them to feel the metal plate, and they felt that the metal nearer the fire was cooler, and the metal further away was warmer. And she said, write down your guess for why this happens. So some students wrote down “because of how the metal conducts heat”, and some students wrote down “because of how the air moves”, and no one said “this just seems impossible”, and the real answer was that before the students came into the room, the teacher turned the plate around.’

‘Interesting,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘That does sound similar. Is there a moral?’

‘That your strength as a rationalist is your ability to be more confused by fiction than by reality,’ said Harry. ‘If you’re equally good at explaining any outcome, you have zero knowledge. The students thought they could use words like “because of heat conduction” to explain anything, even a metal plate being cooler on the side nearer the fire. So they didn’t notice how confused they were, and that meant they couldn’t be more confused by falsehood than by truth. If you tell me that the centaurs were under the Imperius Curse, I still have the feeling of something being not quite right. I notice that I’m still confused even after hearing your explanation.’

‘Hm,’ said Professor Quirrell.

They walked on further.

‘I don’t suppose,’ said Harry, ‘that it’s possible to actually swap people into alternate universes? Like, this isn’t our own Rita Skeeter, or they temporarily sent her somewhere else?’

‘If that was possible,’ Professor Quirrell said, his voice rather dry, ‘would I still be here?’

And just as they were almost to the huge white front of the Gringotts building, Professor Quirrell said:

‘Ah. Of course. I see it now. Let me guess, the Weasley twins?’

‘What?’ said Harry, his voice rising an octave. ‘How?’

‘I’m afraid I couldn’t say.’

‘… That is not fair.’

‘I think it is extremely fair,’ said Professor Quirrell, and they entered through the bronze doors.

Empathy

It wasn’t every day you got to see Harry Potter beg.

‘Pleeaaase,’ whined Harry Potter.

Fred and George shook their heads again, smiling.

There was an agonized look on Harry Potter’s face. ‘But I told you how I did the one with Kevin Entwhistle’s cat, and Hermione and the vanishing soda, and I can’t tell you about the Sorting Hat or the Remembrall or Professor Snape …’

Fred and George shrugged and turned to leave.

‘If you ever do figure it out,’ said the Weasley twins, ‘be sure to let us know.’

‘You’re evil! You’re both evil!’

Fred and George firmly closed the door to the empty classroom behind them, and made sure to keep the grin on their faces for a while, just in case Harry Potter could see through doors.

Then they turned a corner and their faces sagged.

‘I don’t suppose Harry’s guesses –’

‘– gave you any ideas?’ they said to each other at the same time, and then their shoulders slumped further.

Their last relevant memory was of Flume refusing to help them, though they couldn’t remember what they’d asked him to do …

… but they must have looked elsewhere and found someone to help them do something illegal, or they wouldn’t have agreed to be Obliviated afterwards.

How had they possibly been able to get all that done on just forty Galleons?

At first they’d worried that they’d forged evidence so good that Harry actually would end up married to Ginny … but they’d thought of that too, it seemed. The Wizengamot proceedings had been tampered with again to put them back the way they’d been originally, the fake betrothal contract had vanished from its dragon-guarded vault in Gringotts, and so on. It was pretty scary, actually. Most people now thought the Daily Prophet had just made the whole thing up for unguessable reasons, and the Quibbler had helpfully twisted the knife deeper with the next day’s headline, ‘Harry Potter secretly betrothed to luna lovegood’.

Whoever they’d hired would tell them after the statute of limitations expired, they desperately hoped. But meanwhile it was awful, they’d pulled their greatest prank ever, maybe the greatest prank in the history of pranking, and they couldn’t remember how. It was crazy, they’d been able to think of a way the first time, so why couldn’t they see it now after knowing everything they’d done?

Their only consolation was that Harry didn’t know they didn’t know.

Not even Mum had questioned them about it, despite the obvious Weasley connection. Whatever had been done, it was far out of the reach of any Hogwarts student … except possibly one, who, if certain rumours were true, might have done it by snapping his fingers. Harry had been questioned under Veritaserum, he’d told them … with Dumbledore present and giving the Aurors scary looks. The Aurors had asked just enough to determine that Harry hadn’t pulled the prank himself or disappeared anyone, and then they got the heck out of Hogwarts.

Fred and George had wondered whether to feel insulted about Harry Potter being questioned by the Aurors for their prank, but the look on Harry’s face, probably for exactly the same reason, made everything worth it.

Unsurprisingly, Rita Skeeter and the editor of the Daily Prophet had both vanished and were probably in another country by now. They would’ve liked to be able to tell their family about that part. Dad would have congratulated them, they thought, after Mum had finished killing them and Ginny had burned the remains.

But everything was still all right, they’d tell Dad some day, and meanwhile …

… meanwhile Dumbledore had happened to sneeze while passing them in the hallway, and a small package had accidentally dropped out of his pockets, and inside had been two matched wardbreaker’s monocles of incredible quality. The Weasley twins had tested their new monocles on the ‘forbidden’ third-floor corridor, making a quick trip to the magic mirror and back, and they hadn’t been able to see all the detection webs clearly, but the monocles had shown a lot more than they’d seen the first time.

Of course they would have to be very careful never to get caught with the monocles in their possession, or they would end up in the Headmaster’s office getting a stern lecture and maybe even threats of expulsion.

It was good to know that not everyone who got Sorted into Gryffindor grew up to be Professor McGonagall.

Harry was in a white room, windowless, featureless, sitting before a desk, facing an expressionless man in formal robes of solid black.

The room was screened against detection, and the man had performed exactly twenty-seven spells before saying so much as ‘Hello, Mr Potter.’

It was oddly appropriate that the man in black was about to try reading Harry’s mind.

‘Prepare yourself,’ the man said tonelessly.

A human mind, Harry’s Occlumency book had said, was only exposed to a Legilimens along certain surfaces. If you failed to defend your surfaces, the Legilimens would go through and be able to access any part of you which their own mind was able to comprehend …

… which tended not to be much. Human minds, it seemed, were hard for humans to understand on any level but the shallowest. Harry had wondered if knowing lots of cognitive science could make him an incredibly powerful Legilimens, but repeated experience had finally driven into him the lesson that he needed to get a little less excited in his anticipations about this sort of thing. It wasn’t as if any cognitive scientist understood humans well enough to make one.

To learn the counter, Occlumency, the first step was to imagine yourself to be a different person, pretending it as thoroughly as you could, immersing yourself entirely in that alternate persona. You wouldn’t always have to do that, but in the beginning, it was how you learned where your surfaces were. The Legilimens would try to read you, and you would feel it happening if you paid close enough attention, you would sense them trying to enter. And your job was to make sure that they always touched your imaginary persona and not the real one.

When you were good enough at that, you could imagine being a very simple sort of person, pretend to be a rock, and make a habit of leaving the pretence in place where all your surfaces were. That was a standard Occlumency barrier. Pretending to be a rock was hard to learn, but easy to do afterwards, and the exposed surface of a mind was much shallower than its interior, so with enough practise you could keep it up as a background habit.

Or if you were a perfect Occlumens, you could race ahead of any probes, answering queries as fast as they were asked, so that the Legilimens would enter through your surfaces and see a mind indistinguishable from whoever you were pretending to be.

Even the best Legilimens could be fooled that way. If a perfect Occlumens claimed they were dropping their Occlumency barriers, there was no way to know if they were lying. Worse, you might not know you were dealing with a perfect Occlumens. They were rare, but the fact that they existed meant you couldn’t trust Legilimency on anyone.

It was a sad commentary on how little human beings understood each other, how little any wizard comprehended the depths lying beneath the mind’s surface, that you could fool the best human telepaths by pretending to be someone else.

But then human beings only understood each other in the first place by pretending. You didn’t make predictions about people by modelling the hundred trillion synapses in their brain as separate objects. Ask the best social manipulator on Earth to build you an Artificial Intelligence from scratch, and they’d just give you a dumb look. You predicted people by telling your brain to act like theirs. You put yourself in their place. If you wanted to know what an angry person would do, you activated your own brain’s anger circuitry, and whatever that circuitry output, that was your prediction. What did the neural circuitry for anger actually look like inside? Who knew? The best social manipulator on Earth might not know what neurons were, and neither might the best Legilimens.

Anything a Legilimens could understand, an Occlumens could pretend to be. It was the same trick either way – probably implemented by the same neural circuitry in both cases, a single set of control circuits for reconfiguring your own brain to act as a model of someone else’s.

And so the race between telepathic offense and telepathic defence had been a decisive win for defence. Otherwise the entire magical world, maybe even the whole Earth, would have been a very different place …

Harry took a deep breath, and concentrated. There was a slight smile on his face.

For once, just once, Harry hadn’t been short-changed in the mysterious powers department.

After almost a month of work, and more on a whim than any real hunch, Harry had decided to make himself coldly angry and then try the book’s Occlumency exercises again. At that point he’d mostly given up hope on that sort of thing, but it had still seemed worth a quick try –

He’d run through all the book’s hardest exercises in two hours, and the next day he’d gone and told Professor Quirrell he was ready.

His dark side, it had turned out, was very, very good at pretending to be other people.

Harry thought of his standard trigger, from the first time he’d gone over entirely to his dark side …

Severus paused, looking quite pleased with himself. ‘And that will be … five points? No, let us make it an even ten points from Ravenclaw for backchat.’

Harry’s smile grew chillier, and he regarded the black-robed man who thought he was going to read Harry’s mind.

And then Harry turned into someone else entirely, someone who had seemed appropriate to the occasion.

… in a white room, windowless, featureless, sitting before a desk, facing an expressionless man in formal robes of solid black.

Kimball Kinnison regarded the black-robed man who thought he was going to read the mind of a Second-Stage Lensman of the Galactic Patrol.

To say that Kimball Kinnison was confident of the outcome would be an understatement. He had been trained by Mentor of Arisia, the most powerful mind known to this or any other universe, and the mere wizard sitting across from him would see precisely what the Gray Lensman wanted him to see …

… the mind of the boy he was currently disguised as, an innocent child named Harry Potter.

‘I’m ready,’ said Kimball Kinnison in nervous tones that were exactly appropriate for an eleven-year-old boy.

‘Legilimens,’ said the black-robed wizard.

There was a pause.

The black-robed wizard blinked, as if he’d seen something so shocking that it had been enough to make even his eyelids move. His voice wasn’t quite toneless as he said, ‘The Boy-Who-Lived has a mysterious dark side?’

The heat slowly crept up into Harry’s cheeks.

‘Well,’ the man said. His face had now settled back into perfect calm. ‘Excuse me. Mr Potter, it is good to know your advantages, but that is not the same as being wildly overconfident in them. You may indeed be able to learn Occlumency at eleven years of age. This astounds me. I had thought Mr Dumbledore was pretending to be insane again. Your dissociative talent is so strong that I am surprised to find no other signs of childhood abuse, and you may become a perfect Occlumens in time. But there is a considerable difference between that and expecting to put up a successful Occlumency barrier on your first attempt. That is merely ridiculous. Did you feel anything as I read your mind?’

Harry shook his head, now blushing furiously.

‘Then pay closer attention next time. The goal is not to create a perfect image on your first day of lessons. The goal is to learn where your surfaces are. Prepare yourself.’

Harry tried to pretend to be Kimball Kinnison again, tried to pay more attention, but his thoughts were a little scattered and he was suddenly aware of all the things he shouldn’t be thinking about …

Oh, this was going to suck.

Harry gritted his teeth. At least the instructor would be Obliviated afterwards.

‘Legilimens.’

There was a pause –

… in a white room, windowless, featureless, sitting before a desk, facing an expressionless man in formal robes of solid black.

It was their fourth day, on a Sunday evening. When you paid this much, you got your sessions any darned time you wanted, never mind the concept of weekends.

‘Hello, Mr Potter,’ the telepath said tonelessly, having cast the full suite of privacy spells.

‘Hello, Mr Bester,’ Harry said wearily. ‘Let’s just get the initial shock out of the way, shall we?’

‘You managed to surprise me?’ the man said, now sounding slightly interested. ‘Well then.’ He pointed his wand and stared into Harry’s eyes. ‘Legilimens.’

There was a pause, and then the black-robed wizard jerked as if someone had touched him with a cattle prod.

‘The Dark Lord is alive?’ he choked. His eyes were suddenly wild. ‘Dumbledore turns himself invisible and sneaks into girls’ dorms?’

Harry sighed and looked down at his watch. In about another three seconds …

‘So,’ the man said. He hadn’t quite recovered his tonelessness. ‘You genuinely believe you’re going to discover the secret rules of magic and become all-powerful.’

‘That’s right,’ Harry said evenly, still looking at his watch. ‘I’m that overconfident.’

‘I wonder. It seems the Sorting Hat thinks you’ll be the next Dark Lord.’

‘And you know I’m trying pretty hard not to be, and you saw that we already had a long discussion about whether you were willing to teach me Occlumency, and in the end you decided to do it, so can we just get this over with?’

‘All right,’ said the man exactly six seconds later, same as last time. ‘Prepare yourself.’ He paused, and then said, his voice rather wistful, ‘Though I do wish I could remember that trick with the gold and silver.’

Harry was finding himself very disturbed by how reproducible human thoughts were when you reset people back to the same initial conditions and exposed them to the same stimuli. It was dispelling illusions that a good reductionist wasn’t supposed to have in the first place.

Harry was in a rather bad mood as he stomped out of his Herbology class the next Monday morning.

Hermione was seething alongside him.

The other children were still inside, a bit slow to assemble their things because they were gibbering excitedly to each other about Ravenclaw winning the year’s second Quidditch match.

It seemed that last night after dinner, a girl had flown around on a broomstick for thirty minutes and then caught some sort of giant mosquito. There were other facts about what had happened during this match, but they were irrelevant.

Harry had missed this exciting sports event due to his Occlumency lesson, and also having a life.

He had then avoided all conversations in the Ravenclaw dorm, weren’t Quieting Charms and magical trunks wonderful. He had eaten breakfast at the Gryffindor table.

But Harry couldn’t avoid Herbology, and the Ravenclaws had talked about it before class, and after class, and during class, until Harry had looked up from the baby furcot whose diaper he was changing, and announced loudly that some of them were trying to learn about plants and Snitches didn’t grow on anything so could they all please shut up about Quidditch. Everyone else present had given him shocked looks, except Hermione, who’d looked like she wanted to applaud, and Professor Sprout, who had awarded him a point for Ravenclaw.

A point for Ravenclaw.

One point.

The seven idiots on their idiot brooms playing their idiot game had earned one hundred and ninety points for Ravenclaw.

It seemed that Quidditch scores added directly onto the House points total.

In other words, catching a golden mosquito was worth 150 House points.

Harry couldn’t even imagine what he would have to do to earn one hundred and fifty House points.

Besides, y’know, rescuing a hundred and fifty Hufflepuffs, or coming up with fifteen ideas as good as putting protective shells on time machines, or inventing one thousand five hundred creative ways to kill people, or being Hermione Granger for the entire year.

‘We should kill them,’ Harry said to Hermione, who was walking beside him with an equally offended air.

‘Who?’ said Hermione. ‘The Quidditch team?’

‘I was thinking of everyone involved in any way with Quidditch anywhere, but the Ravenclaw team would be a start, yes.’

Hermione’s lips were pursed disapprovingly. ‘You do know that killing people is wrong, Harry?’

‘Yes,’ Harry said.

‘Okay, just checking,’ Hermione said. ‘Let’s get the Seeker first. I’ve read some Agatha Christie mysteries, do you know how we can get her onto a train?’

‘Two students plotting murder,’ said a dry voice. ‘How shocking.’

From around a nearby corner strolled a man in lightly spotted robes, his greasy hair falling long and unkempt about his shoulders. Deadly danger seemed to radiate out from him, filling the hallway with improperly mixed potions and accidental falls and people dying in bed of what the Aurors would rule to be natural causes.

Without thinking about it at all, Harry stepped in front of Hermione.

There was an intake of breath from behind him, and then a moment later Hermione brushed past and stepped in front of him. ‘Run, Harry!’ she said. ‘Boys shouldn’t have to be in danger.’

Severus Snape smiled mirthlessly. ‘Amusing. I request a moment of your time, Potter, if you can tear yourself away from your flirtations with Miss Granger.’

Suddenly there was a very worried look on Hermione’s face. She turned to Harry and opened her mouth, then paused, looking distressed.

‘Oh, don’t worry, Miss Granger,’ said Severus’s silky voice. ‘I promise to return your beau unmaimed.’ His smile vanished. ‘Now Potter and I are about to go off and have a private conversation, just by ourselves. I hope it is clear that you are not invited, but just in case, consider that an order from a Hogwarts professor. I’m sure a good little girl like you won’t disobey.’

And Severus turned and walked back around the corner. ‘Coming, Potter?’ his voice said.

‘Um,’ Harry said to Hermione. ‘Can I just sort of go off and follow him and let you work out what I should say to make sure you’re not all worried and offended?’

‘No,’ Hermione said, her voice trembling.

Severus’s laughter echoed from around the corner.

Harry bowed his head. ‘Sorry,’ he said quietly, ‘really,’ and he went off after the Potions Master.

‘So,’ Harry said. There were no other sounds now but two pairs of legs, the long and the short, padding across a random stone corridor. The Potions Master was striding quickly but not too fast for Harry to keep up, and insofar as Harry could apply the concept of directionality to Hogwarts, they were moving away from the frequented areas. ‘What’s this about?’

‘I don’t suppose you could explain,’ Severus said dryly, ‘why the two of you were plotting to murder Cho Chang?’

‘I don’t suppose you could explain,’ Harry said dryly, ‘in your capacity as an official of the Hogwarts school system, why catching a golden mosquito is deemed an academic accomplishment worthy of a hundred and fifty House points?’

A smile crossed Severus’s lips. ‘Dear me, and I thought you were supposed to be perceptive. Are you truly so incapable of understanding your classmates, Potter, or do you dislike them too much to try? If Quidditch scores did not count toward the House Cup then none of them would care about House points at all. It would merely be an obscure contest for students like you and Miss Granger.’

It was a shockingly good answer.

And that shock brought Harry’s mind fully awake.

In retrospect it shouldn’t have been surprising that Severus understood his students, understood them very well indeed.

He had been reading their minds.

And …

… the book said that a successful Legilimens was extremely rare, rarer than a perfect Occlumens, because almost no one had enough mental discipline.

Mental discipline?

Harry had collected stories about a man who routinely lost his temper in class and blew up at young children.

… but this same man, when Harry had spoken of the Dark Lord still being alive, had responded instantly and perfectly – reacting in precisely the way that someone completely ignorant would react.

The man stalked about Hogwarts with the air of an assassin, radiating danger …

… which was exactly not what a real assassin should do. Real assassins should look like meek little accountants until they killed you.

He was the Head of House for proud and aristocratic Slytherin, and he wore a robe with spotted stains from bits of potions and ingredients, which two minutes of magic could have removed.

Harry noticed that he was confused.

And his threat estimate of the Head of House Slytherin shot up astronomically.

Dumbledore had seemed to think Severus was his, and there’d been nothing to contradict that; the Potions Master had been ‘scary but not abusive’, as promised. So, Harry had reasoned earlier, this was Fellowship business. If Severus had been planning harm, surely he wouldn’t have come to get Harry in front of Hermione, a witness, when he could have simply waited for some time when Harry was alone …

Harry quietly bit his lip.

‘I once knew a boy who truly adored Quidditch,’ said Severus Snape. ‘He was an utter pillock. Just as you and I would expect, we two.’

‘What is this?’ Harry said slowly.

‘Patience, Potter.’

Severus turned his head, and then glided with his assassin’s bearing into a nearby opening in the corridor walls, a smaller and narrower hallway leading off.

Harry followed him, wondering if it would be smarter to simply run away.

They turned and made another turn, and came to a dead end, a simple blank wall. If Hogwarts had actually been built, rather than conjured or summoned or birthed or whatever, Harry would have had some sharp words for the architect about paying people to build hallways that didn’t go anywhere.

‘Quietus,’ said Severus, and a few other things as well.

Harry leaned back, folded his arms across his chest, and watched Severus’s face.

‘Looking me in the eyes, Potter?’ said Severus Snape. ‘Your Occlumency lessons cannot have progressed far enough for you to block Legilimency. But then perhaps they have progressed far enough for you to detect it. Since I cannot know otherwise, I will not risk trying.’ The man smiled thinly. ‘And the same will hold for Dumbledore, I think. Which is why we are now having this little talk.’

Harry’s eyes widened involuntarily.

‘To begin with,’ Severus said, eyes glittering, ‘I should like you to promise not to speak of our conversations to anyone. So far as the school is concerned, we are discussing your Potions homework. Whether or not they believe that is unimportant. So far as Dumbledore and McGonagall are concerned, I am violating Draco Malfoy’s confidences in me, and neither of us think it proper to speak further of the particulars.’

Harry’s brain tried to calculate the ramifications and implications of this and ran out of swap space.

‘Well?’ said the Potions Master.

‘All right,’ Harry said slowly. It was hard to see how having a conversation and being unable to tell anyone could be more constraining than not having it, in which case you also couldn’t tell anyone the contents. ‘I promise.’

Severus was watching Harry intently. ‘You said once in the Headmaster’s office that you would not tolerate bullying or abuse. And so I wonder, Harry Potter. Just how much do you resemble your father?’

‘Unless we’re talking about Michael Verres-Evans,’ Harry said, ‘the answer is that I know very little about James Potter.’

Severus nodded, as though to himself. ‘There is a fifth-year Slytherin. A boy named Lesath Lestrange. He is being bullied by Gryffindors. I am … constrained, in my ability to deal with such situations. You could help him, perhaps. If you wished. I am not asking you for a favour, and will not owe you one. It is simply an opportunity to do as you will.’

Harry stared at Severus, thinking.

‘Wondering if it’s a trap?’ said Severus, a faint smile crossing his lips. ‘It is not. It is a test. Call it curiosity on my part. But Lesath’s troubles are real, as are my own difficulties in intervening.’

That was the trouble with other people knowing you were a good guy. Even if you knew they knew, you still couldn’t ignore the bait.

And if his father had protected students from bullies too … it didn’t matter if Harry knew why Severus had told him. It still made him feel warm inside, and proud, and made it impossible to walk away.

‘Fine,’ Harry said. ‘Tell me about Lesath. Why is he being bullied?’

Severus’s face lost the faint smile. ‘You think there are reasons, Potter?’

‘Perhaps not,’ Harry said quietly. ‘But the thought had occurred to me that he might have pushed some unimportant mudblood girl down the stairs.’

‘Lesath Lestrange,’ Severus said, his voice now cold, ‘is the son of Bellatrix Black, the most fanatic and evil servant of the Dark Lord. Lesath is the acknowledged bastard of Rabastan Lestrange. Shortly after the Dark Lord’s death, Bellatrix and Rabastan and Rabastan’s brother Rodolphus were captured while torturing Alice and Frank Longbottom. All three are in Azkaban for life. The Longbottoms were driven insane by repeated Cruciatus and remain in St. Mungo’s incurable ward. Is any of that a good reason to bully him, Potter?’

‘It is no reason at all,’ Harry said, still quietly. ‘And Lesath himself has done no wrong that you know?’

The faint smile crossed Severus’s lips again. ‘He is no more a saint than anyone else. But he has pushed no mudblood girls down the stairs, not that I ever heard.’

‘Or saw in his mind,’ said Harry.

Severus’s expression was chill. ‘I did not invade his privacy, Potter. I looked within the Gryffindors, rather. He is simply a convenient target for their little satisfactions.’

A cold wash of anger ran down Harry’s spine, and he had to remind himself that Severus might not be a trustworthy source of information.

‘And you think,’ Harry said, ‘that an intervention by Harry Potter, the Boy-Who-Lived, might prove effective.’

‘Indeed,’ said Severus Snape, and told Harry when and where the Gryffindors were planning their next little game.

Reductionism

‘Okay,’ Harry said, swallowing. ‘Okay, Hermione, it’s enough, you can stop.’

The white sugar pill in front of Hermione still hadn’t changed shape or colour at all, even though she was concentrating harder than Harry had ever seen, her eyes squeezed shut, beads of sweat on her forehead, hand trembling as it gripped the wand –

‘Hermione, stop! It’s not going to work, Hermione, I don’t think we can make things that don’t exist yet!’

Slowly, Hermione’s hand relaxed its grasp on the wand.

‘I thought I felt it,’ she said in a bare whisper. ‘I thought I felt it start to Transfigure, just for a second.’

There was a lump in Harry’s throat. ‘You were probably imagining it. Hoping too hard.’

‘I probably was,’ she said. She looked like she wanted to cry.

Slowly, Harry took his mechanical pencil in his hand, and reached over to the sheet of paper with all the items crossed out, and drew a line through the item that said Alzheimer’s cure.

They couldn’t have fed anyone a Transfigured pill. But Transfiguration, at least the kind they could do, didn’t enchant the targets – it wouldn’t Transfigure a regular broomstick into a flying one. So if Hermione had been able to make a pill at all, it would have been a non-magical pill, one that worked for ordinary material reasons. They could have secretly made pills for a Muggle science lab, let them study the pills and try to reverse-engineer them before the Transfiguration wore off … no one in either world would need to know that magic had been involved, it would just be another scientific breakthrough …

It hadn’t been the sort of thing a wizard would think of, either. They didn’t respect mere patterns of atoms that much, they didn’t think of unenchanted material things as objects of power. If it wasn’t magical, it wasn’t interesting.

Earlier, Harry had very secretly – he hadn’t even told Hermione – tried to Transfigure nanotechnology a la Eric Drexler. (He’d tried to produce a desktop nanofactory, of course, not tiny self-replicating assemblers, Harry wasn’t insane.) It would have been godhood in a single shot if it’d worked.

‘That was it for today, right?’ said Hermione. She was slumped back in her chair, leaning her head against the back; and her face showed her tiredness, which was very unusual for Hermione. She liked to pretend she was limitless, at least when Harry was around.

‘One more,’ Harry said cautiously, ‘but that one’s small, plus it might actually work. I saved it for last because I was hoping we could end on an up note. It’s real stuff, not like phasers. They’ve already made it in the laboratory, not like the Alzheimer’s cure. And it’s a generic substance, not specific like the lost books you tried to Transfigure copies of. I made a diagram of the molecular structure to show you. We just want to make it longer than it’s ever been made before, and with all the tubes aligned, and the endpoints embedded in diamond.’ Harry produced a sheet of graph paper.

Hermione sat back up, took it, and studied it, frowning. ‘These are all carbon atoms? And Harry, what’s the name? I can’t Transfigure it if I don’t know what it’s called.’

Harry made a disgusted face. He was still having trouble getting used to that sort of thing, it shouldn’t matter what something was named if you knew what it was. ‘They’re called buckytubes, or carbon nanotubes. It’s a kind of fullerene that was discovered just this year. It’s about a hundred times stronger than steel and a sixth of the weight.’

Hermione looked up from the graph paper, her face surprised. ‘That’s real?’

‘Yeah,’ Harry said, ‘just hard to make the Muggle way. If we could get enough of the stuff, we could use it to build a space elevator all the way up to geosynchronous orbit or higher, and in terms of delta-v that’s halfway to anywhere in the Solar System. Plus we could throw out solar power satellites like confetti.’

Hermione was frowning again. ‘Is this stuff safe?’

‘I don’t see why it wouldn’t be,’ Harry said. ‘A buckytube is just a graphite sheet wrapped into a circular tube, basically, and graphite is the same stuff used in pencils –’

‘I know what graphite is, Harry,’ Hermione said. She brushed her hair back absent-mindedly, her eyebrows furrowed as she stared at the sheet of paper.

Harry reached into a pocket of his robes, and produced a white thread tied to two small grey plastic rings at either end. He’d added drops of superglue where the thread met either ring, to make it all a single object that could be Transfigured as a whole. Cyanoacrylate, if Harry remembered correctly, worked by covalent bonds, and that was as close to being a ‘solid object’ as you ever got in a world ultimately composed of tiny individual atoms. ‘When you’re ready,’ Harry said, ‘try to Transfigure this into a set of aligned buckytube fibres embedded in two solid diamond rings.’

‘All right …’ Hermione said slowly. ‘Harry, I feel like I just missed something.’

Harry shrugged helplessly. Maybe you’re just tired. He knew better than to say it out loud, though.

Hermione laid her wand against one plastic ring, and stared for a while.

Two small circles of glittering diamond lay on the table, connected by a long black thread.

‘It changed,’ said Hermione. She sounded like she was trying to be enthusiastic but had run out of energy. ‘Now what?’

Harry felt a bit deflated by his research partner’s lack of passion, but did his best not to show it; maybe the same process would work in reverse to cheer her up. ‘Now I test it to see if it holds weight.’

There was an A-frame Harry had rigged up to do an earlier experiment with diamond rods – you could make solid diamond objects easily, using Transfiguration, they just wouldn’t last. The earlier experiment had measured whether Transfiguring a long diamond rod into a shorter diamond rod would allow it to lift a suspended heavy weight as it contracted, i.e., could you Transfigure against tension, which you in fact could.

Harry carefully looped one circle of glittering diamond over the thick metal hook at the top of the rig, then attached a thick metal hanger to the bottom ring, and then started attaching weights to the hanger.

(Harry had asked the Weasley twins to Transfigure the apparatus for him, and the Weasley twins had given him an incredulous look, like they couldn’t figure out what sort of prank he could possibly want that for, but they hadn’t asked any questions. And their Transfigurations, according to them, lasted for around three hours, so Harry and Hermione still had a while left.)

‘One hundred kilograms,’ Harry said about a minute later. ‘I don’t think a steel thread this thin would hold that. It should go up much higher, but that’s all the weight I’ve got.’

There was a further silence.

Harry straightened up, and went back to their table, and sat down in his chair, and ceremoniously made a check mark next to Buckytubes. ‘There,’ Harry said. ‘That one worked.’

‘But it’s not really useful, Harry, is it?’ Hermione said from where she was sitting with her head resting in her hands. ‘I mean, even if we gave it to a scientist they couldn’t learn how to make lots of buckytubes from studying ours.’

‘They might be able to learn something,’ Harry said. ‘Hermione, look at it, that little tiny thread holding up all that weight, we just made something that no Muggle laboratory could make –’

‘But any other witch could make it,’ Hermione said. Her exhaustion was coming into her voice, now. ‘Harry, I don’t think this is working out.’

‘You mean our relationship?’ Harry said. ‘Great! Let’s break up.’

That got a slight grin out of her. ‘I mean our research.’

‘Oh, Hermione, how could you?’

‘You’re sweet when you’re mean,’ she said. ‘But Harry, this is nuts, I’m twelve, you’re eleven, it’s silly to think we’re going to discover anything that no one’s ever figured out before.’

‘Are you really saying we should give up on unravelling the secrets of magic after trying for less than one month?’ Harry said, trying to put a note of challenge into his voice. Honestly he was feeling some of the same fatigue as Hermione. None of the good ideas ever worked. He’d made just one discovery worth mentioning, the Mendelian pattern, and he couldn’t tell Hermione about it without breaking his promise to Draco.

‘No,’ Hermione said. Her young face was looking very serious and adult. ‘I’m saying right now we should be studying all the magic that wizards already know, so we can do this sort of thing after we graduate from Hogwarts.’

‘Um …’ Harry said. ‘Hermione, I hate to put it this way, but imagine we’d decided to hold off on research until later, and the first thing we tried after we graduated was Transfiguring an Alzheimer’s cure, and it worked. We’d feel … I don’t think the word stupid would adequately describe how we’d feel. What if there’s something else like that and it does work?’

‘That’s not fair, Harry!’ Hermione said. Her voice was trembling like she was on the verge of breaking out crying. ‘You can’t put that on people! It’s not our job to do that sort of thing, we’re kids!’

For a moment Harry wondered what would happen if someone told Hermione she had to fight an immortal Dark Lord, if she would turn into one of the whiny self-pitying heroes that Harry could never stand reading about in his books.

‘Anyway,’ Hermione said. Her voice shook. ‘I don’t want to keep doing this. I don’t believe children can do things that grown-ups can’t, that’s only in stories.’

There was silence in the classroom.

Hermione started to look a little scared, and Harry knew that his own expression had cooled.

It might not have hurt so much if the same thought hadn’t already come to Harry – that, while thirty might be old for a scientific revolutionary and twenty about right, while there were people who got doctorates when they were seventeen and fourteen-year-old heirs who’d been great kings or generals, there wasn’t really anyone who’d made the history books at eleven.

‘All right,’ Harry said. ‘Figure out how to do something a grown-up can’t. Is that your challenge?’

‘I didn’t mean it like that,’ Hermione said, her voice coming out in a frightened whisper.

With an effort, Harry wrenched his gaze away from Hermione. ‘I’m not angry at you,’ Harry said. His voice was cold, despite his best efforts. ‘I’m angry at, I don’t know, everything. But I’m not willing to lose, Hermione. Losing isn’t always the right thing to do. I’ll figure out how to do something a grown wizard can’t do, and then I’ll get back to you. How’s that?’

There was more silence.

‘Okay,’ said Hermione, her voice wavering a little. She pushed herself up out of her chair, and went over to the door of the abandoned classroom they’d been working in. Her hand went onto the doorknob. ‘We’re still friends, right? And if you can’t figure out anything –’

Her voice halted.

‘Then we’ll study together,’ Harry said. His voice was even colder now.

‘Um, bye for now, then,’ Hermione said, and she quickly went out of the room and shut the door behind her.

Sometimes Harry hated having a dark side, even when he was inside it.

And the part of him that had thought exactly the same thing as Hermione, that no, children couldn’t do what grown-ups couldn’t, was saying all the things that Hermione had been too frightened to say, like, That’s one hell of a difficult challenge you just grabbed for yourself and boy are you going to end up with egg on your face this time and at least this way you’ll know you’ve failed.

And the part of him that didn’t enjoy losing replied, in a very cold voice, Fine, you can shut up and watch.

It was almost lunchtime, and Harry didn’t care. He hadn’t even bothered grabbing a snack bar from his pouch. His stomach could stand a little starving.

The wizarding world was tiny, they didn’t think like scientists, they didn’t know science, they didn’t question what they’d grown up with, they hadn’t put protective shells on their time machines, they played Quidditch, all of magical Britain was smaller than a small Muggle city, the greatest wizarding school only educated up to the age of seventeen, silly wasn’t challenging that at eleven, silly was assuming wizards knew what they were doing and had already exhausted all the low-hanging fruit a scientific polymath would see.

Step One had been to make a list of every magical constraint Harry could remember, all the things you supposedly couldn’t do.

Step Two, mark the constraints that seemed to make the least sense from a scientific perspective.

Step Three, prioritize constraints that a wizard would be unlikely to question if they didn’t know science.

Step Four, come up with avenues for attacking them.

Hermione still felt a little shaky as she sat down next to Mandy at the Ravenclaw table. Hermione’s lunch had two fruits (tomato slices and peeled tangerines), three vegetables (carrots, carrots, and more carrots), one meat (fried Diricawl drumsticks whose unhealthy coating she would carefully remove), and one little piece of chocolate cake that she would earn by eating the other parts.

It hadn’t been as bad as Potions class, sometimes she still had nightmares about that. But this time she had made it happen and she’d felt like its target. Just for a moment, before the terrible cold darkness looked away and said it wasn’t angry with her, because it hadn’t wanted to scare her.

And she still had that feeling like she’d missed something earlier, something really important.

But they hadn’t violated any of the rules of Transfiguration … had they? They hadn’t made any liquids, any gases, they hadn’t taken orders from the Defence Professor …

The pill! That had been something to be eaten!

… well, no, nobody would just eat a pill lying around, it hadn’t worked actually, they could have just Finite Incantatemed it if it had, but she would still have to tell Harry about that and make sure they didn’t mention it in front of Professor McGonagall, in case they were never allowed to study Transfiguration again …

Hermione was starting to get a really sick feeling in her stomach. She pushed back her plate from the table, she couldn’t eat lunch like this.

And she closed her eyes and began to mentally recite the rules of Transfiguration.

‘I will never Transfigure anything into liquid or gas.’

‘I will never Transfigure anything that looks like food or anything else that goes inside a human body.’

No, they really shouldn’t have tried to Transfigure the pill, or they should’ve at least realized … she’d been so caught up in Harry’s brilliant idea that she hadn’t thought …

The sick feeling in Hermione’s stomach was getting worse. There was a feeling in her mind of something hovering just on the edge of recognition, a perception about to invert itself, a young woman about to become a crone, a vase about to become two faces …

And she went on remembering the rules of Transfiguration.

Egocentric Bias

There’d been a sinking feeling in Hermione’s stomach lately, every time she heard the other students talking about her and Harry. She’d been in a shower stall this morning when she’d overheard a conversation between Morag and Padma that had been the last straw piled on top of quite a lot of other straws.

She was starting to think that getting involved in a rivalry with Harry Potter had been a terrible mistake.

If she’d just stayed away from Harry Potter, she could have been Hermione Granger, the brightest academic star of Hogwarts, who was earning more points for Ravenclaw than anyone. She wouldn’t have been as famous as the Boy-Who-Lived, but she would have been famous for herself.

Instead the Boy-Who-Lived had an academic rival, and her name happened to be Hermione Granger.

And worse, she had gone on a date with him.

The idea of getting into a Romance with Harry had seemed like an appealing idea at first. She’d read books like that, and if there was anyone in Hogwarts who was a candidate for the heroine’s love interest it was obviously Harry Potter. Bright, funny, famous, sometimes scary …

So she’d forced Harry into going on a date with her.

And now she was his love interest.

Or worse, one of the options on his dinner menu.

She’d been in a shower stall that morning and just about to turn on the water, when she’d heard giggles coming from outside. And she’d heard Morag talking about how that Muggleborn girl probably wouldn’t fight hard enough to win against Ginevra Weasley, and Padma speculating that Harry Potter might decide he wanted both.

It was like they didn’t understand that girls had options on their dinner menu and boys fought over them.

But that wasn’t even the part that hurt, really. It was that when she scored 98 on one of Professor McGonagall’s tests, the news wasn’t that Hermione Granger had scored the highest in the class, the news was that Harry Potter’s rival had scored seven more points than him.

If you got too close to the Boy-Who-Lived, you became part of his story.

You didn’t get your own.

And the thought had come to Hermione that she should just walk away, but that would’ve been too sad.

But she did want to get back what she’d accidentally given away by letting herself become known as Harry’s rival. She wanted to be a separate person again instead of Harry Potter’s third leg, was that too much to ask?

It was a hard trap to climb out of once you fell in. No matter how high you scored in class, even if you did something that deserved a special dinner time announcement, it just meant you were rivalling Harry Potter again.

But she thought she’d come up with a way.

Something to do that wouldn’t be seen as pushing up on the opposite end of Harry Potter’s see-saw.

It would be hard.

It would go against her nature.

She would have to fight someone very evil.

And she would need to ask someone even more evil for help.

Hermione raised her hand to knock upon that terrible door.

She hesitated.

Hermione realized she was being silly, and raised her hand a bit higher.

She tried to knock again.

Her hand quite failed to touch the door.

And then the door swung open anyway.

‘Dear me,’ said the spider, sitting in its web. ‘Was it really that hard to lose a single Quirrell point, Miss Granger?’

Hermione stood there with her hand raised, her cheeks growing pink. It had been.

‘Well, Miss Granger, I shall be merciful,’ said the evil Professor Quirrell. ‘Consider it already lost. There, I have taken a hard choice from you. Are you not grateful?’

‘Professor Quirrell,’ Hermione managed to say in a voice that squeaked a little. ‘I have a lot of Quirrell points, don’t I?’

‘You do indeed,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Though one less than you had before. Terrible, isn’t it? Just think, if I don’t like your reason for coming here, you could lose another fifty. Maybe I’d take them away one … by one … by one …’

Hermione’s cheeks were going even redder. ‘You’re really evil, did anyone ever tell you that?’

‘Miss Granger,’ Professor Quirrell said gravely, ‘it can be dangerous to give people compliments like that when they have not been truly earned. The recipient might feel bashful and undeserving and want to do something worthy of your praise. Now what was it you wanted to talk to me about, Miss Granger?’

It was after lunch on Thursday afternoon, and Hermione and Harry were ensconced in a little library nook, with a Quietus field up so they could talk. Harry was lying stomach-down on the ground with his elbows resting on the floor and his head in his hands and his feet kicking up casually behind him. Hermione was occupying a stuffed chair much too large for her, as if she was the Hermione centre of a bonbon shell.

Harry had suggested that they could, as a first pass, read just the titles of all the books in the library, and then Hermione could read all the tables of contents.

Hermione had thought this was a brilliant idea. She’d never done that with a library before.

Unfortunately there was a slight flaw in this plan.

Namely, they were both Ravenclaws.

Hermione was reading a book called Magical Mnemonics.

Harry was reading a book called The Skeptical Wizard.

Each had thought it was just one special exception they would make only this one time, and neither had yet realized it was impossible for either of them to ever finish reading all the book titles no matter how hard they tried.

The quiet of their little nook was broken by two words.

‘Oh, no,’ Harry suddenly said out loud, sounding like the words had been torn out of him.

There was a bit more quiet.

‘He didn’t,’ Harry said, in the same voice.

Then she heard Harry start giggling helplessly.

Hermione looked up from her book.

‘All right,’ she said, ‘what is it?’

‘I just found out why you never ask the Weasleys about the family rat,’ Harry said. ‘It’s really awful and I shouldn’t be laughing and I’m a terrible person.’

‘Yes,’ Hermione said primly, ‘you are. Tell me too.’

‘Okay, first the background. There’s a whole chapter in this book about Sirius Black conspiracy theories. You remember who that is, right?’

‘Of course,’ said Hermione. Sirius Black was a traitor, a friend of James Potter who had let Voldemort into the protected home of the Potters.

‘So it turns out there were a number of, shall we say, irregularities, associated with Black going to Azkaban. He didn’t get a trial, and the Junior Minister in charge when the Aurors arrested Black was none other than Cornelius Fudge, who became our current Minister of Magic.’

That sounded a little suspicious to Hermione too, and she said as much.

Harry made a shrugging motion with his shoulders, as he lay on the floor looking at his book. ‘Suspicious things happen all the time, and if you’re a conspiracy theorist you can always find something.’

‘But no trial?’ said Hermione.

‘It was right after the Dark Lord’s defeat,’ Harry said, his voice serious as he said it. ‘Things were incredibly chaotic, and when the Aurors tracked down Black he was standing there laughing in a street ankle-deep in blood, with twenty eyewitnesses to recount how he’d killed a friend of my father’s named Peter Pettigrew plus twelve bystanders. I’m not saying I approve of Black not getting a trial. But these are wizards we’re talking about here, so it’s not really any more suspicious than, I don’t know, the sort of thing people point to when they want to argue over who shot John F. Kennedy. So anyway, Sirius Black is the wizarding Lee Harvey Oswald. There’s all sorts of conspiracy theories about who really betrayed my parents instead of him, and one of the favourites is Peter Pettigrew, and this is where it starts getting complicated.’

Hermione listened, fascinated. ‘But how do you go from there to the Weasleys’ pet rat –’

‘Hold on,’ said Harry, ‘I’m getting there. Now, after Pettigrew’s death it came out that he’d been a spy for the Light – not a double agent, just someone who sneaked around and found things out. He’d been good at that since he was a teenager, even in Hogwarts he had a reputation for finding out all sorts of secrets. So the conspiracy theory is that Pettigrew became an unregistered Animagus while he was still in Hogwarts, an Animagus of something small that could scurry around and listen to conversations. The main problem being that successful Animagi are rare and doing it as a teenager would be really unlikely, so of course the conspiracy theory says that my father and Black were unregistered Animagi too. And in that conspiracy theory, Pettigrew himself killed the twelve bystanders, turned into his small Animagus form, and ran. So Michael Shermer says there are four additional problems with this. One, Black was the only one besides my parents who knew how to get through the wards around their house.’ (Harry’s voice was a little hard as he said that.) ‘Two, Black was a more likely suspect to start with than Pettigrew: there’s a rumour Black deliberately tried to get a student killed during his time at Hogwarts, and he was from this really nasty pureblood family, Bellatrix Black was literally his cousin. Three, Black was twenty times the fighting wizard that Pettigrew was, even if he wasn’t as smart. The duel between them would have been like Professor Quirrell versus Professor Sprout. Pettigrew probably didn’t even get a chance to draw his wand, let alone fake all the evidence the conspiracy theory requires. And four, Black was standing in the street laughing.’

‘But the rat –’ said Hermione.

‘Right,’ Harry said. ‘Well, to make a long story short, Bill Weasley decided that his little brother Percy’s pet rat was Pettigrew’s Animagus form –’

Hermione’s jaw dropped.

‘Yes,’ Harry said, ‘you wouldn’t exactly expect Evil Pettigrew to be living a sad and furtive life as the pet rat of an enemy wizarding family, he’d either be with the Malfoys or, more likely, off in the Caribbean after a bit of plastic surgery. Anyway, Bill knocks out his little brother Percy, stuns and grabs the rat, sends out all these emergency owl messages –’

‘Oh, no!’ Hermione said, the words torn out of her.

‘– and somehow manages to gather Dumbledore, the Minister of Magic, and the Head Auror –’

‘He didn’t!’ said Hermione.

‘And of course when they get there they think he’s crazy, but they use Veritas Oculum on the rat anyway, just to be sure, and what do they discover?’

She would’ve died. ‘A rat.’

‘You win a cookie! So they dragged poor Bill Weasley off to St. Mungo’s and it turned out to be a pretty standard schizophrenic break, it just happens to some people, especially young men around what we’d consider university age. Guy was convinced he was ninety-seven years old and had died and gone back in time to his younger self via train station. And he responded perfectly well to antipsychotics and is back to normal and everything’s fine now, except people don’t talk as much any more about Sirius Black conspiracy theories, and you don’t ever ask the Weasleys about the family rat.’

Hermione was giggling helplessly. It was really awful and she shouldn’t be laughing and she was a terrible person.

‘The thing I don’t understand,’ Harry said, after their giggles had died down, ‘is why Black would hunt down Pettigrew instead of running as fast as he could. He had to know the Aurors would be after him. I wonder if they got the reason out of Black before they took him to Azkaban? See, this is why people who are absolutely positively guilty still go through the legal system and get trials.’

Hermione had to agree with that.

Soon Harry was done with his book while Hermione was only halfway through hers – hers was a much more difficult book than Harry’s, but she still felt embarrassed about that. And then she had to put Magical Mnemonics back on the shelf and drag herself away, because it was time for her to face the most dreaded class in Hogwarts, broomstick riding.

Harry tagged along as she walked there, even though his own class wasn’t until an hour and a half later, like a fighter jet escorting a sad little propeller plane on its way to its own funeral.

The boy wished her goodbye in a quiet, sympathetic voice, and she walked onto the grassy fields of Doom.

And there was much shrieking and almost falling and horrible brushes with death and the ground in completely the wrong place and the Sun getting in her eyes and Morag buzzing her and Mandy thinking she was being subtle about always being near enough to catch her if she fell and she knew the other students were laughing at both of them but she never said anything to Mandy because she didn’t actually want to die.

After ten million years the class ended, and she was back on the ground where she belonged until next Thursday. Sometimes she had nightmares about it always being Thursday.

Why everyone had to learn this, when they were just going to Apparate or Floo or portkey everywhere once they grew up, was a complete and utter mystery to Hermione. Nobody actually needed to ride broomsticks as an adult, it was like being forced to play dodgeball in P.E.

At least Harry had the decency to be ashamed of being good at it.

It was a couple of hours later, and she was in a Hufflepuff study hall with Hannah, Susan, Leanne, and Megan. Professor Flitwick, surprisingly diffident for a teacher, had asked if she might possibly maybe help those four with their Charms homework for a while, even though they weren’t Ravenclaws, and Hermione had felt so proud she’d almost burst.

Hermione took a piece of parchment, spilled a little bit of ink on it, tore it into four pieces, crumpled them, and tossed the pieces on the table.

She could have got it just from crumpling it, but doing all that made it more like garbage, and that helped when someone was first practising the Disposal Charm.

Hermione sharpened her ears and eyes, and said, ‘Okay, try it.’

‘Everto.’

‘Everto.’

‘Everto.’

‘Everto.’

Hermione didn’t think she’d quite caught all the problems. ‘Can you all try it again?’

An hour later Hermione had concluded that (1), Leanne and Megan were sort of sloppy, but if you asked them to keep practising something, they would, (2) Hannah and Susan were focused and driven to the point where you had to keep telling them to slow down and relax and think about things instead of trying so hard – it was odd to think that those two would soon be hers – and (3) she liked helping Hufflepuffs, the whole study hall had a very cheerful atmosphere.

When she left for dinner, she found the Boy-Who-Lived reading a book while he waited to escort her. It made her feel flattered, and also a little worried because Harry didn’t seem to really talk to anyone besides her.

‘Did you know there’s a girl in Hufflepuff who’s a Metamorphmagus?’ said Hermione as they headed toward the Great Hall. ‘She makes her hair really red, like stop-sign red not Weasley red, and when she spilled hot tea on herself she turned into a black-haired boy until she got it under control again.’

‘Really? Cool,’ said Harry, sounding a bit distracted. ‘Um, Hermione, just to check, you know tomorrow is the last day to sign up for Professor Quirrell’s armies, right?’

‘Yes,’ Hermione said. ‘The armies of the evil Professor Quirrell.’ Her voice was a little angry, though Harry didn’t know why, of course.

‘Hermione,’ Harry said, his voice exasperated, ‘he’s not evil. He’s a little bit Dark and a whole lot Slytherin. It’s not the same as being evil.’

Harry Potter had too many words for things, that was his problem. He would have been better off if he’d just divided the universe into Good and Bad. ‘Professor Quirrell called me up in front of the whole class and told me to shoot someone!’

‘He was right,’ Harry said, his face sober. ‘I’m sorry, Hermione, but he was. You should have shot me, I wouldn’t have minded. You can’t learn Battle Magic if you can’t practise against real opponents using real spells. And now you’re doing okay in sparring, aren’t you?’

Hermione was only twelve, and so she knew, but she couldn’t put it into words, she couldn’t find the thing to say that would convince Harry.

Professor Quirrell had taken a young girl and called up that girl in front of everyone, and ordered her to open fire without provocation on a classmate.

It didn’t matter if Professor Quirrell was right about her needing to learn it.

Professor McGonagall wouldn’t ever have done that.

Professor Flitwick wouldn’t ever have done that.

Maybe not even Professor Snape would have done that.

Professor Quirrell was evil.

But she couldn’t find the words, and she knew that Harry would never believe her.

‘Hermione, I’ve talked to older students,’ Harry said. ‘Professor Quirrell could be the only competent Defence Professor we get in all seven years at Hogwarts. Anything else we can learn later. If we want to study Defence, we have to do it this year. The students who sign up for the extracurricular stuff are going to be learning huge amounts, way beyond what the Ministry thinks first-years are supposed to study – did you know we’re going to be learning the Patronus Charm? In January?’

‘The Patronus Charm?’ Hermione said, her voice going up in surprise.

Her books said that was one of the brightest magics known, a weapon against the Darkest creatures, cast with pure positive emotions. It wasn’t something she’d expect the evil Professor Quirrell to teach – or arrange to be taught, since Hermione couldn’t imagine he could do the spell himself.

‘Yes,’ Harry said. ‘Students don’t usually learn the Patronus Charm until their fifth year or even later! But Professor Quirrell says the Ministry schedules were made up by talking Flobberworms, and the ability to cast the Patronus Charm depends on emotions more than magical strength. Professor Quirrell says that he thinks most students do way less than they can, and this year he’s going to prove it.’

There was the usual tone of awed worship that Harry’s voice had when he talked about Professor Quirrell, and Hermione gritted her teeth and kept walking.

‘I already signed up, actually,’ Hermione said, her voice a little quiet. ‘I did it this morning. For everything, just like you said.’

In for a penny, in for a pound was the usual expression.

Besides, she didn’t want to lose, and if she wanted to win she had to learn.

‘So you will be in the armies, then?’ Harry’s voice was suddenly enthusiastic. ‘That’s awesome, Hermione! I’ve already got my list of soldiers, but I’m sure Professor Quirrell will let me add one more, or trade –’

‘I’m not joining your army.’ Hermione’s voice was sharp. She knew it was a reasonable assumption but it still annoyed her.

Harry blinked. ‘Not Draco Malfoy’s, surely. So you want to be in the third army? Even though we don’t know who the general is yet?’ Harry sounded surprised and a little wounded, and she couldn’t blame him, though of course she did blame him, since in fact it was all his fault. ‘But why not mine?’

‘Think about it,’ Hermione snapped, ‘and maybe you’ll work it out!’

And she sped up her stride and left Harry gaping behind her.

Coordination Problems, Pt 1

The terrifying part was how fast the whole thing had spiralled out of control.

‘Albus,’ Minerva said, not even trying to keep the worry out of her voice as the two of them entered the Great Hall, ‘something has to be done.’

The atmosphere at Hogwarts before Yuletide was usually bright and cheerful. The Great Hall had already been decorated in green and red, after a Slytherin and a Gryffindor whose Yule wedding had become a symbol of friendship transcending Houses and allegiances, a tradition almost as ancient as Hogwarts itself and which had even spread to Muggle countries.

Now the students eating dinner were glancing nervously over their shoulders, or sending vicious glares at other tables, or at some tables arguing heatedly. You could have described the atmosphere as tense, perhaps, but the phrase coming to Minerva’s mind was fifth degree of caution.

Take a school, into four Houses divided …

Now into each year, add three armies at war.

And the partisanship of Dragon and Sunshine and Chaos had spread beyond the first-years; they had become the armies for those who had no armies. Students were wearing armbands with insignia of fire or smile or upraised hand, and hexing each other in the corridors. All three first-year generals had told them to stop – even Draco Malfoy had heard her out and then nodded grimly – but their supposed followers hadn’t listened.

Dumbledore gazed out at the tables with a distant look. ‘In every city,’ the old wizard quoted softly, ‘the population has been divided for a long time past into the Blue and the Green factions … And they fight against their opponents knowing not for what end they imperil themselves … So there grows up in them against their fellow men a hostility which has no cause, and at no time does it cease or disappear, for it gives place neither to the ties of marriage nor of relationship nor of friendship, and the case is the same even though those who differ with respect to these colours be brothers or any other kin. I, for my part, am unable to call this anything except a disease of the soul …’

‘I’m sorry,’ said Minerva, ‘I don’t –’

‘Procopius,’ said Dumbledore. ‘They took their chariot-racing very seriously, in the Roman Empire. Yes, Minerva, I agree that something must be done.’

‘Soon,’ Minerva said, her voice lowering even further. ‘Albus, I think it must be done before Saturday.’

On Sunday, most students would leave Hogwarts to stay the holiday with their families; Saturday, then, was the final battle of the three first-year armies that would determine the awarding of Professor Quirrell’s thrice-cursed Christmas wish.

Dumbledore glanced over at her, studying her gravely. ‘You fear that the explosion will come then, and someone will be hurt.’

Minerva nodded.

‘And that Professor Quirrell will be blamed.’

Minerva nodded again, her face tight. She had long since become wise in the ways that Defence Professors were fired. ‘Albus,’ Minerva said, ‘we cannot lose Professor Quirrell now, we cannot! If he but stays through January our fifth-years will pass their OWLs, if he stays through March our seventh-years will pass their NEWTs, he is remedying years of neglect in months, a whole generation will grow up able to defend themselves in spite of the Dark Lord’s curse – you must stop the battle, Albus! Ban the armies now!’

‘I am not sure the Defence Professor would take that kindly,’ said Dumbledore, glancing over toward the Head Table where Quirrell was drooling into his soup. ‘He did seem most attached to his armies, though when I agreed I thought there would be four in each year.’ The old wizard sighed. ‘A clever man, probably with the best of intentions; but perhaps not clever enough, I fear. And to ban the armies might also trigger the explosion.’

‘But then Albus, what will you do?’

The old wizard favoured her with a benign smile. ‘Why, I shall plot, of course. It’s the new fashion in Hogwarts.’

And they had come too close to the Head Table for Minerva to say anything more.

The terrifying part was how fast the whole thing had spiralled out of control.

The first battle in December had been … messy, or so Draco had heard.

The second battle had been deranged.

And the next one would be worse, unless the three of them together succeeded in their last desperate attempt to stop it.

‘Professor Quirrell, this is insanity,’ Draco said flatly. ‘This isn’t Slytherin any more, it’s just …’ Draco was at a loss for words. He waved his hands helplessly. ‘You can’t possibly do any real plots with all this stuff going on. Last battle, one of my soldiers faked his own suicide. We have Hufflepuffs trying to plot, and they think they can, but they can’t. Things just happen at random now, it doesn’t have anything to do with who’s cleverest, or which army fights best, it’s …’ He couldn’t even describe it.

‘I agree with Mr Malfoy,’ said Granger in the tones of someone who hadn’t ever expected to hear herself saying those words. ‘Allowing traitors isn’t working, Professor Quirrell.’

Draco had tried forbidding anyone in his army to plot except him, and that had just driven the plots underground, no one wanted to be left out when the soldiers in other armies got to plot. After miserably losing their last battle, he’d finally given in and revoked his decree; but by then his soldiers had already started setting their own personal plans in motion, without any sort of central coordination.

After being told all the plans, or what his soldiers claimed were their plans, Draco had tried to sketch a plot to win the final battle. It had required considerably more than three different things to go right, and Draco had used Incendio on the paper and Everto to vanish the ashes, because if Father had seen it he would have been disowned.

Professor Quirrell’s eyelids were half-closed, his chin resting on his hands as he leaned forward onto his desk. ‘And you, Mr Potter?’ said the Defence Professor. ‘Are you likewise in agreement?’

‘All we’d need to do is shoot Franz Ferdinand and we could start World War One,’ said Harry. ‘It’s gone to complete chaos. I’m all for it.’

‘Harry!’ said Draco in utter shock.

He didn’t even realize until a second later that he’d said it at exactly the same time, and in exactly the same tone of indignation, as Granger.

Granger shot him a startled glance, and Draco carefully kept his face neutral. Oops.

‘That’s right!’ said Harry. ‘I’m betraying you! Both of you! Again! Ha ha!’

Professor Quirrell was smiling thinly, though his eyes were still half-closed. ‘And why is that, Mr Potter?’

‘Because I think I can cope with the chaos better than Miss Granger or Mr Malfoy,’ said the traitor. ‘Our war is a zero-sum game, and it doesn’t matter whether it’s easy or hard in an absolute sense, only who does better or worse.’

Harry Potter was learning far too fast.

Professor Quirrell’s eyes moved beneath their lids to regard Draco, and then Granger. ‘In truth, Mr Malfoy, Miss Granger, I simply could not live with myself if I shut down the grand debacle before its climax. One of your soldiers has even become a quadruple agent.’

‘Quadruple?’ said Granger. ‘But there’s only three sides in the war!’

‘Yes,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘you’d think that, wouldn’t you. I am not sure that there has ever in history been a quadruple agent, or any army with such a high fraction of real and pretended traitors. We are exploring new realms, Miss Granger, and we cannot turn back now.’

Draco left the Defence Professor’s office with his teeth gritting hard against each other, and Granger looking even more annoyed beside him.

‘I can’t believe you did that, Harry!’ said Granger.

‘Sorry,’ Harry said, not sounding sorry at all, his lips curved up in a merry smile of evil. ‘Remember, Hermione, it is just a game, and why should generals like us be the only ones who get to plot? And besides, what are the two of you going to do about it? Team up against me?’

Draco traded glances with Granger, knowing that his own face was as tight as hers. Harry had been relying, more and more openly and gloatingly, on Draco’s refusal to make common cause with a mudblood girl; and Draco was beginning to get sick of having that used against him. If this kept up much longer he was going to ally with Granger just to crush Harry Potter, and see how much the son of a mudblood liked that.

The terrifying part was how fast the whole thing had spiralled out of control.

Hermione stared at the parchment Zabini had given her, feeling utterly and completely helpless.

There were names, and lines connecting the names to other names, and some of the lines were in different colours and …

‘Tell me,’ said General Granger, ‘is there anyone in my army who isn’t a spy?’

The two of them weren’t in the office but in another, deserted classroom, and they were alone; because, Colonel Zabini had said, it was now nearly certain that at least one of the captains was a traitor. Probably Captain Goldstein, but Zabini didn’t know for sure.

Her question had put an ironic smile on the young Slytherin’s face. Blaise Zabini always seemed a little disdainful of her, but he didn’t seem to actively dislike her; nothing like the derision he held for Draco Malfoy, or the resentment he had developed for Harry Potter. She had worried at first about Zabini betraying her, but the boy seemed desperate to show that the other two generals were no better than him; and Hermione thought that while Zabini would probably be happy to sell her out to anyone else, he’d never let Malfoy or Harry win.

‘Most of your soldiers are still loyal to you, I’m pretty sure,’ said Zabini. ‘It’s just that no one wants to be left out of the fun.’ The scornful look on the Slytherin’s face made it clear what he thought of people who didn’t take plotting seriously. ‘So they think they can be double agents and secretly work for our side while pretending to betray us.’

‘And that would also go for anyone in the other armies who says they want to be our spy,’ Hermione said carefully.

The young Slytherin shrugged. ‘I think I did a good job of telling which ones really want to sell out Malfoy, I’m not sure anyone really wants to sell out Potter to you. But Nott is a sure bet for betraying Potter to Malfoy and since I had Entwhistle approach him supposedly on behalf of Malfoy and Entwhistle really reports to us, that’s almost as good –’

Hermione closed her eyes for a moment. ‘We’re going to lose, aren’t we?’

‘Look,’ Zabini said patiently, ‘You’re in the lead right now on Quirrell points. We just have to not lose this last battle completely and you’ll have enough Quirrell points to win the Christmas wish.’

Professor Quirrell had announced that the final battle would operate on a formal scoring system, which he’d been asked to do to avoid recriminations afterwards. Each time you shot someone, the general of your army got two Quirrell points. A gong would ring through the battle area (they didn’t know yet where they would be fighting, though Hermione was hoping for the forest again, where Sunshine did well) and its pitch would tell which army had won the points. And if anyone was faking being hit, the gong would ring out anyway, and then a double gong would ring later, after no fixed time, to hail the retraction. And if you called the name of an army, cried ‘For Sunshine!’ or ‘For Chaos!’ or ‘For Dragon!’, it switched your allegiance to that army …

Even Hermione had been able to see the flaw in that set of rules. But Professor Quirrell had gone on to announce that if you’d been originally assigned to Sunshine, nobody could shoot you in the name of Sunshine – or rather, they could, but then Sunshine lost a single Quirrell point, symbolized by a triple gong. That prevented you from shooting your own soldiers for points, and discouraged suicide before the enemy got you, but you could still shoot spies if you had to.

Right now, Hermione had two hundred and forty-four Quirrell points, and Malfoy had two hundred and nineteen, and Harry had two hundred and twenty-one; and there were twenty-four soldiers in each army.

‘So we fight carefully,’ Hermione said, ‘and just try not to lose too badly.’

‘No,’ said Zabini. The young Slytherin’s face was now serious. ‘The problem is, Malfoy and Potter both know that their only way to win is to combine and crush us, then fight it out on their own. So here’s what I think we should do –’

Hermione left the classroom in something of a daze. Zabini’s plan hadn’t been the obvious one, it had been strange and complicated and layered and the sort of thing she would’ve expected Harry to come up with, not Zabini. It felt wrong just for her to be able to understand a plan like that. Young girls shouldn’t be able to understand plans like that. The Hat would’ve Sorted her into Slytherin, if it’d seen that she could understand plans like that …

The awesome thing was how fast he’d been able to escalate the chaos once he started doing it deliberately.

Harry sat in his office; he’d been given the authority to order furniture from the house elves, so he’d ordered a throne, and curtains in a black and crimson pattern. Scarlet light like blood, mixed with shadow, poured over the floor.

Something in Harry felt like he’d finally come home.

Before him stood the four Lieutenants of Chaos, his most trusted minions, one of whom was a traitor.

This. This was what life should be like.

‘We are gathered,’ said Harry.

‘Let Chaos reign,’ chorused his four Lieutenants.

‘My hovercraft is full of eels,’ said Harry.

‘I will not buy this record, it is scratched,’ chorused his four Lieutenants.

‘All mimsy were the borogroves.’

‘And the mome raths outgrabe!’

That concluded the formalities.

‘How goes the confusion?’ Harry said in a dry whisper like Emperor Palpatine.

‘It goes well, General Chaos,’ said Neville in the tone he always used for military matters, a tone so deep that the boy often had to stop and cough. The Chaotic Lieutenant was neatly dressed in his black school robes, trimmed in the yellow of Hufflepuff House, and his hair was parted and combed in the usual look for an earnest young boy. Harry had liked the incongruity better than any of the cloaks they’d tried. ‘Our Legionnaires have begun five new plots since yesterday evening.’

Harry smiled evilly. ‘Do any of them have a chance of working?’

‘I don’t think so,’ said Neville of Chaos. ‘Here’s the report.’

‘Excellent,’ said Harry, and laughed chillingly as he took the parchment from Neville’s hand, trying his best to make it sound like he was choking on dust. That brought the total to sixty.

Let Draco try to handle that. Let him try.

And as for Blaise Zabini …

Harry laughed again, and this time it didn’t even take an effort to sound evil. He really needed to borrow someone’s pet Kneazle for his staff meetings, so he’d have a cat to stroke while he did this.

‘Can the Legion stop making plots now?’ said Finnigan of Chaos. ‘I mean, don’t we have enough already –’

‘No,’ Harry said flatly. ‘We can never have enough plots.’

Professor Quirrell had put it perfectly. They were pushing the boundaries further, perhaps, than they had ever been pushed; and Harry wouldn’t have been able to live with himself if he’d turned back now.

There came a knock at the door.

‘That will be the Dragon General,’ Harry said, smiling with evil prescience. ‘He arrives precisely as I expected. Do show him in, and yourselves out.’

And the four Lieutenants of Chaos shuffled out, casting dark looks at Draco as the enemy general entered into Harry’s secret lair.

If he wasn’t allowed to do this when he was older, Harry was just going to stay eleven forever.

The Sun was dripping through the red curtains, sending rays of blood dancing across the floor from behind Harry Potter’s grown-up–sized cushioned chair, which he had covered in gold and silver glitter and insisted on referring to as his throne.

(Draco was beginning to feel a lot more confident that he’d done the right thing in deciding to overthrow Harry Potter before he could take over the world. Draco couldn’t even imagine what it would be like to live under his rule.)

‘Good evening, Dragon General,’ said Harry Potter in a chill whisper. ‘You have arrived just as I expected.’

This was not surprising, considering that Draco and Harry had agreed on the meeting time in advance.

And it also wasn’t evening, but by now Draco knew better than to say anything.

‘General Potter,’ Draco said with as much dignity as he could manage, ‘you know that our two armies have to work together for either of us to win Professor Quirrell’s wish, right?’

‘Yesss,’ hissed Harry, like the boy thought he was a Parselmouth. ‘We must cooperate to destroy Sunshine, and only then fight it out between us. But if one of us betrays the other earlier on, that one could gain an advantage in the later fight. And the Sunshine General, who knows all this, will try to trick each of us into thinking the other has betrayed them. And you and I, who know that, will be tempted to betray the other and pretend that it is Granger’s trickery. And Granger knows that, as well.’

Draco nodded. That much was obvious. ‘And … both of us only want to win, and there’s no one else who’ll punish either of us if we defect …’

‘Precisely,’ said Harry Potter, his face now turning serious. ‘We are faced with a true Prisoner’s Dilemma.’

The Prisoner’s Dilemma, according to Harry’s teachings, ran thus. Two prisoners had been locked in separate cells. There was evidence against each prisoner, but only minor evidence, enough for a prison sentence of two years apiece. Each prisoner could opt to defect, betray the other, testify against them in court; and this would take one year off their own prison sentence, but add two years to the other’s. Or a prisoner could cooperate, staying silent. So if both prisoners defected, each testifying against the other, they would serve three years apiece; if both cooperated, or stayed silent, they would serve two years each; but if one defected and the other cooperated, the defector would serve a single year, and the cooperator would serve four.

And both prisoners had to make their decision without knowing the other one’s choice, and neither would be given a chance to change their decision afterwards.

Draco had observed that if the two prisoners had been Death Eaters during the Wizarding War, the Dark Lord would have killed any traitors.

Harry had nodded and said that was one way to resolve the Prisoner’s Dilemma – and in fact both Death Eaters would want there to be a Dark Lord for exactly that reason.

(Draco had asked Harry to stop and let him to think about this for a while before they continued. It had explained a lot about why Father and his friends had agreed to serve under a Dark Lord who often wasn’t nice to them … )

In fact, Harry had said, this was pretty much the reason why people had governments – you might be better off if you stole from someone else, just like each prisoner would be individually better off if they defected in the Prisoner’s Dilemma. But if everyone thought like that, the country would fall into chaos and everyone would be worse off, like what would happen if both prisoners defected. So people let themselves be ruled by governments, just like the Death Eaters had let themselves be ruled by the Dark Lord.

(Draco had asked Harry to stop again. Draco had always taken for granted that ambitious wizards put themselves in power because they wanted to rule, and people let themselves be ruled because they were scared little Hufflepuffs. And this, on reflection, still seemed true; but Harry’s perspective was fascinating even if it was wrong.)

But, Harry had continued afterwards, the fear of a third party punishing you was not the only possible reason to cooperate in the Prisoner’s Dilemma.

Suppose, Harry had said, you were playing the game against a magically produced identical copy of yourself.

Draco had said that if there were two Dracos, of course neither Draco would want anything bad to happen to the other one, not to mention that no Malfoy would let himself become known as a traitor.

Harry had nodded again, and said that this was yet another solution to the Prisoner’s Dilemma – people might cooperate because they cared about each other, or because they had senses of honour, or because they wanted to preserve their reputation. Indeed, Harry had said, it was rather difficult to construct a true Prisoner’s Dilemma – in real life, people usually cared about the other person, or their honour or their reputation or a Dark Lord’s punishment or something besides the prison sentences. But suppose the copy had been of someone completely selfish –

(Pansy Parkinson had been the example they’d used)

– so each Pansy only cared what happened to her and not to the other Pansy.

Given that this was all Pansy cared about … and that there was no Dark Lord … and Pansy wasn’t worried about her reputation … and Pansy either had no sense of honour or didn’t consider herself obliged to the other prisoner … then would the rational thing be for Pansy to cooperate, or defect?

Some people, Harry said, claimed that the rational thing to do was for Pansy to defect against her copy, but Harry, plus someone named Douglas Hofstadter, thought these people were wrong. Because, Harry had said, if Pansy defected – not at random, but for what seemed to her like rational reasons – then the other Pansy would think exactly the same way. Two identical copies wouldn’t decide different things. So Pansy had to choose between a world in which both Pansies cooperated, or a world in which both Pansies defected, and she was better off if both copies cooperated. And if Harry had thought rational people did defect in the Prisoner’s Dilemma, then he wouldn’t have done anything to spread that kind of rationality, because a country or a conspiracy full of rational people would dissolve into chaos. You would tell your enemies about rationality.

Which had all sounded reasonable at the time, but now the thought was occurring to Draco that …

‘You said,’ Draco said, ‘that the rational solution to the Prisoner’s Dilemma is to cooperate. But of course you would want me to believe that, wouldn’t you?’ And if Draco was fooled into cooperating, Harry would just say, Ha ha, betrayed you again! and laugh at him about it afterwards.

‘I wouldn’t fake your lessons,’ Harry said seriously. ‘But I have to remind you, Draco, that I didn’t say you should just automatically cooperate. Not on a true Prisoner’s Dilemma like this one. What I said was that when you choose, you shouldn’t think like you’re choosing for just yourself, or like you’re choosing for everyone. You should think like you’re choosing for all the people who are similar enough to you that they’ll probably do the same thing you do for the same reasons. And also choosing the predictions made by anyone who knows you well enough to predict you accurately, so that you never have to regret being rational because of the correct predictions that other people make about you – remind me to explain about Newcomb’s Problem at some point. So the question you and I have to ask, Draco, is this: are we similar enough that we’ll probably do the same thing whatever it is, making our decisions in mostly the same way? Or do we know each other well enough to predict each other, so that I can predict whether you’ll cooperate or defect, and you can predict that I’ve decided to do the same thing I predict you’ll do, because I know that you can predict me deciding that?’

… and Draco could not help but think that since he had to strain just to understand half of that, the answer was obviously No.

‘Yes,’ said Draco.

There was a pause.

‘I see,’ said Harry, sounding disappointed. ‘Oh, well. I guess we’ll have to think of some other way, then.’

Draco hadn’t thought that was going to work.

Draco and Harry talked about it back and forth. They had both agreed much earlier that what they did on the battlefield would not count as broken promises in real life – though Draco was a little angry about what Harry had done in Professor Quirrell’s office, and said so.

But if the two of them couldn’t rely on honour or friendship, that did leave the question of how to get their armies to work together on beating Sunshine, despite everything Granger might try to break them up. Professor Quirrell’s rules didn’t make it tempting to let Sunshine kill the other army’s soldiers – that just increased the bar you had to pass yourself – but it did tempt each side to steal kills instead of acting like a single army would, or to shoot some of the other side’s soldiers during the confusion of battle …

Hermione was walking back to Ravenclaw not really looking where she was going, her mind preoccupied with war and treachery and other age-inappropriate concepts, and she turned a corner and bumped straight into a grown-up.

‘Sorry,’ she said automatically, and then, entirely without thinking, ‘Eeeeek!’

‘Don’t worry, Miss Granger,’ said the cheerful smile, set beneath the twinkling eyes, and above the silver beard, of the Headmaster of Hogwarts. ‘You are quite forgiven.’

Her gaze was helplessly locked on the kindly face of the most powerful wizard in the world, who was also the Chief Warlock, who was also the Supreme Mugwump, who had gone insane years ago from the stress of fighting the Dark Lord, and numerous other facts that were popping up into her mind one after the other while her throat went on making little embarrassing squeaks.

‘In fact, Miss Granger,’ said Albus Percival Wulfric Brian Dumbledore, ‘it is quite lucky that we bumped into each other. Why, I was just now wondering curiously what the three of you were thinking of asking for your wishes …’

Pretending to be Wise, Pt 1

Whistle. Tick. Bzzzt. Ding. Glorp. Pop. Splat. Chime. Toot. Puff. Tinkle. Bubble. Beep. Thud. Crackle. Whoosh. Hiss. Pffft. Whirr.

Professor Flitwick had silently passed Harry a folded parchment during Charms class that Monday, and the note had said that Harry was to visit the Headmaster at his convenience and in such fashion that no one else would notice, especially not Draco Malfoy or Professor Quirrell. His one-time password for the gargoyle would be ‘squeamish ossifrage’. This had been accompanied by a remarkably artistic ink drawing of Professor Flitwick staring at him sternly, the eyes of which occasionally blinked; and at the bottom of the note, underlined three times, was the phrase ‘Don’t get into trouble’.

And so Harry had finished up Transfiguration class, and studied with Hermione, and eaten dinner, and spoken with his lieutenants, and finally, when the clock struck nine, turned himself invisible and dropped back to 6PM and wearily trudged off toward the gargoyle, the turning spiral stairs, the wooden door, the room full of little fiddly things, and the silver-bearded figure of the Headmaster.

This time, Dumbledore looked quite serious, the customary smile absent; and he was dressed in pyjamas of a darker and more sober purple than usual.

‘Thank you for coming, Harry,’ said the Headmaster. The old wizard rose from his throne, began to slowly pace through the room and the strange devices. ‘First, do you have with you the notes of yesterday’s encounter with Lucius Malfoy?’

‘Notes?’ blurted Harry.

‘Surely you wrote it down …’ said the old wizard, and his voice trailed off.

Harry felt rather embarrassed. Yes, if you’d just fumbled through a mysterious conversation full of significant hints you didn’t understand, the bloody obvious thing to do would be to write it all down immediately afterwards, before the memory faded, so you could try to figure it out later.

‘All right,’ said the Headmaster, ‘from memory then.’

Harry sheepishly recited as best he could, and got almost halfway through before he realized that it wasn’t smart to just go around telling the possibly-crazy Headmaster everything, at least not without thinking about it first, but then Lucius was definitely a bad guy and Dumbledore’s opponent so it probably was a good idea to tell him, and Harry had already started talking and it was too late to try and calculate things out now …

Harry finished his recollections honestly.

Dumbledore’s face had grown more remote as Harry went on, and at the end there was a look of ancientness about him, a sternness in the air.

‘Well,’ said Dumbledore. ‘I suggest you take the best of care that the heir of Malfoy does not come to harm, then. And I will do the same.’ The Headmaster was frowning, his fingers drumming soundlessly through the inky black surface of a plate inscribed with the word Leliel. ‘And I think it would be most extremely wise for you to avoid all interaction with Lord Malfoy henceforth.’

‘Did you intercept owls from him to me?’ said Harry.

The Headmaster gazed at Harry for a long moment, then reluctantly nodded.

For some reason Harry wasn’t feeling as outraged as he should have been. Maybe it was just that Harry was finding it very easy to sympathize with the Headmaster’s point of view right now. Even Harry could understand why Dumbledore wouldn’t want him to interact with Lucius Malfoy; it didn’t seem like an evil deed.

Not like the Headmaster blackmailing Zabini … for which they had only Zabini’s word, and Zabini was wildly untrustworthy, in fact it was hard to see why Zabini wouldn’t just tell the story that got him the most sympathy from Professor Quirrell …

‘How about if, instead of protesting, I say that I understand your point of view,’ said Harry, ‘and you go on intercepting my owls, but you tell me who from?’

‘I have intercepted a great many owls to you, I am afraid,’ Dumbledore said soberly. ‘You are a celebrity, Harry, and you would receive dozens of letters a day, some from far outside this country, did I not turn them back.’

‘That,’ Harry said, now starting to feel a bit of indignation, ‘seems like going a little too far –’

‘Many of those letters,’ the old wizard said quietly, ‘will be asking you for things you cannot give. I have not read them, of course, only turned them back to their senders undelivered. But I know, for I receive them too. And you are too young, Harry, to have your heart broken six times before breakfast each morning.’

Harry looked down at his shoes. He should insist on reading the letters and judging for himself, but … there was a small voice of common sense inside him, and it was screaming very loudly right now.

‘Thank you,’ Harry muttered.

‘The other reason I asked you here,’ said the old wizard, ‘was that I wished to consult your unique genius.’

‘Transfiguration?’ said Harry, surprised and flattered.

‘No, not that unique genius,’ said Dumbledore. ‘Tell me, Harry, what evil could you accomplish if a Dementor were allowed onto the grounds of Hogwarts?’

It developed that Professor Quirrell had asked, or rather demanded, that his students test their skills against an actual Dementor after they learned the words and gestures to the Patronus Charm.

‘Professor Quirrell is unable to cast the Patronus Charm himself,’ said Dumbledore, as he paced slowly through the devices. ‘Which is never a good sign. But then, he volunteered that fact to me in the course of demanding that outside instructors be brought in to teach the Patronus Charm to every student who wished to learn; he offered to pay the expense himself, if I would not. This impressed me greatly. But now he insists on bringing in a Dementor –’

‘Headmaster,’ Harry said quietly, ‘Professor Quirrell believes very strongly in live-fire tests under realistic combat conditions. Wanting to bring in an actual Dementor is completely in character for him.’

Now the Headmaster was giving Harry a strange look.

‘In character?’ said the old wizard.

‘I mean,’ said Harry, ‘it’s entirely consistent with the way Professor Quirrell usually acts …’ Harry trailed off. Why had he put it that way?

The Headmaster nodded. ‘So you have the same sense I do; that it is an excuse. A very reasonable excuse, to be sure; more so than you may realize. Often, wizards seemingly unable to cast a Patronus Charm will succeed in the presence of an actual Dementor, going from not a single flicker of light to a full corporeal Patronus. Why this should be, no one knows; but it is so.’

Harry frowned. ‘Then I really don’t see why you’re suspicious –’

The Headmaster spread his hands as though in helplessness. ‘Harry, the Defence Professor has asked me to pass the darkest of all creatures through the gates of Hogwarts. I must be suspicious.’ The Headmaster sighed. ‘And yet the Dementor will be guarded, warded, in a mighty cage, I will be there myself to watch it at all times – I cannot think of what ill could be done. But perhaps I am merely unable to see it. And so I am asking you.’

Harry stared at the Headmaster with his mouth open. He was so shocked he couldn’t even feel flattered.

‘Me?’ said Harry.

‘Yes,’ said Dumbledore, smiling slightly. ‘I try my best to anticipate my foes, to encompass their wicked minds and predict their evil thoughts. But I would never have imagined sharpening a Hufflepuff’s bones into weapons.’

Was Harry ever going to live that down?

‘Headmaster,’ Harry said wearily, ‘I know it doesn’t sound good, but in all seriousness: I’m not evil, I’m just very creative –’

‘I did not say that you were evil,’ Dumbledore said seriously. ‘There are those who say that to comprehend evil is to become evil; but they are merely pretending to be wise. Rather it is evil which does not know love, and dares not imagine love, and cannot ever understand love without ceasing to be evil. And I suspect that you can imagine your way into the minds of Dark Wizards better than I ever could, while still knowing love yourself. So, Harry.’ The Headmaster’s eyes were intent. ‘If you stood in Professor Quirrell’s shoes, what misdeeds could you accomplish after you tricked me into allowing a Dementor onto the grounds of Hogwarts?’

‘Hold on,’ said Harry, and in something of a daze trudged over to the chair in front of the Headmaster’s desk, and sat down. It was a large and comfortable chair this time, not a wooden stool, and Harry could feel himself enveloped as he sank into it.

Dumbledore was asking him to outwit Professor Quirrell.

Point one: Harry was rather fonder of Professor Quirrell than of Dumbledore.

Point two: The hypothesis was that the Defence Professor was planning to do something evil, and in that subjunctive case, Harry ought to be helping the Headmaster prevent it.

Point three …

‘Headmaster,’ Harry said, ‘if Professor Quirrell is up to something, I’m not sure I can outwit him. He’s got a lot more experience than I do.’

The old wizard shook his head, somehow managing to appear very solemn despite his smile. ‘You underestimate yourself.’

That was the first time anyone had ever said that to Harry.

‘I remember,’ the old wizard continued, ‘a young man in this very office, cold and controlled as he faced down the Head of House Slytherin, blackmailing his own Headmaster to protect his classmates. And I believe that young man is more cunning than Professor Quirrell, more cunning than Lucius Malfoy, that he will grow to be the equal of Voldemort himself. It is he who I wish to consult.’

Harry suppressed the chill that went through him at the name, frowned thoughtfully at the Headmaster.

How much does he know … ?

The Headmaster had seen Harry in the grip of his mysterious dark side, as deep as Harry had ever sunk into it. Harry still remembered what it had been like to watch, invisibly Time-Turned, as his past self faced down the older Slytherins; the boy with the scar on his forehead who didn’t act like the others. Of course the Headmaster would have noticed something odd about the boy in his office …

And Dumbledore had concluded that his pet hero had cunning to match his destined foe, the Dark Lord.

Which wasn’t asking for very much, considering that the Dark Lord had put a clearly visible Dark Mark on all of his servants’ left arms, and that he’d slaughtered the entire monastery that taught the martial art he’d wanted to learn.

Enough cunning to match Professor Quirrell would be a whole different order of problem.

But it was also clear that the Headmaster wouldn’t be satisfied until Harry went all cold and darkish, and came up with some sort of answer that sounded impressively cunning … which had better not actually get in the way of Professor Quirrell’s teaching Defence …

And of course Harry would go over to his dark side and think it through from that direction, just to be honest, and just in case.

‘Tell me,’ Harry said, ‘everything about how the Dementor is to be brought in, and how it is to be guarded.’

Dumbledore’s eyebrows rose for a moment, and then the old wizard began to speak.

The Dementor would be transported to the grounds of Hogwarts by an Auror trio, all three personally known to the Headmaster, and all three able to cast a corporeal Patronus Charm. They would be met at the edge of the grounds by Dumbledore, who would pass the Dementor through the Hogwarts wards –

Harry asked if the pass was permanent or temporary – whether someone could just bring in the same Dementor again the next day.

The pass was temporary (replied the Headmaster with an approving nod), and the explanation went on: the Dementor would be in a cage of solid titanium bars, not Transfigured but true-forged; in time a Dementor’s presence would corrode that metal to dust, but not in a single day.

Students awaiting their turn would stay well back of the Dementor, behind two corporeal Patronuses maintained by two of the three Aurors at any given time. Dumbledore would wait by the Dementor’s cage with his Patronus. A single student would approach the Dementor; and Dumbledore would dispel his Patronus; and the student would attempt to cast their own Patronus Charm; and if they failed, Dumbledore would restore his Patronus before the student could suffer any permanent damage. Past duelling champion Professor Flitwick would also be present while there were students near, just to add safety margin.

‘Why just you waiting by the Dementor?’ said Harry. ‘I mean, shouldn’t it be you plus an Auror –’

The Headmaster shook his head. ‘They could not withstand the repeated exposure to the Dementor, each time I dispel my Patronus.’

And if Dumbledore’s Patronus did fail for some reason, while one of the students was still near the Dementor, the third Auror would cast another corporeal Patronus and send it to shield the student …

Harry poked and prodded, but he couldn’t see a flaw in the security.

So Harry took a deep breath, sank further into the chair, closed his eyes, and remembered:

‘And that will be … five points? No, let us make it an even ten points from Ravenclaw for backchat.’

The cold came more slowly now, more reluctantly, Harry hadn’t been calling much on his dark side lately …

Harry had to run through that entire session in Potions in his mind, before his blood chilled into something approaching deadly crystalline clarity.

And then he thought of the Dementor.

And it was obvious.

‘The Dementor is a distraction,’ Harry said. The coldness clear in his voice, since that was what Dumbledore wanted and expected. ‘A large, salient threat, but in the end straightforward, and easy to defend against. So while all your attention is focused on the Dementor, the real plot will be happening elsewhere.’

Dumbledore stared at Harry for a moment, and then gave a slow nod. ‘Yes …’ said the Headmaster. ‘And I do believe I know what it might be a distraction from, if Professor Quirrell means ill … thank you, Harry.’

The Headmaster was still staring at Harry, a strange look in those ancient eyes.

‘What?’ said Harry with a tinge of annoyance, the cold still lingering in his blood.

‘I have another question for that young man,’ said the Headmaster. ‘It is something I have long wondered to myself, yet been unable to comprehend. Why?’ There was a tinge of pain in his voice. ‘Why would anyone deliberately make himself a monster? Why do evil for the sake of evil? Why Voldemort?’

Whirr, bzzzt, tick; ding, puff, splat …

Harry stared at the Headmaster in surprise.

‘How would I know?’ said Harry. ‘Am I supposed to magically understand the Dark Lord because I’m the hero, or something?’

‘Yes!’ said Dumbledore. ‘My own great foe was Grindelwald, and him I understood very well indeed. Grindelwald was my dark mirror, the man I could so easily have been, had I given in to the temptation to believe that I was a good person, and therefore always in the right. For the greater good, that was his slogan; and he truly believed it himself, even as he tore at all Europe like a wounded animal. And him, I defeated in the end. But then after him came Voldemort, to destroy everything I had protected in Britain.’ The hurt was plain now in Dumbledore’s voice, exposed upon his face. ‘He committed acts worse by far than Grindelwald’s worst, horror for the sake of horror. I sacrificed everything only to hold him back, and I still don’t understand why! Why, Harry? Why did he do it? He was never my destined foe, but yours, so if you have any guesses at all, Harry, please tell me! Why?’

Harry stared down at his hands. The truth was that Harry hadn’t read up on the Dark Lord yet, and right now he hadn’t the tiniest clue. And somehow that didn’t seem like an answer the Headmaster wanted to hear. ‘Too many Dark rituals, maybe? In the beginning he thought he’d do just one, but it sacrificed part of his good side, and that made him less reluctant to perform other Dark rituals, so he did more and more rituals in a positive feedback cycle until he ended up as a tremendously powerful monster –’

‘No!’ Now the Headmaster’s voice was agonized. ‘I can’t believe that, Harry! There has to be something more to it than just that!’

Why should there be? thought Harry, but he didn’t say it, because it was clear that the Headmaster thought the universe was a story and had a plot, and that huge tragedies weren’t allowed to happen except for equally huge, significant reasons. ‘I’m sorry, Headmaster. The Dark Lord doesn’t seem like much of a dark mirror to me, not at all. There isn’t anything I find even the tiniest bit tempting about nailing the skins of Yermy Wibble’s family to a newsroom wall.’

‘Have you no wisdom to share?’ said Dumbledore. There was pleading in the old wizard’s voice, almost begging.

Evil happens, thought Harry, it doesn’t mean anything or teach us anything, except to not be evil? The Dark Lord was probably just a selfish bastard who didn’t care who he hurt, or an idiot who made stupidly avoidable mistakes that snowballed. There is no destiny behind the ills of this world; if Hitler had been allowed into architecture school like he wanted, the whole history of Europe would have been different; if we lived in the sort of universe where horrible things were only allowed to happen for good reasons, they just wouldn’t happen in the first place.

And none of that, obviously, was what the Headmaster wanted to hear.

The old wizard was still looking at Harry from over a fiddly thing like a frozen puff of smoke, a painful desperation in those ancient, waiting eyes.

Well, sounding wise wasn’t difficult. It was a lot easier than being intelligent, actually, since you didn’t have to say anything surprising or come up with any new insights. You just let your brain’s pattern-matching software complete the cliche, using whatever Deep Wisdom you’d stored previously.

‘Headmaster,’ Harry said solemnly, ‘I would rather not define myself by my enemies.’

Somehow, even in the midst of all the whirring and ticking, there was a kind of silence.

That had come out a bit more Deeply Wise than Harry had intended.

‘You may be very wise, Harry …’ the Headmaster said slowly. ‘I do wish … that I could have been defined by my friends.’ The pain in his voice had grown deeper.

Harry’s mind searched hastily for something else Deeply Wise to say that would soften the unintended force of the blow –

‘Or perhaps,’ Harry said more softly, ‘it is the foe that makes the Gryffindor, as it is the friend that makes the Hufflepuff, and the ambition that makes the Slytherin. I do know that it is always, in every generation, the puzzle that makes the scientist.’

‘It is a dreadful fate to which you condemn my House, Harry,’ said the Headmaster. The pain was still in his voice. ‘For now that you remark on it, I do think that I was very much made by my enemies.’

Harry stared at his own hands, where they lay in his lap. Maybe he should just shut up while he was ahead.

‘But you have answered my question,’ said Dumbledore more softly, as though to himself. ‘I should have realized that would be a Slytherin’s key. For his ambition, all for the sake of his ambition; and that I know, though not why …’ For a time Dumbledore stared off into nothingness; then he straightened, and his eyes seemed to focus on Harry again.

‘And you, Harry,’ said the Headmaster, ‘you name yourself a scientist?’ His voice was laced with surprise and mild disapproval.

‘You don’t like science?’ said Harry a little wearily. He’d hoped Dumbledore would be fonder of Muggle things.

‘I suppose it is useful to those without wands,’ said Dumbledore, frowning. ‘But it seems a strange thing by which to define yourself. Is science as important as love? As kindness? As friendship? Is it science that makes you fond of Minerva McGonagall? Is it science that makes you care for Hermione Granger? Will it be science to which you turn, when you try to kindle warmth in Draco Malfoy’s heart?’

You know, the sad thing is, you probably think you just uttered some kind of incredibly wise knockdown argument.

Now, how to phrase the rejoinder in such fashion that it also sounded incredibly wise …

‘You are not Ravenclaw,’ Harry said with calm dignity, ‘and so it might not have occurred to you that to respect the truth, and seek it all the days of your life, could also be an act of grace.’

The Headmaster’s eyebrows rose up. And then he sighed. ‘How did you become so wise, so young … ?’ The old wizard sounded sad, as he said it. ‘Perhaps it will prove valuable to you.’

Only for impressing ancient wizards who are overly impressed with themselves, thought Harry. He was actually a bit disappointed by Dumbledore’s credulity; it wasn’t that Harry had lied, but Dumbledore seemed far too impressed with Harry’s ability to phrase things so that they sounded profound, instead of putting them into plain English like Richard Feynman had done with his wisdom …

‘Love is more important than wisdom,’ said Harry, just to test the limits of Dumbledore’s tolerance for blindingly obvious cliches completed by sheer pattern matching without any sort of detailed analysis.

The Headmaster nodded gravely, and said, ‘Indeed.’

Harry stood up out of the chair, and stretched his arms. Well, I’d better go off and love something, then, that’s bound to help me defeat the Dark Lord. And next time you ask me for advice, I’ll just give you a hug –

‘This day you have helped me much, Harry,’ said the Headmaster. ‘And so there is one last thing I would ask that young man.’

Great.

‘Tell me, Harry,’ said the Headmaster (and now his voice sounded simply puzzled, though there was still a hint of pain in his eyes), ‘why do Dark Wizards fear death so greatly?’

‘Er,’ said Harry, ‘sorry, I’ve got to back the Dark Wizards on that one.’